Genesis

The First Book of Moses Called

Genesis

I

^1In the beginning God created the heaven and the earth. ^2And the earth was without form, and void; and darkness was upon the face of the deep. And the Spirit of God moved upon the face of the waters. ^3And God said, Let there be light: and there was light. ^4And God saw the light, that it was good: and God divided the light from the darkness. ^5And God called the light Day, and the darkness he called Night. And the evening and the morning were the first day.

^6And God said, Let there be a firmament in the midst of the waters, and let it divide the waters from the waters. ^7And God made the firmament, and divided the waters which were under the firmament from the waters which were above the firmament: and it was so. ^8And God called the firmament Heaven. And the evening and the morning were the second day.

^9And God said, Let the waters under the heaven be gathered together unto one place, and let the dry land appear: and it was so. ^10And God called the dry land Earth; and the gathering together of the waters called he Seas: and God saw that it was good. ^11And God said, Let the earth bring forth grass, the herb yielding seed, and the fruit tree yielding fruit after his kind, whose seed is in itself, upon the earth: and it was so. ^12And the earth brought forth grass, and herb yielding seed after his kind, and the tree yielding fruit, whose seed was in itself, after his kind: and God saw that it was good. ^13And the evening and the morning were the third day.

^14And God said, Let there be lights in the firmament of the heaven to divide the day from the night; and let them be for signs, and for seasons, and for days, and years: ^15and let them be for lights in the firmament of the heaven to give light upon the earth: and it was so. ^16And God made two great lights; the greater light to rule the day, and the lesser light to rule the night: he made the stars also. ^17And God set them in the firmament of the heaven to give light upon the earth, ^18and to rule over the day and over the night, and to divide the light from the darkness: and God saw that it was good. ^19And the evening and the morning were the fourth day.

^20And God said, Let the waters bring forth abundantly the moving creature that hath life, and fowl that may fly above the earth in the open firmament of heaven. ^21And God created great whales, and every living creature that moveth, which the waters brought forth abundantly, after their kind, and every winged fowl after his kind: and God saw that it was good. ^22And God blessed them, saying, Be fruitful, and multiply, and fill the waters in the seas, and let fowl multiply in the earth. ^23And the evening and the morning were the fifth day.

^24And God said, Let the earth bring forth the living creature after his kind, cattle, and creeping thing, and beast of the earth after his kind: and it was so. ^25And God made the beast of the earth after his kind, and cattle after their kind, and every thing that creepeth upon the earth after his kind: and God saw that it was good. ^26And God said, Let us make man in our image, after our likeness: and let them have dominion over the fish of the sea, and over the fowl of the air, and over the cattle, and over all the earth, and over every creeping thing that creepeth upon the earth. ^27So God created man in his own image, in the image of God created he him; male and female created he them. ^28And God blessed them, and God said unto them, Be fruitful, and multiply, and replenish the earth, and subdue it: and have dominion over the fish of the sea, and over the fowl of the air, and over every living thing that moveth upon the earth. ^29And God said, Behold, I have given you every herb bearing seed, which is upon the face of all the earth, and every tree, in the which is the fruit of a tree yielding seed; to you it shall be for meat. ^30And to every beast of the earth, and to every fowl of the air, and to every thing that creepeth upon the earth, wherein there is life, I have given every green herb for meat: and it was so. ^31And God saw every thing that he had made, and, behold, it was very good. And the evening and the morning were the sixth day.

II

^1Thus the heavens and the earth were finished, and all the host of them. ^2And on the seventh day God ended his work which he had made; and he rested on the seventh day from all his work which he had made. ^3And God blessed the seventh day, and sanctified it: because that in it he had rested from all his work which God created and made.

^4These are the generations of the heavens and of the earth when they were created, in the day that the Lord God made the earth and the heavens, ^5and every plant of the field before it was in the earth, and every herb of the field before it grew: for the Lord God had not caused it to rain upon the earth, and there was not a man to till the ground. ^6But there went up a mist from the earth, and watered the whole face of the ground. ^7And the Lord God formed man of the dust of the ground, and breathed into his nostrils the breath of life; and man became a living soul.

^8And the Lord God planted a garden eastward in Eden; and there he put the man whom he had formed. ^9And out of the ground made the Lord God to grow every tree that is pleasant to the sight, and good for food; the tree of life also in the midst of the garden, and the tree of knowledge of good and evil. ^10And a river went out of Eden to water the garden; and from thence it was parted, and became into four heads. ^11The name of the first is Pison: that is it which compasseth the whole land of Havilah, where there is gold; ^12and the gold of that land is good: there is bdellium and the onyx stone. ^13And the name of the second river is Gihon: the same is it that compasseth the whole land of Ethiopia. ^14And the name of the third river is Hiddekel: that is it which goeth toward the east of Assyria. And the fourth river is Euphrates. ^15And the Lord God took the man, and put him into the garden of Eden to dress it and to keep it. ^16And the Lord God commanded the man, saying, Of every tree of the garden thou mayest freely eat: ^17but of the tree of the knowledge of good and evil, thou shalt not eat of it: for in the day that thou eatest thereof thou shalt surely die.

^18And the Lord God said, It is not good that the man should be alone; I will make him an help meet for him. ^19And out of the ground the Lord God formed every beast of the field, and every fowl of the air; and brought them unto Adam to see what he would call them: and whatsoever Adam called every living creature, that was the name thereof. ^20And Adam gave names to all cattle, and to the fowl of the air, and to every beast of the field; but for Adam there was not found an help meet for him. ^21And the Lord God caused a deep sleep to fall upon Adam, and he slept: and he took one of his ribs, and closed up the flesh instead thereof; ^22and the rib, which the Lord God had taken from man, made he a woman, and brought her unto the man. ^23And Adam said, This is now bone of my bones, and flesh of my flesh: she shall be called Woman, because she was taken out of Man. ^24Therefore shall a man leave his father and his mother, and shall cleave unto his wife: and they shall be one flesh. ^25And they were both naked, the man and his wife, and were not ashamed.

III

^1Now the serpent was more subtil than any beast of the field which the Lord God had made. And he said unto the woman, Yea, hath God said, Ye shall not eat of every tree of the garden? ^2And the woman said unto the serpent, We may eat of the fruit of the trees of the garden: ^3but of the fruit of the tree which is in the midst of the garden, God hath said, Ye shall not eat of it, neither shall ye touch it, lest ye die. ^4And the serpent said unto the woman, Ye shall not surely die: ^5for God doth know that in the day ye eat thereof, then your eyes shall be opened, and ye shall be as gods, knowing good and evil. ^6And when the woman saw that the tree was good for food, and that it was pleasant to the eyes, and a tree to be desired to make one wise, she took of the fruit thereof, and did eat, and gave also unto her husband with her; and he did eat. ^7And the eyes of them both were opened, and they knew that they were naked; and they sewed fig leaves together, and made themselves aprons. ^8And they heard the voice of the Lord God walking in the garden in the cool of the day: and Adam and his wife hid themselves from the presence of the Lord God amongst the trees of the garden. ^9And the Lord God called unto Adam, and said unto him, Where art thou? ^10And he said, I heard thy voice in the garden, and I was afraid, because I was naked; and I hid myself. ^11And he said, Who told thee that thou wast naked? Hast thou eaten of the tree, whereof I commanded thee that thou shouldest not eat? ^12And the man said, The woman whom thou gavest to be with me, she gave me of the tree, and I did eat. ^13And the Lord God said unto the woman, What is this that thou hast done? And the woman said, The serpent beguiled me, and I did eat. ^14And the Lord God said unto the serpent, Because thou hast done this, thou art cursed above all cattle, and above every beast of the field; upon thy belly shalt thou go, and dust shalt thou eat all the days of thy life: ^15and I will put enmity between thee and the woman, and between thy seed and her seed; it shall bruise thy head, and thou shalt bruise his heel. ^16Unto the woman he said, I will greatly multiply thy sorrow and thy conception; in sorrow thou shalt bring forth children; and thy desire shall be to thy husband, and he shall rule over thee. ^17And unto Adam he said, Because thou hast hearkened unto the voice of thy wife, and hast eaten of the tree, of which I commanded thee, saying, Thou shalt not eat of it: cursed is the ground for thy sake; in sorrow shalt thou eat of it all the days of thy life; ^18thorns also and thistles shall it bring forth to thee; and thou shalt eat the herb of the field; ^19in the sweat of thy face shalt thou eat bread, till thou return unto the ground; for out of it wast thou taken: for dust thou art, and unto dust shalt thou return. ^20And Adam called his wife’s name Eve; because she was the mother of all living. ^21Unto Adam also and to his wife did the Lord God make coats of skins, and clothed them.

^22And the Lord God said, Behold, the man is become as one of us, to know good and evil: and now, lest he put forth his hand, and take also of the tree of life, and eat, and live for ever: ^23therefore the Lord God sent him forth from the garden of Eden, to till the ground from whence he was taken. ^24So he drove out the man; and he placed at the east of the garden of Eden Cherubims, and a flaming sword which turned every way, to keep the way of the tree of life.

IV

^1And Adam knew Eve his wife; and she conceived, and bare Cain, and said, I have gotten a man from the Lord. ^2And she again bare his brother Abel. And Abel was a keeper of sheep, but Cain was a tiller of the ground. ^3And in process of time it came to pass, that Cain brought of the fruit of the ground an offering unto the Lord. ^4And Abel, he also brought of the firstlings of his flock and of the fat thereof. And the Lord had respect unto Abel and to his offering: ^5but unto Cain and to his offering he had not respect. And Cain was very wroth, and his countenance fell. ^6And the Lord said unto Cain, Why art thou wroth? and why is thy countenance fallen? ^7If thou doest well, shalt thou not be accepted? and if thou doest not well, sin lieth at the door. And unto thee shall be his desire, and thou shalt rule over him. ^8And Cain talked with Abel his brother: and it came to pass, when they were in the field, that Cain rose up against Abel his brother, and slew him.

^9And the Lord said unto Cain, Where is Abel thy brother? And he said, I know not: Am I my brother’s keeper? ^10And he said, What hast thou done? the voice of thy brother’s blood crieth unto me from the ground. ^11And now art thou cursed from the earth, which hath opened her mouth to receive thy brother’s blood from thy hand; ^12when thou tillest the ground, it shall not henceforth yield unto thee her strength; a fugitive and a vagabond shalt thou be in the earth. ^13And Cain said unto the Lord, My punishment is greater than I can bear. ^14Behold, thou hast driven me out this day from the face of the earth; and from thy face shall I be hid; and I shall be a fugitive and a vagabond in the earth; and it shall come to pass, that every one that findeth me shall slay me. ^15And the Lord said unto him, Therefore whosoever slayeth Cain, vengeance shall be taken on him sevenfold. And the Lord set a mark upon Cain, lest any finding him should kill him.

^16And Cain went out from the presence of the Lord, and dwelt in the land of Nod, on the east of Eden. ^17And Cain knew his wife; and she conceived, and bare Enoch: and he builded a city, and called the name of the city, after the name of his son, Enoch. ^18And unto Enoch was born Irad: and Irad begat Mehujael: and Mehujael begat Methusael: and Methusael begat Lamech.

^19And Lamech took unto him two wives: the name of the one was Adah, and the name of the other Zillah. ^20And Adah bare Jabal: he was the father of such as dwell in tents, and of such as have cattle. ^21And his brother’s name was Jubal: he was the father of all such as handle the harp and organ. ^22And Zillah, she also bare Tubalcain, an instructor of every artificer in brass and iron: and the sister of Tubalcain was Naamah. ^23And Lamech said unto his wives,

Adah and Zillah, Hear my voice;
Ye wives of Lamech, hearken unto my speech:
For I have slain a man to my wounding,
And a young man to my hurt.
^24If Cain shall be avenged sevenfold,
Truly Lamech seventy and sevenfold.

^25And Adam knew his wife again; and she bare a son, and called his name Seth: For God, said she, hath appointed me another seed instead of Abel, whom Cain slew. ^26And to Seth, to him also there was born a son; and he called his name Enos: then began men to call upon the name of the Lord.

V

^1This is the book of the generations of Adam. In the day that God created man, in the likeness of God made he him; ^2male and female created he them; and blessed them, and called their name Adam, in the day when they were created.

^3And Adam lived an hundred and thirty years, and begat a son in his own likeness, and after his image; and called his name Seth: ^4and the days of Adam after he had begotten Seth were eight hundred years: and he begat sons and daughters: ^5and all the days that Adam lived were nine hundred and thirty years: and he died.

^6And Seth lived an hundred and five years, and begat Enos: ^7and Seth lived after he begat Enos eight hundred and seven years, and begat sons and daughters: ^8and all the days of Seth were nine hundred and twelve years: and he died.

^9And Enos lived ninety years, and begat Cainan: ^10and Enos lived after he begat Cainan eight hundred and fifteen years, and begat sons and daughters: ^11and all the days of Enos were nine hundred and five years: and he died.

^12And Cainan lived seventy years and begat Mahalaleel: ^13and Cainan lived after he begat Mahalaleel eight hundred and forty years, and begat sons and daughters: ^14and all the days of Cainan were nine hundred and ten years: and he died.

^15And Mahalaleel lived sixty and five years, and begat Jared: ^16and Mahalaleel lived after he begat Jared eight hundred and thirty years, and begat sons and daughters: ^17and all the days of Mahalaleel were eight hundred ninety and five years: and he died.

^18And Jared lived an hundred sixty and two years, and he begat Enoch: ^19and Jared lived after he begat Enoch eight hundred years, and begat sons and daughters: ^20and all the days of Jared were nine hundred sixty and two years: and he died.

^21And Enoch lived sixty and five years, and begat Methuselah: ^22and Enoch walked with God after he begat Methuselah three hundred years, and begat sons and daughters: ^23and all the days of Enoch were three hundred sixty and five years: ^24and Enoch walked with God: and he was not; for God took him.

^25And Methuselah lived an hundred eighty and seven years, and begat Lamech. ^26and Methuselah lived after he begat Lamech seven hundred eighty and two years, and begat sons and daughters: ^27and all the days of Methuselah were nine hundred sixty and nine years: and he died.

^28And Lamech lived an hundred eighty and two years, and begat a son: ^29and he called his name Noah, saying, This same shall comfort us concerning our work and toil of our hands, because of the ground which the Lord hath cursed. ^30And Lamech lived after he begat Noah five hundred ninety and five years, and begat sons and daughters: ^31and all the days of Lamech were seven hundred seventy and seven years: and he died. ^32And Noah was five hundred years old: and Noah begat Shem, Ham, and Japheth.

VI

^1And it came to pass, when men began to multiply on the face of the earth, and daughters were born unto them, ^2that the sons of God saw the daughters of men that they were fair; and they took them wives of all which they chose. ^3And the Lord said, My spirit shall not always strive with man, for that he also is flesh: yet his days shall be an hundred and twenty years. ^4There were giants in the earth in those days; and also after that, when the sons of God came in unto the daughters of men, and they bare children to them, the same became mighty men which were of old, men of renown.

^5And God saw that the wickedness of man was great in the earth, and that every imagination of the thoughts of his heart was only evil continually. ^6And it repented the Lord that he had made man on the earth, and it grieved him at his heart. ^7And the Lord said, I will destroy man whom I have created from the face of the earth; both man, and beast, and the creeping thing, and the fowls of the air; for it repenteth me that I have made them. ^8But Noah found grace in the eyes of the Lord.

^9These are the generations of Noah: Noah was a just man and perfect in his generations, and Noah walked with God. ^10And Noah begat three sons, Shem, Ham, and Japheth. ^11The earth also was corrupt before God, and the earth was filled with violence. ^12And God looked upon the earth, and, behold, it was corrupt; for all flesh had corrupted his way upon the earth.

^13And God said unto Noah, The end of all flesh is come before me; for the earth is filled with violence through them; and, behold, I will destroy them with the earth. ^14Make thee an ark of gopher wood; rooms shalt thou make in the ark, and shalt pitch it within and without with pitch. ^15And this is the fashion which thou shalt make it of: The length of the ark shall be three hundred cubits, the breadth of it fifty cubits, and the height of it thirty cubits. ^16A window shalt thou make to the ark, and in a cubit shalt thou finish it above; and the door of the ark shalt thou set in the side thereof; with lower, second, and third stories shalt thou make it. ^17And, behold, I, even I, do bring a flood of waters upon the earth, to destroy all flesh, wherein is the breath of life, from under heaven; and every thing that is in the earth shall die. ^18But with thee will I establish my covenant; and thou shalt come into the ark, thou, and thy sons, and thy wife, and thy sons’ wives with thee. ^19And of every living thing of all flesh, two of every sort shalt thou bring into the ark, to keep them alive with thee; they shall be male and female. ^20Of fowls after their kind, and of cattle after their kind, of every creeping thing of the earth after his kind, two of every sort shall come unto thee, to keep them alive. ^21And take thou unto thee of all food that is eaten, and thou shalt gather it to thee; and it shall be for food for thee, and for them. ^22Thus did Noah; according to all that God commanded him, so did he.

VII

^1And the Lord said unto Noah, Come thou and all thy house into the ark; for thee have I seen righteous before me in this generation. ^2Of every clean beast thou shalt take to thee by sevens, the male and his female: and of beasts that are not clean by two, the male and his female. ^3Of fowls also of the air by sevens, the male and the female; to keep seed alive upon the face of all the earth. ^4For yet seven days, and I will cause it to rain upon the earth forty days and forty nights; and every living substance that I have made will I destroy from off the face of the earth. ^5And Noah did according unto all that the Lord commanded him. ^6And Noah was six hundred years old when the flood of waters was upon the earth.

^7And Noah went in, and his sons, and his wife, and his sons’ wives with him, into the ark, because of the waters of the flood. ^8Of clean beasts, and of beasts that are not clean, and of fowls, and of every thing that creepeth upon the earth, ^9there went in two and two unto Noah into the ark, the male and the female, as God had commanded Noah. ^10And it came to pass after seven days, that the waters of the flood were upon the earth.

^11In the six hundredth year of Noah’s life, in the second month, the seventeenth day of the month, the same day were all the fountains of the great deep broken up, and the windows of heaven were opened. ^12And the rain was upon the earth forty days and forty nights. ^13In the selfsame day entered Noah, and Shem, and Ham, and Japheth, the sons of Noah, and Noah’s wife, and the three wives of his sons with them, into the ark; ^14they, and every beast after his kind, and all the cattle after their kind, and every creeping thing that creepeth upon the earth after his kind, and every fowl after his kind, every bird of every sort. ^15And they went in unto Noah into the ark, two and two of all flesh, wherein is the breath of life. ^16And they that went in, went in male and female of all flesh, as God had commanded him: and the Lord shut him in. ^17And the flood was forty days upon the earth; and the waters increased, and bare up the ark, and it was lift up above the earth. ^18And the waters prevailed, and were increased greatly upon the earth; and the ark went upon the face of the waters. ^19And the waters prevailed exceedingly upon the earth; and all the high hills, that were under the whole heaven, were covered. ^20Fifteen cubits upward did the waters prevail; and the mountains were covered. ^21And all flesh died that moved upon the earth, both of fowl, and of cattle, and of beast, and of every creeping thing that creepeth upon the earth, and every man: ^22all in whose nostrils was the breath of life, of all that was in the dry land, died. ^23And every living substance was destroyed which was upon the face of the ground, both man, and cattle, and the creeping things, and the fowl of the heaven; and they were destroyed from the earth: and Noah only remained alive, and they that were with him in the ark. ^24And the waters prevailed upon the earth an hundred and fifty days.

VIII

^1And God remembered Noah, and every living thing, and all the cattle that was with him in the ark: and God made a wind to pass over the earth, and the waters asswaged; ^2the fountains also of the deep and the windows of heaven were stopped, and the rain from heaven was restrained; ^3and the waters returned from off the earth continually: and after the end of the hundred and fifty days the waters were abated. ^4And the ark rested in the seventh month, on the seventeenth day of the month, upon the mountains of Ararat. ^5And the waters decreased continually until the tenth month: in the tenth month, on the first day of the month, were the tops of the mountains seen.

^6And it came to pass at the end of forty days, that Noah opened the window of the ark which he had made: ^7and he sent forth a raven, which went forth to and fro, until the waters were dried up from off the earth. ^8Also he sent forth a dove from him, to see if the waters were abated from off the face of the ground; ^9but the dove found no rest for the sole of her foot, and she returned unto him into the ark, for the waters were on the face of the whole earth: then he put forth his hand, and took her, and pulled her in unto him into the ark. ^10And he stayed yet other seven days; and again he sent forth the dove out of the ark; ^11and the dove came in to him in the evening; and, lo, in her mouth was an olive leaf pluckt off: so Noah knew that the waters were abated from off the earth. ^12And he stayed yet other seven days; and sent forth the dove; which returned not again unto him any more.

^13And it came to pass in the six hundredth and first year, in the first month, the first day of the month, the waters were dried up from off the earth: and Noah removed the covering of the ark, and looked, and, behold, the face of the ground was dry. ^14And in the second month, on the seven and twentieth day of the month, was the earth dried.

^15And God spake unto Noah, saying, ^16Go forth of the ark, thou, and thy wife, and thy sons, and thy sons’ wives with thee. ^17Bring forth with thee every living thing that is with thee, of all flesh, both of fowl, and of cattle, and of every creeping thing that creepeth upon the earth; that they may breed abundantly in the earth, and be fruitful, and multiply upon the earth. ^18And Noah went forth, and his sons, and his wife, and his sons’ wives with him: ^19every beast, every creeping thing, and every fowl, and whatsoever creepeth upon the earth, after their kinds, went forth out of the ark.

^20And Noah builded an altar unto the Lord; and took of every clean beast, and of every clean fowl, and offered burnt offerings on the altar. ^21And the Lord smelled a sweet savour; and the Lord said in his heart, I will not again curse the ground any more for man’s sake; for the imagination of man’s heart is evil from his youth; neither will I again smite any more every thing living, as I have done. ^22While the earth remaineth, seedtime and harvest, and cold and heat, and summer and winter, and day and night shall not cease.

IX

^1And God blessed Noah and his sons, and said unto them, Be fruitful, and multiply, and replenish the earth. ^2And the fear of you and the dread of you shall be upon every beast of the earth, and upon every fowl of the air, upon all that moveth upon the earth, and upon all the fishes of the sea; into your hand are they delivered. ^3Every moving thing that liveth shall be meat for you; even as the green herb have I given you all things. ^4But flesh with the life thereof, which is the blood thereof, shall ye not eat. ^5And surely your blood of your lives will I require; at the hand of every beast will I require it, and at the hand of man; at the hand of every man’s brother will I require the life of man. ^6Whoso sheddeth man’s blood, by man shall his blood be shed: for in the image of God made he man. ^7And you, be ye fruitful, and multiply; bring forth abundantly in the earth, and multiply therein.

^8And God spake unto Noah, and to his sons with him, saying, ^9And I, behold, I establish my covenant with you, and with your seed after you; ^10and with every living creature that is with you, of the fowl, of the cattle, and of every beast of the earth with you; from all that go out of the ark, to every beast of the earth. ^11And I will establish my covenant with you, neither shall all flesh be cut off any more by the waters of a flood; neither shall there any more be a flood to destroy the earth. ^12And God said, This is the token of the covenant which I make between me and you and every living creature that is with you, for perpetual generations: ^13I do set my bow in the cloud, and it shall be for a token of a covenant between me and the earth. ^14And it shall come to pass, when I bring a cloud over the earth, that the bow shall be seen in the cloud: ^15and I will remember my covenant, which is between me and you and every living creature of all flesh; and the waters shall no more become a flood to destroy all flesh. ^16And the bow shall be in the cloud; and I will look upon it, that I may remember the everlasting covenant between God and every living creature of all flesh that is upon the earth. ^17And God said unto Noah, This is the token of the covenant, which I have established between me and all flesh that is upon the earth.

^18And the sons of Noah, that went forth of the ark, were Shem, and Ham, and Japheth: and Ham is the father of Canaan. ^19These are the three sons of Noah: and of them was the whole earth overspread.

^20And Noah began to be an husbandman, and he planted a vineyard: ^21and he drank of the wine, and was drunken; and he was uncovered within his tent. ^22And Ham, the father of Canaan, saw the nakedness of his father, and told his two brethren without. ^23And Shem and Japheth took a garment, and laid it upon both their shoulders, and went backward, and covered the nakedness of their father; and their faces were backward, and they saw not their father’s nakedness. ^24And Noah awoke from his wine, and knew what his younger son had done unto him. ^25And he said,

Cursed be Canaan;
A servant of servants shall he be unto his brethren.

^26And he said,

Blessed be the Lord God of Shem;
And Canaan shall be his servant.
^27God shall enlarge Japheth,
And he shall dwell in the tents of Shem;
And Canaan shall be his servant.

^28And Noah lived after the flood three hundred and fifty years. ^29And all the days of Noah were nine hundred and fifty years: and he died.

X

^1Now these are the generations of the sons of Noah, Shem, Ham, and Japheth: and unto them were sons born after the flood.

^2The sons of Japheth; Gomer, and Magog, and Madai, and Javan, and Tubal, and Meshech, and Tiras. ^3And the sons of Gomer; Ashkenaz, and Riphath, and Togarmah. ^4And the sons of Javan; Elishah, and Tarshish, Kittim, and Dodanim. ^5By these were the isles of the Gentiles divided in their lands; every one after his tongue, after their families, in their nations.

^6And the sons of Ham; Cush, and Mizraim, and Phut, and Canaan. ^7And the sons of Cush; Seba, and Havilah, and Sabtah, and Raamah, and Sabtechah: and the sons of Raamah; Sheba, and Dedan. ^8And Cush begat Nimrod: he began to be a mighty one in the earth. ^9He was a mighty hunter before the Lord: wherefore it is said, Even as Nimrod the mighty hunter before the Lord. ^10And the beginning of his kingdom was Babel, and Erech, and Accad, and Calneh, in the land of Shinar. ^11Out of that land went forth Asshur, and builded Nineveh, and the city Rehoboth, and Calah, ^12and Resen between Nineveh and Calah: the same is a great city. ^13And Mizraim begat Ludim, and Anamim, and Lehabim, and Naphtuhim, ^14and Pathrusim, and Casluhim, (out of whom came Philistim,) and Caphtorim.

^15And Canaan begat Sidon his first born, and Heth, ^16and the Jebusite, and the Amorite, and the Girgasite, ^17and the Hivite, and the Arkite, and the Sinite, ^18and the Arvadite, and the Zemarite, and the Hamathite: and afterward were the families of the Canaanites spread abroad. ^19And the border of the Canaanites was from Sidon, as thou comest to Gerar, unto Gaza; as thou goest, unto Sodom, and Gomorrah, and Admah, and Zeboim, even unto Lasha. ^20These are the sons of Ham, after their families, after their tongues, in their countries, and in their nations.

^21Unto Shem also, the father of all the children of Eber, the brother of Japheth the elder, even to him were children born. ^22The children of Shem; Elam, and Asshur, and Arphaxad, and Lud, and Aram. ^23And the children of Aram; Uz, and Hul, and Gether, and Mash. ^24And Arphaxad begat Salah; and Salah begat Eber. ^25And unto Eber were born two sons: the name of one was Peleg; for in his days was the earth divided; and his brother’s name was Joktan. ^26And Joktan begat Almodad, and Sheleph, and Hazarmaveth, and Jerah, ^27and Hadoram, and Uzal, and Diklah, ^28and Obal, and Abimael, and Sheba, ^29and Ophir, and Havilah, and Jobab: all these were the sons of Joktan. ^30And their dwelling was from Mesha, as thou goest unto Sephar a mount of the east. ^31These are the sons of Shem, after their families, after their tongues, in their lands, after their nations. ^32These are the families of the sons of Noah, after their generations, in their nations: and by these were the nations divided in the earth after the flood.

XI

^1And the whole earth was of one language, and of one speech. ^2And it came to pass, as they journeyed from the east, that they found a plain in the land of Shinar; and they dwelt there. ^3And they said one to another, Go to, let us make brick, and burn them thoroughly. And they had brick for stone, and slime had they for morter. ^4And they said, Go to, let us build us a city and a tower, whose top may reach unto heaven; and let us make us a name, lest we be scattered abroad upon the face of the whole earth. ^5And the Lord came down to see the city and the tower, which the children of men builded. ^6And the Lord said, Behold, the people is one, and they have all one language; and this they begin to do: and now nothing will be restrained from them, which they have imagined to do. ^7Go to, let us go down, and there confound their language, that they may not understand one another’s speech. ^8So the Lord scattered them abroad from thence upon the face of all the earth: and they left off to build the city. ^9Therefore is the name of it called Babel; because the Lord did there confound the language of all the earth: and from thence did the Lord scatter them abroad upon the face of all the earth.

^10These are the generations of Shem: Shem was an hundred years old, and begat Arphaxad two years after the flood: ^11and Shem lived after he begat Arphaxad five hundred years, and begat sons and daughters. ^12And Arphaxad lived five and thirty years, and begat Salah: ^13and Arphaxad lived after he begat Salah four hundred and three years, and begat sons and daughters. ^14And Salah lived thirty years, and begat Eber: ^15and Salah lived after he begat Eber four hundred and three years, and begat sons and daughters. ^16And Eber lived four and thirty years, and begat Peleg: ^17and Eber lived after he begat Peleg four hundred and thirty years, and begat sons and daughters. ^18And Peleg lived thirty years, and begat Reu: ^19and Peleg lived after he begat Reu two hundred and nine years, and begat sons and daughters. ^20And Reu lived two and thirty years, and begat Serug: ^21and Reu lived after he begat Serug two hundred and seven years, and begat sons and daughters. ^22And Serug lived thirty years, and begat Nahor: ^23and Serug lived after he begat Nahor two hundred years, and begat sons and daughters. ^24And Nahor lived nine and twenty years, and begat Terah: ^25and Nahor lived after he begat Terah an hundred and nineteen years, and begat sons and daughters. ^26And Terah lived seventy years, and begat Abram, Nahor, and Haran.

^27Now these are the generations of Terah: Terah begat Abram, Nahor, and Haran; and Haran begat Lot. ^28And Haran died before his father Terah in the land of his nativity, in Ur of the Chaldees. ^29And Abram and Nahor took them wives: the name of Abram’s wife was Sarai; and the name of Nahor’s wife, Milcah, the daughter of Haran, the father of Milcah, and the father of Iscah. ^30But Sarai was barren; she had no child. ^31And Terah took Abram his son, and Lot the son of Haran his son’s son, and Sarai his daughter in law, his son Abram’s wife; and they went forth with them from Ur of the Chaldees, to go into the land of Canaan; and they came unto Haran, and dwelt there. ^32And the days of Terah were two hundred and five years: and Terah died in Haran.

XII

^1Now the Lord had said unto Abram, Get thee out of thy country, and from thy kindred, and from thy father’s house, unto a land that I will shew thee: ^2and I will make of thee a great nation, and I will bless thee, and make thy name great; and thou shalt be a blessing: ^3and I will bless them that bless thee, and curse him that curseth thee: and in thee shall all families of the earth be blessed. ^4So Abram departed, as the Lord had spoken unto him; and Lot went with him: and Abram was seventy and five years old when he departed out of Haran. ^5And Abram took Sarai his wife, and Lot his brother’s son, and all their substance that they had gathered, and the souls that they had gotten in Haran; and they went forth to go into the land of Canaan; and into the land of Canaan they came.

^6And Abram passed through the land unto the place of Sichem, unto the plain of Moreh. And the Canaanite was then in the land. ^7And the Lord appeared unto Abram, and said, Unto thy seed will I give this land: and there builded he an altar unto the Lord, who appeared unto him. ^8And he removed from thence unto a mountain on the east of Bethel, and pitched his tent, having Bethel on the west, and Hai on the east: and there he builded an altar unto the Lord, and called upon the name of the Lord. ^9And Abram journeyed, going on still toward the south.

^10And there was a famine in the land: and Abram went down into Egypt to sojourn there; for the famine was grievous in the land. ^11And it came to pass, when he was come near to enter into Egypt, that he said unto Sarai his wife, Behold now, I know that thou art a fair woman to look upon: ^12therefore it shall come to pass, when the Egyptians shall see thee, that they shall say, This is his wife: and they will kill me, but they will save thee alive. ^13Say, I pray thee, thou art my sister: that it may be well with me for thy sake; and my soul shall live because of thee.

^14And it came to pass, that, when Abram was come into Egypt, the Egyptians beheld the woman that she was very fair. ^15The princes also of Pharaoh saw her, and commended her before Pharaoh: and the woman was taken into Pharaoh’s house. ^16And he entreated Abram well for her sake: and he had sheep, and oxen, and he asses, and menservants, and maidservants, and she asses, and camels. ^17And the Lord plagued Pharaoh and his house with great plagues because of Sarai Abram’s wife. ^18And Pharaoh called Abram and said, What is this that thou hast done unto me? why didst thou not tell me that she was thy wife? ^19Why saidst thou, She is my sister? so I might have taken her to me to wife: now therefore behold thy wife, take her, and go thy way. ^20And Pharaoh commanded his men concerning him: and they sent him away, and his wife, and all that he had.

XIII

^1And Abram went up out of Egypt, he, and his wife, and all that he had, and Lot with him, into the south. ^2And Abram was very rich in cattle, in silver, and in gold. ^3And he went on his journeys from the south even to Bethel, unto the place where his tent had been at the beginning, between Bethel and Hai; ^4unto the place of the altar, which he had make there at the first: and there Abram called on the name of the Lord.

^5And Lot also, which went with Abram, had flocks, and herds, and tents. ^6And the land was not able to bear them, that they might dwell together: for their substance was great, so that they could not dwell together. ^7And there was a strife between the herdmen of Abram’s cattle and the herdmen of Lot’s cattle: and the Canaanite and the Perizzite dwelled then in the land. ^8And Abram said unto Lot, Let there be no strife, I pray thee, between me and thee, and between my herdmen and thy herdmen; for we be brethren. ^9Is not the whole land before thee? separate thyself, I pray thee, from me: if thou wilt take the left hand, then I will go to the right; or if thou depart to the right hand, then I will go to the left. ^10And Lot lifted up his eyes, and beheld all the plain of Jordan, that it was well watered every where, before the Lord destroyed Sodom and Gomorrah, even as the garden of the Lord, like the land of Egypt, as thou comest unto Zoar. ^11Then Lot chose him all the plain of Jordan; and Lot journeyed east: and they separated themselves the one from the other. ^12Abram dwelled in the land of Canaan, and Lot dwelled in the cities of the plain, and pitched his tent toward Sodom. ^13But the men of Sodom were wicked and sinners before the Lord exceedingly.

^14And the Lord said unto Abram, after that Lot was separated from him, Lift up now thine eyes, and look from the place where thou art northward, and southward, and eastward, and westward: ^15for all the land which thou seest, to thee will I give it, and to thy seed for ever. ^16And I will make thy seed as the dust of the earth: so that if a man can number the dust of the earth, then shall thy seed also be numbered. ^17Arise, walk through the land in the length of it and in the breadth of it; for I will give it unto thee. ^18Then Abram removed his tent, and came and dwelt in the plain of Mamre, which is in Hebron, and built there an altar unto the Lord.

XIV

^1And it came to pass in the days of Amraphel king of Shinar, Arioch king of Ellasar, Chedorlaomer king of Elam, and Tidal king of nations; ^2that these made war with Bera king of Sodom, and with Birsha king of Gomorrah, Shinab king of Admah, and Shemeber king of Zeboiim, and the king of Bela, which is Zoar. ^3All these were joined together in the vale of Siddim, which is the salt sea. ^4Twelve years they served Chedorlaomer, and in the thirteenth year they rebelled. ^5And in the fourteenth year came Chedorlaomer, and the kings that were with him, and smote the Rephaims in Ashteroth Karnaim, and the Zuzims in Ham, and the Emins in Shaveh Kiriathaim, ^6and the Horites in their mount Seir, unto Elparan, which is by the wilderness. ^7And they returned, and came to Enmishpat, which is Kadesh, and smote all the country of the Amalekites, and also the Amorites, that dwelt in Hazezontamar. ^8And there went out the king of Sodom, and the king of Gomorrah, and the king of Admah, and the king of Zeboiim, and the king of Bela (the same is Zoar;) and they joined battle with them in the vale of Siddim; ^9with Chedorlaomer the king of Elam, and with Tidal king of nations, and Amraphel king of Shinar, and Arioch king of Ellasar; four kings with five. ^10And the vale of Siddim was full of slimepits; and the kings of Sodom and Gomorrah fled, and fell there; and they that remained fled to the mountain. ^11And they took all the goods of Sodom and Gomorrah, and all their victuals, and went their way. ^12And they took Lot, Abram’s brother’s son, who dwelt in Sodom, and his goods, and departed.

^13And there came one that had escaped, and told Abram the Hebrew; for he dwelt in the plain of Mamre the Amorite, brother of Eshcol, and brother of Aner: and these were confederate with Abram. ^14And when Abram heard that his brother was taken captive, he armed his trained servants, born in his own house, three hundred and eighteen, and pursued them unto Dan. ^15And he divided himself against them, he and his servants, by night, and smote them, and pursued them unto Hobah, which is on the left hand of Damascus. ^16And he brought back all the goods, and also brought again his brother Lot, and his goods, and the women also, and the people.

^17And the king of Sodom went out to meet him after his return from the slaughter of Chedorlaomer, and of the kings that were with him, at the valley of Shaveh, which is the king’s dale. ^18And Melchizedek king of Salem brought forth bread and wine: and he was the priest of the most high God. ^19And he blessed him, and said, Blessed be Abram of the most high God, possessor of heaven and earth: ^20and blessed be the most high God, which hath delivered thine enemies into thy hand. And he gave him tithes of all. ^21And the king of Sodom said unto Abram, Give me the persons, and take the goods to thyself. ^22And Abram said to the king of Sodom, I have lift up mine hand unto the Lord, the most high God, the possessor of heaven and earth, ^23that I will not take from a thread even to a shoelatchet, and that I will not take any thing that is thine, lest thou shouldest say, I have made Abram rich: ^24save only that which the young men have eaten, and the portion of the men which went with me, Aner, Eshcol, and Mamre; let them take their portion.

XV

^1After these things the word of the Lord came unto Abram in a vision, saying, Fear not, Abram: I am thy shield, and thy exceeding great reward. ^2And Abram said, Lord God, what wilt thou give me, seeing I go childless, and the steward of my house is this Eliezer of Damascus? ^3And Abram said, Behold, to me thou hast given no seed: and, lo, one born in my house is mine heir. ^4And, behold, the word of the Lord came unto him, saying, This shall not be thine heir; but he that shall come forth out of thine own bowels shall be thine heir. ^5And he brought him forth abroad, and said, Look now toward heaven, and tell the stars, if thou be able to number them: and he said unto him, So shall thy seed be. ^6And he believed in the Lord; and he counted it to him for righteousness. ^7And he said unto him, I am the Lord that brought thee out of Ur of the Chaldees, to give thee this land to inherit it. ^8And he said, Lord God, whereby shall I know that I shall inherit it? ^9And he said unto him, Take me an heifer of three years old, and a she goat of three years old, and a ram of three years old, and a turtledove, and a young pigeon. ^10And he took unto him all these, and divided them in the midst, and laid each piece one against another: but the birds divided he not. ^11And when the fowls came down upon the carcases, Abram drove them away.

^12And when the sun was going down, a deep sleep fell upon Abram; and, lo, an horror of great darkness fell upon him. ^13And he said unto Abram, Know of a surety that thy seed shall be a stranger in a land that is not their’s, and shall serve them; and they shall afflict them four hundred years; ^14and also that nation, whom they shall serve, will I judge: and afterward shall they come out with great substance. ^15And thou shalt go to thy fathers in peace; thou shalt be buried in a good old age. ^16But in the fourth generation they shall come hither again: for the iniquity of the Amorites is not yet full. ^17And it came to pass, that, when the sun went down, and it was dark, behold a smoking furnace, and a burning lamp that passed between those pieces. ^18In the same day the Lord made a covenant with Abram, saying, Unto thy seed have I given this land, from the river of Egypt unto the great river, the river Euphrates: ^19the Kenites, and the Kenizzites, and the Kadmonites, ^20and the Hittites, and the Perizzites, and the Rephaims, ^21and the Amorites, and the Canaanites, and the Girgashites, and the Jebusites.

XVI

^1Now Sarai Abram’s wife bare him no children: and she had an handmaid, an Egyptian, whose name was Hagar. ^2And Sarai said unto Abram, Behold now, the Lord hath restrained me from bearing: I pray thee, go in unto my maid; it may be that I may obtain children by her. And Abram hearkened to the voice of Sarai. ^3And Sarai Abram’s wife took Hagar her maid the Egyptian, after Abram had dwelt ten years in the land of Canaan, and gave her to her husband Abram to be his wife.

^4And he went in unto Hagar, and she conceived: and when she saw that she had conceived, her mistress was despised in her eyes. ^5And Sarai said unto Abram, My wrong be upon thee: I have given my maid into thy bosom; and when she saw that she had conceived, I was despised in her eyes: the Lord judge between me and thee. ^6But Abram said unto Sarai, Behold, thy maid is in thine hand; do to her as it pleaseth thee. And when Sarai dealt hardly with her, she fled from her face.

^7And the angel of the Lord found her by a fountain of water in the wilderness, by the fountain in the way to Shur. ^8And he said, Hagar, Sarai’s maid, whence camest thou? and whither wilt thou go? And she said, I flee from the face of my mistress Sarai. ^9And the angel of the Lord said unto her, Return to thy mistress, and submit thyself under her hands. ^10And the angel of the Lord said unto her, I will multiply thy seed exceedingly, that it shall not be numbered for multitude. ^11And the angel of the Lord said unto her, Behold, thou art with child and shalt bear a son, and shalt call his name Ishmael; because the Lord hath heard thy affliction. ^12And he will be a wild man; his hand will be against every man, and every man’s hand against him; and he shall dwell in the presence of all his brethren. ^13And she called the name of the Lord that spake unto her, Thou God seest me: for she said, Have I also here looked after him that seeth me? ^14Wherefore the well was called Beerlahairoi; behold, it is between Kadesh and Bered.

^15And Hagar bare Abram a son: and Abram called his son’s name, which Hagar bare, Ishmael. ^16And Abram was fourscore and six years old, when Hagar bare Ishmael to Abram.

XVII

^1And when Abram was ninety years old and nine, the Lord appeared to Abram, and said unto him, I am the Almighty God; walk before me, and be thou perfect. ^2And I will make my covenant between me and thee, and will multiply thee exceedingly. ^3And Abram fell on his face: and God talked with him, saying, ^4As for me, behold, my covenant is with thee, and thou shalt be a father of many nations. ^5Neither shall thy name any more be called Abram, but thy name shall be Abraham; for a father of many nations have I made thee. ^6And I will make thee exceeding fruitful, and I will make nations of thee, and kings shall come out of thee. ^7And I will establish my covenant between me and thee and thy seed after thee in their generations for an everlasting covenant, to be a God unto thee, and to thy seed after thee. ^8And I will give unto thee, and to thy seed after thee, the land wherein thou art a stranger, all the land of Canaan, for an everlasting possession; and I will be their God.

^9And God said unto Abraham, Thou shalt keep my covenant therefore, thou, and thy seed after thee in their generations. ^10This is my covenant, which ye shall keep, between me and you and thy seed after thee; Every man child among you shall be circumcised. ^11And ye shall circumcise the flesh of your foreskin; and it shall be a token of the covenant betwixt me and you. ^12And he that is eight days old shall be circumcised among you, every man child in your generations, he that is born in the house, or bought with money of any stranger, which is not of thy seed. ^13He that is born in thy house, and he that is bought with thy money, must needs be circumcised: and my covenant shall be in your flesh for an everlasting covenant. ^14And the uncircumcised man child whose flesh of his foreskin is not circumcised, that soul shall be cut off from his people; he hath broken my covenant.

^15And God said unto Abraham, As for Sarai thy wife, thou shalt not call her name Sarai, but Sarah shall her name be. ^16And I will bless her, and give thee a son also of her: yea, I will bless her, and she shall be a mother of nations; kings of people shall be of her. ^17Then Abraham fell upon his face, and laughed, and said in his heart, Shall a child be born unto him that is an hundred years old? and shall Sarah, that is ninety years old, bear? ^18And Abraham said unto God, O that Ishmael might live before thee! ^19And God said, Sarah thy wife shall bear thee a son indeed; and thou shalt call his name Isaac: and I will establish my covenant with him for an everlasting covenant, and with his seed after him. ^20And as for Ishmael, I have heard thee: Behold, I have blessed him, and will make him fruitful, and will multiply him exceedingly; twelve princes shall he beget, and I will make him a great nation. ^21But my covenant will I establish with Isaac, which Sarah shall bear unto thee at this set time in the next year. ^22And he left off talking with him, and God went up from Abraham.

^23And Abraham took Ishmael his son, and all that were born in his house, and all that were bought with his money, every male among the men of Abraham’s house; and circumcised the flesh of their foreskin in the selfsame day, as God had said unto him. ^24And Abraham was ninety years old and nine, when he was circumcised in the flesh of his foreskin. ^25And Ishmael his son was thirteen years old, when he was circumcised in the flesh of his foreskin. ^26In the selfsame day was Abraham circumcised, and Ishmael his son. ^27And all the men of his house, born in the house, and bought with money of the stranger, were circumcised with him.

XVIII

^1And the Lord appeared unto him in the plains of Mamre: and he sat in the tent door in the heat of the day; ^2and he lift up his eyes and looked, and, lo, three men stood by him: and when he saw them, he ran to meet them from the tent door, and bowed himself toward the ground, ^3and said, My Lord, if now I have found favour in thy sight, pass not away, I pray thee, from thy servant: ^4let a little water, I pray you, be fetched, and wash your feet, and rest yourselves under the tree: ^5and I will fetch a morsel of bread, and comfort ye your hearts; after that ye shall pass on: for therefore are ye come to your servant. And they said, So do, as thou hast said. ^6And Abraham hastened into the tent unto Sarah, and said, Make ready quickly three measures of fine meal, knead it, and make cakes upon the hearth. ^7And Abraham ran unto the herd, and fetcht a calf tender and good, and gave it unto a young man; and he hasted to dress it. ^8And he took butter, and milk, and the calf which he had dressed, and set it before them; and he stood by them under the tree, and they did eat.

^9And they said unto him, Where is Sarah thy wife? And he said, Behold, in the tent. ^10And he said, I will certainly return unto thee according to the time of life; and, lo, Sarah thy wife shall have a son. And Sarah heard it in the tent door, which was behind him. ^11Now Abraham and Sarah were old and well stricken in age; and it ceased to be with Sarah after the manner of women. ^12Therefore Sarah laughed within herself, saying, After I am waxed old shall I have pleasure, my lord being old also? ^13And the Lord said unto Abraham, Wherefore did Sarah laugh, saying, Shall I of a surety bear a child, which am old? ^14Is any thing too hard for the Lord? At the time appointed I will return unto thee, according to the time of life, and Sarah shall have a son. ^15Then Sarah denied, saying, I laughed not; for she was afraid. And he said, Nay; but thou didst laugh.

^16And the men rose up from thence, and looked toward Sodom: and Abraham went with them to bring them on the way. ^17And the Lord said, Shall I hide from Abraham that thing which I do; ^18seeing that Abraham shall surely become a great and mighty nation, and all the nations of the earth shall be blessed in him? ^19For I know him, that he will command his children and his household after him, and they shall keep the way of the Lord, to do justice and judgment; that the Lord may bring upon Abraham that which he hath spoken of him. ^20And the Lord said, Because the cry of Sodom and Gomorrah is great, and because their sin is very grievous; ^21I will go down now, and see whether they have done altogether according to the cry of it, which is come unto me; and if not, I will know. ^22And the men turned their faces from thence, and went toward Sodom: but Abraham stood yet before the Lord.

^23And Abraham drew near, and said, Wilt thou also destroy the righteous with the wicked? ^24Peradventure there be fifty righteous within the city: wilt thou also destroy and not spare the place for the fifty righteous that are therein? ^25That be far from thee to do after this manner, to slay the righteous with the wicked: and that the righteous should be as the wicked, that be far from thee: Shall not the Judge of all the earth do right? ^26And the Lord said, If I find in Sodom fifty righteous within the city, then I will spare all the place for their sakes. ^27And Abraham answered and said, Behold now, I have taken upon me to speak unto the Lord, which am but dust and ashes: ^28peradventure there shall lack five of the fifty righteous: wilt thou destroy all the city for lack of five? And he said, If I find there forty and five, I will not destroy it. ^29And he spake unto him yet again, and said, Peradventure there shall be forty found there. And he said, I will not do it for forty’s sake. ^30And he said unto him, Oh let not the Lord be angry, and I will speak: Peradventure there shall thirty be found there. And he said, I will not do it, if I find thirty there. ^31And he said, Behold now, I have taken upon me to speak unto the Lord: Peradventure there shall be twenty found there. And he said, I will not destroy it for twenty’s sake. ^32And he said, Oh let not the Lord be angry, and I will speak yet but this once: Peradventure ten shall be found there. And he said, I will not destroy it for ten’s sake. ^33And the Lord went his way, as soon as he had left communing with Abraham: and Abraham returned unto his place.

XIX

^1And there came two angels to Sodom at even; and Lot sat in the gate of Sodom: and Lot seeing them rose up to meet them; and he bowed himself with his face toward the ground; ^2and he said, Behold now, my lords, turn in, I pray you, into your servant’s house, and tarry all night, and wash your feet, and ye shall rise up early, and go on your ways. And they said, Nay; but we will abide in the street all night. ^3And he pressed upon them greatly; and they turned in unto him, and entered into his house; and he made them a feast, and did bake unleavened bread, and they did eat.

^4But before they lay down, the men of the city, even the men of Sodom, compassed the house round, both old and young, all the people from every quarter: ^5and they called unto Lot, and said unto him, Where are the men which came in to thee this night? bring them out unto us, that we may know them. ^6And Lot went out at the door unto them, and shut the door after him, ^7and said, I pray you, brethren, do not so wickedly. ^8Behold now, I have two daughters which have not known man; let me, I pray you, bring them out unto you, and do ye to them as is good in your eyes: only unto these men do nothing; for therefore came they under the shadow of my roof. ^9And they said, Stand back. And they said again, This one fellow came in to sojourn, and he will needs be a judge: now will we deal worse with thee, than with them. And they pressed sore upon the man, even Lot, and came near to break the door. ^10But the men put forth their hand, and pulled Lot into the house to them, and shut to the door. ^11And they smote the men that were at the door of the house with blindness, both small and great: so that they wearied themselves to find the door.

^12And the men said unto Lot, Hast thou here any besides? son in law, and thy sons, and thy daughters, and whatsoever thou hast in the city, bring them out of this place: ^13for we will destroy this place, because the cry of them is waxen great before the face of the Lord; and the Lord hath sent us to destroy it. ^14And Lot went out, and spake unto his sons in law, which married his daughters, and said, Up, get you out of this place; for the Lord will destroy this city. But he seemed as one that mocked unto his sons in law.

^15And when the morning arose, then the angels hastened Lot, saying, Arise, take thy wife, and thy two daughters, which are here; lest thou be consumed in the iniquity of the city. ^16And while he lingered, the men laid hold upon his hand, and upon the hand of his wife, and upon the hand of his two daughters; the Lord being merciful unto him: and they brought him forth, and set him without the city.

^17And it came to pass, when they had brought them forth abroad, that he said, Escape for thy life; look not behind thee, neither stay thou in all the plain; escape to the mountain, lest thou be consumed. ^18And Lot said unto them, Oh, not so, my Lord: ^19behold now, thy servant hath found grace in thy sight, and thou hast magnified thy mercy, which thou hast shewed unto me in saving my life; and I cannot escape to the mountain, lest some evil take me, and I die: ^20behold now, this city is near to flee unto, and it is a little one: Oh, let me escape thither, (is it not a little one?) and my soul shall live. ^21And he said unto him, See, I have accepted thee concerning this thing also, that I will not overthrow this city, for the which thou hast spoken. ^22Haste thee, escape thither; for I cannot do anything till thou be come thither. Therefore the name of the city was called Zoar.

^23The sun was risen upon the earth when Lot entered into Zoar. ^24Then the Lord rained upon Sodom and upon Gomorrah brimstone and fire from the Lord out of heaven; ^25and he overthrew those cities, and all the plain, and all the inhabitants of the cities, and that which grew upon the ground. ^26But his wife looked back from behind him, and she became a pillar of salt. ^27And Abraham gat up early in the morning to the place where he stood before the Lord: ^28and he looked toward Sodom and Gomorrah, and toward all the land of the plain, and beheld, and, lo, the smoke of the country went up as the smoke of a furnace.

^29And it came to pass, when God destroyed the cities of the plain, that God remembered Abraham, and sent Lot out of the midst of the overthrow, when he overthrew the cities in the which Lot dwelt.

^30And Lot went up out of Zoar, and dwelt in the mountain, and his two daughters with him; for he feared to dwell in Zoar: and he dwelt in a cave, he and his two daughters. ^31And the firstborn said unto the younger, Our father is old, and there is not a man in the earth to come in unto us after the manner of all the earth: ^32come, let us make our father drink wine, and we will lie with him, that we may preserve seed of our father. ^33And they made their father drink wine that night: and the firstborn went in, and lay with her father; and he perceived not when she lay down, nor when she arose. ^34And it came to pass on the morrow, that the firstborn said unto the younger, Behold, I lay yesternight with my father: let us make him drink wine this night also; and go thou in, and lie with him, that we may preserve seed of our father. ^35And they made their father drink wine that night also: and the younger arose, and lay with him; and he perceived not when she lay down, nor when she arose. ^36Thus were both the daughters of Lot with child by their father. ^37And the first born bare a son, and called his name Moab: the same is the father of the Moabites unto this day. ^38And the younger, she also bare a son, and called his name Benammi: the same is the father of the children of Ammon unto this day.

XX

^1And Abraham journeyed from thence toward the south country, and dwelled between Kadesh and Shur, and sojourned in Gerar. ^2And Abraham said of Sarah his wife, She is my sister: and Abimelech king of Gerar sent, and took Sarah. ^3But God came to Abimelech in a dream by night, and said to him, Behold, thou art but a dead man, for the woman which thou hast taken; for she is a man’s wife. ^4But Abimelech had not come near her: and he said, Lord, wilt thou slay also a righteous nation? ^5Said he not unto me, She is my sister? and she, even she herself said, He is my brother: in the integrity of my heart and innocency of my hands have I done this. ^6And God said unto him in a dream, Yea, I know that thou didst this in the integrity of thy heart; for I also withheld thee from sinning against me: therefore suffered I thee not to touch her. ^7Now therefore restore the man his wife; for he is a prophet, and he shall pray for thee, and thou shalt live: and if thou restore her not, know thou that thou shalt surely die, thou, and all that are thine.

^8Therefore Abimelech rose early in the morning, and called all his servants, and told all these things in their ears: and the men were sore afraid. ^9Then Abimelech called Abraham, and said unto him, What hast thou done unto us? and what have I offended thee, that thou hast brought on me and on my kingdom a great sin? thou hast done deeds unto me that ought not to be done. ^10And Abimelech said unto Abraham, What sawest thou, that thou hast done this thing? ^11And Abraham said, Because I thought, Surely the fear of God is not in this place; and they will slay me for my wife’s sake. ^12And yet indeed she is my sister; she is the daughter of my father, but not the daughter of my mother; and she became my wife. ^13And it came to pass, when God caused me to wander from my father’s house, that I said unto her, This is thy kindness which thou shalt shew unto me; at every place whither we shall come, say of me, He is my brother. ^14And Abimelech took sheep, and oxen, and menservants, and womenservants, and gave them unto Abraham, and restored him Sarah his wife. ^15And Abimelech said, Behold, my land is before thee: dwell where it pleaseth thee. ^16And unto Sarah he said, Behold, I have given thy brother a thousand pieces of silver: behold, he is to thee a covering of the eyes, unto all that are with thee, and with all other: thus she was reproved.

^17So Abraham prayed unto God: and God healed Abimelech, and his wife, and his maidservants; and they bare children. ^18For the Lord had fast closed up all the wombs of the house of Abimelech, because of Sarah Abraham’s wife.

XXI

^1And the Lord visited Sarah as he had said, and the Lord did unto Sarah as he had spoken. ^2For Sarah conceived, and bare Abraham a son in his old age, at the set time of which God had spoken to him. ^3And Abraham called the name of his son that was born unto him, whom Sarah bare to him, Isaac. ^4And Abraham circumcised his son Isaac being eight days old, as God had commanded him. ^5And Abraham was an hundred years old, when his son Isaac was born unto him. ^6And Sarah said, God hath made me to laugh, so that all that hear will laugh with me. ^7And she said, Who would have said unto Abraham, that Sarah should have given children suck? for I have born him a son in his old age.

^8And the child grew, and was weaned: and Abraham made a great feast the same day that Isaac was weaned. ^9And Sarah saw the son of Hagar the Egyptian, which she had born unto Abraham, mocking. ^10Wherefore she said unto Abraham, Cast out this bondwoman and her son: for the son of this bondwoman shall not be heir with my son, even with Isaac. ^11And the thing was very grievous in Abraham’s sight because of his son. ^12And God said unto Abraham, Let it not be grievous in thy sight because of the lad, and because of thy bondwoman; in all that Sarah hath said unto thee, hearken unto her voice; for in Isaac shall thy seed be called. ^13And also of the son of the bondwoman will I make a nation, because he is thy seed.

^14And Abraham rose up early in the morning, and took bread, and a bottle of water, and gave it unto Hagar, putting it on her shoulder, and the child, and sent her away: and she departed, and wandered in the wilderness of Beersheba. ^15And the water was spent in the bottle, and she cast the child under one of the shrubs. ^16And she went, and sat her down over against him a good way off, as it were a bow shot: for she said, Let me not see the death of the child. And she sat over against him, and lift up her voice, and wept. ^17And God heard the voice of the lad; and the angel of God called to Hagar out of heaven, and said unto her, What aileth thee, Hagar? fear not; for God hath heard the voice of the lad where he is. ^18Arise, lift up the lad, and hold him in thine hand; for I will make him a great nation. ^19And God opened her eyes, and she saw a well of water; and she went, and filled the bottle with water, and gave the lad drink. ^20And God was with the lad; and he grew, and dwelt in the wilderness, and became an archer. ^21And he dwelt in the wilderness of Paran: and his mother took him a wife out of the land of Egypt.

^22And it came to pass at that time, that Abimelech and Phichol the chief captain of his host spake unto Abraham, saying, God is with thee in all that thou doest: ^23now therefore swear unto me here by God that thou wilt not deal falsely with me, nor with my son, nor with my son’s son: but according to the kindness that I have done unto thee, thou shalt do unto me, and to the land wherein thou hast sojourned. ^24And Abraham said, I will swear. ^25And Abraham reproved Abimelech because of a well of water, which Abimelech’s servants had violently taken away. ^26And Abimelech said, I wot not who hath done this thing; neither didst thou tell me, neither yet heard I of it, but to day. ^27And Abraham took sheep and oxen, and gave them unto Abimelech; and both of them made a covenant. ^28And Abraham set seven ewe lambs of the flock by themselves. ^29And Abimelech said unto Abraham, What mean these seven ewe lambs which thou hast set by themselves? ^30And he said, For these seven ewe lambs shalt thou take of my hand, that they may be a witness unto me, that I have digged this well. ^31Wherefore he called that place Beersheba; because there they sware both of them. ^32Thus they made a covenant at Beersheba: then Abimelech rose up, and Phichol the chief captain of his host, and they returned into the land of the Philistines.

^33And Abraham planted a grove in Beersheba, and called there on the name of the Lord, the everlasting God. ^34And Abraham sojourned in the Philistines’ land many days.

XXII

^1And it came to pass after these things, that God did tempt Abraham, and said unto him, Abraham: and he said, Behold, here I am. ^2And he said, Take now thy son, thine only son Isaac, whom thou lovest, and get thee into the land of Moriah; and offer him there for a burnt offering upon one of the mountains which I will tell thee of.

^3And Abraham rose up early in the morning, and saddled his ass, and took two of his young men with him, and Isaac his son, and clave the wood for the burnt offering, and rose up, and went unto the place of which God had told him. ^4Then on the third day Abraham lifted up his eyes, and saw the place afar off. ^5And Abraham said unto his young men, Abide ye here with the ass; and I and the lad will go yonder and worship, and come again to you. ^6And Abraham took the wood of the burnt offering, and laid it upon Isaac his son; and he took the fire in his hand, and a knife; and they went both of them together. ^7And Isaac spake unto Abraham his father, and said, My father: and he said, Here am I, my son. And he said, Behold the fire and the wood: but where is the lamb for a burnt offering? ^8and Abraham said, My son, God will provide himself a lamb for a burnt offering: so they went both of them together.

^9And they came to the place which God had told him of; and Abraham built an altar there, and laid the wood in order, and bound Isaac his son, and laid him on the altar upon the wood. ^10And Abraham stretched forth his hand, and took the knife to slay his son. ^11And the angel of the Lord called unto him out of heaven, and said, Abraham, Abraham: and he said, Here am I. ^12And he said, Lay not thine hand upon the lad, neither do thou any thing unto him: for now I know that thou fearest God, seeing thou hast not withheld thy son, thine only son from me. ^13And Abraham lifted up his eyes, and looked, and behold behind him a ram caught in a thicket by his horns: and Abraham went and took the ram, and offered him up for a burnt offering in the stead of his son. ^14And Abraham called the name of that place Jehovahjireh: as it is said to this day, In the mount of the Lord it shall be seen.

^15And the angel of the Lord called unto Abraham out of heaven the second time, ^16and said, By myself have I sworn, saith the Lord, for because thou hast done this thing, and hast not withheld thy son, thine only son: ^17that in blessing I will bless thee, and in multiplying I will multiply thy seed as the stars of the heaven, and as the sand which is upon the sea shore; and thy seed shall possess the gate of his enemies; ^18and in thy seed shall all the nations of the earth be blessed; because thou hast obeyed my voice. ^19So Abraham returned unto his young men, and they rose up and went together to Beersheba; and Abraham dwelt at Beersheba.

^20And it came to pass after these things, that it was told Abraham, saying, Behold, Milcah, she hath also born children unto thy brother Nahor; ^21Huz his firstborn, and Buz his brother, and Kemuel the father of Aram, ^22and Chesed, and Hazo, and Pildash, and Jidlaph, and Bethuel. ^23And Bethuel begat Rebekah: these eight Milcah did bear to Nahor, Abraham’s brother. ^24And his concubine, whose name was Reumah, she bare also Tebah, and Gaham, and Thahash, and Maachah.

XXIII

^1And Sarah was an hundred and seven and twenty years old: these were the years of the life of Sarah. ^2And Sarah died in Kirjatharba; the same is Hebron in the land of Canaan: and Abraham came to mourn for Sarah, and to weep for her.

^3And Abraham stood up from before his dead, and spake unto the sons of Heth, saying, ^4I am a stranger and a sojourner with you: give me a possession of a buryingplace with you, that I may bury my dead out of my sight. ^5And the children of Heth answered Abraham, saying unto him, ^6Hear us, my lord: thou art a mighty prince among us: in the choice of our sepulchres bury thy dead; none of us shall withhold from thee his sepulchre, but that thou mayest bury thy dead. ^7And Abraham stood up, and bowed himself to the people of the land, even to the children of Heth. ^8And he communed with them, saying, If it be your mind that I should bury my dead out of my sight; hear me, and intreat for me to Ephron the son of Zohar, ^9that he may give me the cave of Machpelah, which he hath, which is in the end of his field; for as much money as it is worth he shall give it me for a possession of a buryingplace amongst you. ^10And Ephron dwelt among the children of Heth: and Ephron the Hittite answered Abraham in the audience of the children of Heth, even of all that went in at the gate of his city, saying, ^11Nay, my lord, hear me: the field give I thee, and the cave that is therein, I give it thee; in the presence of the sons of my people give I it thee: bury thy dead. ^12And Abraham bowed down himself before the people of the land. ^13And he spake unto Ephron in the audience of the people of the land, saying, But if thou wilt give it, I pray thee, hear me: I will give thee money for the field; take it of me, and I will bury my dead there. ^14And Ephron answered Abraham, saying unto him, ^15My lord, hearken unto me: the land is worth four hundred shekels of silver; what is that betwixt me and thee? bury therefore thy dead. ^16And Abraham hearkened unto Ephron; and Abraham weighed to Ephron the silver, which he had named in the audience of the sons of Heth, four hundred shekels of silver, current money with the merchant.

^17And the field of Ephron which was in Machpelah, which was before Mamre, the field, and the cave which was therein, and all the trees that were in the field, that were in all the borders round about, were made sure ^18unto Abraham for a possession in the presence of the children of Heth, before all that went in at the gate of his city. ^19And after this, Abraham buried Sarah his wife in the cave of the field of Machpelah before Mamre: the same is Hebron in the land of Canaan. ^20And the field, and the cave that is therein, were made sure unto Abraham for a possession of a buryingplace by the sons of Heth.

XXIV

^1And Abraham was old, and well stricken in age: and the Lord had blessed Abraham in all things. ^2And Abraham said unto his eldest servant of his house, that ruled over all that he had, Put, I pray thee, thy hand under my thigh: ^3and I will make thee swear by the Lord, the God of heaven, and the God of the earth, that thou shalt not take a wife unto my son of the daughters of the Canaanites, among whom I dwell: ^4but thou shalt go unto my country, and to my kindred, and take a wife unto my son Isaac. ^5And the servant said unto him, Peradventure the woman will not be willing to follow me unto this land: must I needs bring thy son again unto the land from whence thou camest? ^6And Abraham said unto him, Beware thou that thou bring not my son thither again. ^7The Lord God of heaven, which took me from my father’s house, and from the land of my kindred, and which spake unto me, and that sware unto me, saying, Unto thy seed will I give this land; he shall send his angel before thee, and thou shalt take a wife unto my son from thence. ^8And if the woman will not be willing to follow thee, then thou shalt be clear from this my oath: only bring not my son thither again. ^9And the servant put his hand under the thigh of Abraham his master, and sware to him concerning that matter.

^10And the servant took ten camels of the camels of his master, and departed; for all the goods of his master were in his hand: and he arose, and went to Mesopotamia, unto the city of Nahor. ^11And he made his camels to kneel down without the city by a well of water at the time of the evening, even the time that women go out to draw water. ^12And he said O Lord God of my master Abraham, I pray thee, send me good speed this day, and shew kindness unto my master Abraham. ^13Behold, I stand here by the well of water; and the daughters of the men of the city come out to draw water: ^14and let it come to pass, that the damsel to whom I shall say, Let down thy pitcher, I pray thee, that I may drink; and she shall say, Drink, and I will give thy camels drink also: let the same be she that thou hast appointed for thy servant Isaac; and thereby shall I know that thou hast shewed kindness unto my master.

^15And it came to pass, before he had done speaking, that, behold, Rebekah came out, who was born to Bethuel, son of Milcah, the wife of Nahor, Abraham’s brother, with her pitcher upon her shoulder. ^16And the damsel was very fair to look upon, a virgin, neither had any man known her: and she went down to the well, and filled her pitcher, and came up. ^17And the servant ran to meet her, and said, Let me, I pray thee, drink a little water of thy pitcher. ^18And she said, Drink, my lord: and she hasted, and let down her pitcher upon her hand, and gave him drink. ^19And when she had done giving him drink, she said, I will draw water for thy camels also, until they have done drinking. ^20And she hasted, and emptied her pitcher into the trough, and ran again unto the well to draw water, and drew for all his camels. ^21And the man wondering at her held his peace, to wit whether the Lord had made his journey prosperous or not. ^22And it came to pass, as the camels had done drinking, that the man took a golden earring of half a shekel weight, and two bracelets for her hands of ten shekels weight of gold; ^23and said, Whose daughter art thou? tell me, I pray thee: is there room in thy father’s house for us to lodge in? ^24And she said unto him, I am the daughter of Bethuel the son of Milcah, which she bare unto Nahor. ^25She said moreover unto him, We have both straw and provender enough, and room to lodge in. ^26And the man bowed down his head, and worshipped the Lord. ^27And he said, Blessed be the Lord God of my master Abraham, who hath not left destitute my master of his mercy and his truth: I being in the way, the Lord led me to the house of my master’s brethren. ^28And the damsel ran, and told them of her mother’s house these things.

^29And Rebekah had a brother, and his name was Laban: and Laban ran out unto the man, unto the well. ^30And it came to pass, when he saw the earring and bracelets upon his sister’s hands, and when he heard the words of Rebekah his sister, saying, Thus spake the man unto me; that he came unto the man; and, behold, he stood by the camels at the well. ^31And he said, Come in, thou blessed of the Lord; wherefore standest thou without? for I have prepared the house, and room for the camels.

^32And the man came into the house: and he ungirded his camels, and gave straw and provender for the camels, and water to wash his feet, and the men’s feet that were with him. ^33And there was set meat before him to eat: but he said, I will not eat, until I have told mine errand. And he said, Speak on. ^34And he said, I am Abraham’s servant. ^35And the Lord hath blessed my master greatly; and he is become great: and he hath given him flocks, and herds, and silver, and gold, and menservants, and maidservants, and camels, and asses. ^36And Sarah my master’s wife bare a son to my master when she was old: and unto him hath he given all that he hath. ^37And my master made me swear, saying, Thou shalt not take a wife to my son of the daughters of the Canaanites, in whose land I dwell: ^38but thou shalt go unto my father’s house, and to my kindred, and take a wife unto my son. ^39And I said unto my master, Peradventure the woman will not follow me. ^40And he said unto me, The Lord, before whom I walk, will send his angel with thee, and prosper thy way; and thou shalt take a wife for my son of my kindred, and of my father’s house: ^41then shalt thou be clear from this my oath, when thou comest to my kindred; and if they give not thee one, thou shalt be clear from my oath. ^42And I came this day unto the well, and said, O Lord God of my master Abraham, if now thou do prosper my way which I go: ^43behold, I stand by the well of water; and it shall come to pass, that when the virgin cometh forth to draw water, and I say to her, Give me, I pray thee, a little water of thy pitcher to drink; ^44and she say to me, Both drink thou, and I will also draw for thy camels: let the same be the woman whom the Lord hath appointed out for my master’s son. ^45And before I had done speaking in mine heart, behold, Rebekah came forth with her pitcher on her shoulder; and she went down unto the well, and drew water: and I said unto her, Let me drink, I pray thee. ^46And she made haste, and let down her pitcher from her shoulder, and said, Drink, and I will give thy camels drink also: so I drank, and she made the camels drink also. ^47And I asked her, and said, Whose daughter art thou? And she said, the daughter of Bethuel, Nahor’s son, whom Milcah bare unto him: and I put the earring upon her face, and the bracelets upon her hands. ^48And I bowed down my head, and worshipped the Lord, and blessed the Lord God of my master Abraham, which had led me in the right way to take my master’s brother’s daughter unto his son. ^49And now if ye will deal kindly and truly with my master, tell me: and if not, tell me; that I may turn to the right hand, or to the left.

^50Then Laban and Bethuel answered and said, The thing proceedeth from the Lord: we cannot speak unto thee bad or good. ^51Behold, Rebekah is before thee, take her, and go, and let her be thy master’s son’s wife, as the Lord hath spoken. ^52And it came to pass, that, when Abraham’s servant heard their words, he worshipped the Lord, bowing himself to the earth. ^53And the servant brought forth jewels of silver, and jewels of gold, and raiment, and gave them to Rebekah: he gave also to her brother and to her mother precious things. ^54And they did eat and drink, he and the men that were with him, and tarried all night; and they rose up in the morning, and he said, Send me away unto my master. ^55And her brother and her mother said, Let the damsel abide with us a few days, at the least ten; after that she shall go. ^56And he said unto them, Hinder me not, seeing the Lord hath prospered my way; send me away that I may go to my master. ^57And they said, We will call the damsel, and enquire at her mouth. ^58And they called Rebekah, and said unto her, Wilt thou go with this man? And she said, I will go. ^59And they sent away Rebekah their sister, and her nurse, and Abraham’s servant, and his men. ^60And they blessed Rebekah, and said unto her, Thou art our sister, be thou the mother of thousands of millions, and let thy seed possess the gate of those which hate them.

^61And Rebekah arose, and her damsels, and they rode upon the camels, and followed the man: and the servant took Rebekah, and went his way. ^62And Isaac came from the way of the well Lahairoi; for he dwelt in the south country. ^63And Isaac went out to meditate in the field at the eventide: and he lifted up his eyes, and saw, and, behold, the camels were coming. ^64And Rebekah lifted up her eyes, and when she saw Isaac, she lighted off the camel. ^65For she had said unto the servant, What man is this that walketh in the field to meet us? And the servant had said, It is my master: therefore she took a vail, and covered herself. ^66And the servant told Isaac all things that he had done. ^67And Isaac brought her into his mother Sarah’s tent, and took Rebekah, and she became his wife; and he loved her: and Isaac was comforted after his mother’s death.

XXV

^1Then again Abraham took a wife, and her name was Keturah. ^2And she bare him Zimran, and Jokshan, and Medan, and Midian, and Ishbak, and Shuah. ^3And Jokshan begat Sheba, and Dedan. And the sons of Dedan were Asshurim, and Letushim, and Leummim. ^4And the sons of Midian; Ephah, and Epher, and Hanoch, and Abidah, and Eldaah. All these were the children of Keturah.

^5And Abraham gave all that he had unto Isaac. ^6But unto the sons of the concubines, which Abraham had, Abraham gave gifts, and sent them away from Isaac his son, while he yet lived, eastward, unto the east country. ^7And these are the days of the years of Abraham’s life which he lived, an hundred threescore and fifteen years. ^8Then Abraham gave up the ghost, and died in a good old age, an old man, and full of years; and was gathered to his people. ^9And his sons Isaac and Ishmael buried him in the cave of Machpelah, in the field of Ephron the son of Zohar the Hittite, which is before Mamre; ^10the field which Abraham purchased of the sons of Heth: there was Abraham buried, and Sarah his wife. ^11And it came to pass after the death of Abraham, that God blessed his son Isaac; and Isaac dwelt by the well Lahairoi.

^12Now these are the generations of Ishmael, Abraham’s son, whom Hagar the Egyptian, Sarah’s handmaid, bare unto Abraham: ^13and these are the names of the sons of Ishmael, by their names, according to their generations: the firstborn of Ishmael, Nebajoth; and Kedar, and Adbeel, and Mibsam, ^14and Mishma, and Dumah, and Massa, ^15Hadar, and Tema, Jetur, Naphish, and Kedemah: ^16these are the sons of Ishmael, and these are their names, by their towns, and by their castles; twelve princes according to their nations. ^17And these are the years of the life of Ishmael, an hundred and thirty and seven years: and he gave up the ghost and died; and was gathered unto his people.

^18And they dwelt from Havilah unto Shur, that is before Egypt, as thou goest toward Assyria: and he died in the presence of all his brethren.

^19And these are the generations of Isaac, Abraham’s son: Abraham begat Isaac: ^20and Isaac was forty years old when he took Rebekah to wife, the daughter of Bethuel the Syrian of Padanaram, the sister to Laban the Syrian. ^21And Isaac intreated the Lord for his wife, because she was barren: and the Lord was intreated of him, and Rebekah his wife conceived. ^22And the children struggled together within her; and she said, If it be so, why am I thus? And she went to enquire of the Lord. ^23And the Lord said unto her,

Two nations are in thy womb,
And two manner of people shall be separated from thy bowels;
And the one people shall be stronger than the other people;
And the elder shall serve the younger.

^24And when her days to be delivered were fulfilled, behold, there were twins in her womb. ^25And the first came out red, all over like an hairy garment; and they called his name Esau. ^26And after that came his brother out, and his hand took hold on Esau’s heel; and his name was called Jacob: and Isaac was threescore years old when she bare them. ^27And the boys grew: and Esau was a cunning hunter, a man of the field; and Jacob was a plain man, dwelling in tents. ^28And Isaac loved Esau, because he did eat of his venison: but Rebekah loved Jacob.

^29And Jacob sod pottage: and Esau came from the field, and he was faint: ^30and Esau said to Jacob, Feed me, I pray thee, with that same red pottage; for I am faint: therefore was his name called Edom. ^31And Jacob said, Sell me this day thy birthright. ^32And Esau said, Behold, I am at the point to die: and what profit shall this birthright do to me? ^33And Jacob said, Swear to me this day; and he sware unto him: and he sold his birthright unto Jacob. ^34Then Jacob gave Esau bread and pottage of lentiles; and he did eat and drink, and rose up, and went his way: thus Esau despised his birthright.

XXVI

^1And there was a famine in the land, beside the first famine that was in the days of Abraham. And Isaac went unto Abimelech king of the Philistines unto Gerar. ^2And the Lord appeared unto him, and said, Go not down into Egypt; dwell in the land which I shall tell thee of: ^3sojourn in this land, and I will be with thee, and will bless thee; for unto thee, and unto thy seed, I will give all these countries, and I will perform the oath which I sware unto Abraham thy father; ^4and I will make thy seed to multiply as the stars of heaven, and will give unto thy seed all these countries; and in thy seed shall all the nations of the earth be blessed; ^5because that Abraham obeyed my voice, and kept my charge, my commandments, my statutes, and my laws.

^6And Isaac dwelt in Gerar: ^7and the men of the place asked him of his wife; and he said, She is my sister: for he feared to say, She is my wife; lest, said he, the men of the place should kill me for Rebekah; because she was fair to look upon. ^8And it came to pass, when he had been there a long time, that Abimelech king of the Philistines looked out at a window, and saw, and, behold, Isaac was sporting with Rebekah his wife. ^9And Abimelech called Isaac, and said, Behold, of a surety she is thy wife; and how saidst thou, She is my sister? And Isaac said unto him, Because I said, Lest I die for her. ^10And Abimelech said, What is this thou hast done unto us? one of the people might lightly have lien with thy wife, and thou shouldest have brought guiltiness upon us. ^11And Abimelech charged all his people, saying, He that toucheth this man or his wife shall surely be put to death. ^12Then Isaac sowed in that land, and received in the same year an hundredfold: and the Lord blessed him. ^13And the man waxed great, and went forward, and grew until he became very great: ^14for he had possession of flocks, and possession of herds, and great store of servants: and the Philistines envied him. ^15For all the wells which his father’s servants had digged in the days of Abraham his father, the Philistines had stopped them, and filled them with earth. ^16And Abimelech said unto Isaac, Go from us; for thou art much mightier than we.

^17And Isaac departed thence, and pitched his tent in the valley of Gerar, and dwelt there. ^18And Isaac digged again the wells of water, which they had digged in the days of Abraham his father; for the Philistines had stopped them after the death of Abraham: and he called their names after the names by which his father had called them. ^19And Isaac’s servants digged in the valley, and found there a well of springing water. ^20And the herdmen of Gerar did strive with Isaac’s herdmen, saying, The water is ours: and he called the name of the well Esek; because they strove with him. ^21And they digged another well, and strove for that also: and he called the name of it Sitnah. ^22And he removed from thence, and digged another well; and for that they strove not: and he called the name of it Rehoboth; and he said, For now the Lord hath made room for us, and we shall be fruitful in the land.

^23And he went up from thence to Beersheba. ^24And the Lord appeared unto him the same night, and said, I am the God of Abraham thy father: fear not, for I am with thee, and will bless thee, and multiply thy seed for my servant Abraham’s sake. ^25And he builded an altar there, and called upon the name of the Lord, and pitched his tent there: and there Isaac’s servants digged a well.

^26Then Abimelech went to him from Gerar, and Ahuzzath one of his friends, and Phichol the chief captain of his army. ^27And Isaac said unto them, Wherefore come ye to me, seeing ye hate me, and have sent me away from you? ^28And they said, We saw certainly that the Lord was with thee: and we said, Let there be now an oath betwixt us, even betwixt us and thee, and let us make a covenant with thee; ^29that thou wilt do us no hurt, as we have not touched thee, and as we have done unto thee nothing but good, and have sent thee away in peace: thou art now the blessed of the Lord. ^30And he made them a feast, and they did eat and drink. ^31And they rose up betimes in the morning, and sware one to another: and Isaac sent them away, and they departed from him in peace. ^32And it came to pass the same day, that Isaac’s servants came, and told him concerning the well which they had digged, and said unto him, We have found water. ^33And he called it Shebah: therefore the name of the city is Beersheba unto this day.

^34And Esau was forty years old when he took to wife Judith the daughter of Beeri the Hittite, and Bashemath the daughter of Elon the Hittite: ^35which were a grief of mind unto Isaac and to Rebekah.

XXVII

^1And it came to pass, that when Isaac was old, and his eyes were dim, so that he could not see, he called Esau his eldest son, and said unto him, My son: and he said unto him, Behold, here am I. ^2And he said, Behold now, I am old, I know not the day of my death: ^3now therefore take, I pray thee, thy weapons, thy quiver and thy bow, and go out to the field, and take me some venison; ^4and make me savoury meat, such as I love, and bring it to me, that I may eat; that my soul may bless thee before I die. ^5And Rebekah heard when Isaac spake to Esau his son. And Esau went to the field to hunt for venison, and to bring it.

^6And Rebekah spake unto Jacob her son, saying, Behold, I heard thy father speak unto Esau thy brother, saying, ^7Bring me venison, and make me savoury meat, that I may eat, and bless thee before the Lord before my death. ^8Now therefore, my son, obey my voice according to that which I command thee. ^9Go now to the flock, and fetch me from thence two good kids of the goats; and I will make them savoury meat for thy father, such as he loveth: ^10and thou shalt bring it to thy father, that he may eat, and that he may bless thee before his death. ^11And Jacob said to Rebekah his mother, Behold, Esau my brother is a hairy man, and I am a smooth man: ^12my father peradventure will feel me, and I shall seem to him as a deceiver; and I shall bring a curse upon me, and not a blessing. ^13And his mother said unto him, Upon me be thy curse, my son: only obey my voice, and go fetch me them. ^14And he went, and fetched, and brought them to his mother: and his mother made savoury meat, such as his father loved. ^15And Rebekah took goodly raiment of her eldest son Esau, which were with her in the house, and put them upon Jacob her younger son: ^16and she put the skins of the kids of the goats upon his hands, and upon the smooth of his neck: ^17and she gave the savoury meat and the bread, which she had prepared, into the hand of her son Jacob.

^18And he came unto his father, and said, My father: and he said, Here am I; who art thou, my son? ^19And Jacob said unto his father, I am Esau thy first born; I have done according as thou badest me: arise, I pray thee, sit and eat of my venison, that thy soul may bless me. ^20And Isaac said unto his son, How is it that thou hast found it so quickly, my son? And he said, Because the Lord thy God brought it to me. ^21And Isaac said unto Jacob, Come near, I pray thee, that I may feel thee, my son, whether thou be my very son Esau or not. ^22And Jacob went near unto Isaac his father; and he felt him, and said, The voice is Jacob’s voice, but the hands are the hands of Esau. ^23And he discerned him not, because his hands were hairy, as his brother Esau’s hands: so he blessed him. ^24And he said, Art thou my very son Esau? And he said, I am. ^25And he said, Bring it near to me, and I will eat of my son’s venison, that my soul may bless thee. And he brought it near to him, and he did eat: and he brought him wine and he drank. ^26And his father Isaac said unto him, Come near now, and kiss me, my son. ^27And he came near, and kissed him: and he smelled the smell of his raiment, and blessed him, and said,

See, the smell of my son
Is as the smell of a field which the Lord hath blessed:
^28Therefore God give thee of the dew of heaven,
And the fatness of the earth,
And plenty of corn and wine:
^29Let people serve thee,
And nations bow down to thee:
Be lord over thy brethren,
And let thy mother’s sons bow down to thee:
Cursed be every one that curseth thee,
And blessed be he that blesseth thee.

^30And it came to pass, as soon as Isaac had made an end of blessing Jacob, and Jacob was yet scarce gone out from the presence of Isaac his father, that Esau his brother came in from his hunting. ^31And he also had made savoury meat, and brought it unto his father, and said unto his father, Let my father arise, and eat of his son’s venison, that thy soul may bless me. ^32And Isaac his father said unto him, Who art thou? And he said, I am thy son, thy firstborn Esau. ^33And Isaac trembled very exceedingly, and said, Who? where is he that hath taken venison, and brought it me, and I have eaten of all before thou camest, and have blessed him? yea, and he shall be blessed. ^34And when Esau heard the words of his father, he cried with a great and exceeding bitter cry, and said unto his father, Bless me, even me also, O my father. ^35And he said, Thy brother came with subtilty, and hath taken away thy blessing. ^36And he said, Is not he rightly named Jacob? for he hath supplanted me these two times: he took away my birthright; and, behold, now he hath taken away my blessing. And he said, Hast thou not reserved a blessing for me? ^37And Isaac answered and said unto Esau, Behold, I have made him thy lord, and all his brethren have I given to him for servants; and with corn and wine have I sustained him: and what shall I do now unto thee, my son? ^38And Esau said unto his father, Hast thou but one blessing, my father? bless me, even me also, O my father. And Esau lifted up his voice, and wept. ^39And Isaac his father answered and said unto him,

Behold, thy dwelling shall be the fatness of the earth,
And of the dew of heaven from above;
^40And by thy sword shalt thou live, and shalt serve thy brother;
And it shall come to pass when thou shalt have the dominion,
That thou shalt break his yoke from off thy neck.

^41And Esau hated Jacob because of the blessing wherewith his father blessed him: and Esau said in his heart, The days of mourning for my father are at hand; then will I slay my brother Jacob. ^42And these words of Esau her elder son were told to Rebekah: and she sent and called Jacob her younger son, and said unto him, Behold, thy brother Esau, as touching thee, doth comfort himself, purposing to kill thee. ^43Now therefore, my son, obey my voice; arise, flee thou to Laban my brother to Haran; ^44and tarry with him a few days, until thy brother’s fury turn away; ^45until thy brother’s anger turn away from thee, and he forget that which thou hast done to him: then I will send, and fetch thee from thence: why should I be deprived also of you both in one day?

^46And Rebekah said to Isaac, I am weary of my life because of the daughters of Heth: if Jacob take a wife of the daughters of Heth, such as these which are of the daughters of the land, what good shall my life do me?

XXVIII

^1And Isaac called Jacob, and blessed him, and charged him, and said unto him, Thou shalt not take a wife of the daughters of Canaan. ^2Arise, go to Padanaram, to the house of Bethuel thy mother’s father; and take thee a wife from thence of the daughers of Laban thy mother’s brother. ^3And God Almighty bless thee, and make thee fruitful, and multiply thee, that thou mayest be a multitude of people; ^4and give thee the blessing of Abraham, to thee, and to thy seed with thee; that thou mayest inherit the land wherein thou art a stranger, which God gave unto Abraham. ^5And Isaac sent away Jacob: and he went to Padanaram unto Laban, son of Bethuel the Syrian, the brother of Rebekah, Jacob’s and Esau’s mother.

^6When Esau saw that Isaac had blessed Jacob, and sent him away to Padanaram, to take him a wife from thence; and that as he blessed him he gave him a charge, saying, Thou shalt not take a wife of the daughers of Canaan; ^7and that Jacob obeyed his father and his mother, and was gone to Padanaram; ^8and Esau seeing that the daughters of Canaan pleased not Isaac his father; ^9then went Esau unto Ishmael, and took unto the wives which he had Mahalath the daughter of Ishmael Abraham’s son, the sister of Nebajoth, to be his wife.

^10And Jacob went out from Beersheba, and went toward Haran. ^11And he lighted upon a certain place, and tarried there all night, because the sun was set; and he took of the stones of that place, and put them for his pillows, and lay down in that place to sleep. ^12And he dreamed, and behold a ladder set up on the earth, and the top of it reached to heaven: and behold the angels of God ascending and descending on it. ^13And, behold, the Lord stood above it, and said, I am the Lord God of Abraham thy father, and the God of Isaac: the land whereon thou liest, to thee will I give it, and to thy seed; ^14and thy seed shall be as the dust of the earth, and thou shalt spread abroad to the west, and to the east, and to the north, and to the south: and in thee and in thy seed shall all the families of the earth be blessed. ^15And, behold, I am with thee, and will keep thee in all places whither thou goest, and will bring thee again into this land; for I will not leave thee, until I have done that which I have spoken to thee of. ^16And Jacob awaked out of his sleep, and he said, Surely the Lord is in this place; and I knew it not. ^17And he was afraid, and said, How dreadful is this place! this is none other but the house of God, and this is the gate of heaven.

^18And Jacob rose up early in the morning, and took the stone that he had put for his pillows, and set it up for a pillar, and poured oil upon the top of it. ^19And he called the name of that place Bethel: but the name of that city was called Luz at the first. ^20And Jacob vowed a vow, saying, If God will be with me, and will keep me in this way that I go, and will give me bread to eat, and raiment to put on, ^21so that I come again to my father’s house in peace; then shall the Lord be my God: ^22and this stone, which I have set for a pillar, shall be God’s house: and of all that thou shalt give me I will surely give the tenth unto thee.

XXIX

^1Then Jacob went on his journey, and came into the land of the people of the east. ^2And he looked, and behold a well in the field, and, lo, there were three flocks of sheep lying by it; for out of that well they watered the flocks: and a great stone was upon the well’s mouth. ^3And thither were all the flocks gathered: and they rolled the stone from the well’s mouth, and watered the sheep, and put the stone again upon the well’s mouth in his place. ^4And Jacob said unto them, My brethren, whence be ye? And they said, Of Haran are we. ^5And he said unto them, Know ye Laban the son of Nahor? And they said, We know him. ^6And he said unto them, Is he well? And they said, He is well: and, behold, Rachel his daughter cometh with the sheep. ^7And he said, Lo, it is yet high day, neither is it time that the cattle should be gathered together: water ye the sheep, and go and feed them. ^8And they said, We cannot, until all the flocks be gathered together, and till they roll the stone from the well’s mouth; then we water the sheep.

^9And while he yet spake with them, Rachel came with her father’s sheep; for she kept them. ^10And it came to pass, when Jacob saw Rachel the daughter of Laban his mother’s brother, and the sheep of Laban his mother’s brother, that Jacob went near, and rolled the stone from the well’s mouth, and watered the flock of Laban his mother’s brother. ^11And Jacob kissed Rachel, and lifted up his voice, and wept. ^12And Jacob told Rachel that he was her father’s brother, and that he was Rebekah’s son: and she ran and told her father.

^13And it came to pass, when Laban heard the tidings of Jacob his sister’s son, that he ran to meet him, and embraced him, and kissed him, and brought him to his house. And he told Laban all these things. ^14And Laban said to him, Surely thou art my bone and my flesh. And he abode with him the space of a month. ^15And Laban said unto Jacob, Because thou art my brother, shouldest thou therefore serve me for nought? tell me, what shall thy wages be? ^16And Laban had two daughters: the name of the elder was Leah, and the name of the younger was Rachel. ^17Leah was tender eyed; but Rachel was beautiful and well favoured. ^18And Jacob loved Rachel; and said, I will serve thee seven years for Rachel thy younger daughter. ^19And Laban said, It is better that I give her to thee, than that I should give her to another man: abide with me. ^20And Jacob served seven years for Rachel; and they seemed unto him but a few days, for the love he had to her.

^21And Jacob said unto Laban, Give me my wife, for my days are fulfilled, that I may go in unto her. ^22And Laban gathered together all the men of the place, and made a feast. ^23And it came to pass in the evening, that he took Leah his daughter, and brought her to him; and he went in unto her. ^24And Laban gave unto his daughter Leah Zilpah his maid for an handmaid. ^25And it came to pass, that in the morning, behold, it was Leah: and he said to Laban, What is this thou hast done unto me? did not I serve with thee for Rachel? wherefore then hast thou beguiled me? ^26And Laban said, It must not be so done in our country, to give the younger before the firstborn. ^27Fulfil her week, and we will give thee this also for the service which thou shalt serve with me yet seven other years. ^28And Jacob did so, and fulfilled her week: and he gave him Rachel his daughter to wife also. ^29And Laban gave to Rachel his daughter Bilhah his handmaid to be her maid. ^30And he went in also unto Rachel, and he loved also Rachel more than Leah, and served with him yet seven other years.

^31And when the Lord saw that Leah was hated, he opened her womb: but Rachel was barren. ^32And Leah conceived, and bare a son, and she called his name Reuben: for she said, Surely the Lord hath looked upon my affliction; now therefore my husband will love me. ^33And she conceived again, and bare a son; and said, Because the Lord hath heard I was hated, he hath therefore given me this son also: and she called his name Simeon. ^34And she conceived again, and bare a son; and said, Now this time will my husband be joined unto me, because I have born him three sons: therefore was his name called Levi. ^35And she conceived again, and bare a son: and she said, Now will I praise the Lord: therefore she called his name Judah; and left bearing.

XXX

^1And when Rachel saw that she bare Jacob no children, Rachel envied her sister; and said unto Jacob, Give me children, or else I die. ^2And Jacob’s anger was kindled against Rachel: and he said, Am I in God’s stead, who hath withheld from thee the fruit of the womb? ^3And she said, Behold my maid Bilhah, go in unto her; and she shall bear upon my knees, that I may also have children by her. ^4And she gave him Bilhah her handmaid to wife: and Jacob went in unto her. ^5And Bilhah conceived, and bare Jacob a son. ^6And Rachel said, God hath judged me, and hath also heard my voice, and hath given me a son: therefore called she his name Dan. ^7And Bilhah Rachel’s maid conceived again, and bare Jacob a second son. ^8And Rachel said, With great wrestlings have I wrestled with my sister, and I have prevailed: and she called his name Naphtali.

^9When Leah saw that she had left bearing, she took Zilpah her maid, and gave her Jacob to wife. ^10And Zilpah Leah’s maid bare Jacob a son. ^11And Leah said, A troop cometh: and she called his name Gad. ^12And Zilpah Leah’s maid bare Jacob a second son. ^13And Leah said, Happy am I, for the daughters will call me blessed: and she called his name Asher.

^14And Reuben went in the days of wheat harvest, and found mandrakes in the field, and brought them unto his mother Leah. Then Rachel said to Leah, Give me, I pray thee, of thy son’s mandrakes. ^15And she said unto her, Is it a small matter that thou hast taken my husband? and wouldest thou take away my son’s mandrakes also? And Rachel said, Therefore he shall lie with thee to night for thy son’s mandrakes. ^16And Jacob came out of the field in the evening, and Leah went out to meet him, and said, Thou must come in unto me; for surely I have hired thee with my son’s mandrakes. And he lay with her that night. ^17And God hearkened unto Leah, and she conceived, and bare Jacob the fifth son. ^18And Leah said, God hath given me my hire, because I have given my maiden to my husband: and she called his name Issachar. ^19And Leah conceived again, and bare Jacob the sixth son. ^20And Leah said, God hath endued me with a good dowry; now will my husband dwell with me, because I have born him six sons: and she called his name Zebulun. ^21And afterwards she bare a daughter, and called her name Dinah.

^22And God remembered Rachel, and God hearkened to her, and opened her womb. ^23And she conceived, and bare a son; and said, God hath taken away my reproach: ^24and she called his name Joseph; and said, The Lord shall add to me another son.

^25And it came to pass, when Rachel had born Joseph, that Jacob said unto Laban, Send me away, that I may go unto mine own place, and to my country. ^26Give me my wives and my children, for whom I have served thee, and let me go: for thou knowest my service which I have done thee. ^27And Laban said unto him, I pray thee, if I have found favour in thine eyes, tarry: for I have learned by experience that the Lord hath blessed me for thy sake. ^28And he said, Appoint me thy wages, and I will give it. ^29And he said unto him, Thou knowest how I have served thee, and how thy cattle was with me. ^30For it was little which thou hadst before I came, and it is now increased unto a multitude; and the Lord hath blessed thee since my coming: and now when shall I provide for mine own house also? ^31And he said, What shall I give thee? And Jacob said, Thou shalt not give me any thing: if thou wilt do this thing for me, I will again feed and keep thy flock. ^32I will pass through all thy flock to day, removing from thence all the speckled and spotted cattle, and all the brown cattle among the sheep, and the spotted and speckled among the goats: and of such shall be my hire. ^33So shall my righteousness answer for me in time to come, when it shall come for my hire before thy face: every one that is not speckled and spotted among the goats, and brown among the sheep, that shall be counted stolen with me. ^34And Laban said, Behold, I would it might be according to thy word. ^35And he removed that day the he goats that were ringstraked and spotted, and all the she goats that were speckled and spotted, and every one that had some white in it, and all the brown among the sheep, and gave them into the hand of his sons. ^36And he set three days’ journey betwixt himself and Jacob: and Jacob fed the rest of Laban’s flocks.

^37And Jacob took him rods of green poplar, and of the hazel and chesnut tree; and pilled white strakes in them, and made the white appear which was in the rods. ^38And he set the rods which he had pilled before the flocks in the gutters in the watering troughs when the flocks came to drink, that they should conceive when they came to drink. ^39And the flocks conceived before the rods, and brought forth cattle ringstraked, speckled, and spotted. ^40And Jacob did separate the lambs, and set the faces of the flocks toward the ringstraked, and all the brown in the flock of Laban; and he put his own flocks by themselves, and put them not unto Laban’s cattle. ^41And it came to pass, whensoever the stronger cattle did conceive, that Jacob laid the rods before the eyes of the cattle in the gutters, that they might conceive among the rods. ^42But when the cattle were feeble, he put them not in: so the feebler were Laban’s, and the stronger Jacob’s. ^43And the man increased exceedingly, and had much cattle, and maidservants, and menservants, and camels, and asses.

XXXI

^1And he heard the words of Laban’s sons, saying, Jacob hath taken away all that was our father’s; and of that which was our father’s hath he gotten all this glory. ^2And Jacob beheld the countenance of Laban, and, behold, it was not toward him as before. ^3And the Lord said unto Jacob, Return unto the land of thy fathers, and to thy kindred; and I will be with thee.

^4And Jacob sent and called Rachel and Leah to the field unto his flock, ^5and said unto them, I see your father’s countenance, that it is not toward me as before; but the God of my father hath been with me. ^6And ye know that with all my power I have served your father. ^7And your father hath deceived me, and changed my wages ten times; but God suffered him not to hurt me. ^8If he said thus, The speckled shall be thy wages; then all the cattle bare speckled: and if he said thus, The ringstraked shall be thy hire; then bare all the cattle ringstraked. ^9Thus God hath taken away the cattle of your father, and given them to me. ^10And it came to pass at the time that the cattle conceived, that I lifted up mine eyes, and saw in a dream, and, behold, the rams which leaped upon the cattle were ringstraked, speckled, and grisled. ^11And the angel of God spake unto me in a dream, saying, Jacob: And I said, Here am I. ^12And he said, Lift up now thine eyes, and see, all the rams which leap upon the cattle are ringstraked, speckled, and grisled: for I have seen all that Laban doeth unto thee. ^13I am the God of Bethel, where thou anointedst the pillar, and where thou vowedst a vow unto me: now arise, get thee out from this land, and return unto the land of thy kindred. ^14And Rachel and Leah answered and said unto him, Is there yet any portion or inheritance for us in our father’s house? ^15Are we not counted of him strangers? for he hath sold us, and hath quite devoured also our money. ^16For all the riches which God hath taken from our father, that is ours, and our children’s: now then, whatsoever God hath said unto thee, do.

^17Then Jacob rose up, and set his sons and his wives upon camels; ^18and he carried away all his cattle, and all his goods which he had gotten, the cattle of his getting, which he had gotten in Padanaram, for to go to Isaac his father in the land of Canaan. ^19And Laban went to shear his sheep: and Rachel had stolen the images that were her father’s. ^20And Jacob stole away unawares to Laban the Syrian, in that he told him not that he fled. ^21So he fled with all that he had; and he rose up, and passed over the river, and set his face toward the mount Gilead.

^22And it was told Laban on the third day that Jacob was fled. ^23And he took his brethren with him, and pursued after him seven days’ journey; and they overtook him in the mount Gilead. ^24And God came to Laban the Syrian in a dream by night, and said unto him, Take heed that thou speak not to Jacob either good or bad.

^25Then Laban overtook Jacob. Now Jacob had pitched his tent in the mount: and Laban with his brethren pitched in the mount of Gilead. ^26And Laban said to Jacob, What hast thou done, that thou hast stolen away unawares to me, and carried away my daughters, as captives taken with the sword? ^27Wherefore didst thou flee away secretly, and steal away from me; and didst not tell me, that I might have sent thee away with mirth, and with songs, with tabret, and with harp? ^28And hast not suffered me to kiss my sons and my daughters? thou hast now done foolishly in so doing. ^29It is in the power of my hand to do you hurt: but the God of your father spake unto me yesternight, saying, Take thou heed that thou speak not to Jacob either good or bad. ^30And now, though thou wouldest needs be gone, because thou sore longedst after thy father’s house, yet wherefore hast thou stolen my gods? ^31And Jacob answered and said to Laban, Because I was afraid: for I said, Peradventure thou wouldest take by force thy daughters from me. ^32With whomsoever thou findest thy gods, let him not live: before our brethren discern thou what is thine with me, and take it to thee. For Jacob knew not that Rachel had stolen them.

^33And Laban went into Jacob’s tent, and into Leah’s tent, and into the two maidservants’ tents; but he found them not. Then went he out of Leah’s tent, and entered into Rachel’s tent. ^34Now Rachel had taken the images, and put them in the camel’s furniture, and sat upon them. And Laban searched all the tent, but found them not. ^35And she said to her father, Let it not displease my lord that I cannot rise up before thee; for the custom of women is upon me. And he searched but found not the images.

^36And Jacob was wroth, and chode with Laban: and Jacob answered and said to Laban, What is my trespass? what is my sin, that thou hast so hotly pursued after me? ^37Whereas thou hast searched all my stuff, what hast thou found of all thy household stuff? set it here before my brethren and thy brethren, that they may judge betwixt us both. ^38This twenty years have I been with thee; thy ewes and thy she goats have not cast their young, and the rams of thy flock have I not eaten. ^39That which was torn of beasts I brought not unto thee; I bare the loss of it; of my hand didst thou require it, whether stolen by day, or stolen by night. ^40Thus I was; in the day the drought consumed me, and the frost by night; and my sleep departed from mine eyes. ^41Thus have I been twenty years in thy house; I served thee fourteen years for thy two daughters, and six years for thy cattle: and thou hast changed my wages ten times. ^42Except the God of my father, the God of Abraham, and the fear of Isaac, had been with me, surely thou hadst sent me away now empty. God hath seen mine affliction and the labour of my hands, and rebuked thee yesternight.

^43And Laban answered and said unto Jacob, These daughters are my daughters, and these children are my children, and these cattle are my cattle, and all that thou seest is mine: and what can I do this day unto these my daughters, or unto their children which they have born? ^44Now therefore come thou, let us make a covenant, I and thou; and let it be for a witness between me and thee.

^45And Jacob took a stone, and set it up for a pillar. ^46And Jacob said unto his brethren, Gather stones; and they took stones, and made an heap: and they did eat there upon the heap. ^47And Laban called it Jegarsahadutha: but Jacob called it Galeed. ^48And Laban said, This heap is a witness between me and thee this day. Therefore was the name of it called Galeed; ^49and Mizpah; for he said, The Lord watch between me and thee, when we are absent one from another. ^50If thou shalt afflict my daughters, or if thou shalt take other wives beside my daughters, no man is with us; see, God is witness betwixt me and thee. ^51And Laban said to Jacob, Behold this heap, and behold this pillar, which I have cast betwixt me and thee: ^52this heap be witness, and this pillar be witness, that I will not pass over this heap to thee, and that thou shalt not pass over this heap and this pillar unto me, for harm. ^53The God of Abraham, and the God of Nahor, the God of their father, judge betwixt us. And Jacob sware by the fear of his father Isaac.

^54Then Jacob offered sacrifice upon the mount, and called his brethren to eat bread: and they did eat bread, and tarried all night in the mount. ^55And early in the morning Laban rose up, and kissed his sons and his daughters, and blessed them: and Laban departed, and returned unto his place.

XXXII

^1And Jacob went on his way, and the angels of God met him. ^2And when Jacob saw them, he said, This is God’s host: and he called the name of that place Mahanaim.

^3And Jacob sent messengers before him to Esau his brother unto the land of Seir, the country of Edom. ^4And he commanded them, saying, Thus shall ye speak unto my lord Esau; Thy servant Jacob saith thus, I have sojourned with Laban, and stayed there until now: ^5and I have oxen, and asses, flocks, and menservants, and womenservants: and I have sent to tell my lord, that I may find grace in thy sight.

^6And the messengers returned to Jacob, saying, We came to thy brother Esau, and also he cometh to meet thee, and four hundred men with him. ^7Then Jacob was greatly afraid and distressed: and he divided the people that was with him, and the flocks, and herds, and the camels, into two bands; ^8and said, If Esau come to the one company, and smite it, then the other company which is left shall escape.

^9And Jacob said, O God of my father Abraham, and God of my father Isaac, the Lord which saidst unto me, Return unto thy country, and to thy kindred, and I will deal well with thee: ^10I am not worthy of the least of all the mercies, and of all the truth, which thou hast shewed unto thy servant; for with my staff I passed over this Jordan; and now I am become two bands. ^11Deliver me, I pray thee, from the hand of my brother, from the hand of Esau: for I fear him, lest he will come and smite me, and the mother with the children. ^12And thou saidst, I will surely do thee good, and make thy seed as the sand of the sea, which cannot be numbered for multitude.

^13And he lodged there that same night; and took of that which came to his hand a present for Esau his brother; ^14two hundred she goats, and twenty he goats, two hundred ewes, and twenty rams, ^15thirty milch camels with their colts, forty kine, and ten bulls, twenty she asses, and ten foals. ^16And he delivered them into the hand of his servants, every drove by themselves; and said unto his servants, Pass over before me, and put a space betwixt drove and drove. ^17And he commanded the foremost, saying, When Esau my brother meeteth thee, and asketh thee, saying, Whose art thou? and whither goest thou? and whose are these before thee? ^18Then thou shalt say, They be thy servant Jacob’s; it is a present sent unto my lord Esau: and, behold, also he is behind us. ^19And so commanded he the second, and the third, and all that followed the droves, saying, On this manner shall ye speak unto Esau, when ye find him. ^20And say ye moreover, Behold, thy servant Jacob is behind us. For he said, I will appease him with the present that goeth before me, and afterward I will see his face; peradventure he will accept of me. ^21So went the present over before him: and himself lodged that night in the company.

^22And he rose up that night, and took his two wives, and his two womenservants, and his eleven sons, and passed over the ford Jabbok. ^23And he took them, and sent them over the brook, and sent over that he had. ^24And Jacob was left alone; and there wrestled a man with him until the breaking of the day. ^25And when he saw that he prevailed not against him, he touched the hollow of his thigh; and the hollow of Jacob’s thigh was out of joint, as he wrestled with him. ^26And he said, Let me go, for the day breaketh. And he said, I will not let thee go, except thou bless me. ^27And he said unto him, What is thy name? And he said, Jacob. ^28And he said, Thy name shall be called no more Jacob, but Israel: for as a prince hast thou power with God and with men, and hast prevailed. ^29And Jacob asked him, and said, Tell me, I pray thee, thy name. And he said, Wherefore is it that thou dost ask after my name? And he blessed him there. ^30And Jacob called the name of the place Peniel: for I have seen God face to face, and my life is preserved. ^31And as he passed over Penuel the sun rose upon him, and he halted upon his thigh. ^32Therefore the children of Israel eat not of the sinew which shrank, which is upon the hollow of the thigh, unto this day: because he touched the hollow of Jacob’s thigh in the sinew that shrank.

XXXIII

^1And Jacob lifted up his eyes, and looked, and, behold, Esau came, and with him four hundred men. And he divided the children unto Leah, and unto Rachel, and unto the two handmaids. ^2And he put the handmaids and their children foremost, and Leah and her children after, and Rachel and Joseph hindermost. ^3And he passed over before them, and bowed himself to the ground seven times, until he came near to his brother. ^4And Esau ran to meet him, and embraced him, and fell on his neck, and kissed him: and they wept. ^5And he lifted up his eyes, and saw the women and the children; and said, Who are those with thee? And he said, The children which God hath graciously given thy servant. ^6Then the handmaidens came near, they and their children, and they bowed themselves. ^7And Leah also with her children came near, and bowed themselves: and after came Joseph near and Rachel, and they bowed themselves. ^8And he said, What meanest thou by all this drove which I met? And he said, These are to find grace in the sight of my lord. ^9And Esau said, I have enough, my brother; keep that thou hast unto thyself. ^10And Jacob said, Nay, I pray thee, if now I have found grace in thy sight, then receive my present at my hand: for therefore I have seen thy face, as though I had seen the face of God, and thou wast pleased with me. ^11Take, I pray thee, my blessing that is brought to thee; because God hath dealt graciously with me, and because I have enough. And he urged him, and he took it.

^12And he said, Let us take our journey, and let us go, and I will go before thee. ^13And he said unto him, My lord knoweth that the children are tender, and the flocks and herds with young are with me: and if men should overdrive them one day, all the flock will die. ^14Let my lord, I pray thee, pass over before his servant: and I will lead on softly, according as the cattle that goeth before me and the children be able to endure, until I come unto my lord unto Seir. ^15And Esau said, Let me now leave with thee some of the folk that are with me. And he said, What needeth it? let me find grace in the sight of my lord. ^16So Esau returned that day on his way unto Seir. ^17And Jacob journeyed to Succoth, and built him an house, and made booths for his cattle: therefore the name of the place is called Succoth.

^18And Jacob came to Shalem, a city of Shechem, which is in the land of Canaan, when he came from Padanaram; and pitched his tent before the city. ^19And he bought a parcel of a field, where he had spread his tent, at the hand of the children of Hamor, Shechem’s father, for an hundred pieces of money. ^20And he erected there an altar, and called it EleloheIsrael.

XXXIV

^1And Dinah the daughter of Leah, which she bare unto Jacob, went out to see the daughters of the land. ^2And when Shechem the son of Hamor the Hivite, prince of the country, saw her, he took her, and lay with her, and defiled her. ^3And his soul clave unto Dinah the daughter of Jacob, and he loved the damsel, and spake kindly unto the damsel. ^4And Shechem spake unto his father Hamor, saying, Get me this damsel to wife. ^5And Jacob heard that he had defiled Dinah his daughter: now his sons were with his cattle in the field: and Jacob held his peace until they were come.

^6And Hamor the father of Shechem went out unto Jacob to commune with him. ^7And the sons of Jacob came out of the field when they heard it: and the men were grieved, and they were very wroth, because he had wrought folly in Israel in lying with Jacob’s daughter: which thing ought not to be done. ^8And Hamor communed with them, saying, The soul of my son Shechem longeth for your daughter: I pray you give her him to wife. ^9And make ye marriages with us, and give your daughters unto us, and take our daughters unto you. ^10And ye shall dwell with us: and the land shall be before you; dwell and trade ye therein, and get you possessions therein. ^11And Shechem said unto her father and unto her brethren, Let me find grace in your eyes, and what ye shall say unto me I will give. ^12Ask me never so much dowry and gift, and I will give according as ye shall say unto me: but give me the damsel to wife. ^13And the sons of Jacob answered Shechem and Hamor his father deceitfully, and said, because he had defiled Dinah their sister: ^14and they said unto them, We cannot do this thing, to give our sister to one that is uncircumcised; for that were a reproach unto us: ^15but in this will we consent unto you: If ye will be as we be, that every male of you be circumcised; ^16then will we give our daughters unto you, and we will take your daughters to us, and we will dwell with you, and we will become one people. ^17But if ye will not hearken unto us, to be circumcised; then will we take our daughter, and we will be gone. ^18And their words pleased Hamor, and Shechem Hamor’s son. ^19And the young man deferred not to do the thing, because he had delight in Jacob’s daughter: and he was more honourable than all the house of his father.

^20And Hamor and Shechem his son came unto the gate of their city, and communed with the men of their city, saying, ^21These men are peaceable with us; therefore let them dwell in the land, and trade therein; for the land, behold, it is large enough for them; let us take their daughters to us for wives, and let us give them our daughters. ^22Only herein will the men consent unto us for to dwell with us, to be one people, if every male among us be circumcised, as they are circumcised. ^23Shall not their cattle and their substance and every beast of their’s be our’s? only let us consent unto them, and they will dwell with us. ^24And unto Hamor and unto Shechem his son hearkened all that went out of the gate of his city; and every male was circumcised, all that went out of the gate of his city.

^25And it came to pass on the third day, when they were sore, that two of the sons of Jacob, Simeon and Levi, Dinah’s brethren, took each man his sword, and came upon the city boldly, and slew all the males. ^26And they slew Hamor and Shechem his son with the edge of the sword, and took Dinah out of Shechem’s house, and went out. ^27The sons of Jacob came upon the slain, and spoiled the city, because they had defiled their sister. ^28They took their sheep, and their oxen, and their asses, and that which was in the city, and that which was in the field, ^29and all their wealth, and all their little ones, and their wives took they captive, and spoiled even all that was in the house. ^30And Jacob said to Simeon and Levi, Ye have troubled me to make me to stink among the inhabitants of the land, among the Canaanites and the Perizzites: and I being few in number, they shall gather themselves together against me, and slay me; and I shall be destroyed, I and my house. ^31And they said, Should he deal with our sister as with an harlot?

XXXV

^1And God said unto Jacob, Arise, go up to Bethel, and dwell there: and make there an altar unto God, that appeared unto thee when thou fleddest from the face of Esau thy brother. ^2Then Jacob said unto his household, and to all that were with him, Put away the strange gods that are among you, and be clean, and change your garments: ^3and let us arise, and go up to Bethel; and I will make there an altar unto God, who answered me in the day of my distress, and was with me in the way which I went. ^4And they gave unto Jacob all the strange gods which were in their hand, and all their earrings which were in their ears; and Jacob hid them under the oak which was by Shechem. ^5And they journeyed: and the terror of God was upon the cities that were round about them, and they did not pursue after the sons of Jacob.

^6So Jacob came to Luz, which is in the land of Canaan, that is, Bethel, he and all the people that were with him. ^7And he built there an altar, and called the place Elbethel: because there God appeared unto him, when he fled from the face of his brother. ^8But Deborah Rebekah’s nurse died, and she was buried beneath Bethel under an oak: and the name of it was called Allonbachuth.

^9And God appeared unto Jacob again, when he came out of Padanaram, and blessed him. ^10And God said unto him, Thy name is Jacob: thy name shall not be called any more Jacob, but Israel shall be thy name: and he called his name Israel. ^11And God said unto him, I am God Almighty: be fruitful and multiply; a nation and a company of nations shall be of thee, and kings shall come out of thy loins; ^12and the land which I gave Abraham and Isaac, to thee I will give it, and to thy seed after thee will I give the land. ^13And God went up from him in the place where he talked with him. ^14And Jacob set up a pillar in the place where he talked with him, even a pillar of stone: and he poured a drink offering thereon, and he poured oil thereon. ^15And Jacob called the name of the place where God spake with him, Bethel.

^16And they journeyed from Bethel; and there was but a little way to come to Ephrath: and Rachel travailed, and she had hard labour. ^17And it came to pass, when she was in hard labour, that the midwife said unto her, Fear not; thou shalt have this son also. ^18And it came to pass, as her soul was in departing, (for she died) that she called his name Benoni: but his father called him Benjamin. ^19And Rachel died, and was buried in the way to Ephrath, which is Bethlehem. ^20And Jacob set a pillar upon her grave: that is the pillar of Rachel’s grave unto this day.

^21And Israel journeyed, and spread his tent beyond the tower of Edar. ^22And it came to pass, when Israel dwelt in that land, that Reuben went and lay with Bilhah his father’s concubine: and Israel heard it. Now the sons of Jacob were twelve: ^23the sons of Leah; Reuben, Jacob’s firstborn, and Simeon, and Levi, and Judah, and Issachar, and Zebulun: ^24the sons of Rachel; Joseph, and Benjamin: ^25and the sons of Bilhah, Rachel’s handmaid; Dan, and Naphtali: ^26and the sons of Zilpah, Leah’s handmaid: Gad, and Asher: these are the sons of Jacob, which were born to him in Padanaram.

^27And Jacob came unto Isaac his father unto Mamre, unto the city of Arbah, which is Hebron, where Abraham and Isaac sojourned. ^28And the days of Isaac were an hundred and fourscore years. ^29And Isaac gave up the ghost, and died, and was gathered unto his people, being old and full of days: and his sons Esau and Jacob buried him.

XXXVI

^1Now these are the generations of Esau, who is Edom. ^2Esau took his wives of the daughters of Canaan; Adah the daughter of Elon the Hittite, and Aholibamah the daughter of Anah the daughter of Zibeon the Hivite; ^3and Bashemath Ishmael’s daughter, sister of Nebajoth. ^4And Adah bare to Esau Eliphaz; and Bashemath bare Reuel; ^5and Aholibamah bare Jeush, and Jaalam, and Korah: these are the sons of Esau, which were born unto him in the land of Canaan. ^6And Esau took his wives, and his sons, and his daughters, and all the persons of his house, and his cattle, and all his beasts, and all his substance, which he had got in the land of Canaan; and went into the country from the face of his brother Jacob. ^7For their riches were more than that they might dwell together; and the land wherein they were strangers could not bear them because of their cattle. ^8Thus dwelt Esau in mount Seir: Esau is Edom.

^9And these are the generations of Esau the father of the Edomites in mount Seir: ^10these are the names of Esau’s sons; Eliphaz the son of Adah the wife of Esau, Reuel the son of Bashemath the wife of Esau. ^11And the sons of Eliphaz were Teman, Omar, Zepho, and Gatam, and Kenaz. ^12And Timna was concubine to Eliphaz Esau’s son; and she bare to Eliphaz Amalek: these were the sons of Adah Esau’s wife. ^13And these are the sons of Reuel; Nahath, and Zerah, Shammah, and Mizzah: these were the sons of Bashemath Esau’s wife. ^14And these were the sons of Aholibamah, the daughter of Anah the daughter of Zibeon, Esau’s wife: and she bare to Esau Jeush, and Jaalam, and Korah.

^15These were dukes of the sons of Esau: the sons of Eliphaz the firstborn son of Esau; duke Teman, duke Omar, duke Zepho, duke Kenaz, ^16duke Korah, duke Gatam, and duke Amalek: these are the dukes that came of Eliphaz in the land of Edom; these were the sons of Adah. ^17And these are the sons of Reuel Esau’s son; duke Nahath, duke Zerah, duke Shammah, duke Mizzah: these are the dukes that came of Reuel in the land of Edom; these are the sons of Bashemath Esau’s wife. ^18And these are the sons of Aholibamah Esau’s wife; duke Jeush, duke Jaalam, duke Korah: these were the dukes that came of Aholibamah the daughter of Anah, Esau’s wife. ^19These are the sons of Esau, who is Edom, and these are their dukes.

^20These are the sons of Seir the Horite, who inhabited the land; Lotan, and Shobal, and Zibeon, and Anah, ^21and Dishon, and Ezer, and Dishan: these are the dukes of the Horites, the children of Seir in the land of Edom. ^22And the children of Lotan were Hori and Hemam; and Lotan’s sister was Timna. ^23And the children of Shobal were these; Alvan, and Manahath, and Ebal, Shepho, and Onam. ^24And these are the children of Zibeon; both Ajah, and Anah: this was that Anah that found the mules in the wilderness, as he fed the asses of Zibeon his father. ^25And the children of Anah were these; Dishon, and Aholibamah the daughter of Anah. ^26And these are the children of Dishon; Hemdan, and Eshban, and Ithran, and Cheran. ^27The children of Ezer are these; Bilhan, and Zaavan, and Akan. ^28The children of Dishan are these; Uz, and Aran. ^29These are the dukes that came of the Horites; duke Lotan, duke Shobal, duke Zibeon, duke Anah, ^30duke Dishon, duke Ezer, duke Dishan: these are the dukes that came of Hori, among their dukes in the land of Seir.

^31And these are the kings that reigned in the land of Edom, before there reigned any king over the children of Israel. ^32And Bela the son of Beor reigned in Edom: and the name of his city was Dinhabah. ^33And Bela died, and Jobab the son of Zerah of Bozrah reigned in his stead. ^34And Jobab died, and Husham of the land of Temani reigned in his stead. ^35And Husham died, and Hadad the son of Bedad, who smote Midian in the field of Moab, reigned in his stead: and the name of his city was Avith. ^36And Hadad died, and Samlah of Masrekah reigned in his stead. ^37And Samlah died, and Saul of Rehoboth by the river reigned in his stead. ^38And Saul died, and Baalhanan the son of Achbor reigned in his stead. ^39And Baalhanan the son of Achbor died, and Hadar reigned in his stead: and the name of his city was Pau; and his wife’s name was Mehetabel, the daughter of Matred, the daughter of Mezahab.

^40And these are the names of the dukes that came of Esau, according to their families, after their places, by their names; duke Timnah, duke Alvah, duke Jetheth, ^41duke Aholibamah, duke Elah, duke Pinon, ^42duke Kenaz, duke Teman, duke Mibzar, ^43duke Magdiel, duke Iram: these be the dukes of Edom, according to their habitations in the land of their possession: he is Esau the father of the Edomites.

XXXVII

^1And Jacob dwelt in the land wherein his father was a stranger, in the land of Canaan. ^2These are the generations of Jacob. Joseph, being seventeen years old, was feeding the flock with his brethren; and the lad was with the sons of Bilhah, and with the sons of Zilpah, his father’s wives: and Joseph brought unto his father their evil report. ^3Now Israel loved Joseph more than all his children, because he was the son of his old age: and he made him a coat of many colours. ^4And when his brethren saw that their father loved him more than all his brethren, they hated him, and could not speak peaceably unto him.

^5And Joseph dreamed a dream, and he told it his brethren: and they hated him yet the more. ^6And he said unto them, Hear, I pray you, this dream which I have dreamed: ^7for, behold, we were binding sheaves in the field, and, lo, my sheaf arose, and also stood upright; and, behold, your sheaves stood round about, and made obeisance to my sheaf. ^8And his brethren said to him, Shalt thou indeed reign over us? or shalt thou indeed have dominion over us? And they hated him yet the more for his dreams, and for his words.

^9And he dreamed yet another dream, and told it his brethren, and said, Behold, I have dreamed a dream more; and, behold, the sun and the moon and the eleven stars made obeisance to me. ^10And he told it to his father, and to his brethren: and his father rebuked him, and said unto him, What is this dream that thou hast dreamed? Shall I and thy mother and thy brethren indeed come to bow down ourselves to thee to the earth? ^11And his brethren envied him; but his father observed the saying.

^12And his brethren went to feed their father’s flock in Shechem. ^13And Israel said unto Joseph, Do not thy brethren feed the flock in Shechem? come, and I will send thee unto them. And he said to him, Here am I. ^14And he said to him, Go, I pray thee, see whether it be well with thy brethren, and well with the flocks; and bring me word again. So he sent him out of the vale of Hebron, and he came to Shechem.

^15And a certain man found him, and, behold, he was wandering in the field: and the man asked him, saying, What seekest thou? ^16And he said, I seek my brethren: tell me, I pray thee, where they feed their flocks. ^17And the man said, They are departed hence; for I heard them say, Let us go to Dothan. And Joseph went after his brethren, and found them in Dothan. ^18And when they saw him afar off, even before he came near unto them, they conspired against him to slay him. ^19And they said one to another, Behold, this dreamer cometh. ^20Come now therefore, and let us slay him, and cast him into some pit, and we will say, Some evil beast hath devoured him: and we shall see what will become of his dreams. ^21And Reuben heard it, and he delivered him out of their hands; and said, Let us not kill him. ^22And Reuben said unto them, Shed no blood, but cast him into this pit that is in the wilderness, and lay no hand upon him; that he might rid him out of their hands, to deliver him to his father again.

^23And it came to pass, when Joseph was come unto his brethren, that they stript Joseph out of his coat, his coat of many colours that was on him; ^24and they took him, and cast him into a pit: and the pit was empty, there was no water in it. ^25And they sat down to eat bread: and they lifted up their eyes and looked, and, behold, a company of Ishmeelites came from Gilead with their camels bearing spicery and balm and myrrh, going to carry it down to Egypt. ^26And Judah said unto his brethren, What profit is it if we slay our brother, and conceal his blood? ^27Come, and let us sell him to the Ishmeelites, and let not our hand be upon him; for he is our brother and our flesh. And his brethren were content. ^28Then there passed by Midianites merchantmen; and they drew and lifted up Joseph out of the pit, and sold Joseph to the Ishmeelites for twenty pieces of silver: and they brought Joseph into Egypt.

^29And Reuben returned unto the pit; and, behold, Joseph was not in the pit; and he rent his clothes. ^30And he returned unto his brethren, and said, The child is not; and I, whither shall I go? ^31And they took Joseph’s coat, and killed a kid of the goats, and dipped the coat in the blood; ^32and they sent the coat of many colours, and they brought it to their father; and said, This have we found: know now whether it be thy son’s coat or no. ^33And he knew it, and said, It is my son’s coat; an evil beast hath devoured him; Joseph is without doubt rent in pieces. ^34And Jacob rent his clothes, and put sackcloth upon his loins, and mourned for his son many days. ^35And all his sons and all his daughters rose up to comfort him; but he refused to be comforted; and he said, For I will go down into the grave unto my son mourning. Thus his father wept for him. ^36And the Midianites sold him into Egypt unto Potiphar, an officer of Pharaoh’s, and captain of the guard.

XXXVIII

^1And it came to pass at that time, that Judah went down from his brethren, and turned in to a certain Adullamite, whose name was Hirah. ^2And Judah saw there a daughter of a certain Canaanite, whose name was Shuah; and he took her, and went in unto her. ^3And she conceived, and bare a son; and he called his name Er. ^4And she conceived again, and bare a son; and she called his name Onan. ^5And she yet again conceived, and bare a son; and called his name Shelah: and he was at Chezib, when she bare him. ^6And Judah took a wife for Er his firstborn, whose name was Tamar. ^7And Er, Judah’s firstborn, was wicked in the sight of the Lord; and the Lord slew him. ^8And Judah said unto Onan, Go in unto thy brother’s wife, and marry her, and raise up seed to thy brother. ^9And Onan knew that the seed should not be his; and it came to pass, when he went in unto his brother’s wife, that he spilled it on the ground, lest that he should give seed to his brother. ^10And the thing which he did displeased the Lord: wherefore he slew him also. ^11Then said Judah to Tamar his daughter in law, Remain a widow at thy father’s house, till Shelah my son be grown: for he said, Lest peradventure he die also, as his brethren did. And Tamar went and dwelt in her father’s house.

^12And in process of time the daughter of Shuah Judah’s wife died; and Judah was comforted, and went up unto his sheepshearers to Timnath, he and his friend Hirah the Adullamite. ^13And it was told Tamar, saying, Behold thy father in law goeth up to Timnath to shear his sheep. ^14And she put her widow’s garments off from her, and covered her with a vail, and wrapped herself, and sat in an open place, which is by the way to Timnath; for she saw that Shelah was grown, and she was not given unto him to wife. ^15When Judah saw her, he thought her to be an harlot; because she had covered her face. ^16And he turned unto her by the way, and said, Go to, I pray thee, let me come in unto thee; (for he knew not that she was his daughter in law.) And she said, What wilt thou give me, that thou mayest come in unto me? ^17And he said, I will send thee a kid from the flock. And she said, Wilt thou give me a pledge, till thou send it? ^18And he said, What pledge shall I give thee? And she said, Thy signet, and thy bracelets, and thy staff that is in thine hand. And he gave it her, and came in unto her, and she conceived by him. ^19And she arose, and went away, and laid by her vail from her, and put on the garments of her widowhood. ^20And Judah sent the kid by the hand of his friend the Adullamite, to receive his pledge from the woman’s hand: but he found her not. ^21Then he asked the men of that place, saying, Where is the harlot, that was openly by the way side? And they said, There was no harlot in this place. ^22And he returned to Judah, and said, I cannot find her; and also the men of the place said, that there was no harlot in this place. ^23And Judah said, Let her take it to her, lest we be shamed: behold, I sent this kid, and thou hast not found her.

^24And it came to pass about three months after, that it was told Judah, saying, Tamar thy daughter in law hath played the harlot; and also, behold, she is with child by whoredom. And Judah said, Bring her forth, and let her be burnt. ^25When she was brought forth, she sent to her father in law, saying, By the man, whose these are, am I with child: and she said, Discern, I pray thee, whose are these, the signet, and bracelets, and staff. ^26And Judah acknowledged them, and said, She hath been more righteous than I; because that I gave her not to Shelah my son. And he knew her again no more.

^27And it came to pass in the time of her travail, that, behold, twins were in her womb. ^28And it came to pass, when she travailed, that the one put out his hand: and the midwife took and bound upon his hand a scarlet thread, saying, This came out first. ^29And it came to pass, as he drew back his hand, that, behold, his brother came out: and she said, How hast thou broken forth? this breach be upon thee: therefore his name was called Pharez. ^30And afterward came out his brother, that had the scarlet thread upon his hand: and his name was called Zarah.

XXXIX

^1And Joseph was brought down to Egypt; and Potiphar, an officer of Pharaoh, captain of the guard, an Egyptian, bought him of the hands of the Ishmeelites, which had brought him down thither. ^2And the Lord was with Joseph, and he was a prosperous man; and he was in the house of his master the Egyptian. ^3And his master saw that the Lord was with him, and that the Lord made all that he did to prosper in his hand. ^4And Joseph found grace in his sight, and he served him: and he made him overseer over his house, and all that he had he put into his hand. ^5And it came to pass from the time that he had made him overseer in his house, and over all that he had, that the Lord blessed the Egyptian’s house for Joseph’s sake; and the blessing of the Lord was upon all that he had in the house, and in the field. ^6And he left all that he had in Joseph’s hand; and he knew not ought he had, save the bread which he did eat. And Joseph was a goodly person, and well favoured.

^7And it came to pass after these things, that his master’s wife cast her eyes upon Joseph; and she said, Lie with me. ^8But he refused, and said unto his master’s wife, Behold, my master wotteth not what is with me in the house, and he hath committed all that he hath to my hand; ^9there is none greater in this house than I; neither hath he kept back any thing from me but thee, because thou art his wife: how then can I do this great wickedness, and sin against God? ^10And it came to pass, as she spake to Joseph day by day, that he hearkened not unto her, to lie by her, or to be with her. ^11And it came to pass about this time, that Joseph went into the house to do his business; and there was none of the men of the house there within. ^12And she caught him by his garment, saying, Lie with me: and he left his garment in her hand, and fled, and got him out. ^13And it came to pass, when she saw that he had left his garment in her hand, and was fled forth, ^14that she called unto the men of her house, and spake unto them, saying, See, he hath brought in an Hebrew unto us to mock us; he came in unto me to lie with me, and I cried with a loud voice: ^15and it came to pass, when he heard that I lifted up my voice and cried, that he left his garment with me, and fled, and got him out. ^16And she laid up his garment by her, until his lord came home. ^17And she spake unto him according to these words, saying, The Hebrew servant, which thou hast brought unto us, came in unto me to mock me: ^18and it came to pass, as I lifted up my voice and cried, that he left his garment with me, and fled out. ^19And it came to pass, when his master heard the words of his wife, which she spake unto him, saying, After this manner did thy servant to me; that his wrath was kindled. ^20And Joseph’s master took him, and put him into the prison, a place where the king’s prisoners were bound: and he was there in the prison.

^21But the Lord was with Joseph, and shewed him mercy, and gave him favour in the sight of the keeper of the prison. ^22And the keeper of the prison committed to Joseph’s hand all the prisoners that were in the prison; and whatsoever they did there, he was the doer of it. ^23The keeper of the prison looked not to any thing that was under his hand; because the Lord was with him, and that which he did, the Lord made it to prosper.

XL

^1And it came to pass after these things, that the butler of the king of Egypt and his baker had offended their lord the king of Egypt. ^2And Pharaoh was wroth against two of his officers, against the chief of the butlers, and against the chief of the bakers. ^3And he put them in ward in the house of the captain of the guard, into the prison, the place where Joseph was bound. ^4And the captain of the guard charged Joseph with them, and he served them: and they continued a season in ward.

^5And they dreamed a dream both of them, each man his dream in one night, each man according to the interpretation of his dream, the butler and the baker of the king of Egypt, which were bound in the prison. ^6And Joseph came in unto them in the morning, and looked upon them, and, behold, they were sad. ^7And he asked Pharaoh’s officers that were with him in the ward of his lord’s house, saying, Wherefore look ye so sadly to day? ^8And they said unto him, We have dreamed a dream, and there is no interpreter of it. And Joseph said unto them, Do not interpretations belong to God? tell me them, I pray you.

^9And the chief butler told his dream to Joseph, and said to him, In my dream, behold, a vine was before me; ^10and in the vine were three branches: and it was as though it budded, and her blossoms shot forth; and the clusters thereof brought forth ripe grapes: ^11and Pharaoh’s cup was in my hand: and I took the grapes, and pressed them into Pharaoh’s cup, and I gave the cup into Pharaoh’s hand. ^12And Joseph said unto him, This is the interpretation of it: The three branches are three days: ^13yet within three days shall Pharaoh lift up thine head, and restore thee unto thy place: and thou shalt deliver Pharaoh’s cup into his hand, after the former manner when thou wast his butler. ^14But think on me when it shall be well with thee, and shew kindness, I pray thee, unto me, and make mention of me unto Pharaoh, and bring me out of this house: ^15for indeed I was stolen away out of the land of the Hebrews: and here also have I done nothing that they should put me into the dungeon.

^16When the chief baker saw that the interpretation was good, he said unto Joseph, I also was in my dream, and, behold, I had three white baskets on my head: ^17and in the uppermost basket there was of all manner of bakemeats for Pharaoh; and the birds did eat them out of the basket upon my head. ^18And Joseph answered and said, This is the interpretation thereof: The three baskets are three days: ^19yet within three days shall Pharaoh lift up thy head from off thee, and shall hang thee on a tree; and the birds shall eat thy flesh from off thee.

^20And it came to pass the third day, which was Pharaoh’s birthday, that he made a feast unto all his servants: and he lifted up the head of the chief butler and of the chief baker among his servants. ^21And he restored the chief butler unto his butlership again; and he gave the cup into Pharaoh’s hand: ^22but he hanged the chief baker: as Joseph had interpreted to them. ^23Yet did not the chief butler remember Joseph, but forgat him.

XLI

^1And it came to pass at the end of two full years, that Pharaoh dreamed: and, behold, he stood by the river. ^2And, behold, there came up out of the river seven well favoured kine and fatfleshed; and they fed in a meadow. ^3And, behold, seven other kine came up after them out of the river, ill favoured and leanfleshed; and stood by the other kine upon the brink of the river. ^4And the ill favoured and leanfleshed kine did eat up the seven well favoured and fat kine. So Pharaoh awoke. ^5And he slept and dreamed the second time: and, behold, seven ears of corn came up upon one stalk, rank and good. ^6And, behold, seven thin ears and blasted with the east wind sprung up after them. ^7And the seven thin ears devoured the seven rank and full ears. And Pharaoh awoke, and, behold, it was a dream. ^8And it came to pass in the morning that his spirit was troubled; and he sent and called for all the magicians of Egypt, and all the wise men thereof: and Pharaoh told them his dream; but there was none that could interpret them unto Pharaoh.

^9Then spake the chief butler unto Pharaoh, saying, I do remember my faults this day: ^10Pharaoh was wroth with his servants, and put me in ward in the captain of the guard’s house, both me and the chief baker: ^11and we dreamed a dream in one night, I and he; we dreamed each man according to the interpretation of his dream. ^12And there was there with us a young man, an Hebrew, servant to the captain of the guard; and we told him, and he interpreted to us our dreams; to each man according to his dream he did interpret. ^13And it came to pass, as he interpreted to us, so it was; me he restored unto mine office, and him he hanged.

^14Then Pharaoh sent and called Joseph, and they brought him hastily out of the dungeon: and he shaved himself, and changed his raiment, and came in unto Pharaoh. ^15And Pharaoh said unto Joseph, I have dreamed a dream, and there is none that can interpret it: and I have heard say of thee, that thou canst understand a dream to interpret it. ^16And Joseph answered Pharaoh, saying, It is not in me: God shall give Pharaoh an answer of peace. ^17And Pharaoh said unto Joseph, In my dream, behold, I stood upon the bank of the river: ^18and, behold, there came up out of the river seven kine, fatfleshed and well favoured; and they fed in a meadow: ^19and, behold, seven other kine came up after them, poor and very ill favoured and leanfleshed, such as I never saw in all the land of Egypt for badness: ^20and the lean and the ill favoured kine did eat up the first seven fat kine: ^21and when they had eaten them up, it could not be known that they had eaten them; but they were still ill favoured, as at the beginning. So I awoke. ^22And I saw in my dream, and, behold, seven ears came up in one stalk, full and good: ^23and, behold, seven ears, withered, thin, and blasted with the east wind, sprung up after them: ^24and the thin ears devoured the seven good ears: and I told this unto the magicians; but there was none that could declare it to me.

^25And Joseph said unto Pharaoh, The dream of Pharaoh is one: God hath shewed Pharaoh what he is about to do. ^26The seven good kine are seven years; and the seven good ears are seven years: the dream is one. ^27And the seven thin and ill favoured kine that came up after them are seven years; and the seven empty ears blasted with the east wind shall be seven years of famine. ^28This is the thing which I have spoken unto Pharaoh: What God is about to do he sheweth unto Pharaoh. ^29Behold, there come seven years of great plenty throughout all the land of Egypt: ^30and there shall arise after them seven years of famine; and all the plenty shall be forgotten in the land of Egypt; and the famine shall consume the land; ^31and the plenty shall not be known in the land by reason of that famine following; for it shall be very grievous. ^32And for that the dream was doubled unto Pharaoh twice; it is because the thing is established by God, and God will shortly bring it to pass. ^33Now therefore let Pharaoh look out a man discreet and wise, and set him over the land of Egypt. ^34Let Pharaoh do this, and let him appoint officers over the land, and take up the fifth part of the land of Egypt in the seven plenteous years. ^35And let them gather all the food of those good years that come, and lay up corn under the hand of Pharaoh, and let them keep food in the cities. ^36And that food shall be for store to the land against the seven years of famine, which shall be in the land of Egypt; that the land perish not through the famine.

^37And the thing was good in the eyes of Pharaoh, and in the eyes of all his servants. ^38And Pharaoh said unto his servants, Can we find such a one as this is, a man in whom the Spirit of God is? ^39And Pharaoh said unto Joseph, Forasmuch as God hath shewed thee all this, there is none so discreet and wise as thou art: ^40thou shalt be over my house, and according unto thy word shall all my people be ruled: only in the throne will I be greater than thou. ^41And Pharaoh said unto Joseph, See, I have set thee over all the land of Egypt. ^42And Pharaoh took off his ring from his hand, and put it upon Joseph’s hand, and arrayed him in vestures of fine linen, and put a gold chain about his neck; ^43and he made him to ride in the second chariot which he had; and they cried before him, Bow the knee: and he made him ruler over all the land of Egypt. ^44And Pharaoh said unto Joseph, I am Pharaoh, and without thee shall no man lift up his hand or foot in all the land of Egypt. ^45And Pharaoh called Joseph’s name Zaphnathpaaneah; and he gave him to wife Asenath the daughter of Potipherah priest of On. And Joseph went out over all the land of Egypt.

^46And Joseph was thirty years old when he stood before Pharaoh king of Egypt. And Joseph went out from the presence of Pharaoh, and went throughout all the land of Egypt. ^47And in the seven plenteous years the earth brought forth by handfuls. ^48And he gathered up all the food of the seven years, which were in the land of Egypt, and laid up the food in the cities: the food of the field, which was round about every city, laid he up in the same. ^49And Joseph gathered corn as the sand of the sea, very much, until he left numbering; for it was without number. ^50And unto Joseph were born two sons before the years of famine came, which Asenath the daughter of Potipherah priest of On bare unto him. ^51And Joseph called the name of the firstborn Manasseh: For God, said he, hath made me forget all my toil, and all my father’s house. ^52And the name of the second called he Ephraim: For God hath caused me to be fruitful in the land of my affliction.

^53And the seven years of plenteousness, that was in the land of Egypt, were ended. ^54And the seven years of dearth began to come, according as Joseph had said: and the dearth was in all lands; but in all the land of Egypt there was bread. ^55And when all the land of Egypt was famished, the people cried to Pharaoh for bread: and Pharaoh said unto all the Egyptians, Go unto Joseph; what he saith to you, do. ^56And the famine was over all the face of the earth: and Joseph opened all the storehouses, and sold unto the Egyptians; and the famine waxed sore in the land of Egypt. ^57And all countries came into Egypt to Joseph for to buy corn; because that the famine was so sore in all lands.

XLII

^1Now when Jacob saw that there was corn in Egypt, Jacob said unto his sons, Why do ye look one upon another? ^2And he said, Behold, I have heard that there is corn in Egypt: get you down thither, and buy for us from thence; that we may live, and not die.

^3And Joseph’s ten brethren went down to buy corn in Egypt. ^4But Benjamin, Joseph’s brother, Jacob sent not with his brethren; for he said, Lest peradventure mischief befall him. ^5And the sons of Israel came to buy corn among those that came: for the famine was in the land of Canaan. ^6And Joseph was the governor over the land, and he it was that sold to all the people of the land: and Joseph’s brethren came, and bowed down themselves before him with their faces to the earth. ^7And Joseph saw his brethren, and he knew them, but made himself strange unto them, and spake roughly unto them; and he said unto them, Whence come ye? And they said, From the land of Canaan to buy food. ^8And Joseph knew his brethren, but they knew not him. ^9And Joseph remembered the dreams which he dreamed of them, and said unto them, Ye are spies; to see the nakedness of the land ye are come. ^10And they said unto him, Nay, my lord, but to buy food are thy servants come. ^11We are all one man’s sons; we are true men, thy servants are no spies. ^12And he said unto them, Nay, but to see the nakedness of the land ye are come. ^13And they said, Thy servants are twelve brethren, the sons of one man in the land of Canaan; and, behold, the youngest is this day with our father, and one is not. ^14And Joseph said unto them, That is it that I spake unto you, saying, Ye are spies: ^15hereby ye shall be proved: By the life of Pharaoh ye shall not go forth hence, except your youngest brother come hither. ^16Send one of you, and let him fetch your brother, and ye shall be kept in prison, that your words may be proved, whether there be any truth in you: or else by the life of Pharaoh surely ye are spies. ^17And he put them all together into ward three days.

^18And Joseph said unto them the third day, This do, and live; for I fear God: ^19if ye be true men, let one of your brethren be bound in the house of your prison: go ye, carry corn for the famine of your houses: ^20but bring your youngest brother unto me; so shall your words be verified, and ye shall not die. And they did so. ^21And they said one to another, We are verily guilty concerning our brother, in that we saw the anguish of his soul, when he besought us, and we would not hear; therefore is this distress come upon us. ^22And Reuben answered them, saying, Spake I not unto you, saying, Do not sin against the child; and ye would not hear? therefore, behold, also his blood is required. ^23And they knew not that Joseph understood them; for he spake unto them by an interpreter. ^24And he turned himself about from them, and wept; and returned to them again, and communed with them, and took from them Simeon, and bound him before their eyes. ^25Then Joseph commanded to fill their sacks with corn, and to restore every man’s money into his sack, and to give them provision for the way: and thus did he unto them.

^26And they laded their asses with the corn, and departed thence. ^27And as one of them opened his sack to give his ass provender in the inn, he espied his money; for, behold, it was in his sack’s mouth. ^28And he said unto his brethren, My money is restored; and, lo, it is even in my sack: and their heart failed them, and they were afraid, saying one to another, What is this that God hath done unto us?

^29And they came unto Jacob their father unto the land of Canaan, and told him all that befell unto them; saying, ^30The man, who is the lord of the land, spake roughly to us, and took us for spies of the country. ^31And we said unto him, We are true men; we are no spies: ^32we be twelve brethren, sons of our father; one is not, and the youngest is this day with our father in the land of Canaan. ^33And the man, the lord of the country, said unto us, Hereby shall I know that ye are true men; leave one of your brethren here with me, and take food for the famine of your households, and be gone: ^34and bring your youngest brother unto me: then shall I know that ye are no spies, but that ye are true men: so will I deliver you your brother, and ye shall traffick in the land.

^35And it came to pass as they emptied their sacks, that, behold, every man’s bundle of money was in his sack: and when both they and their father saw the bundles of money, they were afraid. ^36And Jacob their father said unto them, Me have ye bereaved of my children: Joseph is not, and Simeon is not, and ye will take Benjamin away: all these things are against me. ^37And Reuben spake unto his father, saying, Slay my two sons, if I bring him not to thee: deliver him into my hand, and I will bring him to thee again. ^38And he said, My son shall not go down with you; for his brother is dead, and he is left alone: if mischief befall him by the way in the which ye go, then shall ye bring down my gray hairs with sorrow to the grave.

XLIII

^1And the famine was sore in the land. ^2And it came to pass, when they had eaten up the corn which they had brought out of Egypt, their father said unto them, Go again, buy us a little food. ^3And Judah spake unto him, saying, The man did solemnly protest unto us, saying, Ye shall not see my face, except your brother be with you. ^4If thou wilt send our brother with us, we will go down and buy thee food: ^5but if thou wilt not send him, we will not go down: for the man said unto us, Ye shall not see my face, except your brother be with you. ^6And Israel said, Wherefore dealt ye so ill with me, as to tell the man whether ye had yet a brother? ^7And they said, The man asked us straitly of our state, and of our kindred, saying, Is your father yet alive? have ye another brother? and we told him according to the tenor of these words: could we certainly know that he would say, Bring your brother down? ^8And Judah said unto Israel his father, Send the lad with me, and we will arise and go; that we may live, and not die, both we, and thou, and also our little ones. ^9I will be surety for him; of my hand shalt thou require him: if I bring him not unto thee, and set him before thee, then let me bear the blame for ever: ^10for except we had lingered, surely now we had returned this second time. ^11And their father Israel said unto them, If it must be so now, do this; take of the best fruits in the land in your vessels, and carry down the man a present, a little balm, and a little honey, spices, and myrrh, nuts, and almonds: ^12and take double money in your hand; and the money that was brought again in the mouth of your sacks, carry it again in your hand; peradventure it was an oversight: ^13take also your brother, and arise, go again unto the man: ^14and God Almighty give you mercy before the man, that he may send away your other brother, and Benjamin. If I be bereaved of my children, I am bereaved.

^15And the men took that present, and they took double money in their hand and Benjamin; and rose up, and went down to Egypt, and stood before Joseph. ^16And when Joseph saw Benjamin with them, he said to the ruler of his house, Bring these men home, and slay, and make ready; for these men shall dine with me at noon. ^17And the man did as Joseph bade; and the man brought the men into Joseph’s house. ^18And the men were afraid, because they were brought into Joseph’s house; and they said, Because of the money that was returned in our sacks at the first time are we brought in; that he may seek occasion against us, and fall upon us, and take us for bondmen, and our asses. ^19And they came near to the steward of Joseph’s house, and they communed with him at the door of the house, ^20and said, O sir, we came indeed down at the first time to buy food: ^21and it came to pass, when we came to the inn, that we opened our sacks, and, behold, every man’s money was in the mouth of his sack, our money in full weight: and we have brought it again in our hand. ^22And other money have we brought down in our hands to buy food: we cannot tell who put our money in our sacks. ^23And he said, Peace be to you, fear not: your God, and the God of your father, hath given you treasure in your sacks: I had your money. And he brought Simeon out unto them. ^24And the man brought the men into Joseph’s house, and gave them water, and they washed their feet; and he gave their asses provender. ^25And they made ready the present against Joseph came at noon: for they heard that they should eat bread there.

^26And when Joseph came home, they brought him the present which was in their hand into the house, and bowed themselves to him to the earth. ^27And he asked them of their welfare, and said, Is your father well, the old man of whom ye spake? Is he yet alive? ^28And they answered, Thy servant our father is in good health, he is yet alive. And they bowed down their heads, and made obeisance. ^29And he lifted up his eyes, and saw his brother Benjamin, his mother’s son, and said, Is this your younger brother, of whom ye spake unto me? And he said, God be gracious unto thee, my son. ^30And Joseph made haste; for his bowels did yearn upon his brother: and he sought where to weep; and he entered into his chamber, and wept there. ^31And he washed his face, and went out, and refrained himself, and said, Set on bread. ^32And they set on for him by himself, and for them by themselves, and for the Egyptians, which did eat with him, by themselves: because the Egyptians might not eat bread with the Hebrews; for that is an abomination unto the Egyptians. ^33And they sat before him, the firstborn according to his birthright, and the youngest according to his youth: and the men marvelled one at another. ^34And he took and sent messes unto them from before him: but Benjamin’s mess was five times so much as any of their’s. And they drank, and were merry with him.

XLIV

^1And he commanded the steward of his house, saying, Fill the men’s sacks with food, as much as they can carry, and put every man’s money in his sack’s mouth. ^2And put my cup, the silver cup, in the sack’s mouth of the youngest, and his corn money. And he did according to the word that Joseph had spoken. ^3As soon as the morning was light, the men were sent away, they and their asses. ^4And when they were gone out of the city, and not yet far off, Joseph said unto his steward, Up, follow after the men; and when thou dost overtake them, say unto them, Wherefore have ye rewarded evil for good? ^5Is not this it in which my lord drinketh, and whereby indeed he divineth? ye have done evil in so doing.

^6And he overtook them, and he spake unto them these same words. ^7And they said unto him, Wherefore saith my lord these words? God forbid that thy servants should do according to this thing: ^8behold, the money, which we found in our sacks’ mouths, we brought again unto thee out of the land of Canaan: how then should we steal out of thy lord’s house silver or gold? ^9With whomsoever of thy servants it be found, both let him die, and we also will be my lord’s bondmen. ^10And he said, Now also let it be according unto your words: he with whom it is found shall be my servant; and ye shall be blameless. ^11Then they speedily took down every man his sack to the ground, and opened every man his sack. ^12And he searched, and began at the eldest, and left at the youngest: and the cup was found in Benjamin’s sack. ^13Then they rent their clothes, and laded every man his ass, and returned to the city.

^14And Judah and his brethren came to Joseph’s house; for he was yet there: and they fell before him on the ground. ^15And Joseph said unto them, What deed is this that ye have done? wot ye not that such a man as I can certainly divine? ^16And Judah said, What shall we say unto my lord? what shall we speak? or how shall we clear ourselves? God hath found out the iniquity of thy servants: behold, we are my lord’s servants, both we, and he also with whom the cup is found. ^17And he said, God forbid that I should do so: but the man in whose hand the cup is found, he shall be my servant; and as for you, get you up in peace unto your father.

^18Then Judah came near unto him, and said, Oh my lord, let thy servant, I pray thee, speak a word in my lord’s ears, and let not thine anger burn against thy servant: for thou art even as Pharaoh. ^19My lord asked his servants, saying, Have ye a father, or a brother? ^20And we said unto my lord, We have a father, an old man, and a child of his old age, a little one; and his brother is dead, and he alone is left of his mother, and his father loveth him. ^21And thou saidst unto thy servants, Bring him down unto me, that I may set mine eyes upon him. ^22And we said unto my lord, The lad cannot leave his father: for if he should leave his father, his father would die. ^23And thou saidst unto thy servants, Except your youngest brother come down with you, ye shall see my face no more. ^24And it came to pass when we came up unto thy servant my father, we told him the words of my lord. ^25And our father said, Go again, and buy us a little food. ^26And we said, We cannot go down: if our youngest brother be with us, then will we go down: for we may not see the man’s face, except our youngest brother be with us. ^27And thy servant my father said unto us, Ye know that my wife bare me two sons: ^28and the one went out from me, and I said, Surely he is torn in pieces; and I saw him not since: ^29and if ye take this also from me, and mischief befall him, ye shall bring down my gray hairs with sorrow to the grave. ^30Now therefore when I come to thy servant my father, and the lad be not with us; seeing that his life is bound up in the lad’s life; ^31it shall come to pass, when he seeth that the lad is not with us, that he will die: and thy servants shall bring down the gray hairs of thy servant our father with sorrow to the grave. ^32For thy servant became surety for the lad unto my father, saying, If I bring him not unto thee, then I shall bear the blame to my father for ever. ^33Now therefore, I pray thee, let thy servant abide instead of the lad a bondman to my lord; and let the lad go up with his brethren. ^34For how shall I go up to my father, and the lad be not with me? lest peradventure I see the evil that shall come on my father.

XLV

^1Then Joseph could not refrain himself before all them that stood by him; and he cried, Cause every man to go out from me. And there stood no man with him, while Joseph made himself known unto his brethren. ^2And he wept aloud: and the Egyptians and the house of Pharaoh heard. ^3And Joseph said unto his brethren, I am Joseph; doth my father yet live? And his brethren could not answer him; for they were troubled at his presence. ^4And Joseph said unto his brethren, Come near to me, I pray you. And they came near. And he said, I am Joseph your brother, whom ye sold into Egypt. ^5Now therefore be not grieved, nor angry with yourselves, that ye sold me hither: for God did send me before you to preserve life. ^6For these two years hath the famine been in the land: and yet there are five years, in the which there shall neither be earing nor harvest. ^7And God sent me before you to preserve you a posterity in the earth, and to save your lives by a great deliverance. ^8So now it was not you that sent me hither, but God: and he hath made me a father to Pharaoh, and lord of all his house, and a ruler throughout all the land of Egypt. ^9Haste ye, and go up to my father, and say unto him, Thus saith thy son Joseph, God hath made me lord of all Egypt: come down unto me, tarry not: ^10and thou shalt dwell in the land of Goshen, and thou shalt be near unto me, thou, and thy children, and thy children’s children, and thy flocks, and thy herds, and all that thou hast: ^11and there will I nourish thee; for yet there are five years of famine; lest thou, and thy household, and all that thou hast, come to poverty. ^12And, behold, your eyes see, and the eyes of my brother Benjamin, that it is my mouth that speaketh unto you. ^13And ye shall tell my father of all my glory in Egypt, and of all that ye have seen; and ye shall haste and bring down my father hither. ^14And he fell upon his brother Benjamin’s neck, and wept; and Benjamin wept upon his neck. ^15Moreover he kissed all his brethren, and wept upon them: and after that his brethren talked with him.

^16And the fame thereof was heard in Pharaoh’s house, saying, Joseph’s brethren are come: and it pleased Pharaoh well, and his servants. ^17And Pharaoh said unto Joseph, Say unto thy brethren, This do ye; lade your beasts, and go, get you unto the land of Canaan; ^18and take your father and your households, and come unto me: and I will give you the good of the land of Egypt, and ye shall eat the fat of the land. ^19Now thou art commanded, this do ye; take you wagons out of the land of Egypt for your little ones, and for your wives, and bring your father, and come. ^20Also regard not your stuff; for the good of all the land of Egypt is your’s. ^21And the children of Israel did so: and Joseph gave them wagons, according to the commandment of Pharaoh, and gave them provision for the way. ^22To all of them he gave each man changes of raiment; but to Benjamin he gave three hundred pieces of silver, and five changes of raiment. ^23And to his father he sent after this manner; ten asses laden with the good things of Egypt, and ten she asses laden with corn and bread and meat for his father by the way. ^24So he sent his brethren away, and they departed: and he said unto them, See that ye fall not out by the way.

^25And they went up out of Egypt, and came into the land of Canaan unto Jacob their father, ^26and told him, saying, Joseph is yet alive, and he is governor over all the land of Egypt. And Jacob’s heart fainted, for he believed them not. ^27And they told him all the words of Joseph, which he had said unto them: and when he saw the wagons which Joseph had sent to carry him, the spirit of Jacob their father revived: ^28and Israel said, It is enough; Joseph my son is yet alive: I will go and see him before I die.

XLVI

^1And Israel took his journey with all that he had, and came to Beersheba, and offered sacrifices unto the God of his father Isaac. ^2And God spake unto Israel in the visions of the night, and said, Jacob, Jacob. And he said, Here am I. ^3And he said, I am God, the God of thy father: fear not to go down into Egypt; for I will there make of thee a great nation: ^4I will go down with thee into Egypt; and I will also surely bring thee up again: and Joseph shall put his hand upon thine eyes. ^5And Jacob rose up from Beersheba: and the sons of Israel carried Jacob their father, and their little ones, and their wives, in the wagons which Pharaoh had sent to carry him. ^6And they took their cattle, and their goods, which they had gotten in the land of Canaan, and came into Egypt, Jacob, and all his seed with him: ^7his sons, and his sons’ sons with him, his daughters, and his sons’ daughters, and all his seed brought he with him into Egypt.

^8And these are the names of the children of Israel, which came into Egypt, Jacob and his sons: Reuben, Jacob’s firstborn. ^9And the sons of Reuben; Hanoch, and Phallu, and Hezron, and Carmi. ^10And the sons of Simeon; Jemuel, and Jamin, and Ohad, and Jachin, and Zohar, and Shaul the son of a Canaanitish woman. ^11And the sons of Levi; Gershon, Kohath, and Merari. ^12And the sons of Judah; Er, and Onan, and Shelah, and Pharez, and Zarah: but Er and Onan died in the land of Canaan. And the sons of Pharez were Hezron and Hamul. ^13And the sons of Issachar; Tola, and Phuvah, and Job, and Shimron. ^14And the sons of Zebulun; Sered, and Elon, and Jahleel. ^15These be the sons of Leah, which she bare unto Jacob in Padanaram, with his daughter Dinah: all the souls of his sons and his daughters were thirty and three. ^16And the sons of Gad; Ziphion, and Haggi, Shuni, and Ezbon, Eri, and Arodi, and Areli. ^17And the sons of Asher; Jimnah, and Ishuah, and Isui, and Beriah, and Serah their sister: and the sons of Beriah; Heber, and Malchiel. ^18These are the sons of Zilpah, whom Laban gave to Leah his daughter, and these she bare unto Jacob, even sixteen souls. ^19The sons of Rachel Jacob’s wife; Joseph, and Benjamin. ^20And unto Joseph in the land of Egypt were born Manasseh and Ephraim, which Asenath the daughter of Potipherah priest of On bare unto him. ^21And the sons of Benjamin were Belah, and Becher, and Ashbel, Gera, and Naaman, Ehi, and Rosh, Muppim, and Huppim, and Ard. ^22These are the sons of Rachel, which were born to Jacob: all the souls were fourteen. ^23And the sons of Dan; Hushim. ^24And the sons of Naphtali; Jahzeel, and Guni, and Jezer, and Shillem. ^25These are the sons of Bilhah, which Laban gave unto Rachel his daughter, and she bare these unto Jacob: all the souls were seven. ^26All the souls that came with Jacob into Egypt, which came out of his loins, besides Jacob’s sons’ wives, all the souls were threescore and six; ^27and the sons of Joseph, which were born him in Egypt, were two souls: all the souls of the house of Jacob, which came into Egypt, were threescore and ten.

^28And he sent Judah before him unto Joseph, to direct his face unto Goshen; and they came into the land of Goshen. ^29And Joseph made ready his chariot, and went up to meet Israel his father, to Goshen, and presented himself unto him; and he fell on his neck, and wept on his neck a good while. ^30And Israel said unto Joseph, Now let me die, since I have seen thy face, because thou art yet alive. ^31And Joseph said unto his brethren, and unto his father’s house, I will go up, and shew Pharaoh, and say unto him, My brethren, and my father’s house, which were in the land of Canaan, are come unto me; ^32and the men are shepherds, for their trade hath been to feed cattle; and they have brought their flocks, and their herds, and all that they have. ^33And it shall come to pass, when Pharaoh shall call you, and shall say, What is your occupation? ^34That ye shall say, Thy servants’ trade hath been about cattle from our youth even until now, both we, and also our fathers: that ye may dwell in the land of Goshen; for every shepherd is an abomination unto the Egyptians.

XLVII

^1Then Joseph came and told Pharaoh, and said, My father and my brethren, and their flocks, and their herds, and all that they have, are come out of the land of Canaan; and, behold, they are in the land of Goshen. ^2And he took some of his brethren, even five men, and presented them unto Pharaoh. ^3And Pharaoh said unto his brethren, What is your occupation? And they said unto Pharaoh, Thy servants are shepherds, both we, and also our fathers. ^4They said morever unto Pharaoh, For to sojourn in the land are we come; for thy servants have no pasture for their flocks; for the famine is sore in the land of Canaan: now therefore, we pray thee, let thy servants dwell in the land of Goshen. ^5And Pharaoh spake unto Joseph, saying, Thy father and thy brethren are come unto thee: ^6the land of Egypt is before thee; in the best of the land make thy father and brethren to dwell; in the land of Goshen let them dwell: and if thou knowest any men of activity among them, then make them rulers over my cattle. ^7And Joseph brought in Jacob his father, and set him before Pharaoh: and Jacob blessed Pharaoh. ^8And Pharaoh said unto Jacob, How old art thou? ^9And Jacob said unto Pharaoh, The days of the years of my pilgrimage are an hundred and thirty years: few and evil have the days of the years of my life been, and have not attained unto the days of the years of the life of my fathers in the days of their pilgrimage. ^10And Jacob blessed Pharaoh, and went out from before Pharaoh.

^11And Joseph placed his father and his brethren, and gave them a possession in the land of Egypt, in the best of the land, in the land of Rameses, as Pharaoh had commanded. ^12And Joseph nourished his father, and his brethren, and all his father’s household, with bread, according to their families.

^13And there was no bread in all the land; for the famine was very sore, so that the land of Egypt and all the land of Canaan fainted by reason of the famine. ^14And Joseph gathered up all the money that was found in the land of Egypt, and in the land of Canaan, for the corn which they bought: and Joseph brought the money into Pharaoh’s house. ^15And when money failed in the land of Egypt, and in the land of Canaan, all the Egyptians came unto Joseph, and said, Give us bread: for why should we die in thy presence? for the money faileth. ^16And Joseph said, Give your cattle; and I will give you for your cattle, if money fail. ^17And they brought their cattle unto Joseph: and Joseph gave them bread in exchange for horses, and for the flocks, and for the cattle of the herds, and for the asses: and he fed them with bread for all their cattle for that year. ^18When that year was ended, they came unto him the second year, and said unto him, We will not hide it from my lord, how that our money is spent; my lord also hath our herds of cattle; there is not ought left in the sight of my lord, but our bodies, and our lands: ^19wherefore shall we die before thine eyes, both we and our land? buy us and our land for bread, and we and our land will be servants unto Pharaoh: and give us seed, that we may live, and not die, that the land be not desolate.

^20And Joseph bought all the land of Egypt for Pharaoh; for the Egyptians sold every man his field, because the famine prevailed over them: so the land became Pharaoh’s.

^21And as for the people, he removed them to cities from one end of the borders of Egypt even to the other end thereof. ^22Only the land of the priests bought he not; for the priests had a portion assigned them of Pharaoh, and did eat their portion which Pharaoh gave them: wherefore they sold not their lands. ^23Then Joseph said unto the people, Behold, I have bought you this day and your land for Pharaoh: lo, here is seed for you, and ye shall sow the land. ^24And it shall come to pass in the increase, that ye shall give the fifth part unto Pharaoh, and four parts shall be your own, for seed of the field, and for your food, and for them of your households, and for food for your little ones. ^25And they said, Thou hast saved our lives: let us find grace in the sight of my lord, and we will be Pharaoh’s servants. ^26And Joseph made it a law over the land of Egypt unto this day, that Pharaoh should have the fifth part, except the land of the priests only, which became not Pharaoh’s.

^27And Israel dwelt in the land of Egypt, in the country of Goshen; and they had possessions therein, and grew, and multiplied exceedingly. ^28And Jacob lived in the land of Egypt seventeen years: so the whole age of Jacob was an hundred forty and seven years. ^29And the time drew nigh that Israel must die: and he called his son Joseph, and said unto him, If now I have found grace in thy sight, put, I pray thee, thy hand under my thigh, and deal kindly and truly with me; bury me not, I pray thee, in Egypt: ^30but I will lie with my fathers, and thou shalt carry me out of Egypt, and bury me in their buryingplace. And he said, I will do as thou hast said. ^31And he said, Swear unto me. And he sware unto him. And Israel bowed himself upon the bed’s head.

XLVIII

^1And it came to pass after these things, that one told Joseph, Behold, thy father is sick: and he took with him his two sons, Manasseh and Ephraim. ^2And one told Jacob, and said, Behold, thy son Joseph cometh unto thee: and Israel strengthened himself, and sat upon the bed. ^3And Jacob said unto Joseph, God Almighty appeared unto me at Luz in the land of Canaan, and blessed me, ^4and said unto me, Behold, I will make thee fruitful, and multiply thee, and I will make of thee a multitude of people; and will give this land to thy seed after thee for an everlasting possession. ^5And now thy two sons, Ephraim and Manasseh, which were born unto thee in the land of Egypt before I came unto thee into Egypt, are mine; as Reuben and Simeon, they shall be mine. ^6And thy issue, which thou begettest after them, shall be thine, and shall be called after the name of their brethren in their inheritance. ^7And as for me, when I came from Padan, Rachel died by me in the land of Canaan in the way, when yet there was but a little way to come unto Ephrath: and I buried her there in the way of Ephrath; the same is Bethlehem.

^8And Israel beheld Joseph’s sons, and said, Who are these? ^9And Joseph said unto his father, They are my sons, whom God hath given me in this place. And he said, Bring them, I pray thee, unto me, and I will bless them. ^10Now the eyes of Israel were dim for age, so that he could not see. And he brought them near unto him; and he kissed them, and embraced them. ^11And Israel said unto Joseph, I had not thought to see thy face: and, lo, God hath shewed me also thy seed. ^12And Joseph brought them out from between his knees, and he bowed himself with his face to the earth. ^13And Joseph took them both, Ephraim in his right hand toward Israel’s left hand, and Manasseh in his left hand toward Israel’s right hand, and brought them near unto him. ^14And Israel stretched out his right hand, and laid it upon Ephraim’s head, who was the younger, and his left hand upon Manasseh’s head, guiding his hands wittingly; for Manasseh was the firstborn. ^15And he blessed Joseph, and said, God, before whom my fathers Abraham and Isaac did walk, the God which fed me all my life long unto this day, ^16the Angel which redeemed me from all evil, bless the lads; and let my name be named on them, and the name of my fathers Abraham and Isaac; and let them grow into a multitude in the midst of the earth.

^17And when Joseph saw that his father laid his right hand upon the head of Ephraim, it displeased him: and he held up his father’s hand, to remove it from Ephraim’s head unto Manasseh’s head. ^18And Joseph said unto his father, Not so, my father: for this is the firstborn; put thy right hand upon his head. ^19And his father refused, and said, I know it, my son, I know it: he also shall become a people, and he also shall be great: but truly his younger brother shall be greater than he, and his seed shall become a multitude of nations. ^20And he blessed them that day, saying, In thee shall Israel bless, saying, God make thee as Ephraim and as Manasseh: and he set Ephraim before Manasseh. ^21And Israel said unto Joseph, Behold, I die: but God shall be with you, and bring you again unto the land of your fathers. ^22Moreover I have given to thee one portion above thy brethren, which I took out of the hand of the Amorite with my sword and with my bow.

XLIX

^1And Jacob called unto his sons, and said, Gather yourselves together, that I may tell you that which shall befall you in the last days.

^2Gather yourselves together, and hear, ye sons of Jacob;
And hearken unto Israel your father.
^3Reuben, thou art my firstborn, my might, and the beginning of my strength,
The excellency of dignity, and the excellency of power:
^4Unstable as water, thou shalt not excel;
Because thou wentest up to thy father’s bed;
Then defiledst thou it: he went up to my couch.
^5Simeon and Levi are brethren;
Instruments of cruelty are in their habitations.
^6O my soul, come not thou into their secret;
Unto their assembly, mine honour, be not thou united:
For in their anger they slew a man,
And in their selfwill they digged down a wall.
^7Cursed be their anger, for it was fierce;
And their wrath, for it was cruel:
I will divide them in Jacob,
And scatter them in Israel.
^8Judah, thou art he whom thy brethren shall praise:
Thy hand shall be in the neck of thine enemies;
Thy father’s children shall bow down before thee.
^9Judah is a lion’s whelp:
From the prey, my son, thou art gone up:
He stooped down, he couched as a lion,
And as an old lion; who shall rouse him up?
^10The sceptre shall not depart from Judah,
Nor a lawgiver from between his feet,
Until Shiloh come;
And unto him shall the gathering of the people be.
^11Binding his foal unto the vine,
And his ass’s colt unto the choice vine;
He washed his garments in wine,
And his clothes in the blood of grapes:
^12His eyes shall be red with wine,
And his teeth white with milk.
^13Zebulun shall dwell at the haven of the sea;
And he shall be for an haven of ships;
And his border shall be unto Zidon.
^14Issachar is a strong ass
Couching down between two burdens:
^15And he saw that rest was good,
And the land that it was pleasant;
And bowed his shoulder to bear,
And became a servant unto tribute.
^16Dan shall judge his people,
As one of the tribes of Israel.
^17Dan shall be a serpent by the way,
An adder in the path,
That biteth the horse heels,
So that his rider shall fall backward.
^18I have waited for thy salvation, O Lord.
^19Gad, a troop shall overcome him:
But he shall overcome at the last.
^20Out of Asher his bread shall be fat,
And he shall yield royal dainties.
^21Naphtali is a hind let loose:
He giveth goodly words.
^22Joseph is a fruitful bough,
Even a fruitful bough by a well;
Whose branches run over the wall:
^23The archers have sorely grieved him,
And shot at him, and hated him:
^24But his bow abode in strength,
And the arms of his hands were made strong
By the hands of the mighty God of Jacob;
(From thence is the shepherd, the stone of Israel:)
^25Even by the God of thy father, who shall help thee;
And by the Almighty, who shall bless thee
With blessings of heaven above,
Blessings of the deep that lieth under,
Blessings of the breasts, and of the womb:
^26The blessings of thy father
Have prevailed above the blessings of my progenitors
Unto the utmost bound of the everlasting hills:
They shall be on the head of Joseph,
And on the crown of the head of him that was separate from his brethren.
^27Benjamin shall ravin as a wolf:
In the morning he shall devour the prey,
And at night he shall divide the spoil.

^28All these are the twelve tribes of Israel: and this is it that their father spake unto them, and blessed them; every one according to his blessing he blessed them. ^29And he charged them, and said unto them, I am to be gathered unto my people: bury me with my fathers in the cave that is in the field of Ephron the Hittite, ^30in the cave that is in the field of Machpelah, which is before Mamre, in the land of Canaan, which Abraham bought with the field of Ephron the Hittite for a possession of a buryingplace. ^31There they buried Abraham and Sarah his wife; there they buried Isaac and Rebekah his wife; and there I buried Leah. ^32The purchase of the field and of the cave that is therein was from the children of Heth. ^33And when Jacob had made an end of commanding his sons, he gathered up his feet into the bed, and yielded up the ghost, and was gathered unto his people.

L

^1And Joseph fell upon his father’s face, and wept upon him, and kissed him. ^2And Joseph commanded his servants the physicians to embalm his father: and the physicians embalmed Israel. ^3And forty days were fulfilled for him; for so are fulfilled the days of those which are embalmed: and the Egyptians mourned for him threescore and ten days.

^4And when the days of his mourning were past, Joseph spake unto the house of Pharaoh, saying, If now I have found grace in your eyes, speak, I pray you, in the ears of Pharaoh, saying, ^5My father made me swear, saying, Lo, I die: in my grave which I have digged for me in the land of Canaan, there shalt thou bury me. Now therefore let me go up, I pray thee, and bury my father, and I will come again. ^6And Pharaoh said, Go up, and bury thy father, according as he made thee swear.

^7And Joseph went up to bury his father: and with him went up all the servants of Pharaoh, the elders of his house, and all the elders of the land of Egypt, ^8and all the house of Joseph, and his brethren, and his father’s house: only their little ones, and their flocks, and their herds, they left in the land of Goshen. ^9And there went up with him both chariots and horsemen: and it was a very great company. ^10And they came to the threshingfloor of Atad, which is beyond Jordan, and there they mourned with a great and very sore lamentation: and he made a mourning for his father seven days. ^11And when the inhabitants of the land, the Canaanites, saw the mourning in the floor of Atad, they said, This is a grievous mourning to the Egyptians: wherefore the name of it was called Abelmizraim, which is beyond Jordan. ^12And his sons did unto him according as he commanded them: ^13for his sons carried him into the land of Canaan, and buried him in the cave of the field of Machpelah, which Abraham bought with the field for a possession of a buryingplace of Ephron the Hittite, before Mamre. ^14And Joseph returned into Egypt, he, and his brethren, and all that went up with him to bury his father, after he had buried his father.

^15And when Joseph’s brethren saw that their father was dead, they said, Joseph will peradventure hate us, and will certainly requite us all the evil which we did unto him. ^16And they sent a messenger unto Joseph, saying, Thy father did command before he died, saying, ^17So shall ye say unto Joseph, Forgive, I pray thee now, the trespass of thy brethren, and their sin; for they did unto thee evil: and now, we pray thee, forgive the trespass of the servants of the God of thy father. And Joseph wept when they spake unto him. ^18And his brethren also went and fell down before his face; and they said, Behold, we be thy servants. ^19And Joseph said unto them, Fear not: for am I in the place of God? ^20But as for you, ye thought evil against me; but God meant it unto good, to bring to pass, as it is this day, to save much people alive. ^21Now therefore fear ye not: I will nourish you, and your little ones. And he comforted them, and spake kindly unto them.

^22And Joseph dwelt in Egypt, he, and his father’s house: and Joseph lived an hundred and ten years. ^23And Joseph saw Ephraim’s children of the third generation: the children also of Machir the son of Manasseh were brought up upon Joseph’s knees. ^24And Joseph said unto his brethren, I die: and God will surely visit you, and bring you out of this land unto the land which he sware to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob. ^25And Joseph took an oath of the children of Israel, saying, God will surely visit you, and ye shall carry up my bones from hence. ^26So Joseph died, being an hundred and ten years old: and they embalmed him, and he was put in a coffin in Egypt.

Leviticus

The Third Book of Moses Called

Leviticus

I

^1And the Lord called unto Moses, and spake unto him out of the tabernacle of the congregation, saying, ^2Speak unto the children of Israel, and say unto them, If any man of you bring an offering unto the Lord, ye shall bring your offering of the cattle, even of the herd, and of the flock.

^3If his offering be a burnt sacrifice of the herd, let him offer a male without blemish: he shall offer it of his own voluntary will at the door of the tabernacle of the congregation before the Lord. ^4And he shall put his hand upon the head of the burnt offering; and it shall be accepted for him to make atonement for him. ^5And he shall kill the bullock before the Lord: and the priests, Aaron’s sons, shall bring the blood, and sprinkle the blood round about upon the altar that is by the door of the tabernacle of the congregation. ^6And he shall flay the burnt offering, and cut it into his pieces. ^7And the sons of Aaron the priest shall put fire upon the altar, and lay the wood in order upon the fire: ^8and the priests, Aaron’s sons, shall lay the parts, the head, and the fat, in order upon the wood that is on the fire which is upon the altar: ^9but his inwards and his legs shall he wash in water: and the priest shall burn all on the altar, to be a burnt sacrifice, an offering made by fire, of a sweet savour unto the Lord.

^10And if his offering be of the flocks, namely, of the sheep, or of the goats, for a burnt sacrifice; he shall bring it a male without blemish. ^11And he shall kill it on the side of the altar northward before the Lord: and the priests, Aaron’s sons, shall sprinkle his blood round about upon the altar. ^12And he shall cut it into his pieces, with his head and his fat: and the priest shall lay them in order on the wood that is on the fire which is upon the altar: ^13but he shall wash the inwards and the legs with water: and the priest shall bring it all, and burn it upon the altar: it is a burnt sacrifice, an offering made by fire, of a sweet savour unto the Lord.

^14And if the burnt sacrifice for his offering to the Lord be of fowls, then he shall bring his offering of turtledoves, or of young pigeons. ^15And the priest shall bring it unto the altar, and wring off his head, and burn it on the altar; and the blood thereof shall be wrung out at the side of the altar: ^16and he shall pluck away his crop with his feathers, and cast it beside the altar on the east part, by the place of the ashes: ^17and he shall cleave it with the wings thereof, but shall not divide it asunder: and the priest shall burn it upon the altar, upon the wood that is upon the fire: it is a burnt sacrifice, an offering made by fire, of a sweet savour unto the Lord.

II

^1And when any will offer a meat offering unto the Lord, his offering shall be of fine flour; and he shall pour oil upon it, and put frankincense thereon: ^2and he shall bring it to Aaron’s sons the priests: and he shall take thereout his handful of the flour thereof, and of the oil thereof, with all the frankincense thereof; and the priest shall burn the memorial of it upon the altar, to be an offering made by fire, of a sweet savour unto the Lord: ^3and the remnant of the meat offering shall be Aaron’s and his sons’: it is a thing most holy of the offerings of the Lord made by fire.

^4And if thou bring an oblation of a meat offering baken in the oven, it shall be unleavened cakes of fine flour mingled with oil, or unleavened wafers anointed with oil. ^5And if thy oblation be a meat offering baken in a pan, it shall be of fine flour unleavened, mingled with oil. ^6Thou shalt part it in pieces, and pour oil thereon: it is a meat offering. ^7And if thy oblation be a meat offering baken in the fryingpan, it shall be made of fine flour with oil. ^8And thou shalt bring the meat offering that is made of these things unto the Lord: and when it is presented unto the priest, he shall bring it unto the altar. ^9And the priest shall take from the meat offering a memorial thereof, and shall burn it upon the altar: it is an offering made by fire, of a sweet savour unto the Lord. ^10And that which is left of the meat offering shall be Aaron’s and his sons’: it is a thing most holy of the offerings of the Lord made by fire. ^11No meat offering, which ye shall bring unto the Lord, shall be made with leaven: for ye shall burn no leaven, nor any honey, in any offering of the Lord made by fire.

^12As for the oblation of the firstfruits, ye shall offer them unto the Lord: but they shall not be burnt on the altar for a sweet savour. ^13And every oblation of thy meat offering shalt thou season with salt; neither shalt thou suffer the salt of the covenant of thy God to be lacking from thy meat offering: with all thine offerings thou shalt offer salt.

^14And if thou offer a meat offering of thy firstfruits unto the Lord, thou shalt offer for the meat offering of thy firstfruits green ears of corn dried by the fire, even corn beaten out of full ears. ^15And thou shalt put oil upon it, and lay frankincense thereon: it is a meat offering. ^16And the priest shall burn the memorial of it, part of the beaten corn thereof, and part of the oil thereof, with all the frankincense thereof: it is an offering made by fire unto the Lord.

III

^1And if his oblation be a sacrifice of peace offering, if he offer it of the herd; whether it be a male or female, he shall offer it without blemish before the Lord. ^2And he shall lay his hand upon the head of his offering, and kill it at the door of the tabernacle of the congregation: and Aaron’s sons the priests shall sprinkle the blood upon the altar round about. ^3And he shall offer of the sacrifice of the peace offering an offering made by fire unto the Lord; the fat that covereth the inwards, and all the fat that is upon the inwards, ^4and the two kidneys, and the fat that is on them, which is by the flanks, and the caul above the liver, with the kidneys, it shall he take away. ^5And Aaron’s sons shall burn it on the altar upon the burnt sacrifice, which is upon the wood that is on the fire: it is an offering made by fire, of a sweet savour unto the Lord.

^6And if his offering for a sacrifice of peace offering unto the Lord be of the flock; male or female, he shall offer it without blemish. ^7If he offer a lamb for his offering, then shall he offer it before the Lord. ^8And he shall lay his hand upon the head of his offering, and kill it before the tabernacle of the congregation: and Aaron’s sons shall sprinkle the blood thereof round about upon the altar. ^9And he shall offer of the sacrifice of the peace offering an offering made by fire unto the Lord; the fat thereof, and the whole rump, it shall he take off hard by the backbone; and the fat that covereth the inwards, and all the fat that is upon the inwards, ^10and the two kidneys, and the fat that is upon them, which is by the flanks, and the caul above the liver, with the kidneys, it shall he take away. ^11And the priest shall burn it upon the altar: it is the food of the offering made by fire unto the Lord.

^12And if his offering be a goat, then he shall offer it before the Lord. ^13And he shall lay his hand upon the head of it, and kill it before the tabernacle of the congregation: and the sons of Aaron shall sprinkle the blood thereof upon the altar round about. ^14And he shall offer thereof his offering, even an offering made by fire unto the Lord; the fat that covereth the inwards, and all the fat that is upon the inwards, ^15and the two kidneys, and the fat that is upon them, which is by the flanks, and the caul above the liver, with the kidneys, it shall he take away. ^16And the priest shall burn them upon the altar: it is the food of the offering made by fire for a sweet savour: all the fat is the Lord’s. ^17It shall be a perpetual statute for your generations throughout all your dwellings, that ye eat neither fat nor blood.

IV

^1And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying, ^2Speak unto the children of Israel, saying, If a soul shall sin through ignorance against any of the commandments of the Lord concerning things which ought not to be done, and shall do against any of them:

^3if the priest that is anointed do sin according to the sin of the people; then let him bring for his sin, which he hath sinned, a young bullock without blemish unto the Lord for a sin offering. ^4And he shall bring the bullock unto the door of the tabernacle of the congregation before the Lord; and shall lay his hand upon the bullock’s head, and kill the bullock before the Lord. ^5And the priest that is anointed shall take of the bullock’s blood, and bring it to the tabernacle of the congregation: ^6and the priest shall dip his finger in the blood, and sprinkle of the blood seven times before the Lord, before the vail of the sanctuary. ^7And the priest shall put some of the blood upon the horns of the altar of sweet incense before the Lord, which is in the tabernacle of the congregation; and shall pour all the blood of the bullock at the bottom of the altar of the burnt offering, which is at the door of the tabernacle of the congregation. ^8And he shall take off from it all the fat of the bullock for the sin offering; the fat that covereth the inwards, and all the fat that is upon the inwards, ^9and the two kidneys, and the fat that is upon them, which is by the flanks, and the caul above the liver, with the kidneys, it shall he take away, ^10as it was taken off from the bullock of the sacrifice of peace offerings: and the priest shall burn them upon the altar of the burnt offering. ^11And the skin of the bullock, and all his flesh, with his head, and with his legs, and his inwards, and his dung, ^12even the whole bullock shall he carry forth without the camp unto a clean place, where the ashes are poured out, and burn him on the wood with fire: where the ashes are poured out shall he be burnt.

^13And if the whole congregation of Israel sin through ignorance, and the thing be hid from the eyes of the assembly, and they have done somewhat against any of the commandments of the Lord concerning things which should not be done, and are guilty; ^14when the sin, which they have sinned against it, is known, then the congregation shall offer a young bullock for the sin, and bring him before the tabernacle of the congregation. ^15And the elders of the congregation shall lay their hands upon the head of the bullock before the Lord: and the bullock shall be killed before the Lord. ^16And the priest that is anointed shall bring of the bullock’s blood to the tabernacle of the congregation: ^17and the priest shall dip his finger in some of the blood, and sprinkle it seven times before the Lord, even before the vail. ^18And he shall put some of the blood upon the horns of the altar which is before the Lord, that is in the tabernacle of the congregation, and shall pour out all the blood at the bottom of the altar of the burnt offering, which is at the door of the tabernacle of the congregation. ^19And he shall take all his fat from him, and burn it upon the altar. ^20And he shall do with the bullock as he did with the bullock for a sin offering, so shall he do with this: and the priest shall make an atonement for them, and it shall be forgiven them. ^21And he shall carry forth the bullock without the camp, and burn him as he burned the first bullock: it is a sin offering for the congregation.

^22When a ruler hath sinned, and done somewhat through ignorance against any of the commandments of the Lord his God concerning things which should not be done, and is guilty; ^23or if his sin, wherein he hath sinned, come to his knowledge; he shall bring his offering, a kid of the goats, a male without blemish: ^24and he shall lay his hand upon the head of the goat, and kill it in the place where they kill the burnt offering before the Lord: it is a sin offering. ^25And the priest shall take of the blood of the sin offering with his finger, and put it upon the horns of the altar of burnt offering, and shall pour out his blood at the bottom of the altar of burnt offering. ^26And he shall burn all his fat upon the altar, as the fat of the sacrifice of peace offerings: and the priest shall make an atonement for him as concerning his sin, and it shall be forgiven him.

^27And if any one of the common people sin through ignorance, while he doeth somewhat against any of the commandments of the Lord concerning things which ought not to be done, and be guilty; ^28or if his sin, which he hath sinned, come to his knowledge: then he shall bring his offering, a kid of the goats, a female without blemish, for his sin which he hath sinned. ^29And he shall lay his hand upon the head of the sin offering, and slay the sin offering in the place of the burnt offering. ^30And the priest shall take of the blood thereof with his finger, and put it upon the horns of the altar of burnt offering, and shall pour out all the blood thereof at the bottom of the altar. ^31And he shall take away all the fat thereof, as the fat is taken away from off the sacrifice of peace offerings; and the priest shall burn it upon the altar for a sweet savour unto the Lord; and the priest shall make an atonement for him, and it shall be forgiven him. ^32And if he bring a lamb for a sin offering, he shall bring it a female without blemish. ^33And he shall lay his hand upon the head of the sin offering, and slay it for a sin offering in the place where they kill the burnt offering. ^34And the priest shall take of the blood of the sin offering with his finger, and put it upon the horns of the altar of burnt offering, and shall pour out all the blood thereof at the bottom of the altar: ^35and he shall take away all the fat thereof, as the fat of the lamb is taken away from the sacrifice of the peace offerings; and the priest shall burn them upon the altar, according to the offerings made by fire unto the Lord: and the priest shall make an atonement for his sin that he hath committed, and it shall be forgiven him.

V

^1And if a soul sin, and hear the voice of swearing, and is a witness, whether he hath seen or known of it; if he do not utter it, then he shall bear his iniquity. ^2Or if a soul touch any unclean thing, whether it be a carcase of an unclean beast, or a carcase of unclean cattle, or the carcase of unclean creeping things, and if it be hidden from him; he also shall be unclean, and guilty. ^3Or if he touch the uncleanness of man, whatsoever uncleanness it be that a man shall be defiled withal, and it be hid from him; when he knoweth of it, then he shall be guilty. ^4Or if a soul swear, pronouncing with his lips to do evil, or to do good, whatsoever it be that a man shall pronounce with an oath, and it be hid from him; when he knoweth of it, then he shall be guilty in one of these. ^5And it shall be, when he shall be guilty in one of these things, that he shall confess that he hath sinned in that thing: ^6and he shall bring his trespass offering unto the Lord for his sin which he hath sinned, a female from the flock, a lamb or a kid of the goats, for a sin offering; and the priest shall make an atonement for him concerning his sin. ^7And if he be not able to bring a lamb, then he shall bring for his trespass, which he hath committed, two turtledoves, or two young pigeons, unto the Lord; one for a sin offering, and the other for a burnt offering. ^8And he shall bring them unto the priest, who shall offer that which is for the sin offering first, and wring off his head from his neck, but shall not divide it asunder: ^9and he shall sprinkle of the blood of the sin offering upon the side of the altar; and the rest of the blood shall be wrung out at the bottom of the altar: it is a sin offering. ^10And he shall offer the second for a burnt offering, according to the manner: and the priest shall make an atonement for him for his sin which he hath sinned, and it shall be forgiven him.

^11But if he be not able to bring two turtledoves, or two young pigeons, then he that sinned shall bring for his offering the tenth part of an ephah of fine flour for a sin offering; he shall put no oil upon it, neither shall he put any frankincense thereon: for it is a sin offering. ^12Then shall he bring it to the priest, and the priest shall take his handful of it, even a memorial thereof, and burn it on the altar, according to the offerings made by fire unto the Lord: it is a sin offering. ^13And the priest shall make an atonement for him as touching his sin that he hath sinned in one of these, and it shall be forgiven him: and the remnant shall be the priest’s, as a meat offering.

^14And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying, ^15If a soul commit a trespass, and sin through ignorance, in the holy things of the Lord; then he shall bring for his trespass unto the Lord a ram without blemish out of the flocks, with thy estimation by shekels of silver, after the shekel of the sanctuary, for a trespass offering. ^16And he shall make amends for the harm that he hath done in the holy thing, and shall add the fifth part thereto, and give it unto the priest: and the priest shall make an atonement for him with the ram of the trespass offering, and it shall be forgiven him. ^17And if a soul sin, and commit any of these things which are forbidden to be done by the commandments of the Lord; though he wist it not, yet is he guilty, and shall bear his iniquity. ^18And he shall bring a ram without blemish out of the flock, with thy estimation, for a trespass offering, unto the priest: and the priest shall make an atonement for him concerning his ignorance wherein he erred and wist it not, and it shall be forgiven him. ^19It is a trespass offering: he hath certainly trespassed against the Lord.

VI

^1And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying, ^2If a soul sin, and commit a trespass against the Lord, and lie unto his neighbour in that which was delivered him to keep, or in fellowship, or in a thing taken away by violence, or hath deceived his neighbour; ^3or have found that which was lost, and lieth concerning it, and sweareth falsely; in any of all these that a man doeth, sinning therein: ^4then it shall be, because he hath sinned, and is guilty, that he shall restore that which he took violently away, or the thing which he hath deceitfully gotten, or that which was delivered him to keep, or the lost thing which he found, ^5or all that about which he hath sworn falsely; he shall even restore it in the principal, and shall add the fifth part more thereto, and give it unto him to whom it appertaineth, in the day of his trespass offering. ^6And he shall bring his trespass offering unto the Lord, a ram without blemish out of the flock, with thy estimation, for a trespass offering, unto the priest: ^7and the priest shall make an atonement for him before the Lord: and it shall be forgiven him for any thing of all that he hath done in trespassing therein.

^8And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying, ^9Command Aaron and his sons, saying, This is the law of the burnt offering: It is the burnt offering, because of the burning upon the altar all night unto the morning, and the fire of the altar shall be burning in it. ^10And the priest shall put on his linen garment, and his linen breeches shall he put upon his flesh, and take up the ashes which the fire hath consumed with the burnt offering on the altar, and he shall put them beside the altar. ^11And he shall put off his garments, and put on other garments, and carry forth the ashes without the camp unto a clean place. ^12And the fire upon the altar shall be burning in it; it shall not be put out: and the priest shall burn wood on it every morning, and lay the burnt offering in order upon it; and he shall burn thereon the fat of the peace offerings. ^13The fire shall ever be burning upon the altar; it shall never go out.

^14And this is the law of the meat offering: the sons of Aaron shall offer it before the Lord, before the altar. ^15And he shall take of it his handful, of the flour of the meat offering, and of the oil thereof, and all the frankincense which is upon the meat offering, and shall burn it upon the altar for a sweet savour, even the memorial of it, unto the Lord. ^16And the remainder thereof shall Aaron and his sons eat: with unleavened bread shall it be eaten in the holy place; in the court of the tabernacle of the congregation they shall eat it. ^17It shall not be baken with leaven. I have given it unto them for their portion of my offerings made by fire; it is most holy, as is the sin offering, and as the trespass offering. ^18All the males among the children of Aaron shall eat of it. It shall be a statute for ever in your generations concerning the offerings of the Lord made by fire: every one that toucheth them shall be holy.

^19And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying, ^20This is the offering of Aaron and of his sons, which they shall offer unto the Lord in the day when he is anointed; the tenth part of an ephah of fine flour for a meat offering perpetual, half of it in the morning, and half thereof at night. ^21In a pan it shall be made with oil; and when it is baken, thou shalt bring it in: and the baken pieces of the meat offering shalt thou offer for a sweet savour unto the Lord. ^22And the priest of his sons that is anointed in his stead shall offer it: it is a statute for ever unto the Lord; it shall be wholly burnt. ^23For every meat offering for the priest shall be wholly burnt: it shall not be eaten.

^24And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying, ^25Speak unto Aaron and to his sons, saying, This is the law of the sin offering: In the place where the burnt offering is killed shall the sin offering be killed before the Lord: it is most holy. ^26The priest that offereth it for sin shall eat it: in the holy place shall it be eaten, in the court of the tabernacle of the congregation. ^27Whatsoever shall touch the flesh thereof shall be holy: and when there is sprinkled of the blood thereof upon any garment, thou shalt wash that whereon it was sprinkled in the holy place. ^28But the earthen vessel wherein it is sodden shall be broken: and if it be sodden in a brasen pot, it shall be both scoured, and rinsed in water. ^29All the males among the priests shall eat thereof: it is most holy. ^30And no sin offering, whereof any of the blood is brought into the tabernacle of the congregation to reconcile withal in the holy place, shall be eaten: it shall be burnt in the fire.

VII

^1Likewise this is the law of the trespass offering: it is most holy. ^2In the place where they kill the burnt offering shall they kill the trespass offering: and the blood thereof shall he sprinkle round about upon the altar. ^3And he shall offer of it all the fat thereof; the rump, and the fat that covereth the inwards, ^4and the two kidneys, and the fat that is on them, which is by the flanks, and the caul that is above the liver, with the kidneys, it shall he take away: ^5and the priest shall burn them upon the altar for an offering made by fire unto the Lord: it is a trespass offering. ^6Every male among the priests shall eat thereof: it shall be eaten in the holy place: it is most holy. ^7As the sin offering is, so is the trespass offering: there is one law for them: the priest that maketh atonement therewith shall have it.

^8And the priest that offereth any man’s burnt offering, even the priest shall have to himself the skin of the burnt offering which he hath offered. ^9And all the meat offering that is baken in the oven, and all that is dressed in the fryingpan, and in the pan, shall be the priest’s that offereth it. ^10And every meat offering, mingled with oil, and dry, shall all the sons of Aaron have, one as much as another.

^11And this is the law of the sacrifice of peace offerings, which he shall offer unto the Lord. ^12If he offer it for a thanksgiving, then he shall offer with the sacrifice of thanksgiving unleavened cakes mingled with oil, and unleavened wafers anointed with oil, and cakes mingled with oil, of fine flour, fried. ^13Besides the cakes, he shall offer for his offering leavened bread with the sacrifice of thanksgiving of his peace offerings. ^14And of it he shall offer one out of the whole oblation for an heave offering unto the Lord, and it shall be the priest’s that sprinkleth the blood of the peace offerings. ^15And the flesh of the sacrifice of his peace offerings for thanksgiving shall be eaten the same day that it is offered; he shall not leave any of it until the morning.

^16But if the sacrifice of his offering be a vow, or a voluntary offering, it shall be eaten the same day that he offereth his sacrifice: and on the morrow also the remainder of it shall be eaten: ^17but the remainder of the flesh of the sacrifice on the third day shall be burnt with fire. ^18And if any of the flesh of the sacrifice of his peace offerings be eaten at all on the third day, it shall not be accepted, neither shall it be imputed unto him that offereth it: it shall be an abomination, and the soul that eateth of it shall bear his iniquity.

^19And the flesh that toucheth any unclean thing shall not be eaten; it shall be burnt with fire: and as for the flesh, all that be clean shall eat thereof. ^20But the soul that eateth of the flesh of the sacrifice of peace offerings, that pertain unto the Lord, having his uncleanness upon him, even that soul shall be cut off from his people. ^21Moreover the soul that shall touch any unclean thing, as the uncleanness of man, or any unclean beast, or any abominable unclean thing, and eat of the flesh of the sacrifice of peace offerings, which pertain unto the Lord, even that soul shall be cut off from his people.

^22And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying, ^23Speak unto the children of Israel, saying, Ye shall eat no manner of fat, of ox, or of sheep, or of goat. ^24And the fat of the beast that dieth of itself, and the fat of that which is torn with beasts, may be used in any other use: but ye shall in no wise eat of it. ^25For whosoever eateth the fat of the beast, of which men offer an offering made by fire unto the Lord, even the soul that eateth it shall be cut off from his people. ^26Moreover ye shall eat no manner of blood, whether it be of fowl or of beast, in any of your dwellings. ^27Whatsoever soul it be that eateth any manner of blood, even that soul shall be cut off from his people.

^28And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying, ^29Speak unto the children of Israel, saying, He that offereth the sacrifice of his peace offerings unto the Lord shall bring his oblation unto the Lord of the sacrifice of his peace offerings. ^30His own hands shall bring the offerings of the Lord made by fire, the fat with the breast, it shall he bring, that the breast may be waved for a wave offering before the Lord. ^31And the priest shall burn the fat upon the altar: but the breast shall be Aaron’s and his sons’. ^32And the right shoulder shall ye give unto the priest for an heave offering of the sacrifices of your peace offerings. ^33He among the sons of Aaron, that offereth the blood of the peace offerings, and the fat, shall have the right shoulder for his part. ^34For the wave breast and the heave shoulder have I taken of the children of Israel from off the sacrifices of their peace offerings, and have given them unto Aaron the priest and unto his sons by a statute for ever from among the children of Israel.

^35This is the portion of the anointing of Aaron, and of the anointing of his sons, out of the offerings of the Lord made by fire, in the day when he presented them to minister unto the Lord in the priest’s office; ^36which the Lord commanded to be given them of the children of Israel, in the day that he anointed them, by a statute for ever throughout their generations.

^37This is the law of the burnt offering, of the meat offering, and of the sin offering, and of the trespass offering, and of the consecrations, and of the sacrifice of the peace offerings; ^38which the Lord commanded Moses in mount Sinai, in the day that he commanded the children of Israel to offer their oblations unto the Lord, in the wilderness of Sinai.

VIII

^1And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying, ^2Take Aaron and his sons with him, and the garments, and the anointing oil, and a bullock for the sin offering, and two rams, and a basket of unleavened bread; ^3and gather thou all the congregation together unto the door of the tabernacle of the congregation. ^4And Moses did as the Lord commanded him; and the assembly was gathered together unto the door of the tabernacle of the congregation. ^5And Moses said unto the congregation, This is the thing which the Lord commanded to be done.

^6And Moses brought Aaron and his sons, and washed them with water. ^7And he put upon him the coat, and girded him with the girdle, and clothed him with the robe, and put the ephod upon him, and he girded him with the curious girdle of the ephod, and bound it unto him therewith. ^8And he put the breastplate upon him: also he put in the breastplate the Urim and the Thummim. ^9And he put the mitre upon his head; also upon the mitre, even upon his forefront, did he put the golden plate, the holy crown; as the Lord commanded Moses.

^10And Moses took the anointing oil, and anointed the tabernacle and all that was therein, and sanctified them. ^11And he sprinkled thereof upon the altar seven times, and anointed the altar and all his vessels, both the laver and his foot, to sanctify them. ^12And he poured of the anointing oil upon Aaron’s head, and anointed him, to sanctify him. ^13And Moses brought Aaron’s sons, and put coats upon them, and girded them with girdles, and put bonnets upon them; as the Lord commanded Moses.

^14And he brought the bullock for the sin offering: and Aaron and his sons laid their hands upon the head of the bullock for the sin offering. ^15And he slew it; and Moses took the blood, and put it upon the horns of the altar round about with his finger, and purified the altar, and poured the blood at the bottom of the altar, and sanctified it, to make reconciliation upon it. ^16And he took all the fat that was upon the inwards, and the caul above the liver, and the two kidneys, and their fat, and Moses burned it upon the altar. ^17But the bullock, and his hide, his flesh, and his dung, he burnt with fire without the camp; as the Lord commanded Moses.

^18And he brought the ram for the burnt offering: and Aaron and his sons laid their hands upon the head of the ram. ^19And he killed it; and Moses sprinkled the blood upon the altar round about. ^20And he cut the ram into pieces; and Moses burnt the head, and the pieces, and the fat. ^21And he washed the inwards and the legs in water; and Moses burnt the whole ram upon the altar: it was a burnt sacrifice for a sweet savour, and an offering made by fire unto the Lord; as the Lord commanded Moses.

^22And he brought the other ram, the ram of consecration: and Aaron and his sons laid their hands upon the head of the ram. ^23And he slew it; and Moses took of the blood of it, and put it upon the tip of Aaron’s right ear, and upon the thumb of his right hand, and upon the great toe of his right foot. ^24And he brought Aaron’s sons, and Moses put of the blood upon the tip of their right ear, and upon the thumbs of their right hands, and upon the great toes of their right feet: and Moses sprinkled the blood upon the altar round about. ^25And he took the fat, and the rump, and all the fat that was upon the inwards, and the caul above the liver, and the two kidneys, and their fat, and the right shoulder: ^26and out of the basket of unleavened bread, that was before the Lord, he took one unleavened cake, and a cake of oiled bread, and one wafer, and put them on the fat, and upon the right shoulder: ^27and he put all upon Aaron’s hands, and upon his sons’ hands, and waved them for a wave offering before the Lord. ^28And Moses took them from off their hands, and burnt them on the altar upon the burnt offering: they were consecrations for a sweet savour: it is an offering made by fire unto the Lord. ^29And Moses took the breast, and waved it for a wave offering before the Lord: for of the ram of consecration it was Moses’ part; as the Lord commanded Moses. ^30And Moses took of the anointing oil, and of the blood which was upon the altar, and sprinkled it upon Aaron, and upon his garments, and upon his sons, and upon his sons’ garments with him; and sanctified Aaron, and his garments, and his sons, and his sons’ garments with him.

^31And Moses said unto Aaron and to his sons, Boil the flesh at the door of the tabernacle of the congregation: and there eat it with the bread that is in the basket of consecrations, as I commanded, saying, Aaron and his sons shall eat it. ^32And that which remaineth of the flesh and of the bread shall ye burn with fire. ^33And ye shall not go out of the door of the tabernacle of the congregation in seven days, until the days of your consecration be at an end: for seven days shall he consecrate you. ^34As he hath done this day, so the Lord hath commanded to do, to make an atonement for you. ^35Therefore shall ye abide at the door of the tabernacle of the congregation day and night seven days, and keep the charge of the Lord, that ye die not: for so I am commanded. ^36So Aaron and his sons did all things which the Lord commanded by the hand of Moses.

IX

^1And it came to pass on the eighth day, that Moses called Aaron and his sons, and the elders of Israel; ^2and he said unto Aaron, Take thee a young calf for a sin offering, and a ram for a burnt offering, without blemish, and offer them before the Lord. ^3And unto the children of Israel thou shalt speak, saying, Take ye a kid of the goats for a sin offering; and a calf and a lamb, both of the first year, without blemish, for a burnt offering; ^4also a bullock and a ram for peace offerings, to sacrifice before the Lord; and a meat offering mingled with oil: for to day the Lord will appear unto you.

^5And they brought that which Moses commanded before the tabernacle of the congregation: and all the congregation drew near and stood before the Lord. ^6And Moses said, This is the thing which the Lord commanded that ye should do: and the glory of the Lord shall appear unto you. ^7And Moses said unto Aaron, Go unto the altar, and offer thy sin offering, and thy burnt offering, and make an atonement for thyself, and for the people: and offer the offering of the people, and make an atonement for them; as the Lord commanded.

^8Aaron therefore went unto the altar, and slew the calf of the sin offering, which was for himself. ^9And the sons of Aaron brought the blood unto him: and he dipped his finger in the blood, and put it upon the horns of the altar, and poured out the blood at the bottom of the altar: ^10but the fat, and the kidneys, and the caul above the liver of the sin offering, he burnt upon the altar; as the Lord commanded Moses. ^11And the flesh and the hide he burnt with fire without the camp. ^12And he slew the burnt offering; and Aaron’s sons presented unto him the blood, which he sprinkled round about upon the altar. ^13And they presented the burnt offering unto him, with the pieces thereof, and the head: and he burnt them upon the altar. ^14And he did wash the inwards and the legs, and burnt them upon the burnt offering on the altar.

^15And he brought the people’s offering, and took the goat, which was the sin offering for the people, and slew it, and offered it for sin, as the first. ^16And he brought the burnt offering, and offered it according to the manner. ^17And he brought the meat offering, and took an handful thereof, and burnt it upon the altar, beside the burnt sacrifice of the morning. ^18He slew also the bullock and the ram for a sacrifice of peace offerings, which was for the people: and Aaron’s sons presented unto him the blood, which he sprinkled upon the altar round about, ^19and the fat of the bullock and of the ram, the rump, and that which covereth the inwards, and the kidneys, and the caul above the liver: ^20and they put the fat upon the breasts, and he burnt the fat upon the altar: ^21and the breasts and the right shoulder Aaron waved for a wave offering before the Lord; as Moses commanded.

^22And Aaron lifted up his hand toward the people, and blessed them, and came down from offering of the sin offering, and the burnt offering, and peace offerings. ^23And Moses and Aaron went into the tabernacle of the congregation, and came out, and blessed the people: and the glory of the Lord appeared unto all the people. ^24And there came a fire out from before the Lord, and consumed upon the altar the burnt offering and the fat: which when all the people saw, they shouted, and fell on their faces.

X

^1And Nadab and Abihu, the sons of Aaron, took either of them his censer, and put fire therein, and put incense thereon, and offered strange fire before the Lord, which he commanded them not. ^2And there went out fire from the Lord, and devoured them, and they died before the Lord. ^3Then Moses said unto Aaron, This is it that the Lord spake, saying, I will be sanctified in them that come nigh me, and before all the people I will be glorified. And Aaron held his peace. ^4And Moses called Mishael and Elzaphan, the sons of Uzziel the uncle of Aaron, and said unto them, Come near, carry your brethren from before the sanctuary out of the camp. ^5So they went near, and carried them in their coats out of the camp; as Moses had said. ^6And Moses said unto Aaron, and unto Eleazar and unto Ithamar, his sons, Uncover not your heads, neither rend your clothes; lest ye die, and lest wrath come upon all the people: but let your brethren, the whole house of Israel, bewail the burning which the Lord hath kindled. ^7And ye shall not go out from the door of the tabernacle of the congregation, lest ye die: for the anointing oil of the Lord is upon you. And they did according to the word of Moses.

^8And the Lord spake unto Aaron, saying, ^9Do not drink wine nor strong drink, thou, nor thy sons with thee, when ye go into the tabernacle of the congregation, lest ye die: it shall be a statute for ever throughout your generations: ^10and that ye may put difference between holy and unholy, and between unclean and clean; ^11and that ye may teach the children of Israel all the statutes which the Lord hath spoken unto them by the hand of Moses.

^12And Moses spake unto Aaron, and unto Eleazar and unto Ithamar, his sons that were left, Take the meat offering that remaineth of the offerings of the Lord made by fire, and eat it without leaven beside the altar: for it is most holy: ^13and ye shall eat it in the holy place, because it is thy due, and thy sons’ due, of the sacrifices of the Lord made by fire: for so I am commanded. ^14And the wave breast and heave shoulder shall ye eat in a clean place; thou, and thy sons, and thy daughters with thee: for they be thy due, and thy sons’ due, which are given out of the sacrifices of peace offerings of the children of Israel. ^15The heave shoulder and the wave breast shall they bring with the offerings made by fire of the fat, to wave it for a wave offering before the Lord; and it shall be thine, and thy sons’ with thee, by a statute for ever; as the Lord hath commanded.

^16And Moses diligently sought the goat of the sin offering, and, behold, it was burnt: and he was angry with Eleazar and Ithamar, the sons of Aaron which were left alive, saying, ^17Wherefore have ye not eaten the sin offering in the holy place, seeing it is most holy, and God hath given it you to bear the iniquity of the congregation, to make atonement for them before the Lord? ^18Behold, the blood of it was not brought in within the holy place: ye should indeed have eaten it in the holy place, as I commanded. ^19And Aaron said unto Moses, Behold, this day have they offered their sin offering and their burnt offering before the Lord; and such things have befallen me: and if I had eaten the sin offering to day, should it have been accepted in the sight of the Lord? ^20And when Moses heard that, he was content.

XI

^1And the Lord spake unto Moses and to Aaron, saying unto them, ^2Speak unto the children of Israel, saying, These are the beasts which ye shall eat among all the beasts that are on the earth.

^3Whatsoever parteth the hoof, and is clovenfooted, and cheweth the cud, among the beasts, that shall ye eat. ^4Nevertheless these shall ye not eat of them that chew the cud, or of them that divide the hoof: as the camel, because he cheweth the cud, but divideth not the hoof; he is unclean unto you. ^5And the coney, because he cheweth the cud, but divideth not the hoof; he is unclean unto you. ^6And the hare, because he cheweth the cud, but divideth not the hoof; he is unclean unto you. ^7And the swine, though he divide the hoof, and be clovenfooted, yet he cheweth not the cud; he is unclean to you. ^8Of their flesh shall ye not eat, and their carcase shall ye not touch; they are unclean to you.

^9These shall ye eat of all that are in the waters: whatsoever hath fins and scales in the waters, in the seas, and in the rivers, them shall ye eat. ^10And all that have not fins and scales in the seas, and in the rivers, of all that move in the waters, and of any living thing which is in the waters, they shall be an abomination unto you: ^11they shall be even an abomination unto you; ye shall not eat of their flesh, but ye shall have their carcases in abomination. ^12Whatsoever hath no fins nor scales in the waters, that shall be an abomination unto you.

^13And these are they which ye shall have in abomination among the fowls; they shall not be eaten, they are an abomination: the eagle, and the ossifrage, and the ospray, ^14and the vulture, and the kite after his kind; ^15every raven after his kind; ^16and the owl, and the night hawk, and the cuckow, and the hawk after his kind, ^17and the little owl, and the cormorant, and the great owl, ^18and the swan, and the pelican, and the gier eagle, ^19and the stork, the heron after her kind, and the lapwing, and the bat. ^20All fowls that creep, going upon all four, shall be an abomination unto you. ^21Yet these may ye eat of every flying creeping thing that goeth upon all four, which have legs above their feet, to leap withal upon the earth; ^22even these of them ye may eat; the locust after his kind, and the bald locust after his kind, and the beetle after his kind, and the grasshopper after his kind. ^23But all other flying creeping things, which have four feet, shall be an abomination unto you. ^24And for these ye shall be unclean: whosoever toucheth the carcase of them shall be unclean until the even. ^25And whosoever beareth ought of the carcase of them shall wash his clothes, and be unclean until the even. ^26The carcases of every beast which divideth the hoof, and is not clovenfooted, nor cheweth the cud, are unclean unto you: every one that toucheth them shall be unclean. ^27And whatsoever goeth upon his paws, among all manner of beasts that go on all four, those are unclean unto you: whoso toucheth their carcase shall be unclean until the even. ^28And he that beareth the carcase of them shall wash his clothes, and be unclean until the even: they are unclean unto you.

^29These also shall be unclean unto you among the creeping things that creep upon the earth; the weasel, and the mouse, and the tortoise after his kind, ^30and the ferret, and the chameleon, and the lizard, and the snail, and the mole. ^31These are unclean to you among all that creep: whosoever doth touch them, when they be dead, shall be unclean until the even. ^32And upon whatsoever any of them, when they are dead, doth fall, it shall be unclean; whether it be any vessel of wood, or raiment, or skin, or sack, whatsoever vessel it be, wherein any work is done, it must be put into water, and it shall be unclean until the even; so it shall be cleansed. ^33And every earthen vessel, whereinto any of them falleth, whatsoever is in it shall be unclean; and ye shall break it. ^34Of all meat which may be eaten, that on which such water cometh shall be unclean: and all drink that may be drunk in every such vessel shall be unclean. ^35And every thing whereupon any part of their carcase falleth shall be unclean; whether it be oven, or ranges for pots, they shall be broken down: for they are unclean and shall be unclean unto you. ^36Nevertheless a fountain or pit, wherein there is plenty of water, shall be clean: but that which toucheth their carcase shall be unclean. ^37And if any part of their carcase fall upon any sowing seed which is to be sown, it shall be clean. ^38But if any water be put upon the seed, and any part of their carcase fall thereon, it shall be unclean unto you. ^39And if any beast, of which ye may eat, die; he that toucheth the carcase thereof shall be unclean until the even. ^40And he that eateth of the carcase of it shall wash his clothes, and be unclean until the even: he also that beareth the carcase of it shall wash his clothes, and be unclean until the even. ^41And every creeping thing that creepeth upon the earth shall be an abomination; it shall not be eaten. ^42Whatsoever goeth upon the belly, and whatsoever goeth upon all four, or whatsoever hath more feet among all creeping things that creep upon the earth, them ye shall not eat; for they are an abomination. ^43Ye shall not make yourselves abominable with any creeping thing that creepeth, neither shall ye make yourselves unclean with them, that ye should be defiled thereby. ^44For I am the Lord your God: ye shall therefore sanctify yourselves, and ye shall be holy; for I am holy: neither shall ye defile yourselves with any manner of creeping thing that creepeth upon the earth. ^45For I am the Lord that bringeth you up out of the land of Egypt, to be your God: ye shall therefore be holy, for I am holy. ^46This is the law of the beasts, and of the fowl, and of every living creature that moveth in the waters, and of every creature that creepeth upon the earth: ^47to make a difference between the unclean and the clean, and between the beast that may be eaten and the beast that may not be eaten.

XII

^1And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying, ^2Speak unto the children of Israel, saying, If a woman have conceived seed, and born a man child: then she shall be unclean seven days; according to the days of the separation for her infirmity shall she be unclean. ^3And in the eighth day the flesh of his foreskin shall be circumcised. ^4And she shall then continue in the blood of her purifying three and thirty days; she shall touch no hallowed thing, nor come into the sanctuary, until the days of her purifying be fulfilled. ^5But if she bear a maid child, then she shall be unclean two weeks, as in her separation: and she shall continue in the blood of her purifying threescore and six days. ^6And when the days of her purifying are fulfilled, for a son, or for a daughter, she shall bring a lamb of the first year for a burnt offering, and a young pigeon, or a turtledove, for a sin offering, unto the door of the tabernacle of the congregation, unto the priest: ^7who shall offer it before the Lord, and make an atonement for her; and she shall be cleansed from the issue of her blood. This is the law for her that hath born a male or a female. ^8And if she be not able to bring a lamb, then she shall bring two turtles, or two young pigeons; the one for the burnt offering, and the other for a sin offering: and the priest shall make an atonement for her, and she shall be clean.

XIII

^1And the Lord spake unto Moses and Aaron, saying, ^2When a man shall have in the skin of his flesh a rising, a scab, or bright spot, and it be in the skin of his flesh like the plague of leprosy; then he shall be brought unto Aaron the priest, or unto one of his sons the priests: ^3and the priest shall look on the plague in the skin of the flesh: and when the hair in the plague is turned white, and the plague in sight be deeper than the skin of his flesh, it is a plague of leprosy: and the priest shall look on him, and pronounce him unclean. ^4If the bright spot be white in the skin of his flesh, and in sight be not deeper than the skin, and the hair thereof be not turned white; then the priest shall shut up him that hath the plague seven days: ^5and the priest shall look on him the seventh day: and, behold, if the plague in his sight be at a stay, and the plague spread not in the skin; then the priest shall shut him up seven days more: ^6and the priest shall look on him again the seventh day: and, behold, if the plague be somewhat dark, and the plague spread not in the skin, the priest shall pronounce him clean: it is but a scab: and he shall wash his clothes, and be clean. ^7But if the scab spread much abroad in the skin, after that he hath been seen of the priest for his cleansing, he shall be seen of the priest again. ^8And if the priest see that, behold, the scab spreadeth in the skin, then the priest shall pronounce him unclean: it is a leprosy.

^9When the plague of leprosy is in a man, then he shall be brought unto the priest; ^10and the priest shall see him: and, behold, if the rising be white in the skin, and it have turned the hair white, and there be quick raw flesh in the rising; ^11it is an old leprosy in the skin of his flesh, and the priest shall pronounce him unclean, and shall not shut him up: for he is unclean. ^12And if a leprosy break out abroad in the skin, and the leprosy cover all the skin of him that hath the plague from his head even to his foot, wheresoever the priest looketh; ^13then the priest shall consider: and, behold, if the leprosy have covered all his flesh, he shall pronounce him clean that hath the plague: it is all turned white: he is clean. ^14But when raw flesh appeareth in him, he shall be unclean. ^15And the priest shall see the raw flesh, and pronounce him to be unclean: for the raw flesh is unclean: it is a leprosy. ^16Or if the raw flesh turn again, and be changed unto white, he shall come unto the priest; ^17and the priest shall see him: and, behold, if the plague be turned into white; then the priest shall pronounce him clean that hath the plague: he is clean.

^18The flesh also, in which, even in the skin thereof, was a boil, and is healed, ^19and in the place of the boil there be a white rising, or a bright spot, white, and somewhat reddish, and it be shewed to the priest; ^20and if, when the priest seeth it, behold, it be in sight lower than the skin, and the hair thereof be turned white; the priest shall pronounce him unclean: it is a plague of leprosy broken out of the boil. ^21But if the priest look on it, and, behold, there be no white hairs therein, and if it be not lower than the skin, but be somewhat dark; then the priest shall shut him up seven days: ^22and if it spread much abroad in the skin, then the priest shall pronounce him unclean: it is a plague. ^23But if the bright spot stay in his place, and spread not, it is a burning boil; and the priest shall pronounce him clean.

^24Or if there be any flesh, in the skin whereof there is a hot burning, and the quick flesh that burneth have a white bright spot, somewhat reddish, or white; ^25then the priest shall look upon it: and, behold, if the hair in the bright spot be turned white, and it be in sight deeper than the skin; it is a leprosy broken out of the burning: wherefore the priest shall pronounce him unclean: it is the plague of leprosy. ^26But if the priest look on it, and, behold, there be no white hair in the bright spot, and it be no lower than the other skin, but be somewhat dark; then the priest shall shut him up seven days: ^27and the priest shall look upon him the seventh day: and if it be spread much abroad in the skin, then the priest shall pronounce him unclean: it is the plague of leprosy. ^28And if the bright spot stay in his place, and spread not in the skin, but it be somewhat dark; it is a rising of the burning, and the priest shall pronounce him clean: for it is an inflammation of the burning.

^29If a man or woman have a plague upon the head or the beard; ^30then the priest shall see the plague: and, behold, if it be in sight deeper than the skin; and there be in it a yellow thin hair; then the priest shall pronounce him unclean: it is a dry scall, even a leprosy upon the head or beard. ^31And if the priest look on the plague of the scall, and, behold, it be not in sight deeper than the skin, and that there is no black hair in it; then the priest shall shut up him that hath the plague of the scall seven days: ^32and in the seventh day the priest shall look on the plague: and, behold, if the scall spread not, and there be in it no yellow hair, and the scall be not in sight deeper than the skin; ^33he shall be shaven, but the scall shall he not shave; and the priest shall shut up him that hath the scall seven days more: ^34and in the seventh day the priest shall look on the scall: and, behold, if the scall be not spread in the skin, nor be in sight deeper than the skin; then the priest shall pronounce him clean: and he shall wash his clothes, and be clean. ^35But if the scall spread much in the skin after his cleansing; ^36then the priest shall look on him: and, behold, if the scall be spread in the skin, the priest shall not seek for yellow hair; he is unclean. ^37But if the scall be in his sight at a stay, and that there is black hair grown up therein; the scall is healed, he is clean: and the priest shall pronounce him clean.

^38If a man also or a woman have in the skin of their flesh bright spots, even white bright spots; ^39then the priest shall look: and, behold, if the bright spots in the skin of their flesh be darkish white; it is a freckled spot that groweth in the skin; he is clean. ^40And the man whose hair is fallen off his head, he is bald; yet is he clean. ^41And he that hath his hair fallen off from the part of his head toward his face, he is forehead bald: yet is he clean. ^42And if there be in the bald head, or bald forehead, a white reddish sore; it is a leprosy sprung up in his bald head, or his bald forehead. ^43Then the priest shall look upon it: and, behold, if the rising of the sore be white reddish in his bald head, or in his bald forehead, as the leprosy appeareth in the skin of the flesh; ^44he is a leprous man, he is unclean: the priest shall pronounce him utterly unclean; his plague is in his head. ^45And the leper in whom the plague is, his clothes shall be rent, and his head bare, and he shall put a covering upon his upper lip, and shall cry, Unclean, unclean. ^46All the days wherein the plague shall be in him he shall be defiled; he is unclean: he shall dwell alone; without the camp shall his habitation be.

^47The garment also that the plague of leprosy is in, whether it be a woollen garment, or a linen garment; ^48whether it be in the warp, or woof; of linen, or of woollen; whether in a skin, or in any thing made of skin; ^49and if the plague be greenish or reddish in the garment, or in the skin, either in the warp, or in the woof, or in any thing of skin; it is a plague of leprosy, and shall be shewed unto the priest: ^50and the priest shall look upon the plague, and shut up it that hath the plague seven days: ^51and he shall look on the plague on the seventh day: if the plague be spread in the garment, either in the warp, or in the woof, or in a skin, or in any work that is made of skin; the plague is a fretting leprosy; it is unclean. ^52He shall therefore burn that garment, whether warp or woof, in woollen or in linen, or any thing of skin, wherein the plague is: for it is a fretting leprosy; it shall be burnt in the fire. ^53And if the priest shall look, and, behold, the plague be not spread in the garment, either in the warp, or in the woof, or in any thing of skin; ^54then the priest shall command that they wash the thing wherein the plague is, and he shall shut it up seven days more: ^55and the priest shall look on the plague, after that it is washed: and, behold, if the plague have not changed his colour, and the plague be not spread; it is unclean; thou shalt burn it in the fire; it is fret inward, whether it be bare within or without. ^56And if the priest look, and, behold, the plague be somewhat dark after the washing of it; then he shall rend it out of the garment, or out of the skin, or out of the warp, or out of the woof: ^57and if it appear still in the garment, either in the warp, or in the woof, or in any thing of skin; it is a spreading plague: thou shalt burn that wherein the plague is with fire. ^58And the garment, either warp, or woof, or whatsoever thing of skin it be, which thou shalt wash, if the plague be departed from them, then it shall be washed the second time, and shall be clean. ^59This is the law of the plague of leprosy in a garment of woollen or linen, either in the warp, or woof, or any thing of skins, to pronounce it clean, or to pronounce it unclean.

XIV

^1And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying, ^2This shall be the law of the leper in the day of his cleansing: He shall be brought unto the priest: ^3and the priest shall go forth out of the camp; and the priest shall look, and, behold, if the plague of leprosy be healed in the leper; ^4then shall the priest command to take for him that is to be cleansed two birds alive and clean, and cedar wood, and scarlet, and hyssop: ^5and the priest shall command that one of the birds be killed in an earthen vessel over running water: ^6as for the living bird, he shall take it, and the cedar wood, and the scarlet, and the hyssop, and shall dip them and the living bird in the blood of the bird that was killed over the running water: ^7and he shall sprinkle upon him that is to be cleansed from the leprosy seven times, and shall pronounce him clean, and shall let the living bird loose into the open field. ^8And he that is to be cleansed shall wash his clothes, and shave off all his hair, and wash himself in water, that he may be clean: and after that he shall come into the camp, and shall tarry abroad out of his tent seven days. ^9But it shall be on the seventh day, that he shall shave all his hair off his head and his beard and his eyebrows, even all his hair he shall shave off: and he shall wash his clothes, also he shall wash his flesh in water, and he shall be clean. ^10And on the eighth day he shall take two he lambs without blemish, and one ewe lamb of the first year without blemish, and three tenth deals of fine flour for a meat offering, mingled with oil, and one log of oil. ^11And the priest that maketh him clean shall present the man that is to be made clean, and those things, before the Lord, at the door of the tabernacle of the congregation: ^12and the priest shall take one he lamb, and offer him for a trespass offering, and the log of oil, and wave them for a wave offering before the Lord: ^13and he shall slay the lamb in the place where he shall kill the sin offering and the burnt offering, in the holy place: for as the sin offering is the priest’s, so is the trespass offering: it is most holy: ^14and the priest shall take some of the blood of the trespass offering, and the priest shall put it upon the tip of the right ear of him that is to be cleansed, and upon the thumb of his right hand, and upon the great toe of his right foot: ^15and the priest shall take some of the log of oil, and pour it into the palm of his own left hand: ^16and the priest shall dip his right finger in the oil that is in his left hand, and shall sprinkle of the oil with his finger seven times before the Lord: ^17and of the rest of the oil that is in his hand shall the priest put upon the tip of the right ear of him that is to be cleansed, and upon the thumb of his right hand, and upon the great toe of his right foot, upon the blood of the trespass offering: ^18and the remnant of the oil that is in the priest’s hand he shall pour upon the head of him that is to be cleansed: and the priest shall make an atonement for him before the Lord. ^19And the priest shall offer the sin offering, and make an atonement for him that is to be cleansed from his uncleanness; and afterward he shall kill the burnt offering: ^20and the priest shall offer the burnt offering and the meat offering upon the altar: and the priest shall make an atonement for him, and he shall be clean. ^21And if he be poor, and cannot get so much; then he shall take one lamb for a trespass offering to be waved, to make an atonement for him, and one tenth deal of fine flour mingled with oil for a meat offering, and a log of oil; ^22and two turtledoves, or two young pigeons, such as he is able to get; and the one shall be a sin offering, and the other a burnt offering. ^23And he shall bring them on the eighth day for his cleansing unto the priest, unto the door of the tabernacle of the congregation, before the Lord. ^24And the priest shall take the lamb of the trespass offering, and the log of oil, and the priest shall wave them for a wave offering before the Lord: ^25and he shall kill the lamb of the trespass offering, and the priest shall take some of the blood of the trespass offering, and put it upon the tip of the right ear of him that is to be cleansed, and upon the thumb of his right hand, and upon the great toe of his right foot: ^26and the priest shall pour of the oil into the palm of his own left hand: ^27and the priest shall sprinkle with his right finger some of the oil that is in his left hand seven times before the Lord: ^28and the priest shall put of the oil that is in his hand upon the tip of the right ear of him that is to be cleansed, and upon the thumb of his right hand, and upon the great toe of his right foot, upon the place of the blood of the trespass offering: ^29and the rest of the oil that is in the priest’s hand he shall put upon the head of him that is to be cleansed, to make an atonement for him before the Lord. ^30And he shall offer the one of the turtledoves, or of the young pigeons, such as he can get; ^31even such as he is able to get, the one for a sin offering, and the other for a burnt offering, with the meat offering: and the priest shall make an atonement for him that is to be cleansed before the Lord. ^32This is the law of him in whom is the plague of leprosy, whose hand is not able to get that which pertaineth to his cleansing.

^33And the Lord spake unto Moses and unto Aaron, saying, ^34When ye be come into the land of Canaan, which I give to you for a possession, and I put the plague of leprosy in a house of the land of your possession; ^35and he that owneth the house shall come and tell the priest, saying, It seemeth to me there is as it were a plague in the house: ^36then the priest shall command that they empty the house, before the priest go into it to see the plague, that all that is in the house be not made unclean: and afterward the priest shall go in to see the house: ^37and he shall look on the plague, and, behold, if the plague be in the walls of the house with hollow strakes, greenish or reddish, which in sight are lower than the wall; ^38then the priest shall go out of the house to the door of the house, and shut up the house seven days: ^39and the priest shall come again the seventh day, and shall look: and, behold, if the plague be spread in the walls of the house; ^40then the priest shall command that they take away the stones in which the plague is, and they shall cast them into an unclean place without the city: ^41and he shall cause the house to be scraped within round about, and they shall pour out the dust that they scrape off without the city into an unclean place: ^42and they shall take other stones, and put them in the place of those stones; and he shall take other morter, and shall plaister the house. ^43And if the plague come again, and break out in the house, after that he hath taken away the stones, and after he hath scraped the house, and after it is plaistered; ^44then the priest shall come and look, and, behold, if the plague be spread in the house, it is a fretting leprosy in the house; it is unclean. ^45And he shall break down the house, the stones of it, and the timber thereof, and all the morter of the house; and he shall carry them forth out of the city into an unclean place. ^46Moreover he that goeth into the house all the while that it is shut up shall be unclean until the even. ^47And he that lieth in the house shall wash his clothes; and he that eateth in the house shall wash his clothes. ^48And if the priest shall come in, and look upon it, and, behold, the plague hath not spread in the house, after the house was plaistered: then the priest shall pronounce the house clean, because the plague is healed. ^49And he shall take to cleanse the house two birds, and cedar wood, and scarlet, and hyssop: ^50and he shall kill the one of the birds in an earthen vessel over running water: ^51and he shall take the cedar wood, and the hyssop, and the scarlet, and the living bird, and dip them in the blood of the slain bird, and in the running water, and sprinkle the house seven times: ^52and he shall cleanse the house with the blood of the bird, and with the running water, and with the living bird, and with the cedar wood, and with the hyssop, and with the scarlet: ^53but he shall let go the living bird out of the city into the open fields, and make an atonement for the house: and it shall be clean. ^54This is the law for all manner of plague of leprosy, and scall, ^55and for the leprosy of a garment, and of a house, ^56and for a rising, and for a scab, and for a bright spot: ^57to teach when it is unclean, and when it is clean: this is the law of leprosy.

XV

^1And the Lord spake unto Moses and to Aaron, saying, ^2Speak unto the children of Israel, and say unto them, When any man hath a running issue out of his flesh, because of his issue he is unclean. ^3And this shall be his uncleanness in his issue: whether his flesh run with his issue, or his flesh be stopped from his issue, it is his uncleanness. ^4Every bed, whereon he lieth that hath the issue, is unclean: and every thing, whereon he sitteth, shall be unclean. ^5And whosoever toucheth his bed shall wash his clothes, and bathe himself in water, and be unclean until the even. ^6And he that sitteth on any thing whereon he sat that hath the issue shall wash his clothes, and bathe himself in water, and be unclean until the even. ^7And he that toucheth the flesh of him that hath the issue shall wash his clothes, and bathe himself in water, and be unclean until the even. ^8And if he that hath the issue spit upon him that is clean; then he shall wash his clothes, and bathe himself in water, and be unclean until the even. ^9And what saddle soever he rideth upon that hath the issue shall be unclean. ^10And whosoever toucheth any thing that was under him shall be unclean until the even: and he that beareth any of those things shall wash his clothes, and bathe himself in water, and be unclean until the even. ^11And whomsoever he toucheth that hath the issue, and hath not rinsed his hands in water, he shall wash his clothes, and bathe himself in water, and be unclean until the even. ^12And the vessel of earth, that he toucheth which hath the issue, shall be broken: and every vessel of wood shall be rinsed in water. ^13And when he that hath an issue is cleansed of his issue; then he shall number to himself seven days for his cleansing, and wash his clothes, and bathe his flesh in running water, and shall be clean. ^14And on the eighth day he shall take to him two turtledoves, or two young pigeons, and come before the Lord unto the door of the tabernacle of the congregation, and give them unto the priest: ^15and the priest shall offer them, the one for a sin offering, and the other for a burnt offering; and the priest shall make an atonement for him before the Lord for his issue. ^16And if any man’s seed of copulation go out from him, then he shall wash all his flesh in water, and be unclean until the even. ^17And every garment, and every skin, whereon is the seed of copulation, shall be washed with water, and be unclean until the even. ^18The woman also with whom man shall lie with seed of copulation, they shall both bathe themselves in water, and be unclean until the even.

^19And if a woman have an issue, and her issue in her flesh be blood, she shall be put apart seven days: and whosoever toucheth her shall be unclean until the even. ^20And every thing that she lieth upon in her separation shall be unclean: every thing also that she sitteth upon shall be unclean. ^21And whosoever toucheth her bed shall wash his clothes, and bathe himself in water, and be unclean until the even. ^22And whosoever toucheth any thing that she sat upon shall wash his clothes, and bathe himself in water, and be unclean until the even. ^23And if it be on her bed, or on any thing whereon she sitteth, when he toucheth it, he shall be unclean until the even. ^24And if any man lie with her at all, and her flowers be upon him, he shall be unclean seven days; and all the bed whereon he lieth shall be unclean. ^25And if a woman have an issue of her blood many days out of the time of her separation, or if it run beyond the time of her separation; all the days of the issue of her uncleanness shall be as the days of her separation: she shall be unclean. ^26Every bed whereon she lieth all the days of her issue shall be unto her as the bed of her separation: and whatsoever she sitteth upon shall be unclean, as the uncleanness of her separation. ^27And whosoever toucheth those things shall be unclean, and shall wash his clothes, and bathe himself in water, and be unclean until the even. ^28But if she be cleansed of her issue, then she shall number to herself seven days, and after that she shall be clean. ^29And on the eighth day she shall take unto her two turtles, or two young pigeons, and bring them unto the priest, to the door of the tabernacle of the congregation. ^30And the priest shall offer the one for a sin offering, and the other for a burnt offering; and the priest shall make an atonement for her before the Lord for the issue of her uncleanness. ^31Thus shall ye separate the children of Israel from their uncleanness; that they die not in their uncleanness, when they defile my tabernacle that is among them. ^32This is the law of him that hath an issue, and of him whose seed goeth from him, and is defiled therewith; ^33and of her that is sick of her flowers, and of him that hath an issue, of the man, and of the woman, and of him that lieth with her that is unclean.

XVI

^1And the Lord spake unto Moses after the death of the two sons of Aaron, when they offered before the Lord, and died; ^2and the Lord said unto Moses, Speak unto Aaron thy brother, that he come not at all times into the holy place within the vail before the mercy seat, which is upon the ark; that he die not: for I will appear in the cloud upon the mercy seat. ^3Thus shall Aaron come into the holy place: with a young bullock for a sin offering, and a ram for a burnt offering. ^4He shall put on the holy linen coat, and he shall have the linen breeches upon his flesh, and shall be girded with a linen girdle, and with the linen mitre shall he be attired: these are holy garments; therefore shall he wash his flesh in water, and so put them on. ^5And he shall take of the congregation of the children of Israel two kids of the goats for a sin offering, and one ram for a burnt offering. ^6And Aaron shall offer his bullock of the sin offering, which is for himself, and make an atonement for himself, and for his house. ^7And he shall take the two goats, and present them before the Lord at the door of the tabernacle of the congregation. ^8And Aaron shall cast lots upon the two goats; one lot for the Lord, and the other lot for the scapegoat. ^9And Aaron shall bring the goat upon which the Lord’s lot fell, and offer him for a sin offering. ^10But the goat, on which the lot fell to be the scapegoat, shall be presented alive before the Lord, to make an atonement with him, and to let him go for a scapegoat into the wilderness. ^11And Aaron shall bring the bullock of the sin offering, which is for himself, and shall make an atonement for himself, and for his house, and shall kill the bullock of the sin offering which is for himself: ^12and he shall take a censer full of burning coals of fire from off the altar before the Lord, and his hands full of sweet incense beaten small, and bring it within the vail: ^13and he shall put the incense upon the fire before the Lord, that the cloud of the incense may cover the mercy seat that is upon the testimony, that he die not: ^14and he shall take of the blood of the bullock, and sprinkle it with his finger upon the mercy seat eastward; and before the mercy seat shall he sprinkle of the blood with his finger seven times.

^15Then shall he kill the goat of the sin offering, that is for the people, and bring his blood within the vail, and do with that blood as he did with the blood of the bullock, and sprinkle it upon the mercy seat, and before the mercy seat: ^16and he shall make an atonement for the holy place, because of the uncleanness of the children of Israel, and because of their transgressions in all their sins: and so shall he do for the tabernacle of the congregation, that remaineth among them in the midst of their uncleanness. ^17And there shall be no man in the tabernacle of the congregation when he goeth in to make an atonement in the holy place, until he come out, and have made an atonement for himself, and for his household, and for all the congregation of Israel. ^18And he shall go out unto the altar that is before the Lord, and make an atonement for it; and shall take of the blood of the bullock, and of the blood of the goat, and put it upon the horns of the altar round about. ^19And he shall sprinkle of the blood upon it with his finger seven times, and cleanse it, and hallow it from the uncleanness of the children of Israel.

^20And when he hath made an end of reconciling the holy place, and the tabernacle of the congregation, and the altar, he shall bring the live goat: ^21and Aaron shall lay both his hands upon the head of the live goat, and confess over him all the iniquities of the children of Israel, and all their transgressions in all their sins, putting them upon the head of the goat, and shall send him away by the hand of a fit man into the wilderness: ^22and the goat shall bear upon him all their iniquities unto a land not inhabited: and he shall let go the goat in the wilderness. ^23And Aaron shall come into the tabernacle of the congregation, and shall put off the linen garments, which he put on when he went into the holy place, and shall leave them there: ^24and he shall wash his flesh with water in the holy place, and put on his garments, and come forth, and offer his burnt offering, and the burnt offering of the people, and make an atonement for himself, and for the people. ^25And the fat of the sin offering shall he burn upon the altar. ^26And he that let go the goat for the scapegoat shall wash his clothes, and bathe his flesh in water, and afterward come into the camp. ^27And the bullock for the sin offering, and the goat for the sin offering, whose blood was brought in to make atonement in the holy place, shall one carry forth without the camp; and they shall burn in the fire their skins, and their flesh, and their dung. ^28And he that burneth them shall wash his clothes, and bathe his flesh in water, and afterward he shall come into the camp.

^29And this shall be a statute for ever unto you: that in the seventh month, on the tenth day of the month, ye shall afflict your souls, and do no work at all, whether it be one of your own country, or a stranger that sojourneth among you: ^30for on that day shall the priest make an atonement for you, to cleanse you, that ye may be clean from all your sins before the Lord. ^31It shall be a sabbath of rest unto you, and ye shall afflict your souls, by a statute for ever. ^32And the priest, whom he shall anoint, and whom he shall consecrate to minister in the priest’s office in his father’s stead, shall make the atonement, and shall put on the linen clothes, even the holy garments: ^33and he shall make an atonement for the holy sanctuary, and he shall make an atonement for the tabernacle of the congregation, and for the altar, and he shall make an atonement for the priests, and for all the people of the congregation. ^34And this shall be an everlasting statute unto you, to make an atonement for the children of Israel for all their sins once a year. And he did as the Lord commanded Moses.

XVII

^1And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying, ^2Speak unto Aaron, and unto his sons, and unto all the children of Israel, and say unto them;

This is the thing which the Lord hath commanded, saying, ^3What man soever there be of the house of Israel, that killeth an ox, or lamb, or goat, in the camp, or that killeth it out of the camp, ^4and bringeth it not unto the door of the tabernacle of the congregation, to offer an offering unto the Lord before the tabernacle of the Lord; blood shall be imputed unto that man; he hath shed blood; and that man shall be cut off from among his people: ^5to the end that the children of Israel may bring their sacrifices, which they offer in the open field, even that they may bring them unto the Lord, unto the door of the tabernacle of the congregation, unto the priest, and offer them for peace offerings unto the Lord. ^6And the priest shall sprinkle the blood upon the altar of the Lord at the door of the tabernacle of the congregation, and burn the fat for a sweet savour unto the Lord. ^7And they shall no more offer their sacrifices unto devils, after whom they have gone a whoring. This shall be a statute for ever unto them throughout their generations.

^8And thou shalt say unto them, Whatsoever man there be of the house of Israel, or of the strangers which sojourn among you, that offereth a burnt offering or sacrifice, ^9and bringeth it not unto the door of the tabernacle of the congregation, to offer it unto the Lord; even that man shall be cut off from among his people.

^10And whatsoever man there be of the house of Israel, or of the strangers that sojourn among you, that eateth any manner of blood; I will even set my face against that soul that eateth blood, and will cut him off from among his people. ^11For the life of the flesh is in the blood: and I have given it to you upon the altar to make an atonement for your souls: for it is the blood that maketh an atonement for the soul. ^12Therefore I said unto the children of Israel, No soul of you shall eat blood, neither shall any stranger that sojourneth among you eat blood. ^13And whatsoever man there be of the children of Israel, or of the strangers that sojourn among you, which hunteth and catcheth any beast or fowl that may be eaten; he shall even pour out the blood thereof, and cover it with dust. ^14For it is the life of all flesh; the blood of it is for the life thereof: therefore I said unto the children of Israel, Ye shall eat the blood of no manner of flesh: for the life of all flesh is the blood thereof: whosoever eateth it shall be cut off. ^15And every soul that eateth that which died of itself, or that which was torn with beasts, whether it be one of your own country, or a stranger, he shall both wash his clothes, and bathe himself in water, and be unclean until the even: then shall he be clean. ^16But if he wash them not, nor bathe his flesh; then he shall bear his iniquity.

XVIII

^1And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying, ^2Speak unto the children of Israel, and say unto them, I am the Lord your God. ^3After the doings of the land of Egypt, wherein ye dwelt, shall ye not do: and after the doings of the land of Canaan, whither I bring you, shall ye not do: neither shall ye walk in their ordinances. ^4Ye shall do my judgments, and keep mine ordinances, to walk therein: I am the Lord your God. ^5Ye shall therefore keep my statutes, and my judgments: which if a man do, he shall live in them: I am the Lord.

^6None of you shall approach to any that is near of kin to him, to uncover their nakedness: I am the Lord. ^7The nakedness of thy father, or the nakedness of thy mother, shalt thou not uncover: she is thy mother; thou shalt not uncover her nakedness. ^8The nakedness of thy father’s wife shalt thou not uncover: it is thy father’s nakedness. ^9The nakedness of thy sister, the daughter of thy father, or daughter of thy mother, whether she be born at home, or born abroad, even their nakedness thou shalt not uncover. ^10The nakedness of thy son’s daughter, or of thy daughter’s daughter, even their nakedness thou shalt not uncover: for theirs is thine own nakedness. ^11The nakedness of thy father’s wife’s daughter, begotten of thy father, she is thy sister, thou shalt not uncover her nakedness. ^12Thou shalt not uncover the nakedness of thy father’s sister: she is thy father’s near kinswoman. ^13Thou shalt not uncover the nakedness of thy mother’s sister: for she is thy mother’s near kinswoman. ^14Thou shalt not uncover the nakedness of thy father’s brother, thou shalt not approach to his wife: she is thine aunt. ^15Thou shalt not uncover the nakedness of thy daughter in law: she is thy son’s wife; thou shalt not uncover her nakedness. ^16Thou shalt not uncover the nakedness of thy brother’s wife: it is thy brother’s nakedness. ^17Thou shalt not uncover the nakedness of a woman and her daughter, neither shalt thou take her son’s daughter, or her daughter’s daughter, to uncover her nakedness; for they are her near kinswomen: it is wickedness. ^18Neither shalt thou take a wife to her sister, to vex her, to uncover her nakedness, beside the other in her life time. ^19Also thou shalt not approach unto a woman to uncover her nakedness, as long as she is put apart for her uncleanness. ^20Moreover thou shalt not lie carnally with thy neighbour’s wife, to defile thyself with her. ^21And thou shalt not let any of thy seed pass through the fire to Molech, neither shalt thou profane the name of thy God: I am the Lord. ^22Thou shalt not lie with mankind, as with womankind: it is abomination. ^23Neither shalt thou lie with any beast to defile thyself therewith: neither shall any woman stand before a beast to lie down thereto: it is confusion. ^24Defile not ye yourselves in any of these things: for in all these the nations are defiled which I cast out before you: ^25and the land is defiled: therefore I do visit the iniquity thereof upon it, and the land itself vomiteth out her inhabitants. ^26Ye shall therefore keep my statutes and my judgments, and shall not commit any of these abominations; neither any of your own nation, nor any stranger that sojourneth among you: ^27(for all these abominations have the men of the land done, which were before you, and the land is defiled;) ^28that the land spue not you out also, when ye defile it, as it spued out the nations that were before you. ^29For whosoever shall commit any of these abominations, even the souls that commit them shall be cut off from among their people. ^30Therefore shall ye keep mine ordinance, that ye commit not any one of these abominable customs, which were committed before you, and that ye defile not yourselves therein: I am the Lord your God.

XIX

^1And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying, ^2Speak unto all the congregation of the children of Israel, and say unto them, Ye shall be holy: for I the Lord your God am holy.

^3Ye shall fear every man his mother, and his father, and keep my sabbaths: I am the Lord your God.

^4Turn ye not unto idols, nor make to yourselves molten gods: I am the Lord your God.

^5And if ye offer a sacrifice of peace offerings unto the Lord, ye shall offer it at your own will. ^6It shall be eaten the same day ye offer it, and on the morrow: and if ought remain until the third day, it shall be burnt in the fire. ^7And if it be eaten at all on the third day, it is abominable; it shall not be accepted. ^8Therefore every one that eateth it shall bear his iniquity, because he hath profaned the hallowed thing of the Lord: and that soul shall be cut off from among his people.

^9And when ye reap the harvest of your land, thou shalt not wholly reap the corners of thy field, neither shalt thou gather the gleanings of thy harvest. ^10And thou shalt not glean thy vineyard, neither shalt thou gather every grape of thy vineyard; thou shalt leave them for the poor and stranger: I am the Lord your God.

^11Ye shall not steal, neither deal falsely, neither lie one to another.

^12And ye shall not swear by my name falsely, neither shalt thou profane the name of thy God: I am the Lord.

^13Thou shalt not defraud thy neighbour, neither rob him: the wages of him that is hired shall not abide with thee all night until the morning.

^14Thou shalt not curse the deaf, nor put a stumblingblock before the blind, but shalt fear thy God: I am the Lord.

^15Ye shall do no unrighteousness in judgment: thou shalt not respect the person of the poor, nor honor the person of the mighty: but in righteousness shalt thou judge thy neighbour.

^16Thou shalt not go up and down as a talebearer among thy people: neither shalt thou stand against the blood of thy neighbour; I am the Lord.

^17Thou shalt not hate thy brother in thine heart: thou shalt in any wise rebuke thy neighbour, and not suffer sin upon him.

^18Thou shalt not avenge, nor bear any grudge against the children of thy people, but thou shalt love thy neighbour as thyself: I am the Lord.

^19Ye shall keep my statutes. Thou shalt not let thy cattle gender with a diverse kind: thou shalt not sow thy field with mingled seed: neither shall a garment mingled of linen and woollen come upon thee.

^20And whosoever lieth carnally with a woman, that is a bondmaid, betrothed to an husband, and not at all redeemed, nor freedom given her; she shall be scourged; they shall not be put to death, because she was not free. ^21And he shall bring his trespass offering unto the Lord, unto the door of the tabernacle of the congregation, even a ram for a trespass offering. ^22And the priest shall make an atonement for him with the ram of the trespass offering before the Lord for his sin which he hath done: and the sin which he hath done shall be forgiven him.

^23And when ye shall come into the land, and shall have planted all manner of trees for food, then ye shall count the fruit thereof as uncircumcised: three years shall it be as uncircumcised unto you: it shall not be eaten of. ^24But in the fourth year all the fruit thereof shall be holy to praise the Lord withal. ^25And in the fifth year shall ye eat of the fruit thereof, that it may yield unto you the increase thereof: I am the Lord your God.

^26Ye shall not eat any thing with the blood: neither shall ye use enchantment, nor observe times. ^27Ye shall not round the corners of your heads, neither shalt thou mar the corners of thy beard. ^28Ye shall not make any cuttings in your flesh for the dead, nor print any marks upon you: I am the Lord.

^29Do not prostitute thy daughter, to cause her to be a whore; lest the land fall to whoredom, and the land become full of wickedness.

^30Ye shall keep my sabbaths, and reverence my sanctuary: I am the Lord.

^31Regard not them that have familiar spirits, neither seek after wizards, to be defiled by them: I am the Lord your God.

^32Thou shalt rise up before the hoary head, and honour the face of the old man, and fear thy God: I am the Lord.

^33And if a stranger sojourn with thee in your land, ye shall not vex him. ^34But the stranger that dwelleth with you shall be unto you as one born among you, and thou shalt love him as thyself; for ye were strangers in the land of Egypt: I am the Lord your God.

^35Ye shall do no unrighteousness in judgment, in meteyard, in weight, or in measure. ^36Just balances, just weights, a just ephah, and a just hin, shall ye have: I am the Lord your God, which brought you out of the land of Egypt. ^37Therefore shall ye observe all my statutes, and all my judgments, and do them: I am the Lord.

XX

^1And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying, ^2Again, thou shalt say to the children of Israel, Whosoever he be of the children of Israel, or of the strangers that sojourn in Israel, that giveth any of his seed unto Molech; he shall surely be put to death: the people of the land shall stone him with stones. ^3And I will set my face against that man, and will cut him off from among his people; because he hath given of his seed unto Molech, to defile my sanctuary, and to profane my holy name. ^4And if the people of the land do any ways hide their eyes from the man, when he giveth of his seed unto Molech, and kill him not: ^5then I will set my face against that man, and against his family, and will cut him off, and all that go a whoring after him, to commit whoredom with Molech, from among their people.

^6And the soul that turneth after such as have familiar spirits, and after wizards, to go a whoring after them, I will even set my face against that soul, and will cut him off from among his people.

^7Sanctify yourselves therefore, and be ye holy: for I am the Lord your God. ^8And ye shall keep my statutes, and do them: I am the Lord which sanctify you.

^9For every one that curseth his father or his mother shall be surely put to death: he hath cursed his father or his mother; his blood shall be upon him.

^10And the man that committeth adultery with another man’s wife, even he that committeth adultery with his neighbour’s wife, the adulterer and the adulteress shall surely be put to death. ^11And the man that lieth with his father’s wife hath uncovered his father’s nakedness: both of them shall surely be put to death; their blood shall be upon them. ^12And if a man lie with his daughter in law, both of them shall surely be put to death: they have wrought confusion; their blood shall be upon them. ^13If a man also lie with mankind, as he lieth with a woman, both of them have committed an abomination: they shall surely be put to death; their blood shall be upon them. ^14And if a man take a wife and her mother, it is wickedness: they shall be burnt with fire, both he and they; that there be no wickedness among you. ^15And if a man lie with a beast, he shall surely be put to death: and ye shall slay the beast. ^16And if a woman approach unto any beast, and lie down thereto, thou shalt kill the woman, and the beast: they shall surely be put to death; their blood shall be upon them. ^17And if a man shall take his sister, his father’s daughter, or his mother’s daughter, and see her nakedness, and she see his nakedness; it is a wicked thing; and they shall be cut off in the sight of their people: he hath uncovered his sister’s nakedness; he shall bear his iniquity. ^18And if a man shall lie with a woman having her sickness, and shall uncover her nakedness; he hath discovered her fountain, and she hath uncovered the fountain of her blood: and both of them shall be cut off from among their people. ^19And thou shalt not uncover the nakedness of thy mother’s sister, nor of thy father’s sister: for he uncovereth his near kin: they shall bear their iniquity. ^20And if a man shall lie with his uncle’s wife, he hath uncovered his uncle’s nakedness: they shall bear their sin; they shall die childless. ^21And if a man shall take his brother’s wife, it is an unclean thing: he hath uncovered his brother’s nakedness; they shall be childless.

^22Ye shall therefore keep all my statutes, and all my judgments, and do them: that the land, whither I bring you to dwell therein, spue you not out. ^23And ye shall not walk in the manners of the nation, which I cast out before you: for they committed all these things, and therefore I abhorred them. ^24But I have said unto you, Ye shall inherit their land, and I will give it unto you to possess it, a land that floweth with milk and honey: I am the Lord your God, which have separated you from other people. ^25Ye shall therefore put difference between clean beasts and unclean, and between unclean fowls and clean: and ye shall not make your souls abominable by beast, or by fowl, or by any manner of living thing that creepeth on the ground, which I have separated from you as unclean. ^26And ye shall be holy unto me: for I the Lord am holy, and have severed you from other people, that ye should be mine.

^27A man also or woman that hath a familiar spirit, or that is a wizard, shall surely be put to death: they shall stone them with stones: their blood shall be upon them.

XXI

^1And the Lord said unto Moses, Speak unto the priests the sons of Aaron, and say unto them, There shall none be defiled for the dead among his people: ^2but for his kin, that is near unto him, that is, for his mother, and for his father, and for his son, and for his daughter, and for his brother. ^3And for his sister a virgin, that is nigh unto him, which hath had no husband; for her may he be defiled. ^4But he shall not defile himself, being a chief man among his people, to profane himself. ^5They shall not make baldness upon their head, neither shall they shave off the corner of their beard, nor make any cuttings in their flesh. ^6They shall be holy unto their God, and not profane the name of their God: for the offerings of the Lord made by fire, and the bread of their God, they do offer: therefore they shall be holy. ^7They shall not take a wife that is a whore, or profane; neither shall they take a woman put away from her husband: for he is holy unto his God. ^8Thou shalt sanctify him therefore; for he offereth the bread of thy God: he shall be holy unto thee: for I the Lord, which sanctify you, am holy. ^9And the daughter of any priest, if she profane herself by playing the whore, she profaneth her father: she shall be burnt with fire.

^10And he that is the high priest among his brethren, upon whose head the anointing oil was poured, and that is consecrated to put on the garments, shall not uncover his head, nor rend his clothes; ^11neither shall he go in to any dead body, nor defile himself for his father, or for his mother; ^12neither shall he go out of the sanctuary, nor profane the sanctuary of his God; for the crown of the anointing oil of his God is upon him: I am the Lord. ^13And he shall take a wife in her virginity. ^14A widow, or a divorced woman, or profane, or an harlot, these shall he not take: but he shall take a virgin of his own people to wife. ^15Neither shall he profane his seed among his people: for I the Lord do sanctify him.

^16And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying, ^17Speak unto Aaron, saying, Whosoever he be of thy seed in their generations that hath any blemish, let him not approach to offer the bread of his God. ^18For whatsoever man he be that hath a blemish, he shall not approach: a blind man, or a lame, or he that hath a flat nose, or any thing superfluous, ^19or a man that is brokenfooted, or brokenhanded, ^20or crookbackt, or a dwarf, or that hath a blemish in his eye, or be scurvy, or scabbed, or hath his stones broken; ^21no man that hath a blemish of the seed of Aaron the priest shall come nigh to offer the offerings of the Lord made by fire: he hath a blemish; he shall not come nigh to offer the bread of his God. ^22He shall eat the bread of his God, both of the most holy, and of the holy. ^23Only he shall not go in unto the vail, nor come nigh unto the altar, because he hath a blemish; that he profane not my sanctuaries: for I the Lord do sanctify them. ^24And Moses told it unto Aaron, and to his sons, and unto all the children of Israel.

XXII

^1And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying, ^2Speak unto Aaron and to his sons, that they separate themselves from the holy things of the children of Israel, and that they profane not my holy name in those things which they hallow unto me: I am the Lord. ^3Say unto them, Whosoever he be of all your seed among your generations, that goeth unto the holy things, which the children of Israel hallow unto the Lord, having his uncleanness upon him, that soul shall be cut off from my presence: I am the Lord. ^4What man soever of the seed of Aaron is a leper, or hath a running issue; he shall not eat of the holy things, until he be clean. And whoso toucheth any thing that is unclean by the dead, or a man whose seed goeth from him; ^5or whosoever toucheth any creeping thing, whereby he may be made unclean, or a man of whom he may take uncleanness, whatsoever uncleanness he hath; ^6the soul which hath touched any such shall be unclean until even, and shall not eat of the holy things, unless he wash his flesh with water. ^7And when the sun is down, he shall be clean, and shall afterward eat of the holy things; because it is his food. ^8That which dieth of itself, or is torn with beasts, he shall not eat to defile himself therewith; I am the Lord. ^9They shall therefore keep mine ordinance, lest they bear sin for it, and die therefore, if they profane it: I the Lord do sanctify them.

^10There shall no stranger eat of the holy thing: a sojourner of the priest, or an hired servant, shall not eat of the holy thing. ^11But if the priest buy any soul with his money, he shall eat of it, and he that is born in his house: they shall eat of his meat. ^12If the priest’s daughter also be married unto a stranger, she may not eat of an offering of the holy things. ^13But if the priest’s daughter be a widow, or divorced, and have no child, and is returned unto her father’s house, as in her youth, she shall eat of her father’s meat: but there shall be no stranger eat thereof.

^14And if a man eat of the holy thing unwittingly, then he shall put the fifth part thereof unto it, and shall give it unto the priest with the holy thing. ^15And they shall not profane the holy things of the children of Israel, which they offer unto the Lord; ^16or suffer them to bear the iniquity of trespass, when they eat their holy things: for I the Lord do sanctify them.

^17And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying, ^18Speak unto Aaron, and to his sons, and unto all the children of Israel, and say unto them, Whatsoever he be of the house of Israel, or of the strangers in Israel, that will offer his oblation for all his vows, and for all his freewill offerings, which they will offer unto the Lord for a burnt offering; ^19ye shall offer at your own will a male without blemish, of the beeves, of the sheep, or of the goats. ^20But whatsoever hath a blemish, that shall ye not offer: for it shall not be acceptable for you. ^21And whosoever offereth a sacrifice of peace offerings unto the Lord to accomplish his vow, or a freewill offering in beeves or sheep, it shall be perfect to be accepted; there shall be no blemish therein. ^22Blind, or broken, or maimed, or having a wen, or scurvy, or scabbed, ye shall not offer these unto the Lord, nor make an offering by fire of them upon the altar unto the Lord. ^23Either a bullock or a lamb that hath any thing superfluous or lacking in his parts, that mayest thou offer for a freewill offering; but for a vow it shall not be accepted. ^24Ye shall not offer unto the Lord that which is bruised, or crushed, or broken, or cut; neither shall ye make any offering thereof in your land. ^25Neither from a stranger’s hand shall ye offer the bread of your God of any of these; because their corruption is in them, and blemishes be in them: they shall not be accepted for you.

^26And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying, ^27When a bullock, or a sheep, or a goat, is brought forth, then it shall be seven days under the dam; and from the eighth day and thenceforth it shall be accepted for an offering made by fire unto the Lord. ^28And whether it be cow, or ewe, ye shall not kill it and her young both in one day. ^29And when ye will offer a sacrifice of thanksgiving unto the Lord, offer it at your own will. ^30On the same day it shall be eaten up; ye shall leave none of it until the morrow: I am the Lord. ^31Therefore shall ye keep my commandments, and do them: I am the Lord. ^32Neither shall ye profane my holy name; but I will be hallowed among the children of Israel: I am the Lord which hallow you, ^33that brought you out of the land of Egypt, to be your God: I am the Lord.

XXIII

^1And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying, ^2Speak unto the children of Israel, and say unto them, Concerning the feasts of the Lord, which ye shall proclaim to be holy convocations, even these are my feasts. ^3Six days shall work be done: but the seventh day is the sabbath of rest, an holy convocation; ye shall do no work therein: it is the sabbath of the Lord in all your dwellings.

^4These are the feasts of the Lord, even holy convocations, which ye shall proclaim in their seasons. ^5In the fourteenth day of the first month at even is the Lord’s passover. ^6And on the fifteenth day of the same month is the feast of unleavened bread unto the Lord: seven days ye must eat unleavened bread. ^7In the first day ye shall have an holy convocation: ye shall do no servile work therein. ^8But ye shall offer an offering made by fire unto the Lord seven days: in the seventh day is an holy convocation: ye shall do no servile work therein.

^9And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying, ^10Speak unto the children of Israel, and say unto them, When ye be come into the land which I give unto you, and shall reap the harvest thereof, then ye shall bring a sheaf of the firstfruits of your harvest unto the priest: ^11and he shall wave the sheaf before the Lord, to be accepted for you: on the morrow after the sabbath the priest shall wave it. ^12And ye shall offer that day when ye wave the sheaf an he lamb without blemish of the first year for a burnt offering unto the Lord. ^13And the meat offering thereof shall be two tenth deals of fine flour mingled with oil, an offering made by fire unto the Lord for a sweet savour: and the drink offering thereof shall be of wine, the fourth part of an hin. ^14And ye shall eat neither bread, nor parched corn, nor green ears, until the selfsame day that ye have brought an offering unto your God: it shall be a statute for ever throughout your generations in all your dwellings.

^15And ye shall count unto you from the morrow after the sabbath, from the day that ye brought the sheaf of the wave offering; seven sabbaths shall be complete: ^16even unto the morrow after the seventh sabbath shall ye number fifty days; and ye shall offer a new meat offering unto the Lord. ^17Ye shall bring out of your habitations two wave loaves of two tenth deals; they shall be of fine flour; they shall be baken with leaven; they are the firstfruits unto the Lord. ^18And ye shall offer with the bread seven lambs without blemish of the first year, and one young bullock, and two rams: they shall be for a burnt offering unto the Lord, with their meat offering, and their drink offerings, even an offering made by fire, of sweet savour unto the Lord. ^19Then ye shall sacrifice one kid of the goats for a sin offering, and two lambs of the first year for a sacrifice of peace offerings. ^20And the priest shall wave them with the bread of the firstfruits for a wave offering before the Lord, with the two lambs: they shall be holy to the Lord for the priest. ^21And ye shall proclaim on the selfsame day, that it may be an holy convocation unto you: ye shall do no servile work therein: it shall be a statute for ever in all your dwellings throughout your generations. ^22And when ye reap the harvest of your land, thou shalt not make clean riddance of the corners of thy field when thou reapest, neither shalt thou gather any gleaning of thy harvest: thou shalt leave them unto the poor, and to the stranger: I am the Lord your God.

^23And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying, ^24Speak unto the children of Israel, saying, In the seventh month, in the first day of the month, shall ye have a sabbath, a memorial of blowing of trumpets, an holy convocation. ^25Ye shall do no servile work therein: but ye shall offer an offering made by fire unto the Lord.

^26And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying, ^27Also on the tenth day of this seventh month there shall be a day of atonement: it shall be an holy convocation unto you; and ye shall afflict your souls, and offer an offering made by fire unto the Lord. ^28And ye shall do no work in that same day: for it is a day of atonement, to make an atonement for you before the Lord your God. ^29For whatsoever soul it be that shall not be afflicted in that same day, he shall be cut off from among his people. ^30And whatsoever soul it be that doeth any work in that same day, the same soul will I destroy from among his people. ^31Ye shall do no manner of work: it shall be a statute for ever throughout your generations in all your dwellings. ^32It shall be unto you a sabbath of rest, and ye shall afflict your souls: in the ninth day of the month at even, from even unto even, shall ye celebrate your sabbath.

^33And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying, ^34Speak unto the children of Israel, saying, The fifteenth day of this seventh month shall be the feast of tabernacles for seven days unto the Lord. ^35On the first day shall be an holy convocation: ye shall do no servile work therein. ^36Seven days ye shall offer an offering made by fire unto the Lord: on the eighth day shall be an holy convocation unto you; and ye shall offer an offering made by fire unto the Lord: it is a solemn assembly; and ye shall do no servile work therein. ^37These are the feasts of the Lord, which ye shall proclaim to be holy convocations, to offer an offering made by fire unto the Lord, a burnt offering, and a meat offering, a sacrifice, and drink offerings, every thing upon his day: ^38beside the sabbaths of the Lord, and beside your gifts, and beside all your vows, and beside all your freewill offerings, which ye give unto the Lord. ^39Also in the fifteenth day of the seventh month, when ye have gathered in the fruit of the land, ye shall keep a feast unto the Lord seven days: on the first day shall be a sabbath, and on the eighth day shall be a sabbath. ^40And ye shall take you on the first day the boughs of goodly trees, branches of palm trees, and the boughs of thick trees, and willows of the brook; and ye shall rejoice before the Lord your God seven days. ^41And ye shall keep it a feast unto the Lord seven days in the year. It shall be a statute for ever in your generations: ye shall celebrate it in the seventh month. ^42Ye shall dwell in booths seven days; all that are Israelites born shall dwell in booths: ^43that your generations may know that I made the children of Israel to dwell in booths, when I brought them out of the land of Egypt: I am the Lord your God. ^44And Moses declared unto the children of Israel the feasts of the Lord.

XXIV

^1And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying, ^2Command the children of Israel, that they bring unto thee pure oil olive beaten for the light, to cause the lamps to burn continually. ^3Without the vail of the testimony, in the tabernacle of the congregation, shall Aaron order it from the evening unto the morning before the Lord continually: it shall be a statute for ever in your generations. ^4He shall order the lamps upon the pure candlestick before the Lord continually.

^5And thou shalt take fine flour, and bake twelve cakes thereof: two tenth deals shall be in one cake. ^6And thou shalt set them in two rows, six on a row, upon the pure table before the Lord. ^7And thou shalt put pure frankincense upon each row, that it may be on the bread for a memorial, even an offering made by fire unto the Lord. ^8Every sabbath he shall set it in order before the Lord continually, being taken from the children of Israel by an everlasting covenant. ^9And it shall be Aaron’s and his sons’; and they shall eat it in the holy place: for it is most holy unto him of the offerings of the Lord made by fire by a perpetual statute.

^10And the son of an Israelitish woman, whose father was an Egyptian, went out among the children of Israel: and this son of the Israelitish woman and a man of Israel strove together in the camp; ^11and the Israelitish woman’s son blasphemed the name of the Lord, and cursed. And they brought him unto Moses: (and his mother’s name was Shelomith, the daughter of Dibri, of the tribe of Dan:) ^12and they put him in ward, that the mind of the Lord might be shewed them. ^13And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying, ^14Bring forth him that hath cursed without the camp; and let all that heard him lay their hands upon his head, and let all the congregation stone him. ^15And thou shalt speak unto the children of Israel, saying, Whosoever curseth his God shall bear his sin. ^16And he that blasphemeth the name of the Lord, he shall surely be put to death, and all the congregation shall certainly stone him: as well the stranger, as he that is born in the land, when he blasphemeth the name of the Lord, shall be put to death.

^17And he that killeth any man shall surely be put to death. ^18And he that killeth a beast shall make it good; beast for beast. ^19And if a man cause a blemish in his neighbour; as he hath done, so shall it be done to him; ^20breach for breach, eye for eye, tooth for tooth: as he hath caused a blemish in a man, so shall it be done to him again. ^21And he that killeth a beast, he shall restore it: and he that killeth a man, he shall be put to death. ^22Ye shall have one manner of law, as well for the stranger, as for one of your own country: for I am the Lord your God.

^23And Moses spake to the children of Israel, that they should bring forth him that had cursed out of the camp, and stone him with stones. And the children of Israel did as the Lord commanded Moses.

XXV

^1And the Lord spake unto Moses in mount Sinai, saying, ^2Speak unto the children of Israel, and say unto them, When ye come into the land which I give you, then shall the land keep a sabbath unto the Lord. ^3Six years thou shalt sow thy field, and six years thou shalt prune thy vineyard, and gather in the fruit thereof; ^4but in the seventh year shall be a sabbath of rest unto the land, a sabbath for the Lord: thou shalt neither sow thy field, nor prune thy vineyard. ^5That which groweth of its own accord of thy harvest thou shalt not reap, neither gather the grapes of thy vine undressed: for it is a year of rest unto the land. ^6And the sabbath of the land shall be meat for you; for thee, and for thy servant, and for thy maid, and for thy hired servant, and for thy stranger that sojourneth with thee. ^7And for thy cattle, and for the beast that are in thy land, shall all the increase thereof be meat.

^8And thou shalt number seven sabbaths of years unto thee, seven times seven years; and the space of the seven sabbaths of years shall be unto thee forty and nine years. ^9Then shalt thou cause the trumpet of the jubile to sound on the tenth day of the seventh month, in the day of atonement shall ye make the trumpet sound throughout all your land. ^10And ye shall hallow the fiftieth year, and proclaim liberty throughout all the land unto all the inhabitants thereof: it shall be a jubile unto you; and ye shall return every man unto his possession, and ye shall return every man unto his family. ^11A jubile shall that fiftieth year be unto you: ye shall not sow, neither reap that which groweth of itself in it, nor gather the grapes in it of thy vine undressed. ^12For it is the jubile; it shall be holy unto you: ye shall eat the increase thereof out of the field. ^13In the year of this jubile ye shall return every man unto his possession. ^14And if thou sell ought unto thy neighbour, or buyest ought of thy neighbour’s hand, ye shall not oppress one another: ^15according to the number of years after the jubile thou shalt buy of thy neighbour, and according unto the number of years of the fruits he shall sell unto thee: ^16according to the multitude of years thou shalt increase the price thereof, and according to the fewness of years thou shalt diminish the price of it: for according to the number of the years of the fruits doth he sell unto thee. ^17Ye shall not therefore oppress one another; but thou shalt fear thy God: for I am the Lord your God.

^18Wherefore ye shall do my statutes, and keep my judgments, and do them; and ye shall dwell in the land in safety. ^19And the land shall yield her fruit, and ye shall eat your fill, and dwell therein in safety. ^20And if ye shall say, What shall we eat the seventh year? behold, we shall not sow, nor gather in our increase: ^21then I will command my blessing upon you in the sixth year, and it shall bring forth fruit for three years. ^22And ye shall sow the eighth year, and eat yet of old fruit until the ninth year; until her fruits come in ye shall eat of the old store.

^23The land shall not be sold for ever: for the land is mine, for ye are strangers and sojourners with me. ^24And in all the land of your possession ye shall grant a redemption for the land.

^25If thy brother be waxen poor, and hath sold away some of his possession, and if any of his kin come to redeem it, then shall he redeem that which his brother sold. ^26And if the man have none to redeem it, and himself be able to redeem it; ^27then let him count the years of the sale thereof, and restore the overplus unto the man to whom he sold it; that he may return unto his possession. ^28But if he be not able to restore it to him, then that which is sold shall remain in the hand of him that hath bought it until the year of jubile: and in the jubile it shall go out, and he shall return unto his possession. ^29And if a man sell a dwelling house in a walled city, then he may redeem it within a whole year after it is sold; within a full year may he redeem it. ^30And if it be not redeemed within the space of a full year, then the house that is in the walled city shall be established for ever to him that bought it throughout his generations: it shall not go out in the jubile. ^31But the houses of the villages which have no wall round about them shall be counted as the fields of the country: they may be redeemed, and they shall go out in the jubile. ^32Notwithstanding the cities of the Levites, and the houses of the cities of their possession, may the Levites redeem at any time. ^33And if a man purchase of the Levites, then the house that was sold, and the city of his possession, shall go out in the year of jubile: for the houses of the cities of the Levites are their possession among the children of Israel. ^34But the field of the suburbs of their cities may not be sold; for it is their perpetual possession.

^35And if thy brother be waxen poor, and fallen in decay with thee; then thou shalt relieve him: yea, though he be a stranger, or a sojourner; that he may live with thee. ^36Take thou no usury of him, or increase: but fear thy God; that thy brother may live with thee. ^37Thou shalt not give him thy money upon usury, nor lend him thy victuals for increase. ^38I am the Lord your God, which brought you forth out of the land of Egypt, to give you the land of Canaan, and to be your God.

^39And if thy brother that dwelleth by thee be waxen poor, and be sold unto thee; thou shalt not compel him to serve as a bondservant: ^40but as an hired servant, and as a sojourner, he shall be with thee, and shall serve thee unto the year of jubile. ^41And then shall he depart from thee, both he and his children with him, and shall return unto his own family, and unto the possession of his fathers shall he return. ^42For they are my servants, which I brought forth out of the land of Egypt: they shall not be sold as bondmen. ^43Thou shalt not rule over him with rigour; but shalt fear thy God. ^44Both thy bondmen, and thy bondmaids, which thou shalt have, shall be of the heathen that are round about you; of them shall ye buy bondmen and bondmaids. ^45Moreover of the children of the strangers that do sojourn among you, of them shall ye buy, and of their families that are with you, which they begat in your land: and they shall be your possession. ^46And ye shall take them as an inheritance for your children after you, to inherit them for a possession; they shall be your bondmen for ever: but over your brethren the children of Israel, ye shall not rule one over another with rigour.

^47And if a sojourner or stranger wax rich by thee, and thy brother that dwelleth by him wax poor, and sell himself unto the stranger or sojourner by thee, or to the stock of the stranger’s family: ^48after that he is sold he may be redeemed again; one of his brethren may redeem him: ^49either his uncle, or his uncle’s son, may redeem him, or any that is nigh of kin unto him of his family may redeem him; or if he be able, he may redeem himself. ^50And he shall reckon with him that bought him from the year that he was sold to him unto the year of jubile: and the price of his sale shall be according unto the number of years, according to the time of an hired servant shall it be with him. ^51If there be yet many years behind, according unto them he shall give again the price of his redemption out of the money that he was bought for. ^52And if there remain but few years unto the year of jubile, then he shall count with him, and according unto his years shall he give him again the price of his redemption. ^53And as a yearly hired servant shall he be with him: and the other shall not rule with rigour over him in thy sight. ^54And if he be not redeemed in these years, then he shall go out in the year of jubile, both he, and his children with him. ^55For unto me the children of Israel are servants; they are my servants whom I brought forth out of the land of Egypt: I am the Lord your God.

XXVI

^1Ye shall make you no idols nor graven image, neither rear you up a standing image, neither shall ye set up any image of stone in your land, to bow down unto it: for I am the Lord your God. ^2Ye shall keep my sabbaths, and reverence my sanctuary: I am the Lord.

^3If ye walk in my statutes, and keep my commandments, and do them; ^4then I will give you rain in due season, and the land shall yield her increase, and the trees of the field shall yield their fruit. ^5And your threshing shall reach unto the vintage, and the vintage shall reach unto the sowing time: and ye shall eat your bread to the full, and dwell in your land safely. ^6And I will give peace in the land, and ye shall lie down, and none shall make you afraid: and I will rid evil beasts out of the land, neither shall the sword go through your land. ^7And ye shall chase your enemies, and they shall fall before you by the sword. ^8And five of you shall chase an hundred, and an hundred of you shall put ten thousand to flight: and your enemies shall fall before you by the sword. ^9For I will have respect unto you, and make you fruitful, and multiply you, and establish my covenant with you. ^10And ye shall eat old store, and bring forth the old because of the new. ^11And I set my tabernacle among you: and my soul shall not abhor you. ^12And I will walk among you, and will be your God, and ye shall be my people. ^13I am the Lord your God, which brought you forth out of the land of Egypt, that ye should not be their bondmen; and I have broken the bands of your yoke, and made you go upright.

^14But if ye will not hearken unto me, and will not do all these commandments; ^15and if ye shall despise my statutes, or if your soul abhor my judgments, so that ye will not do all my commandments, but that ye break my covenant: ^16I also will do this unto you; I will even appoint over you terror, consumption, and the burning ague, that shall consume the eyes, and cause sorrow of heart: and ye shall sow your seed in vain, for your enemies shall eat it. ^17And I will set my face against you, and ye shall be slain before your enemies: they that hate you shall reign over you; and ye shall flee when none pursueth you. ^18And if ye will not yet for all this hearken unto me, then I will punish you seven times more for your sins. ^19And I will break the pride of your power; and I will make your heaven as iron, and your earth as brass: ^20and your strength shall be spent in vain: for your land shall not yield her increase, neither shall the trees of the land yield their fruits.

^21And if ye walk contrary unto me, and will not hearken unto me; I will bring seven times more plagues upon you according to your sins. ^22I will also send wild beasts among you, which shall rob you of your children, and destroy your cattle, and make you few in number; and your high ways shall be desolate. ^23And if ye will not be reformed by me by these things, but will walk contrary unto me; ^24then will I also walk contrary unto you, and will punish you yet seven times for your sins. ^25And I will bring a sword upon you, that shall avenge the quarrel of my covenant: and when ye are gathered together within your cities, I will send the pestilence among you; and ye shall be delivered into the hand of the enemy. ^26And when I have broken the staff of your bread, ten women shall bake your bread in one oven, and they shall deliver you your bread again by weight: and ye shall eat, and not be satisfied. ^27And if ye will not for all this hearken unto me, but walk contrary unto me; ^28then I will walk contrary unto you also in fury; and I, even I, will chastise you seven times for your sins. ^29And ye shall eat the flesh of your sons, and the flesh of your daughters shall ye eat. ^30And I will destroy your high places, and cut down your images, and cast your carcases upon the carcases of your idols, and my soul shall abhor you. ^31And I will make your cities waste, and bring your sanctuaries unto desolation, and I will not smell the savour of your sweet odours. ^32And I will bring the land into desolation: and your enemies which dwell therein shall be astonished at it. ^33And I will scatter you among the heathen, and will draw out a sword after you: and your land shall be desolate, and your cities waste. ^34Then shall the land enjoy her sabbaths, as long as it lieth desolate, and ye be in your enemies’ land; even then shall the land rest, and enjoy her sabbaths. ^35As long as it lieth desolate it shall rest; because it did not rest in your sabbaths, when ye dwelt upon it. ^36And upon them that are left alive of you I will send a faintness into their hearts in the lands of their enemies; and the sound of a shaken leaf shall chase them; and they shall flee, as fleeing from a sword; and they shall fall when none pursueth. ^37And they shall fall one upon another, as it were before a sword, when none pursueth: and ye shall have no power to stand before your enemies. ^38And ye shall perish among the heathen, and the land of your enemies shall eat you up. ^39And they that are left of you shall pine away in their iniquity in your enemies’ lands; and also in the iniquities of their fathers shall they pine away with them. ^40If they shall confess their iniquity, and the iniquity of their fathers, with their trespass which they trespassed against me, and that also they have walked contrary unto me; ^41and that I also have walked contrary unto them, and have brought them into the land of their enemies; if then their uncircumcised hearts be humbled, and they then accept of the punishment of their iniquity: ^42then will I remember my covenant with Jacob, and also my covenant with Isaac, and also my covenant with Abraham will I remember; and I will remember the land. ^43The land also shall be left of them, and shall enjoy her sabbaths, while she lieth desolate without them: and they shall accept of the punishment of their iniquity: because, even because they despised my judgments, and because their soul abhorred my statutes.

^44And yet for all that, when they be in the land of their enemies, I will not cast them away, neither will I abhor them, to destroy them utterly, and to break my covenant with them: for I am the Lord their God. ^45But I will for their sakes remember the covenant of their ancestors, whom I brought forth out of the land of Egypt in the sight of the heathen, that I might be their God: I am the Lord.

^46These are the statutes and judgments and laws, which the Lord made between him and the children of Israel in mount Sinai by the hand of Moses.

XXVII

^1And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying, ^2Speak unto the children of Israel, and say unto them, When a man shall make a singular vow, the persons shall be for the Lord by thy estimation. ^3And thy estimation shall be of the male from twenty years old even unto sixty years old, even thy estimation shall be fifty shekels of silver, after the shekel of the sanctuary. ^4And if it be a female, then thy estimation shall be thirty shekels. ^5And if it be from five years old even unto twenty years old, then thy estimation shall be of the male twenty shekels, and for the female ten shekels. ^6And if it be from a month old even unto five years old, then thy estimation shall be of the male five shekels of silver, and for the female thy estimation shall be three shekels of silver. ^7And if it be from sixty years old and above; if it be a male, then thy estimation shall be fifteen shekels, and for the female ten shekels. ^8But if he be poorer than thy estimation, then he shall present himself before the priest, and the priest shall value him; according to his ability that vowed shall the priest value him. ^9And if it be a beast, whereof men bring an offering unto the Lord, all that any man giveth of such unto the Lord shall be holy. ^10He shall not alter it, nor change it, a good for a bad, or a bad for a good: and if he shall at all change beast for beast, then it and the exchange thereof shall be holy. ^11And if it be any unclean beast, of which they do not offer a sacrifice unto the Lord, then he shall present the beast before the priest: ^12and the priest shall value it, whether it be good or bad: as thou valuest it, who art the priest, so shall it be. ^13But if he will at all redeem it, then he shall add a fifth part thereof unto thy estimation.

^14And when a man shall sanctify his house to be holy unto the Lord, then the priest shall estimate it, whether it be good or bad: as the priest shall estimate it, so shall it stand. ^15And if he that sanctified it will redeem his house, then he shall add the fifth part of the money of thy estimation unto it, and it shall be his. ^16And if a man shall sanctify unto the Lord some part of a field of his possession, then thy estimation shall be according to the seed thereof: an homer of barley seed shall be valued at fifty shekels of silver. ^17If he sanctify his field from the year of jubile, according to thy estimation it shall stand. ^18But if he sanctify his field after the jubile, then the priest shall reckon unto him the money according to the years that remain, even unto the year of the jubile, and it shall be abated from thy estimation. ^19And if he that sanctified the field will in any wise redeem it, then he shall add the fifth part of the money of thy estimation unto it, and it shall be assured to him. ^20And if he will not redeem the field, or if he have sold the field to another man, it shall not be redeemed any more. ^21But the field, when it goeth out in the jubile, shall be holy unto the Lord, as a field devoted; the possession thereof shall be the priest’s. ^22And if a man sanctify unto the Lord a field which he hath bought, which is not of the fields of his possession; ^23then the priest shall reckon unto him the worth of thy estimation, even unto the year of the jubile: and he shall give thine estimation in that day, as a holy thing unto the Lord. ^24In the year of the jubile the field shall return unto him of whom it was bought, even to him to whom the possession of the land did belong. ^25And all thy estimations shall be according to the shekel of the sanctuary: twenty gerahs shall be the shekel.

^26Only the firstling of the beasts, which should be the Lord’s firstling, no man shall sanctify it; whether it be ox, or sheep: it is the Lord’s. ^27And if it be of an unclean beast, then he shall redeem it according to thine estimation, and shall add a fifth part of it thereto: or if it be not redeemed, then it shall be sold according to thy estimation. ^28Notwithstanding no devoted thing, that a man shall devote unto the Lord of all that he hath, both of man and beast, and of the field of his possession, shall be sold or redeemed: every devoted thing is most holy unto the Lord. ^29None devoted, which shall be devoted of men, shall be redeemed; but shall surely be put to death. ^30And all the tithe of the land, whether of the seed of the land, or of the fruit of the tree, is the Lord’s: it is holy unto the Lord. ^31And if a man will at all redeem ought of his tithes, he shall add thereto the fifth part thereof. ^32And concerning the tithe of the herd, or of the flock, even of whatsoever passeth under the rod, the tenth shall be holy unto the Lord. ^33He shall not search whether it be good or bad, neither shall he change it: and if he change it at all, then both it and the change thereof shall be holy; it shall not be redeemed. ^34These are the commandments, which the Lord commanded Moses for the children of Israel in mount Sinai.

Deuteronomy

The Fifth Book of Moses Called

Deuteronomy

I

^1These be the words which Moses spake unto all Israel on this side Jordan in the wilderness, in the plain over against the Red sea, between Paran, and Tophel, and Laban, and Hazeroth, and Dizahab. ^2(There are eleven days’ journey from Horeb by the way of mount Seir unto Kadeshbarnea.) ^3And it came to pass in the fortieth year, in the eleventh month, on the first day of the month, that Moses spake unto the children of Israel, according unto all that the Lord had given him in commandment unto them; ^4after he had slain Sihon the king of the Amorites, which dwelt in Heshbon, and Og the king of Bashan, which dwelt at Astaroth in Edrei: ^5on this side Jordan, in the land of Moab, began Moses to declare this law, saying, ^6The Lord our God spake unto us in Horeb, saying, Ye have dwelt long enough in this mount: ^7turn you, and take your journey, and go to the mount of the Amorites, and unto all the places nigh thereunto, in the plain, in the hills, and in the vale, and in the south, and by the sea side, to the land of the Canaanites, and unto Lebanon, unto the great river, the river Euphrates. ^8Behold, I have set the land before you: go in and possess the land which the Lord sware unto your fathers, Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob, to give unto them and to their seed after them.

^9And I spake unto you at that time, saying, I am not able to bear you myself alone: ^10the Lord your God hath multiplied you, and, behold, ye are this day as the stars of heaven for multitude. ^11(The Lord God of your fathers make you a thousand times so many more as ye are, and bless you, as he hath promised you!) ^12How can I myself alone bear your cumbrance, and your burden, and your strife? ^13Take you wise men, and understanding, and known among your tribes, and I will make them rulers over you. ^14And ye answered me, and said, The thing which thou hast spoken is good for us to do. ^15So I took the chief of your tribes, wise men, and known, and made them heads over you, captains over thousands, and captains over hundreds, and captains over fifties, and captains over tens, and officers among your tribes. ^16And I charged your judges at that time, saying, Hear the causes between your brethren, and judge righteously between every man and his brother, and the stranger that is with him. ^17Ye shall not respect persons in judgment; but ye shall hear the small as well as the great; ye shall not be afraid of the face of man; for the judgment is God’s: and the cause that is too hard for you, bring it unto me, and I will hear it. ^18And I commanded you at that time all the things which ye should do.

^19And when we departed from Horeb, we went through all that great and terrible wilderness, which ye saw by the way of the mountain of the Amorites, as the Lord our God commanded us; and we came to Kadeshbarnea. ^20And I said unto you, Ye are come unto the mountain of the Amorites, which the Lord our God doth give unto us. ^21Behold, the Lord thy God hath set the land before thee: go up and possess it, as the Lord God of thy fathers hath said unto thee; fear not, neither be discouraged. ^22And ye came near unto me every one of you, and said, We will send men before us, and they shall search us out the land, and bring us word again by what way we must go up, and into what cities we shall come. ^23And the saying pleased me well: and I took twelve men of you, one of a tribe: ^24and they turned and went up into the mountain, and came unto the valley of Eshcol, and searched it out. ^25And they took of the fruit of the land in their hands, and brought it down unto us, and brought us word again, and said, It is a good land which the Lord our God doth give us.

^26Notwithstanding ye would not go up, but rebelled against the commandment of the Lord your God: ^27and ye murmured in your tents, and said, Because the Lord hated us, he hath brought us forth out of the land of Egypt, to deliver us into the hand of the Amorites, to destroy us. ^28Whither shall we go up? our brethren have discouraged our heart, saying, The people is greater and taller than we; the cities are great and walled up to heaven; and moreover we have seen the sons of the Anakims there. ^29Then I said unto you, Dread not, neither be afraid of them. ^30The Lord your God which goeth before you, he shall fight for you, according to all that he did for you in Egypt before your eyes; ^31and in the wilderness, where thou hast seen how that the Lord thy God bare thee, as a man doth bear his son, in all the way that ye went, until ye came into this place. ^32Yet in this thing ye did not believe the Lord your God, ^33who went in the way before you, to search you out a place to pitch your tents in, in fire by night, to shew you by what way ye should go, and in a cloud by day.

^34And the Lord heard the voice of your words, and was wroth, and sware, saying, ^35Surely there shall not one of these men of this evil generation see that good land, which I sware to give unto your fathers. ^36Save Caleb the son of Jephunneh; he shall see it, and to him will I give the land that he hath trodden upon, and to his children, because he hath wholly followed the Lord. ^37Also the Lord was angry with me for your sakes, saying, Thou also shalt not go in thither. ^38But Joshua the son of Nun, which standeth before thee, he shall go in thither: encourage him: for he shall cause Israel to inherit it. ^39Moreover your little ones, which ye said should be a prey, and your children, which in that day had no knowledge between good and evil, they shall go in thither, and unto them will I give it, and they shall possess it. ^40But as for you, turn you, and take your journey into the wilderness by the way of the Red sea.

^41Then ye answered and said unto me, We have sinned against the Lord, we will go up and fight, according to all that the Lord our God commanded us. And when ye had girded on every man his weapons of war, ye were ready to go up into the hill. ^42And the Lord said unto me, Say unto them. Go not up, neither fight; for I am not among you; lest ye be smitten before your enemies. ^43So I spake unto you; and ye would not hear, but rebelled against the commandment of the Lord, and went presumptuously up into the hill. ^44And the Amorites, which dwelt in that mountain, came out against you, and chased you, as bees do, and destroyed you in Seir, even unto Hormah. ^45And ye returned and wept before the Lord; but the Lord would not hearken to your voice, nor give ear unto you. ^46So ye abode in Kadesh many days, according unto the days that ye abode there.

II

^1Then we turned, and took our journey into the wilderness by the way of the Red sea, as the Lord spake unto me: and we compassed mount Seir many days. ^2And the Lord spake unto me, saying, ^3Ye have compassed this mountain long enough: turn you northward. ^4And command thou the people, saying, Ye are to pass through the coast of your brethren the children of Esau, which dwell in Seir; and they shall be afraid of you: take ye good heed unto yourselves therefore: ^5meddle not with them; for I will not give you of their land, no, not so much as a foot breadth; because I have given mount Seir unto Esau for a possession. ^6Ye shall buy meat of them for money, that ye may eat; and ye shall also buy water of them for money, that ye may drink. ^7For the Lord thy God hath blessed thee in all the works of thy hand: he knoweth thy walking through this great wilderness: these forty years the Lord thy God hath been with thee; thou hast lacked nothing.

^8And when we passed by from our brethren the children of Esau, which dwelt in Seir, through the way of the plain from Elath, and from Eziongaber, we turned and passed by the way of the wilderness of Moab. ^9And the Lord said unto me, Distress not the Moabites, neither contend with them in battle: for I will not give thee of their land for a possession; because I have given Ar unto the children of Lot for a possession. ^10The Emims dwelt therein in times past, a people great, and many, and tall, as the Anakims; ^11which also were accounted giants, as the Anakims; but the Moabites called them Emims. ^12The Horims also dwelt in Seir beforetime; but the children of Esau succeeded them, when they had destroyed them from before them, and dwelt in their stead; as Israel did unto the land of his possession, which the Lord gave unto them. ^13Now rise up, said I, and get you over the brook Zered. And we went over the brook Zered. ^14And the space in which we came from Kadeshbarnea, until we were come over the brook Zered, was thirty and eight years; until all the generation of the men of war were wasted out from among the host, as the Lord sware unto them. ^15For indeed the hand of the Lord was against them, to destroy them from among the host, until they were consumed.

^16So it came to pass, when all the men of war were consumed and dead from among the people, ^17that the Lord spake unto me, saying, ^18Thou art to pass over through Ar, the coast of Moab, this day: ^19and when thou comest nigh over against the children of Ammon, distress them not, nor meddle with them: for I will not give thee of the land of the children of Ammon any possession; because I have given it unto the children of Lot for a possession. ^20(That also was accounted a land of giants: giants dwelt therein in old time; and the Ammonites call them Zamzummims; ^21a people great, and many, and tall, as the Anakims; but the Lord destroyed them before them; and they succeeded them, and dwelt in their stead: ^22as he did to the children of Esau, which dwelt in Seir, when he destroyed the Horims from before them; and they succeeded them, and dwelt in their stead even unto this day: ^23and the Avims which dwelt in Hazerim, even unto Azzah, the Caphtorims, which came forth out of Caphtor, destroyed them, and dwelt in their stead.) ^24Rise ye up, take your journey, and pass over the river Arnon: behold, I have given into thine hand Sihon the Amorite, king of Heshbon, and his land: begin to possess it, and contend with him in battle. ^25This day will I begin to put the dread of thee and the fear of thee upon the nations that are under the whole heaven, who shall hear report of thee, and shall tremble, and be in anguish because of thee.

^26And I sent messengers out of the wilderness of Kedemoth unto Sihon king of Heshbon with words of peace, saying, ^27Let me pass through thy land: I will go along by the high way, I will neither turn unto the right hand nor to the left. ^28Thou shalt sell me meat for money, that I may eat; and give me water for money, that I may drink: only I will pass through on my feet; ^29(as the children of Esau which dwell in Seir, and the Moabites which dwell in Ar, did unto me;) until I shall pass over Jordan into the land which the Lord our God giveth us. ^30But Sihon king of Heshbon would not let us pass by him: for the Lord thy God hardened his spirit, and made his heart obstinate, that he might deliver him into thy hand, as appeareth this day. ^31And the Lord said unto me, Behold, I have begun to give Sihon and his land before thee: begin to possess, that thou mayest inherit his land. ^32Then Sihon came out against us, he and all his people, to fight at Jahaz. ^33And the Lord our God delivered him before us; and we smote him, and his sons, and all his people. ^34And we took all his cities at that time, and utterly destroyed the men, and the women, and the little ones, of every city, we left none to remain: ^35only the cattle we took for a prey unto ourselves, and the spoil of the cities which we took. ^36From Aroer, which is by the brink of the river of Arnon, and from the city that is by the river, even unto Gilead, there was not one city too strong for us: the Lord our God delivered all unto us: ^37only unto the land of the children of Ammon thou camest not, nor unto any place of the river Jabbok, nor unto the cities in the mountains, nor unto whatsoever the Lord our God forbad us.

III

^1Then we turned, and went up the way to Bashan: and Og the king of Bashan came out against us, he and all his people, to battle at Edrei. ^2And the Lord said unto me, Fear him not: for I will deliver him, and all his people, and his land, into thy hand; and thou shalt do unto him as thou didst unto Sihon king of the Amorites, which dwelt at Heshbon. ^3So the Lord our God delivered into our hands Og also, the king of Bashan, and all his people: and we smote him until none was left to him remaining. ^4And we took all his cities at that time, there was not a city which we took not from them, threescore cities, all the region of Argob, the kingdom of Og in Bashan. ^5All these cities were fenced with high walls, gates, and bars; beside unwalled towns a great many. ^6And we utterly destroyed them, as we did unto Sihon king of Heshbon, utterly destroying the men, women, and children, of every city. ^7But all the cattle, and the spoil of the cities, we took for a prey to ourselves. ^8And we took at that time out of the hand of the two kings of the Amorites the land that was on this side Jordan, from the river of Arnon unto mount Hermon; ^9(which Hermon the Sidonians call Sirion; and the Amorites call it Shenir;) ^10all the cities of the plain, and all Gilead, and all Bashan, unto Salchah and Edrei, cities of the kingdom of Og in Bashan. ^11For only Og king of Bashan remained of the remnant of giants; behold his bedstead was a bedstead of iron; is it not in Rabbath of the children of Ammon? nine cubits was the length thereof, and four cubits the breadth of it, after the cubit of a man.

^12And this land, which we possessed at that time, from Aroer, which is by the river Arnon, and half mount Gilead, and the cities thereof, gave I unto the Reubenites and to the Gadites. ^13And the rest of Gilead, and all Bashan, being the kingdom of Og, gave I unto the half tribe of Manasseh; all the region of Argob, with all Bashan, which was called the land of giants. ^14Jair the son of Manasseh took all the country of Argob unto the coasts of Geshuri and Maachathi; and called them after his own name, Bashanhavothjair, unto this day. ^15And I gave Gilead unto Machir. ^16And unto the Reubenites and unto the Gadites I gave from Gilead even unto the river Arnon half the valley, and the border even unto the river Jabbok, which is the border of the children of Ammon; ^17the plain also, and Jordan, and the coast thereof, from Chinnereth even unto the sea of the plain, even the salt sea, under Ashdothpisgah eastward.

^18And I commanded you at that time, saying, The Lord your God hath given you this land to possess it: ye shall pass over armed before your brethren the children of Israel, all that are meet for the war. ^19But your wives, and your little ones, and your cattle, (for I know that ye have much cattle,) shall abide in your cities which I have given you; ^20until the Lord have given rest unto your brethren, as well as unto you, and until they also possess the land which the Lord your God hath given them beyond Jordan: and then shall ye return every man unto his possession, which I have given you. ^21And I commanded Joshua at that time, saying, Thine eyes have seen all that the Lord your God hath done unto these two kings: so shall the Lord do unto all the kingdoms whither thou passest. ^22Ye shall not fear them: for the Lord your God he shall fight for you.

^23And I besought the Lord at that time, saying, ^24O Lord God, thou hast begun to shew thy servant thy greatness, and thy mighty hand: for what God is there in heaven or in earth, that can do according to thy works, and according to thy might? ^25I pray thee, let me go over, and see the good land that is beyond Jordan, that goodly mountain, and Lebanon. ^26But the Lord was wroth with me for your sakes, and would not hear me: and the Lord said unto me, Let it suffice thee; speak no more unto me of this matter. ^27Get thee up into the top of Pisgah, and lift up thine eyes westward, and northward, and southward, and eastward, and behold it with thine eyes: for thou shalt not go over this Jordan. ^28But charge Joshua, and encourage him, and strengthen him: for he shall go over before this people, and he shall cause them to inherit the land which thou shalt see. ^29So we abode in the valley over against Bethpeor.

IV

^1Now therefore hearken, O Israel, unto the statutes and unto the judgments, which I teach you, for to do them, that ye may live, and go in and possess the land which the Lord God of your fathers giveth you. ^2Ye shall not add unto the word which I command you, neither shall ye diminish ought from it, that ye may keep the commandments of the Lord your God which I command you. ^3Your eyes have seen what the Lord did because of Baalpeor: for all the men that followed Baalpeor, the Lord thy God hath destroyed them from among you. ^4But ye that did cleave unto the Lord your God are alive every one of you this day. ^5Behold, I have taught you statutes and judgments, even as the Lord my God commanded me, that ye should do so in the land whither ye go to possess it. ^6Keep therefore and do them; for this is your wisdom and your understanding in the sight of the nations, which shall hear all these statutes, and say, Surely this great nation is a wise and understanding people. ^7For what nation is there so great, who hath God so nigh unto them, as the Lord our God is in all things that we call upon him for? ^8And what nation is there so great, that hath statutes and judgments so righteous as all this law, which I set before you this day?

^9Only take heed to thyself, and keep thy soul diligently, lest thou forget the things which thine eyes have seen, and lest they depart from thy heart all the days of thy life: but teach them thy sons, and thy sons’ sons; ^10specially the day that thou stoodest before the Lord thy God in Horeb, when the Lord said unto me, Gather me the people together, and I will make them hear my words, that they may learn to fear me all the days that they shall live upon the earth, and that they may teach their children. ^11And ye came near and stood under the mountain; and the mountain burned with fire unto the midst of heaven, with darkness, clouds, and thick darkness. ^12And the Lord spake unto you out of the midst of the fire: ye heard the voice of the words, but saw no similitude; only ye heard a voice. ^13And he declared unto you his covenant, which he commanded you to perform, even ten commandments; and he wrote them upon two tables of stone. ^14And the Lord commanded me at that time to teach you statutes and judgments, that ye might do them in the land whither ye go over to possess it.

^15Take ye therefore good heed unto yourselves; for ye saw no manner of similitude on the day that the Lord spake unto you in Horeb out of the midst of the fire: ^16lest ye corrupt yourselves, and make you a graven image, the similitude of any figure, the likeness of male or female, ^17the likeness of any beast that is on the earth, the likeness of any winged fowl that flieth in the air, ^18the likeness of any thing that creepeth on the ground, the likeness of any fish that is in the waters beneath the earth: ^19and lest thou lift up thine eyes unto heaven, and when thou seest the sun, and the moon, and the stars, even all the host of heaven, shouldest be driven to worship them, and serve them, which the Lord thy God hath divided unto all nations under the whole heaven. ^20But the Lord hath taken you, and brought you forth out of the iron furnace, even out of Egypt, to be unto him a people of inheritance, as ye are this day. ^21Furthermore the Lord was angry with me for your sakes, and sware that I should not go over Jordan, and that I should not go in unto that good land, which the Lord thy God giveth thee for an inheritance: ^22but I must die in this land, I must not go over Jordan: but ye shall go over, and possess that good land. ^23Take heed unto yourselves, lest ye forget the covenant of the Lord your God, which he made with you, and make you a graven image, or the likeness of any thing, which the Lord thy God hath forbidden thee. ^24For the Lord thy God is a consuming fire, even a jealous God.

^25When thou shalt beget children, and children’s children, and ye shall have remained long in the land, and shall corrupt yourselves, and make a graven image, or the likeness of any thing, and shall do evil in the sight of the Lord thy God, to provoke him to anger: ^26I call heaven and earth to witness against you this day, that ye shall soon utterly perish from off the land whereunto ye go over Jordan to possess it; ye shall not prolong your days upon it, but shall utterly be destroyed. ^27And the Lord shall scatter you among the nations, and ye shall be left few in number among the heathen, whither the Lord shall lead you. ^28And there ye shall serve gods, the work of men’s hands, wood and stone, which neither see, nor hear, nor eat, nor smell. ^29But if from thence thou shalt seek the Lord thy God, thou shalt find him, if thou seek him with all thy heart and with all thy soul. ^30When thou art in tribulation, and all these things are come upon thee, even in the latter days, if thou turn to the Lord thy God, and shalt be obedient unto his voice; ^31(for the Lord thy God is a merciful God;) he will not forsake thee, neither destroy thee, nor forget the covenant of thy fathers which he sware unto them.

^32For ask now of the days that are past, which were before thee, since the day that God created man upon the earth, and ask from the one side of heaven unto the other, whether there hath been any such thing as this great thing is, or hath been heard like it? ^33Did ever people hear the voice of God speaking out of the midst of the fire, as thou hast heard, and live? ^34Or hath God assayed to go and take him a nation from the midst of another nation, by temptations, by signs, and by wonders, and by war, and by a mighty hand, and by a stretched out arm, and by great terrors, according to all that the Lord your God did for you in Egypt before your eyes? ^35Unto thee it was shewed, that thou mightest know that the Lord he is God; there is none else beside him. ^36Out of heaven he made thee to hear his voice, that he might instruct thee: and upon earth he shewed thee his great fire; and thou heardest his words out of the midst of the fire. ^37And because he loved thy fathers, therefore he chose their seed after them, and brought thee out in his sight with his mighty power out of Egypt; ^38to drive out nations from before thee greater and mightier than thou art, to bring thee in, to give thee their land for an inheritance, as it is this day. ^39Know therefore this day, and consider it in thine heart, that the Lord he is God in heaven above, and upon the earth beneath: there is none else. ^40Thou shalt keep therefore his statutes, and his commandments, which I command thee this day, that it may go well with thee, and with thy children after thee, and that thou mayest prolong thy days upon the earth, which the Lord thy God giveth thee, for ever.

^41Then Moses severed three cities on this side Jordan toward the sunrising; ^42that the slayer might flee thither, which should kill his neighbour unawares, and hated him not in times past; and that fleeing unto one of these cities he might live: ^43namely, Bezer in the wilderness, in the plain country, of the Reubenites; and Ramoth in Gilead, of the Gadites; and Golan in Bashan, of the Manassites.

^44And this is the law which Moses set before the children of Israel: ^45these are the testimonies, and the statutes, and the judgments, which Moses spake unto the children of Israel, after they came forth out of Egypt. ^46On this side Jordan, in the valley over against Bethpeor, in the land of Sihon king of the Amorites, who dwelt at Heshbon, whom Moses and the children of Israel smote, after they were come forth out of Egypt: ^47and they possessed his land, and the land of Og king of Bashan, two kings of the Amorites, which were on this side Jordan toward the sunrising; ^48from Aroer, which is by the bank of the river Arnon, even unto mount Sion, which is Hermon, ^49and all the plain on this side Jordan eastward, even unto the sea of the plain, under the springs of Pisgah.

V

^1And Moses called all Israel, and said unto them, Hear, O Israel, the statutes and judgments which I speak in your ears this day, that ye may learn them, and keep, and do them. ^2The Lord our God made a covenant with us in Horeb. ^3The Lord made not this covenant with our fathers, but with us, even us, who are all of us here alive this day. ^4The Lord talked with you face to face in the mount out of the midst of the fire, ^5(I stood between the Lord and you at that time, to shew you the word of the Lord: for ye were afraid by reason of the fire, and went not up into the mount;) saying,

^6I am the Lord thy God, which brought thee out of the land of Egypt, from the house of bondage.

^7Thou shalt have none other gods before me.

^8Thou shalt not make thee any graven image, or any likeness of any thing that is in heaven above, or that is in the earth beneath, or that is in the waters beneath the earth: ^9thou shalt not bow down thyself unto them, nor serve them: for I the Lord thy God am a jealous God, visiting the iniquity of the fathers upon the children unto the third and fourth generation of them that hate me, ^10and shewing mercy unto thousands of them that love me and keep my commandments.

^11Thou shalt not take the name of the Lord thy God in vain: for the Lord will not hold him guiltless that taketh his name in vain.

^12Keep the sabbath day to sanctify it, as the Lord thy God hath commanded thee. ^13Six days thou shalt labour, and do all thy work: ^14but the seventh day is the sabbath of the Lord thy God: in it thou shalt not do any work, thou, nor thy son, nor thy daughter, nor thy manservant, nor thy maidservant, nor thine ox, nor thine ass, nor any of thy cattle, nor thy stranger that is within thy gates; that thy manservant and thy maidservant may rest as well as thou. ^15And remember that thou wast a servant in the land of Egypt, and that the Lord thy God brought thee out thence through a mighty hand and by a stretched out arm: therefore the Lord thy God commanded thee to keep the sabbath day.

^16Honour thy father and thy mother, as the Lord thy God hath commanded thee; that thy days may be prolonged, and that it may go well with thee, in the land which the Lord thy God giveth thee.

^17Thou shalt not kill.

^18Neither shalt thou commit adultery.

^19Neither shalt thou steal.

^20Neither shalt thou bear false witness against thy neighbour.

^21Neither shalt thou desire thy neighbour’s wife, neither shalt thou covet thy neighbour’s house, his field, or his manservant, or his maidservant, his ox, or his ass, or any thing that is thy neighbour’s.

^22These words the Lord spake unto all your assembly in the mount out of the midst of the fire, of the cloud, and of the thick darkness, with a great voice: and he added no more. And he wrote them in two tables of stone, and delivered them unto me. ^23And it came to pass, when ye heard the voice out of the midst of the darkness, (for the mountain did burn with fire,) that ye came near unto me, even all the heads of your tribes, and your elders; ^24and ye said, Behold, the Lord our God hath shewed us his glory and his greatness, and we have heard his voice out of the midst of the fire: we have seen this day that God doth talk with man, and he liveth. ^25Now therefore why should we die? for this great fire will consume us: if we hear the voice of the Lord our God any more, then we shall die. ^26For who is there of all flesh, that hath heard the voice of the living God speaking out of the midst of the fire, as we have, and lived? ^27Go thou near, and hear all that the Lord our God shall say: and speak thou unto us all that the Lord our God shall speak unto thee; and we will hear it, and do it.

^28And the Lord heard the voice of your words, when ye spake unto me; and the Lord said unto me, I have heard the voice of the words of this people, which they have spoken unto thee: they have well said all that they have spoken. ^29O that there were such an heart in them, that they would fear me, and keep all my commandments always, that it might be well with them, and with their children for ever! ^30Go say to them, Get you into your tents again. ^31But as for thee, stand thou here by me, and I will speak unto thee all the commandments, and the statutes, and the judgments, which thou shalt teach them, that they may do them in the land which I give them to possess it. ^32Ye shall observe to do therefore as the Lord your God hath commanded you: ye shall not turn aside to the right hand or to the left. ^33Ye shall walk in all the ways which the Lord your God hath commanded you, that ye may live, and that it may be well with you, and that ye may prolong your days in the land which ye shall possess.

VI

^1Now these are the commandments, the statutes, and the judgments, which the Lord your God commanded to teach you, that ye might do them in the land whither ye go to possess it: ^2that thou mightest fear the Lord thy God, to keep all his statutes and his commandments, which I command thee, thou, and thy son, and thy son’s son, all the days of thy life; and that thy days may be prolonged. ^3Hear therefore, O Israel, and observe to do it; that it may be well with thee, and that ye may increase mightily, as the Lord God of thy fathers hath promised thee, in the land that floweth with milk and honey.

^4Hear, O Israel: The Lord our God is one Lord: ^5and thou shalt love the Lord thy God with all thine heart, and with all thy soul, and with all thy might. ^6And these words, which I command thee this day, shall be in thine heart: ^7and thou shalt teach them diligently unto thy children, and shalt talk of them when thou sittest in thine house, and when thou walkest by the way, and when thou liest down, and when thou risest up. ^8And thou shalt bind them for a sign upon thine hand, and they shall be as frontlets between thine eyes. ^9And thou shalt write them upon the posts of thy house, and on thy gates.

^10And it shall be, when the Lord thy God shall have brought thee into the land which he sware unto thy fathers, to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob, to give thee great and goodly cities, which thou buildedst not, ^11and houses full of all good things, which thou filledst not, and wells digged, which thou diggedst not, vineyards and olive trees, which thou plantedst not; when thou shalt have eaten and be full; ^12then beware lest thou forget the Lord, which brought thee forth out of the land of Egypt, from the house of bondage. ^13Thou shalt fear the Lord thy God, and serve him, and shalt swear by his name. ^14Ye shall not go after other gods, of the gods of the people which are round about you; ^15(for the Lord thy God is a jealous God among you) lest the anger of the Lord thy God be kindled against thee, and destroy thee from off the face of the earth.

^16Ye shall not tempt the Lord your God, as ye tempted him in Massah. ^17Ye shall diligently keep the commandments of the Lord your God, and his testimonies, and his statutes, which he hath commanded thee. ^18And thou shalt do that which is right and good in the sight of the Lord: that it may be well with thee, and that thou mayest go in and possess the good land which the Lord sware unto thy fathers. ^19To cast out all thine enemies from before thee, as the Lord hath spoken.

^20And when thy son asketh thee in time to come, saying, What mean the testimonies, and the statutes, and the judgments, which the Lord our God hath commanded you? ^21Then thou shalt say unto thy son, We were Pharaoh’s bondmen in Egypt; and the Lord brought us out of Egypt with a mighty hand: ^22and the Lord shewed signs and wonders, great and sore, upon Egypt, upon Pharaoh, and upon all his household, before our eyes: ^23and he brought us out from thence, that he might bring us in, to give us the land which he sware unto our fathers. ^24And the Lord commanded us to do all these statutes, to fear the Lord our God, for our good always, that he might preserve us alive, as it is at this day. ^25And it shall be our righteousness, if we observe to do all these commandments before the Lord our God, as he hath commanded us.

VII

^1When the Lord thy God shall bring thee into the land whither thou goest to possess it, and hath cast out many nations before thee, the Hittites, and the Girgashites, and the Amorites, and the Canaanites, and the Perizzites, and the Hivites, and the Jebusites, seven nations greater and mightier than thou; ^2and when the Lord thy God shall deliver them before thee; thou shalt smite them, and utterly destroy them; thou shalt make no covenant with them, nor shew mercy unto them: ^3neither shalt thou make marriages with them; thy daughter thou shalt not give unto his son, nor his daughter shalt thou take unto thy son. ^4For they will turn away thy son from following me, that they may serve other gods: so will the anger of the Lord be kindled against you, and destroy thee suddenly. ^5But thus shall ye deal with them; ye shall destroy their altars, and break down their images, and cut down their groves, and burn their graven images with fire.

^6For thou art an holy people unto the Lord thy God: the Lord thy God hath chosen thee to be a special people unto himself, above all people that are upon the face of the earth. ^7The Lord did not set his love upon you, nor choose you, because ye were more in number than any people; for ye were the fewest of all people: ^8but because the Lord loved you, and because he would keep the oath which he had sworn unto your fathers, hath the Lord brought you out with a mighty hand, and redeemed you out of the house of bondmen, from the hand of Pharaoh king of Egypt. ^9Know therefore that the Lord thy God, he is God, the faithful God, which keepeth covenant and mercy with them that love him and keep his commandments to a thousand generations; ^10and repayeth them that hate him to their face, to destroy them: he will not be slack to him that hateth him, he will repay him to his face. ^11Thou shalt therefore keep the commandments, and the statutes, and the judgments, which I command thee this day, to do them.

^12Wherefore it shall come to pass, if ye hearken to these judgments, and keep, and do them, that the Lord thy God shall keep unto thee the covenant and the mercy which he sware unto thy fathers: ^13and he will love thee, and bless thee, and multiply thee: he will also bless the fruit of thy womb, and the fruit of thy land, thy corn, and thy wine, and thine oil, the increase of thy kine, and the flocks of thy sheep, in the land which he sware unto thy fathers to give thee. ^14Thou shalt be blessed above all people: there shall not be male or female barren among you, or among your cattle. ^15And the Lord will take away from thee all sickness, and will put none of the evil diseases of Egypt, which thou knowest, upon thee; but will lay them upon all them that hate thee. ^16And thou shalt consume all the people which the Lord thy God shall deliver thee; thine eye shall have no pity upon them: neither shalt thou serve their gods; for that will be a snare unto thee.

^17If thou shalt say in thine heart, These nations are more than I; how can I dispossess them? ^18Thou shalt not be afraid of them: but shalt well remember what the Lord thy God did unto Pharaoh, and unto all Egypt; ^19the great temptations which thine eyes saw, and the signs, and the wonders, and the mighty hand, and the stretched out arm, whereby the Lord thy God brought thee out: so shall the Lord thy God do unto all the people of whom thou art afraid. ^20Moreover the Lord thy God will send the hornet among them, until they that are left, and hide themselves from thee, be destroyed. ^21Thou shalt not be affrighted at them: for the Lord thy God is among you, a mighty God and terrible. ^22And the Lord thy God will put out those nations before thee by little and little: thou mayest not consume them at once, lest the beasts of the field increase upon thee. ^23But the Lord thy God shall deliver them unto thee, and shall destroy them with a mighty destruction, until they be destroyed. ^24And he shall deliver their kings into thine hand, and thou shalt destroy their name from under heaven: there shall no man be able to stand before thee, until thou have destroyed them. ^25The graven images of their gods shall ye burn with fire: thou shalt not desire the silver or gold that is on them, nor take it unto thee, lest thou be snared therin: for it is an abomination to the Lord thy God. ^26Neither shalt thou bring an abomination into thine house, lest thou be a cursed thing like it: but thou shalt utterly detest it, and thou shalt utterly abhor it; for it is a cursed thing.

VIII

^1All the commandments which I command thee this day shall ye observe to do, that ye may live, and multiply, and go in and possess the land which the Lord sware unto your fathers. ^2And thou shalt remember all the way which the Lord thy God led thee these forty years in the wilderness, to humble thee, and to prove thee, to know what was in thine heart, whether thou wouldest keep his commandments, or no. ^3And he humbled thee, and suffered thee to hunger, and fed thee with manna, which thou knewest not, neither did thy fathers know; that he might make thee know that man doth not live by bread only, but by every word that proceedeth out of the mouth of the Lord doth man live. ^4Thy raiment waxed not old upon thee, neither did thy foot swell, these forty years. ^5Thou shalt also consider in thine heart, that, as a man chasteneth his son, so the Lord thy God chasteneth thee. ^6Therefore thou shalt keep the commandments of the Lord thy God, to walk in his ways, and to fear him. ^7For the Lord thy God bringeth thee into a good land, a land of brooks of water, of fountains and depths that spring out of valleys and hills; ^8a land of wheat, and barley, and vines, and fig trees, and pomegranates; a land of oil olive, and honey; ^9a land wherein thou shalt eat bread without scarceness, thou shalt not lack any thing in it; a land whose stones are iron, and out of whose hills thou mayest dig brass. ^10When thou hast eaten and art full, then thou shalt bless the Lord thy God for the good land which he hath given thee.

^11Beware that thou forget not the Lord thy God, in not keeping his commandments, and his judgments, and his statutes, which I command thee this day: ^12lest when thou hast eaten and art full, and hast built goodly houses, and dwelt therein; ^13and when thy herds and thy flocks multiply, and thy silver and thy gold is multiplied, and all that thou hast is multiplied; ^14then thine heart be lifted up, and thou forget the Lord thy God, which brought thee forth out of the land of Egypt, from the house of bondage; ^15who led thee through that great and terrible wilderness, wherein were fiery serpents, and scorpions, and drought, where there was no water; who brought thee forth water out of the rock of flint; ^16who fed thee in the wilderness with manna, which thy fathers knew not, that he might humble thee, and that he might prove thee, to do thee good at thy latter end; ^17and thou say in thine heart, My power and the might of mine hand hath gotten me this wealth. ^18But thou shalt remember the Lord thy God: for it is he that giveth thee power to get wealth, that he may establish his covenant which he sware unto thy fathers, as it is this day. ^19And it shall be, if thou do at all forget the Lord thy God, and walk after other gods, and serve them, and worship them, I testify against you this day that ye shall surely perish. ^20As the nations which the Lord destroyeth before your face, so shall ye perish; because ye would not be obedient unto the voice of the Lord your God.

IX

^1Hear, O Israel: Thou art to pass over Jordan this day, to go in to possess nations greater and mightier than thyself, cities great and fenced up to heaven, ^2a people great and tall, the children of the Anakims, whom thou knowest, and of whom thou hast heard say, Who can stand before the children of Anak! ^3Understand therefore this day, that the Lord thy God is he which goeth over before thee; as a consuming fire he shall destroy them, and he shall bring them down before thy face: so shalt thou drive them out, and destroy them quickly, as the Lord hath said unto thee. ^4Speak not thou in thine heart, after that the Lord thy God hath cast them out from before thee, saying, For my righteousness the Lord hath brought me in to possess this land: but for the wickedness of these nations the Lord doth drive them out from before thee. ^5Not for thy righteousness, or for the uprightness of thine heart, dost thou go to possess their land: but for the wickedness of these nations the Lord thy God doth drive them out from before thee, and that he may perform the word which the Lord sware unto thy fathers, Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob.

^6Understand therefore, that the Lord thy God giveth thee not this good land to possess it for thy righteousness; for thou art a stiffnecked people. ^7Remember, and forget not, how thou provokedst the Lord thy God to wrath in the wilderness: from the day that thou didst depart out of the land of Egypt, until ye came unto this place, ye have been rebellious against the Lord. ^8Also in Horeb ye provoked the Lord to wrath, so that the Lord was angry with you to have destroyed you. ^9When I was gone up into the mount to receive the tables of stone, even the tables of the covenant which the Lord made with you, then I abode in the mount forty days and forty nights, I neither did eat bread nor drink water: ^10and the Lord delivered unto me two tables of stone written with the finger of God; and on them was written according to all the words, which the Lord spake with you in the mount out of the midst of the fire in the day of the assembly. ^11And it came to pass at the end of forty days and forty nights, that the Lord gave me the two tables of stone, even the tables of the covenant. ^12And the Lord said unto me, Arise, get thee down quickly from hence; for thy people which thou hast brought forth out of Egypt have corrupted themselves; they are quickly turned aside out of the way which I commanded them; they have made them a molten image. ^13Furthermore the Lord spake unto me, saying, I have seen this people, and, behold, it is a stiffnecked people: ^14let me alone, that I may destroy them, and blot out their name from under heaven: and I will make of thee a nation mightier and greater than they. ^15So I turned and came down from the mount, and the mount burned with fire: and the two tables of the covenant were in my two hands. ^16And I looked, and, behold, ye had sinned against the Lord your God, and had made you a molten calf: ye had turned aside quickly out of the way which the Lord had commanded you. ^17And I took the two tables, and cast them out of my two hands, and brake them before your eyes. ^18And I fell down before the Lord, as at the first, forty days and forty nights: I did neither eat bread, nor drink water, because of all your sins which ye sinned, in doing wickedly in the sight of the Lord, to provoke him to anger. ^19For I was afraid of the anger and hot displeasure, wherewith the Lord was wroth against you to destroy you. But the Lord hearkened unto me at that time also. ^20And the Lord was very angry with Aaron to have destroyed him: and I prayed for Aaron also the same time. ^21And I took your sin, the calf which ye had made, and burnt it with fire, and stamped it, and ground it very small, even until it was as small as dust: and I cast the dust thereof into the brook that descended out of the mount. ^22And at Taberah, and at Massah, and at Kibrothhattaavah, ye provoked the Lord to wrath. ^23Likewise when the Lord sent you from Kadeshbarnea, saying, Go up and possess the land which I have given you; then ye rebelled against the commandment of the Lord your God, and ye believed him not, nor hearkened to his voice. ^24Ye have been rebellious against the Lord from the day that I knew you.

^25Thus I fell down before the Lord forty days and forty nights, as I fell down at the first; because the Lord had said he would destroy you. ^26I prayed therefore unto the Lord, and said, O Lord God, destroy not thy people and thine inheritance, which thou hast redeemed through thy greatness, which thou hast brought forth out of Egypt with a mighty hand. ^27Remember thy servants, Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob; look not unto the stubbornness of this people, nor to their wickedness, nor to their sin: ^28lest the land whence thou broughtest us out say, Because the Lord was not able to bring them into the land which he promised them, and because he hated them, he hath brought them out to slay them in the wilderness. ^29Yet they are thy people and thine inheritance, which thou broughtest out by thy mighty power and by thy stretched out arm.

X

^1At that time the Lord said unto me, Hew thee two tables of stone like unto the first, and come up unto me into the mount, and make thee an ark of wood. ^2And I will write on the tables the words that were in the first tables which thou brakest, and thou shalt put them in the ark. ^3And I made an ark of shittim wood, and hewed two tables of stone like unto the first, and went up into the mount, having the two tables in mine hand. ^4And he wrote on the tables, according to the first writing, the ten commandments, which the Lord spake unto you in the mount out of the midst of the fire in the day of the assembly: and the Lord gave them unto me. ^5And I turned myself and came down from the mount, and put the tables in the ark which I had made; and there they be, as the Lord commanded me. ^6And the children of Israel took their journey from Beeroth of the children of Jaakan to Mosera: there Aaron died, and there he was buried; and Eleazar his son ministered in the priest’s office in his stead. ^7From thence they journeyed unto Gudgodah; and from Gudgodah to Jotbath, a land of rivers of waters. ^8At that time the Lord separated the tribe of Levi, to bear the ark of the covenant of the Lord, to stand before the Lord to minister unto him, and to bless in his name, unto this day. ^9Wherefore Levi hath no part nor inheritance with his brethren; the Lord is his inheritance, according as the Lord thy God promised him. ^10And I stayed in the mount, according to the first time, forty days and forty nights; and the Lord hearkened unto me at that time also, and the Lord would not destroy thee. ^11And the Lord said unto me, Arise, take thy journey before the people, that they may go in and possess the land, which I sware unto their fathers to give unto them.

^12And now, Israel, what doth the Lord thy God require of thee, but to fear the Lord thy God, to walk in all his ways, and to love him, and to serve the Lord thy God with all thy heart and with all thy soul, ^13to keep the commandments of the Lord, and his statutes, which I command thee this day for thy good? ^14Behold, the heaven and the heaven of heavens is the Lord’s thy God, the earth also, with all that therein is. ^15Only the Lord had a delight in thy fathers to love them, and he chose their seed after them, even you above all people, as it is this day. ^16Circumcise therefore the foreskin of your heart, and be no more stiffnecked. ^17For the Lord your God is God of gods, and Lord of lords, a great God, a mighty, and a terrible, which regardeth not persons, nor taketh reward: ^18he doth execute the judgment of the fatherless and widow, and loveth the stranger, in giving him food and raiment. ^19Love ye therefore the stranger: for ye were strangers in the land of Egypt. ^20Thou shalt fear the Lord thy God; him shalt thou serve, and to him shalt thou cleave, and swear by his name. ^21He is thy praise, and he is thy God, that hath done for thee these great and terrible things, which thine eyes have seen. ^22Thy fathers went down into Egypt with threescore and ten persons; and now the Lord thy God hath made thee as the stars of heaven for multitude.

XI

^1Therefore thou shalt love the Lord thy God, and keep his charge, and his statutes, and his judgments, and his commandments, alway. ^2And know ye this day: for I speak not with your children which have not known, and which have not seen the chastisement of the Lord your God, his greatness, his mighty hand, and his stretched out arm, ^3and his miracles, and his acts, which he did in the midst of Egypt unto Pharaoh the king of Egypt, and unto all his land; ^4and what he did unto the army of Egypt, unto their horses, and to their chariots; how he made the water of the Red sea to overflow them as they pursued after you, and how the Lord hath destroyed them unto this day; ^5and what he did unto you in the wilderness, until ye came into this place; ^6and what he did unto Dathan and Abiram, the sons of Eliab, the son of Reuben: how the earth opened her mouth, and swallowed them up, and their households, and their tents, and all the substance that was in their possession, in the midst of all Israel: ^7but your eyes have seen all the great acts of the Lord which he did.

^8Therefore shall ye keep all the commandments which I command you this day, that ye may be strong, and go in and possess the land, whither ye go to possess it; ^9and that ye may prolong your days in the land, which the Lord sware unto your fathers to give unto them and to their seed, a land that floweth with milk and honey. ^10For the land, whither thou goest in to possess it, is not as the land of Egypt, from whence ye came out, where thou sowedst thy seed, and wateredst it with thy foot, as a garden of herbs: ^11but the land, whither ye go to possess it, is a land of hills and valleys, and drinketh water of the rain of heaven: ^12a land which the Lord thy God careth for: the eyes of the Lord thy God are always upon it, from the beginning of the year even unto the end of the year.

^13And it shall come to pass, if ye shall hearken diligently unto my commandments which I command you this day, to love the Lord your God, and to serve him with all your heart and with all your soul, ^14that I will give you the rain of your land in his due season, the first rain and the latter rain, that thou mayest gather in thy corn, and thy wine, and thine oil. ^15And I will send grass in thy fields for thy cattle, that thou mayest eat and be full. ^16Take heed to yourselves, that your heart be not deceived, and ye turn aside, and serve other gods, and worship them; ^17and then the Lord’s wrath be kindled against you, and he shut up the heaven, that there be no rain, and that the land yield not her fruit; and lest ye perish quickly from off the good land which the Lord giveth you.

^18Therefore shall ye lay up these my words in your heart and in your soul, and bind them for a sign upon your hand, that they may be as frontlets between your eyes. ^19And ye shall teach them your children, speaking of them when thou sittest in thine house, and when thou walkest by the way, when thou liest down, and when thou risest up. ^20And thou shalt write them upon the door posts of thine house, and upon thy gates: ^21that your days may be multiplied, and the days of your children, in the land which the Lord sware unto your fathers to give them, as the days of heaven upon the earth. ^22For if ye shall diligently keep all these commandments which I command you, to do them, to love the Lord your God, to walk in all his ways, and to cleave unto him; ^23then will the Lord drive out all these nations from before you, and ye shall possess greater nations and mightier than yourselves. ^24Every place whereon the soles of your feet shall tread shall be yours: from the wilderness and Lebanon, from the river, the river Euphrates, even unto the uttermost sea shall your coast be. ^25There shall no man be able to stand before you: for the Lord your God shall lay the fear of you and the dread of you upon all the land that ye shall tread upon, as he hath said unto you.

^26Behold, I set before you this day a blessing and a curse; ^27a blessing, if ye obey the commandments of the Lord your God, which I command you this day: ^28and a curse, if ye will not obey the commandments of the Lord your God, but turn aside out of the way which I command you this day, to go after other gods, which ye have not known. ^29And it shall come to pass, when the Lord thy God hath brought thee in unto the land whither thou goest to possess it, that thou shalt put the blessing upon mount Gerizim, and the curse upon mount Ebal. ^30Are they not on the other side Jordan, by the way where the sun goeth down, in the land of the Canaanites, which dwell in the champaign over against Gilgal, beside the plains of Moreh? ^31For ye shall pass over Jordan to go in to possess the land which the Lord your God giveth you, and ye shall possess it, and dwell therein. ^32And ye shall observe to do all the statutes and judgments which I set before you this day.

XII

^1These are the statutes and judgments, which ye shall observe to do in the land, which the Lord God of thy fathers giveth thee to possess it, all the days that ye live upon the earth.

^2Ye shall utterly destroy all the places, wherein the nations which ye shall possess served their gods, upon the high mountains, and upon the hills, and under every green tree: ^3and ye shall overthrow their altars, and break their pillars, and burn their groves with fire; and ye shall hew down the graven images of their gods, and destroy the names of them out of that place. ^4Ye shall not do so unto the Lord your God. ^5But unto the place which the Lord your God shall choose out of all your tribes to put his name there, even unto his habitation shall ye seek, and thither thou shalt come: ^6and thither ye shall bring your burnt offerings, and your sacrifices, and your tithes, and heave offerings of your hand, and your vows, and your freewill offerings, and the firstlings of your herds and of your flocks: ^7and there ye shall eat before the Lord your God, and ye shall rejoice in all that ye put your hand unto, ye and your households, wherein the Lord thy God hath blessed thee. ^8Ye shall not do after all the things that we do here this day, every man whatsoever is right in his own eyes. ^9For ye are not as yet come to the rest and to the inheritance, which the Lord your God giveth you. ^10But when ye go over Jordan, and dwell in the land which the Lord your God giveth you to inherit, and when he giveth you rest from all your enemies round about, so that ye dwell in safety; ^11then there shall be a place which the Lord your God shall choose to cause his name to dwell there; thither shall ye bring all that I command you; your burnt offerings, and your sacrifices, your tithes, and the heave offering of your hand, and all your choice vows which ye vow unto the Lord: ^12and ye shall rejoice before the Lord your God, ye, and your sons, and your daughters, and your menservants, and your maidservants, and the Levite that is within your gates; forasmuch as he hath no part nor inheritance with you. ^13Take heed to thyself that thou offer not thy burnt offerings in every place that thou seest: ^14but in the place which the Lord shall choose in one of thy tribes, there thou shalt offer thy burnt offerings, and there thou shalt do all that I command thee.

^15Notwithstanding thou mayest kill and eat flesh in all thy gates, whatsoever thy soul lusteth after, according to the blessing of the Lord thy God which he hath given thee: the unclean and the clean may eat thereof, as of the roebuck, and as of the hart. ^16Only ye shall not eat the blood; ye shall pour it upon the earth as water. ^17Thou mayest not eat within thy gates the tithe of thy corn, or of thy wine, or of thy oil, or the firstlings of thy herds or of thy flock, nor any of thy vows which thou vowest, nor thy freewill offerings, or heave offering of thine hand: ^18but thou must eat them before the Lord thy God in the place which the Lord thy God shall choose, thou, and thy son, and thy daughter, and thy manservant, and thy maidservant, and the Levite that is within thy gates: and thou shalt rejoice before the Lord thy God in all that thou puttest thine hands unto. ^19Take heed to thyself that thou forsake not the Levite as long as thou livest upon the earth.

^20When the Lord thy God shall enlarge thy border, as he hath promised thee, and thou shalt say, I will eat flesh, because thy soul longeth to eat flesh; thou mayest eat flesh, whatsoever thy soul lusteth after. ^21If the place which the Lord thy God hath chosen to put his name there be too far from thee, then thou shalt kill of thy herd and of thy flock, which the Lord hath given thee, as I have commanded thee, and thou shalt eat in thy gates whatsoever thy soul lusteth after. ^22Even as the roebuck and the hart is eaten, so thou shalt eat them: the unclean and the clean shall eat of them alike. ^23Only be sure that thou eat not the blood: for the blood is the life; and thou mayest not eat the life with the flesh. ^24Thou shalt not eat it; thou shalt pour it upon the earth as water. ^25Thou shalt not eat it; that it may go well with thee, and with thy children after thee, when thou shalt do that which is right in the sight of the Lord. ^26Only thy holy things which thou hast, and thy vows, thou shalt take, and go unto the place which the Lord shall choose: ^27and thou shalt offer thy burnt offerings, the flesh and the blood, upon the altar of the Lord thy God: and the blood of thy sacrifices shall be poured out upon the altar of the Lord thy God, and thou shalt eat the flesh. ^28Observe and hear all these words which I command thee, that it may go well with thee, and with thy children after thee for ever, when thou doest that which is good and right in the sight of the Lord thy God.

^29When the Lord thy God shall cut off the nations from before thee, whither thou goest to possess them, and thou succeedest them, and dwellest in their land; ^30take heed to thyself that thou be not snared by following them, after that they be destroyed from before thee; and that thou enquire not after their gods, saying, How did these nations serve their gods? even so will I do likewise. ^31Thou shalt not do so unto the Lord thy God: for every abomination to the Lord, which he hateth, have they done unto their gods; for even their sons and their daughters they have burnt in the fire to their gods. ^32What thing soever I command you, observe to do it: thou shalt not add thereto, nor diminish from it.

XIII

^1If there arise among you a prophet, or a dreamer of dreams, and giveth thee a sign or a wonder, ^2and the sign or the wonder come to pass, whereof he spake unto thee, saying, Let us go after other gods, which thou hast not known, and let us serve them; ^3thou shalt not hearken unto the words of that prophet, or that dreamer of dreams: for the Lord your God proveth you, to know whether ye love the Lord your God with all your heart and with all your soul. ^4Ye shall walk after the Lord your God, and fear him, and keep his commandments, and obey his voice, and ye shall serve him, and cleave unto him. ^5And that prophet, or that dreamer of dreams, shall be put to death; because he hath spoken to turn you away from the Lord your God, which brought you out of the land of Egypt, and redeemed you out of the house of bondage, to thrust thee out of the way which the Lord thy God commanded thee to walk in. So shalt thou put the evil away from the midst of thee.

^6If thy brother, the son of thy mother, or thy son, or thy daughter, or the wife of thy bosom, or thy friend, which is as thine own soul, entice thee secretly, saying, Let us go and serve other gods, which thou hast not known, thou, nor thy fathers; ^7namely, of the gods of the people which are round about you, nigh unto thee, or far off from thee, from the one end of the earth even unto the other end of the earth; ^8thou shalt not consent unto him, nor hearken unto him; neither shall thine eye pity him, neither shalt thou spare, neither shalt thou conceal him: ^9but thou shalt surely kill him; thine hand shall be first upon him to put him to death, and afterwards the hand of all the people. ^10And thou shalt stone him with stones, that he die; because he hath sought to thrust thee away from the Lord thy God, which brought thee out of the land of Egypt, from the house of bondage. ^11And all Israel shall hear, and fear, and shall do no more any such wickedness as this is among you.

^12If thou shalt hear say in one of thy cities, which the Lord thy God hath given thee to dwell there, saying, ^13Certain men, the children of Belial, are gone out from among you, and have withdrawn the inhabitants of their city, saying, Let us go and serve other gods, which ye have not known; ^14then shalt thou enquire, and make search, and ask diligently; and, behold, if it be truth, and the thing certain, that such abomination is wrought among you; ^15thou shalt surely smite the inhabitants of that city with the edge of the sword, destroying it utterly, and all that is therein, and the cattle thereof, with the edge of the sword. ^16And thou shalt gather all the spoil of it into the midst of the street thereof, and shalt burn with fire the city, and all the spoil thereof every whit, for the Lord thy God: and it shall be an heap for ever; it shall not be built again. ^17And there shall cleave nought of the cursed thing to thine hand: that the Lord may turn from the fierceness of his anger, and shew thee mercy, and have compassion upon thee, and multiply thee, as he hath sworn unto thy fathers; ^18when thou shalt hearken to the voice of the Lord thy God, to keep all his commandments which I command thee this day, to do that which is right in the eyes of the Lord thy God.

XIV

^1Ye are the children of the Lord your God: ye shall not cut yourselves, nor make any baldness between your eyes for the dead. ^2For thou art an holy people unto the Lord thy God, and the Lord hath chosen thee to be a peculiar people unto himself, above all the nations that are upon the earth.

^3Thou shalt not eat any abominable thing. ^4These are the beasts which ye shall eat: the ox, the sheep, and the goat, ^5the hart, and the roebuck, and the fallow deer, and the wild goat, and the pygarg, and the wild ox, and the chamois. ^6And every beast that parteth the hoof, and cleaveth the cleft into two claws, and cheweth the cud among the beasts, that ye shall eat. ^7Nevertheless these ye shall not eat of them that chew the cud, or of them that divide the cloven hoof; as the camel, and the hare, and the coney: for they chew the cud, but divide not the hoof; therefore they are unclean unto you. ^8And the swine, because it divideth the hoof, yet cheweth not the cud, it is unclean unto you: ye shall not eat of their flesh, nor touch their dead carcase. ^9These ye shall eat of all that are in the waters: all that have fins and scales shall ye eat: ^10and whatsoever hath not fins and scales ye may not eat; it is unclean unto you.

^11Of all clean birds ye shall eat. ^12But these are they of which ye shall not eat: the eagle, and the ossifrage, and the ospray, ^13and the glede, and the kite, and the vulture after his kind, ^14and every raven after his kind, ^15and the owl, and the night hawk, and the cuckow, and the hawk after his kind, ^16the little owl, and the great owl, and the swan, ^17and the pelican, and the gier eagle, and the cormorant, ^18and the stork, and the heron after her kind, and the lapwing, and the bat. ^19And every creeping thing that flieth is unclean unto you: they shall not be eaten. ^20But of all clean fowls ye may eat.

^21Ye shall not eat of anything that dieth of itself: thou shalt give it unto the stranger that is in thy gates, that he may eat it; or thou mayest sell it unto an alien: for thou art an holy people unto the Lord thy God. Thou shalt not seethe a kid in his mother’s milk.

^22Thou shalt truly tithe all the increase of thy seed, that the field bringeth forth year by year. ^23And thou shalt eat before the Lord thy God, in the place which he shall choose to place his name there, the tithe of thy corn, of thy wine, and of thine oil, and the firstlings of thy herds and of thy flocks; that thou mayest learn to fear the Lord thy God always. ^24And if the way be too long for thee, so that thou art not able to carry it; or if the place be too far from thee, which the Lord thy God shall choose to set his name there, when the Lord thy God hath blessed thee: ^25then shalt thou turn it into money, and bind up the money in thine hand, and shalt go unto the place which the Lord thy God shall choose: ^26and thou shalt bestow that money for whatsoever thy soul lusteth after, for oxen, or for sheep, or for wine, or for strong drink, or for whatsoever thy soul desireth: and thou shalt eat there before the Lord thy God, and thou shalt rejoice, thou, and thine household, ^27and the Levite that is within thy gates; thou shalt not forsake him; for he hath no part nor inheritance with thee.

^28At the end of three years thou shalt bring forth all the tithe of thine increase the same year, and shalt lay it up within thy gates: ^29and the Levite, (because he hath no part nor inheritance with thee,) and the stranger, and the fatherless, and the widow, which are within thy gates, shall come, and shall eat and be satisfied; that the Lord thy God may bless thee in all the work of thine hand which thou doest.

XV

^1At the end of every seven years thou shalt make a release. ^2And this is the manner of the release: Every creditor that lendeth ought unto his neighbour shall release it; he shall not exact it of his neighbour, or of his brother; because it is called the Lord’s release. ^3Of a foreigner thou mayest exact it again: but that which is thine with thy brother thine hand shall release; ^4save when there shall be no poor among you; for the Lord shall greatly bless thee in the land which the Lord thy God giveth thee for an inheritance to possess it: ^5only if thou carefully hearken unto the voice of the Lord thy God, to observe to do all these commandments which I command thee this day. ^6For the Lord thy God blesseth thee, as he promised thee: and thou shalt lend unto many nations, but thou shalt not borrow; and thou shalt reign over many nations, but they shall not reign over thee.

^7If there be among you a poor man of one of thy brethren within any of thy gates in thy land which the Lord thy God giveth thee, thou shalt not harden thine heart, nor shut thine hand from thy poor brother: ^8but thou shalt open thine hand wide unto him, and shalt surely lend him sufficient for his need, in that which he wanteth. ^9Beware that there be not a thought in thy wicked heart, saying, The seventh year, the year of release, is at hand; and thine eye be evil against thy poor brother, and thou givest him nought; and he cry unto the Lord against thee, and it be sin unto thee. ^10Thou shalt surely give him, and thine heart shall not be grieved when thou givest unto him: because that for this thing the Lord thy God shall bless thee in all thy works, and in all that thou puttest thine hand unto. ^11For the poor shall never cease out of the land: therefore I command thee, saying, Thou shalt open thine hand wide unto thy brother, to thy poor, and to thy needy, in thy land.

^12And if thy brother, an Hebrew man, or an Hebrew woman, be sold unto thee, and serve thee six years; then in the seventh year thou shalt let him go free from thee. ^13And when thou sendest him out free from thee, thou shalt not let him go away empty: ^14thou shalt furnish him liberally out of thy flock, and out of thy floor, and out of thy winepress: of that wherewith the Lord thy God hath blessed thee thou shalt give unto him. ^15And thou shalt remember that thou wast a bondman in the land of Egypt, and the Lord thy God redeemed thee: therefore I command thee this thing to day. ^16And it shall be, if he say unto thee, I will not go away from thee; because he loveth thee and thine house, because he is well with thee; ^17then thou shalt take an aul, and thrust it through his ear unto the door, and he shall be thy servant for ever. And also unto thy maidservant thou shalt do likewise. ^18It shall not seem hard unto thee, when thou sendest him away free from thee; for he hath been worth a double hired servant to thee, in serving thee six years: and the Lord thy God shall bless thee in all that thou doest.

^19All the firstling males that come of thy herd and of thy flock thou shalt sanctify unto the Lord thy God: thou shalt do no work with the firstling of thy bullock, nor shear the firstling of thy sheep. ^20Thou shalt eat it before the Lord thy God year by year in the place which the Lord shall choose, thou and thy household. ^21And if there be any blemish therein, as if it be lame, or blind, or have any ill blemish, thou shalt not sacrifice it unto the Lord thy God. ^22Thou shalt eat it within thy gates: the unclean and the clean person shall eat it alike, as the roebuck, and as the hart. ^23Only thou shalt not eat the blood thereof; thou shalt pour it upon the ground as water.

XVI

^1Observe the month of Abib, and keep the passover unto the Lord thy God: for in the month of Abib the Lord thy God brought thee forth out of Egypt by night. ^2Thou shalt therefore sacrifice the passover unto the Lord thy God, of the flock and the herd, in the place which the Lord shall choose to place his name there. ^3Thou shalt eat no leavened bread with it; seven days shalt thou eat unleavened bread therewith, even the bread of affliction; for thou camest forth out of the land of Egypt in haste: that thou mayest remember the day when thou camest forth out of the land of Egypt all the days of thy life. ^4And there shall be no leavened bread seen with thee in all thy coast seven days; neither shall there any thing of the flesh, which thou sacrificedst the first day at even, remain all night until the morning. ^5Thou mayest not sacrifice the passover within any of thy gates, which the Lord thy God giveth thee: ^6but at the place which the Lord thy God shall choose to place his name in, there thou shalt sacrifice the passover at even, at the going down of the sun, at the season that thou camest forth out of Egypt. ^7And thou shalt roast and eat it in the place which the Lord thy God shall choose: and thou shalt turn in the morning, and go unto thy tents. ^8Six days thou shalt eat unleavened bread: and on the seventh day shall be a solemn assembly to the Lord thy God: thou shalt do no work therein.

^9Seven weeks shalt thou number unto thee: begin to number the seven weeks from such time as thou beginnest to put the sickle to the corn. ^10And thou shalt keep the feast of weeks unto the Lord thy God with a tribute of a freewill offering of thine hand, which thou shalt give unto the Lord thy God, according as the Lord thy God hath blessed thee: ^11and thou shalt rejoice before the Lord thy God, thou, and thy son, and thy daughter, and thy manservant, and thy maidservant, and the Levite that is within thy gates, and the stranger, and the fatherless, and the widow, that are among you, in the place which the Lord thy God hath chosen to place his name there. ^12And thou shalt remember that thou wast a bondman in Egypt: and thou shalt observe and do these statutes.

^13Thou shalt observe the feast of tabernacles seven days, after that thou hast gathered in thy corn and thy wine: ^14and thou shalt rejoice in thy feast, thou, and thy son, and thy daughter, and thy manservant, and thy maidservant, and the Levite, the stranger, and the fatherless, and the widow, that are within thy gates. ^15Seven days shalt thou keep a solemn feast unto the Lord thy God in the place which the Lord shall choose: because the Lord thy God shall bless thee in all thine increase, and in all the works of thine hands, therefore thou shalt surely rejoice. ^16Three times in a year shall all thy males appear before the Lord thy God in the place which he shall choose; in the feast of unleavened bread, and in the feast of weeks, and in the feast of tabernacles: and they shall not appear before the Lord empty: ^17every man shall give as he is able, according to the blessing of the Lord thy God which he hath given thee.

^18Judges and officers shalt thou make thee in all thy gates, which the Lord thy God giveth thee, throughout thy tribes: and they shall judge the people with just judgment. ^19Thou shalt not wrest judgment; thou shalt not respect persons, neither take a gift: for a gift doth blind the eyes of the wise, and pervert the words of the righteous. ^20That which is altogether just shalt thou follow, that thou mayest live, and inherit the land which the Lord thy God giveth thee.

^21Thou shalt not plant thee a grove of any trees near unto the altar of the Lord thy God, which thou shalt make thee. ^22Neither shalt thou set thee up any image; which the Lord thy God hateth.

XVII

^1Thou shalt not sacrifice unto the Lord thy God any bullock, or sheep, wherein is blemish, or any evilfavouredness: for that is an abomination unto the Lord thy God.

^2If there be found among you, within any of thy gates which the Lord thy God giveth thee, man or woman, that hath wrought wickedness in the sight of the Lord thy God, in transgressing his covenant, ^3and hath gone and served other gods, and worshipped them, either the sun, or moon, or any of the host of heaven, which I have not commanded; ^4and it be told thee, and thou hast heard of it, and enquired diligently, and, behold, it be true, and the thing certain, that such abomination is wrought in Israel: ^5then shalt thou bring forth that man or that woman, which have committed that wicked thing, unto thy gates, even that man or that woman, and shalt stone them with stones, till they die. ^6At the mouth of two witnesses, or three witnesses, shall he that is worthy of death be put to death; but at the mouth of one witness he shall not be put to death. ^7The hands of the witnesses shall be first upon him to put him to death, and afterward the hands of all the people. So thou shalt put the evil away from among you.

^8If there arise a matter too hard for thee in judgment, between blood and blood, between plea and plea, and between stroke and stroke, being matters of controversy within thy gates: then shalt thou arise, and get thee up into the place which the Lord thy God shall choose; ^9and thou shalt come unto the priests the Levites, and unto the judge that shall be in those days, and enquire; and they shall shew thee the sentence of judgment: ^10and thou shalt do according to the sentence, which they of that place which the Lord shall choose shall shew thee; and thou shalt observe to do according to all that they inform thee: ^11according to the sentence of the law which they shall teach thee, and according to the judgment which they shall tell thee, thou shalt do: thou shalt not decline from the sentence which they shall shew thee, to the right hand, nor to the left. ^12And the man that will do presumptuously, and will not hearken unto the priest that standeth to minister there before the Lord thy God, or unto the judge, even that man shall die: and thou shalt put away the evil from Israel. ^13And all the people shall hear, and fear, and do no more presumptuously.

^14When thou art come unto the land which the Lord thy God giveth thee, and shalt possess it, and shalt dwell therein, and shalt say, I will set a king over me, like as all the nations that are about me; ^15thou shalt in any wise set him king over thee, whom the Lord thy God shall choose: one from among thy brethren shalt thou set king over thee: thou mayest not set a stranger over thee, which is not thy brother. ^16But he shall not multiply horses to himself, nor cause the people to return to Egypt, to the end that he should multiply horses: forasmuch as the Lord hath said unto you, Ye shall henceforth return no more that way. ^17Neither shall he multiply wives to himself, that his heart turn not away: neither shall he greatly multiply to himself silver and gold.

^18And it shall be, when he sitteth upon the throne of his kingdom, that he shall write him a copy of this law in a book out of that which is before the priests the Levites: ^19and it shall be with him, and he shall read therein all the days of his life: that he may learn to fear the Lord his God, to keep all the words of this law and these statutes, to do them: ^20that his heart be not lifted up above his brethren, and that he turn not aside from the commandment, to the right hand, or to the left: to the end that he may prolong his days in his kingdom, he, and his children, in the midst of Israel.

XVIII

^1The priests the Levites, and all the tribe of Levi, shall have no part nor inheritance with Israel: they shall eat the offerings of the Lord made by fire, and his inheritance. ^2Therefore shall they have no inheritance among their brethren: the Lord is their inheritance, as he hath said unto them. ^3And this shall be the priest’s due from the people, from them that offer a sacrifice, whether it be ox or sheep; and they shall give unto the priest the shoulder, and the two cheeks, and the maw. ^4The firstfruit also of thy corn, of thy wine, and of thine oil, and the first of the fleece of thy sheep, shalt thou give him. ^5For the Lord thy God hath chosen him out of all thy tribes, to stand to minister in the name of the Lord, him and his sons for ever.

^6And if a Levite come from any of thy gates out of all Israel, where he sojourned, and come with all the desire of his mind unto the place which the Lord shall choose; ^7then he shall minister in the name of the Lord his God, as all his brethren the Levites do, which stand there before the Lord. ^8They shall have like portions to eat, beside that which cometh of the sale of his patrimony.

^9When thou art come into the land which the Lord thy God giveth thee, thou shalt not learn to do after the abominations of those nations. ^10There shall not be found among you any one that maketh his son or his daughter to pass through the fire, or that useth divination, or an observer of times, or an enchanter, or a witch. ^11Or a charmer, or a consulter with familiar spirits, or a wizard, or a necromancer. ^12For all that do these things are an abomination unto the Lord: and because of these abominations the Lord thy God doth drive them out from before thee. ^13Thou shalt be perfect with the Lord thy God. ^14For these nations, which thou shalt possess, hearkened unto observers of times, and unto diviners: but as for thee, the Lord thy God hath not suffered thee so to do.

^15The Lord thy God will raise up unto thee a Prophet from the midst of thee, of thy brethren, like unto me; unto him ye shall hearken; ^16according to all that thou desiredst of the Lord thy God in Horeb in the day of the assembly, saying, Let me not hear again the voice of the Lord my God, neither let me see this great fire any more, that I die not. ^17And the Lord said unto me, They have well spoken that which they have spoken. ^18I will raise them up a Prophet from among their brethren, like unto thee, and will put my words in his mouth; and he shall speak unto them all that I shall command him. ^19And it shall come to pass, that whosoever will not hearken unto my words which he shall speak in my name, I will require it of him.

^20But the prophet, which shall presume to speak a word in my name, which I have not commanded him to speak, or that shall speak in the name of other gods, even that prophet shall die. ^21And if thou say in thine heart, How shall we know the word which the Lord hath not spoken? ^22When a prophet speaketh in the name of the Lord, if the thing follow not, nor come to pass, that is the thing which the Lord hath not spoken, but the prophet hath spoken it presumptuously: thou shalt not be afraid of him.

XIX

^1When the Lord thy God hath cut off the nations, whose land the Lord thy God giveth thee, and thou succeedest them, and dwellest in their cities, and in their houses; ^2thou shalt separate three cities for thee in the midst of thy land, which the Lord thy God giveth thee to possess it. ^3Thou shalt prepare thee a way, and divide the coasts of thy land, which the Lord thy God giveth thee to inherit, into three parts, that every slayer may flee thither.

^4And this is the case of the slayer, which shall flee thither, that he may live: Whoso killeth his neighbour ignorantly, whom he hated not in time past; ^5as when a man goeth into the wood with his neighbour to hew wood, and his hand fetcheth a stroke with the axe to cut down the tree, and the head slippeth from the helve, and lighteth upon his neighbour, that he die; he shall flee unto one of those cities, and live: ^6lest the avenger of the blood pursue the slayer, while his heart is hot, and overtake him, because the way is long, and slay him; whereas he was not worthy of death, inasmuch as he hated him not in time past. ^7Wherefore I command thee, saying, Thou shalt separate three cities for thee. ^8And if the Lord thy God enlarge thy coast, as he hath sworn unto thy fathers, and give thee all the land which he promised to give unto thy fathers; ^9if thou shalt keep all these commandments to do them, which I command thee this day, to love the Lord thy God, and to walk ever in his ways; then shalt thou add three cities more for thee, beside these three: ^10that innocent blood be not shed in thy land, which the Lord thy God giveth thee for an inheritance, and so blood be upon thee.

^11But if any man hate his neighbour, and lie in wait for him, and rise up against him, and smite him mortally that he die, and fleeth into one of these cities: ^12then the elders of his city shall send and fetch him thence, and deliver him into the hand of the avenger of blood, that he may die. ^13Thine eye shall not pity him, but thou shalt put away the guilt of innocent blood from Israel, that it may go well with thee.

^14Thou shalt not remove thy neighbour’s landmark, which they of old time have set in thine inheritance, which thou shalt inherit in the land that the Lord thy God giveth thee to possess it.

^15One witness shall not rise up against a man for any iniquity, or for any sin, in any sin that he sinneth: at the mouth of two witnesses, or at the mouth of three witnesses, shall the matter be established. ^16If a false witness rise up against any man to testify against him that which is wrong; ^17then both the men, between whom the controversy is, shall stand before the Lord, before the priests and the judges, which shall be in those days; ^18and the judges shall make diligent inquisition: and, behold, if the witness be a false witness, and hath testified falsely against his brother; ^19then shall ye do unto him, as he had thought to have done unto his brother: so shalt thou put the evil away from among you. ^20And those which remain shall hear, and fear, and shall henceforth commit no more any such evil among you. ^21And thine eye shall not pity; but life shall go for life, eye for eye, tooth for tooth, hand for hand, foot for foot.

XX

^1When thou goest out to battle against thine enemies, and seest horses, and chariots, and a people more than thou, be not afraid of them: for the Lord thy God is with thee, which brought thee up out of the land of Egypt. ^2And it shall be, when ye are come nigh unto the battle, that the priest shall approach and speak unto the people, ^3and shall say unto them, Hear, O Israel, ye approach this day unto battle against your enemies: let not your hearts faint, fear not, and do not tremble, neither be ye terrified because of them; ^4for the Lord your God is he that goeth with you, to fight for you against your enemies, to save you. ^5And the officers shall speak unto the people, saying, What man is there that hath built a new house, and hath not dedicated it? let him go and return to his house, lest he die in the battle, and another man dedicate it. ^6And what man is he that hath planted a vineyard, and hath not yet eaten of it? let him also go and return unto his house, lest he die in the battle, and another man eat of it. ^7And what man is there that hath betrothed a wife, and hath not taken her? let him go and return unto his house, lest he die in the battle, and another man take her. ^8And the officers shall speak further unto the people, and they shall say, What man is there that is fearful and fainthearted? let him go and return unto his house, lest his brethren’s heart faint as well as his heart. ^9And it shall be, when the officers have made an end of speaking unto the people that they shall make captains of the armies to lead the people.

^10When thou comest nigh unto a city to fight against it, then proclaim peace unto it. ^11And it shall be, if it make thee answer of peace, and open unto thee, then it shall be, that all the people that is found therein shall be tributaries unto thee, and they shall serve thee. ^12And if it will make no peace with thee, but will make war against thee, then thou shalt besiege it: ^13and when the Lord thy God hath delivered it into thine hands, thou shalt smite every male thereof with the edge of the sword: ^14but the women, and the little ones, and the cattle, and all that is in the city, even all the spoil thereof, shalt thou take unto thyself; and thou shalt eat the spoil of thine enemies, which the Lord thy God hath given thee. ^15Thus shalt thou do unto all the cities which are very far off from thee, which are not of the cities of these nations. ^16But of the cities of these people, which the Lord thy God doth give thee for an inheritance, thou shalt save alive nothing that breatheth: ^17but thou shalt utterly destroy them; namely, the Hittites, and the Amorites, the Canaanites, and the Perizzites, the Hivites, and the Jebusites; as the Lord thy God hath commanded thee: ^18that they teach you not to do after all their abominations, which they have done unto their gods; so should ye sin against the Lord your God.

^19When thou shalt besiege a city a long time, in making war against it to take it, thou shalt not destroy the trees thereof by forcing an axe against them: for thou mayest eat of them, and thou shalt not cut them down (for the tree of the field is man’s life) to employ them in the siege: ^20only the trees which thou knowest that they be not trees for meat, thou shalt destroy and cut them down; and thou shalt build bulwarks against the city that maketh war with thee, until it be subdued.

XXI

^1If one be found slain in the land which the Lord thy God giveth thee to possess it, lying in the field, and it be not known who hath slain him: ^2then thy elders and thy judges shall come forth, and they shall measure unto the cities which are round about him that is slain: ^3and it shall be, that the city which is next unto the slain man, even the elders of that city shall take an heifer, which hath not been wrought with, and which hath not drawn in the yoke; ^4and the elders of that city shall bring down the heifer unto a rough valley, which is neither eared nor sown, and shall strike off the heifer’s neck there in the valley: ^5and the priests the sons of Levi shall come near; for them the Lord thy God hath chosen to minister unto him, and to bless in the name of the Lord; and by their word shall every controversy and every stroke be tried: ^6and all the elders of that city, that are next unto the slain man, shall wash their hands over the heifer that is beheaded in the valley: ^7and they shall answer and say, Our hands have not shed this blood, neither have our eyes seen it. ^8Be merciful, O Lord, unto thy people Israel, whom thou hast redeemed, and lay not innocent blood unto thy people of Israel’s charge. And the blood shall be forgiven them. ^9So shalt thou put away the guilt of innocent blood from among you, when thou shalt do that which is right in the sight of the Lord.

^10When thou goest forth to war against thine enemies, and the Lord thy God hath delivered them into thine hands, and thou hast taken them captive, ^11and seest among the captives a beautiful woman, and hast a desire unto her, that thou wouldest have her to thy wife; ^12then thou shalt bring her home to thine house, and she shall shave her head, and pare her nails; ^13and she shall put the raiment of her captivity from off her, and shall remain in thine house, and bewail her father and her mother a full month: and after that thou shalt go in unto her, and be her husband, and she shall be thy wife. ^14And it shall be, if thou have no delight in her, then thou shalt let her go whither she will; but thou shalt not sell her at all for money, thou shalt not make merchandise of her, because thou hast humbled her.

^15If a man have two wives, one beloved, and another hated, and they have born him children, both the beloved and the hated; and if the firstborn son be hers that was hated: ^16then it shall be, when he maketh his sons to inherit that which he hath, that he may not make the son of the beloved firstborn before the son of the hated, which is indeed the firstborn: ^17but he shall acknowledge the son of the hated for the firstborn, by giving him a double portion of all that he hath: for he is the beginning of his strength; the right of the firstborn is his.

^18If a man have a stubborn and rebellious son, which will not obey the voice of his father, or the voice of his mother, and that, when they have chastened him, will not hearken unto them: ^19then shall his father and his mother lay hold on him, and bring him out unto the elders of his city, and unto the gate of his place; ^20and they shall say unto the elders of his city, This our son is stubborn and rebellious, he will not obey our voice; he is a glutton, and a drunkard. ^21And all the men of his city shall stone him with stones, that he die: so shalt thou put evil away from among you; and all Israel shall hear, and fear.

^22And if a man have committed a sin worthy of death, and he be to be put to death, and thou hang him on a tree: ^23his body shall not remain all night upon the tree, but thou shalt in any wise bury him that day; (for he that is hanged is accursed of God;) that thy land be not defiled, which the Lord thy God giveth thee for an inheritance.

XXII

^1Thou shalt not see thy brother’s ox or his sheep go astray, and hide thyself from them: thou shalt in any case bring them again unto thy brother. ^2And if thy brother be not nigh unto thee, or if thou know him not, then thou shalt bring it unto thine own house, and it shall be with thee until thy brother seek after it, and thou shalt restore it to him again. ^3In like manner shalt thou do with his ass; and so shalt thou do with his raiment; and with all lost thing of thy brother’s, which he hath lost, and thou hast found, shalt thou do likewise: thou mayest not hide thyself. ^4Thou shalt not see thy brother’s ass or his ox fall down by the way, and hide thyself from them: thou shalt surely help him to lift them up again.

^5The woman shall not wear that which pertaineth unto a man, neither shall a man put on a woman’s garment: for all that do so are abomination unto the Lord thy God. ^6If a bird’s nest chance to be before thee in the way in any tree, or on the ground, whether they be young ones, or eggs, and the dam sitting upon the young, or upon the eggs, thou shalt not take the dam with the young: ^7but thou shalt in any wise let the dam go, and take the young to thee; that it may be well with thee, and that thou mayest prolong thy days.

^8When thou buildest a new house, then thou shalt make a battlement for thy roof, that thou bring not blood upon thine house, if any man fall from thence.

^9Thou shalt not sow thy vineyard with divers seeds: lest the fruit of thy seed which thou hast sown, and the fruit of thy vineyard, be defiled. ^10Thou shalt not plow with an ox and an ass together. ^11Thou shalt not wear a garment of divers sorts, as of woollen and linen together.

^12Thou shalt make thee fringes upon the four quarters of thy vesture, wherewith thou coverest thyself.

^13If any man take a wife, and go in unto her, and hate her, ^14and give occasions of speech against her, and bring up an evil name upon her, and say, I took this woman, and when I came to her, I found her not a maid: ^15then shall the father of the damsel, and her mother, take and bring forth the tokens of the damsel’s virginity unto the elders of the city in the gate: ^16and the damsel’s father shall say unto the elders, I gave my daughter unto this man to wife, and he hateth her; ^17and, lo, he hath given occasions of speech against her, saying, I found not thy daughter a maid; and yet these are the tokens of my daughter’s virginity. And they shall spread the cloth before the elders of the city. ^18And the elders of that city shall take that man and chastise him; ^19and they shall amerce him in an hundred shekels of silver, and give them unto the father of the damsel, because he hath brought up an evil name upon a virgin of Israel: and she shall be his wife; he may not put her away all his days. ^20But if this thing be true, and the tokens of virginity be not found for the damsel: ^21then they shall bring out the damsel to the door of her father’s house, and the men of her city shall stone her with stones that she die: because she hath wrought folly in Israel, to play the whore in her father’s house: so shalt thou put evil away from among you.

^22If a man be found lying with a woman married to an husband, then they shall both of them die, both the man that lay with the woman, and the woman: so shalt thou put away evil from Israel.

^23If a damsel that is a virgin be betrothed unto an husband, and a man find her in the city, and lie with her; ^24then ye shall bring them both out unto the gate of that city, and ye shall stone them with stones that they die; the damsel, because she cried not, being in the city; and the man, because he hath humbled his neighbour’s wife: so thou shalt put away evil from among you.

^25But if a man find a betrothed damsel in the field, and the man force her, and lie with her: then the man only that lay with her shall die. ^26But unto the damsel thou shalt do nothing; there is in the damsel no sin worthy of death: for as when a man riseth against his neighbour, and slayeth him, even so is this matter: ^27for he found her in the field, and the betrothed damsel cried, and there was none to save her.

^28If a man find a damsel that is a virgin, which is not betrothed, and lay hold on her, and lie with her, and they be found; ^29then the man that lay with her shall give unto the damsel’s father fifty shekels of silver, and she shall be his wife; because he hath humbled her, he may not put her away all his days.

^30A man shall not take his father’s wife, nor discover his father’s skirt.

XXIII

^1He that is wounded in the stones, or hath his privy member cut off, shall not enter into the congregation of the Lord.

^2A bastard shall not enter into the congregation of the Lord; even to his tenth generation shall he not enter into the congregation of the Lord.

^3An Ammonite or Moabite shall not enter into the congregation of the Lord; even to their tenth generation shall they not enter into the congregation of the Lord for ever: ^4because they met you not with bread and with water in the way, when ye came forth out of Egypt; and because they hired against thee Balaam the son of Beor of Pethor of Mesopotamia, to curse thee. ^5Nevertheless the Lord thy God would not hearken unto Balaam; but the Lord thy God turned the curse into a blessing unto thee, because the Lord thy God loved thee. ^6Thou shalt not seek their peace nor their prosperity all thy days for ever.

^7Thou shalt not abhor an Edomite; for he is thy brother: thou shalt not abhor an Egyptian; because thou wast a stranger in his land. ^8The children that are begotten of them shall enter into the congregation of the Lord in their third generation.

^9When the host goeth forth against thine enemies, then keep thee from every wicked thing. ^10If there be among you any man, that is not clean by reason of uncleanness that chanceth him by night, then shall he go abroad out of the camp, he shall not come within the camp: ^11but it shall be, when evening cometh on, he shall wash himself with water: and when the sun is down, he shall come into the camp again. ^12Thou shalt have a place also without the camp, whither thou shalt go forth abroad: ^13and thou shalt have a paddle upon thy weapon; and it shall be, when thou wilt ease thyself abroad, thou shalt dig therewith, and shalt turn back and cover that which cometh from thee: ^14for the Lord thy God walketh in the midst of thy camp, to deliver thee, and to give up thine enemies before thee; therefore shall thy camp be holy: that he see no unclean thing in thee, and turn away from thee.

^15Thou shalt not deliver unto his master the servant which is escaped from his master unto thee: ^16he shall dwell with thee, even among you, in that place which he shall choose in one of thy gates, where it liketh him best: thou shalt not oppress him.

^17There shall be no whore of the daughters of Israel, nor a sodomite of the sons of Israel. ^18Thou shalt not bring the hire of a whore, or the price of a dog, into the house of the Lord thy God for any vow: for even both these are abomination unto the Lord thy God.

^19Thou shalt not lend upon usury to thy brother; usury of money, usury of victuals, usury of any thing that is lent upon usury: ^20unto a stranger thou mayest lend upon usury; but unto thy brother thou shalt not lend upon usury: that the Lord thy God may bless thee in all that thou settest thine hand to in the land whither thou goest to possess it.

^21When thou shalt vow a vow unto the Lord thy God, thou shalt not slack to pay it: for the Lord thy God will surely require it of thee; and it would be sin in thee. ^22But if thou shalt forbear to vow, it shall be no sin in thee. ^23That which is gone out of thy lips thou shalt keep and perform; even a freewill offering, according as thou hast vowed unto the Lord thy God, which thou hast promised with thy mouth.

^24When thou comest into thy neighbour’s vineyard, then thou mayest eat grapes thy fill at thine own pleasure; but thou shalt not put any in thy vessel. ^25When thou comest into the standing corn of thy neighbour, then thou mayest pluck the ears with thine hand; but thou shalt not move a sickle unto thy neighbour’s standing corn.

XXIV

^1When a man hath taken a wife, and married her, and it come to pass that she find no favour in his eyes, because he hath found some uncleanness in her: then let him write her a bill of divorcement, and give it in her hand, and send her out of his house. ^2And when she is departed out of his house, she may go and be another man’s wife. ^3And if the latter husband hate her, and write her a bill of divorcement, and giveth it in her hand, and sendeth her out of his house; or if the latter husband die, which took her to be his wife; ^4her former husband, which sent her away, may not take her again to be his wife, after that she is defiled; for that is abomination before the Lord: and thou shalt not cause the land to sin, which the Lord thy God giveth thee for an inheritance.

^5When a man hath taken a new wife, he shall not go out to war, neither shall he be charged with any business: but he shall be free at home one year, and shall cheer up his wife which he hath taken.

^6No man shall take the nether or the upper millstone to pledge: for he taketh a man’s life to pledge.

^7If a man be found stealing any of his brethren of the children of Israel, and maketh merchandise of him, or selleth him; then that thief shall die; and thou shalt put evil away from among you.

^8Take heed in the plague of leprosy, that thou observe diligently, and do according to all that the priests the Levites shall teach you: as I commanded them, so ye shall observe to do. ^9Remember what the Lord thy God did unto Miriam by the way, after that ye were come forth out of Egypt.

^10When thou dost lend thy brother any thing, thou shalt not go into his house to fetch his pledge. ^11Thou shalt stand abroad, and the man to whom thou dost lend shall bring out the pledge abroad unto thee. ^12And if the man be poor, thou shalt not sleep with his pledge: ^13in any case thou shalt deliver him the pledge again when the sun goeth down, that he may sleep in his own raiment, and bless thee: and it shall be righteousness unto thee before the Lord thy God.

^14Thou shalt not oppress an hired servant that is poor and needy, whether he be of thy brethren, or of thy strangers that are in thy land within thy gates: ^15at his day thou shalt give him his hire, neither shall the sun go down upon it; for he is poor, and setteth his heart upon it: lest he cry against thee unto the Lord, and it be sin unto thee.

^16The fathers shall not be put to death for the children, neither shall the children be put to death for the fathers: every man shall be put to death for his own sin.

^17Thou shalt not pervert the judgment of the stranger, nor of the fatherless; nor take a widow’s raiment to pledge: ^18but thou shalt remember that thou wast a bondman in Egypt, and the Lord thy God redeemed thee thence: therefore I command thee to do this thing.

^19When thou cuttest down thine harvest in thy field, and hast forgot a sheaf in the field, thou shalt not go again to fetch it: it shall be for the stranger, for the fatherless, and for the widow: that the Lord thy God may bless thee in all the work of thine hands. ^20When thou beatest thine olive tree, thou shalt not go over the boughs again: it shall be for the stranger, for the fatherless, and for the widow. ^21When thou gatherest the grapes of thy vineyard, thou shalt not glean it afterward: it shall be for the stranger, for the fatherless, and for the widow. ^22And thou shalt remember that thou wast a bondman in the land of Egypt: therefore I command thee to do this thing.

XXV

^1If there be a controversy between men, and they come unto judgment, that the judges may judge them; then they shall justify the righteous, and condemn the wicked. ^2And it shall be, if the wicked man be worthy to be beaten, that the judge shall cause him to lie down, and to be beaten before his face, according to his fault, by a certain number. ^3Forty stripes he may give him, and not exceed: lest, if he should exceed, and beat him above these with many stripes, then thy brother should seem vile unto thee.

^4Thou shalt not muzzle the ox when he treadeth out the corn.

^5If brethren dwell together, and one of them die, and have no child, the wife of the dead shall not marry without unto a stranger: her husband’s brother shall go in unto her, and take her to him to wife, and perform the duty of an husband’s brother unto her. ^6And it shall be, that the firstborn which she beareth shall succeed in the name of his brother which is dead, that his name be not put out of Israel. ^7And if the man like not to take his brother’s wife, then let his brother’s wife go up to the gate unto the elders, and say, My husband’s brother refuseth to raise up unto his brother a name in Israel, he will not perform the duty of my husband’s brother. ^8Then the elders of his city shall call him, and speak unto him: and if he stand to it, and say, I like not to take her; ^9then shall his brother’s wife come unto him in the presence of the elders, and loose his shoe from off his foot, and spit in his face, and shall answer and say, So shall it be done unto that man that will not build up his brother’s house. ^10And his name shall be called in Israel, The house of him that hath his shoe loosed.

^11When men strive together one with another, and the wife of the one draweth near for to deliver her husband out of the hand of him that smiteth him, and putteth forth her hand, and taketh him by the secrets: ^12then thou shalt cut off her hand, thine eye shall not pity her.

^13Thou shalt not have in thy bag divers weights, a great and a small. ^14Thou shalt not have in thine house divers measures, a great and a small. ^15But thou shalt have a perfect and just weight, a perfect and just measure shalt thou have: that thy days may be lengthened in the land which the Lord thy God giveth thee. ^16For all that do such things, and all that do unrighteously, are an abomination unto the Lord thy God.

^17Remember what Amalek did unto thee by the way, when ye were come forth out of Egypt; ^18how he met thee by the way, and smote the hindmost of thee, even all that were feeble behind thee, when thou wast faint and weary; and he feared not God. ^19Therefore it shall be, when the Lord thy God hath given thee rest from all thine enemies round about, in the land which the Lord thy God giveth thee for an inheritance to possess it, that thou shalt blot out the remembrance of Amalek from under heaven; thou shalt not forget it.

XXVI

^1And it shall be, when thou art come in unto the land which the Lord thy God giveth thee for an inheritance, and possessest it, and dwellest therein; ^2that thou shalt take of the first of all the fruit of the earth, which thou shalt bring of thy land that the Lord thy God giveth thee, and shalt put it in a basket, and shalt go unto the place which the Lord thy God shall choose to place his name there. ^3And thou shalt go unto the priest that shall be in those days, and say unto him, I profess this day unto the Lord thy God, that I am come unto the country which the Lord sware unto our fathers for to give us. ^4And the priest shall take the basket out of thine hand, and set it down before the altar of the Lord thy God. ^5And thou shalt speak and say before the Lord thy God, A Syrian ready to perish was my father, and he went down into Egypt, and sojourned there with a few, and became there a nation, great, mighty, and populous: ^6and the Egyptians evil entreated us, and afflicted us, and laid upon us hard bondage: ^7and when we cried unto the Lord God of our fathers, the Lord heard our voice, and looked on our affliction, and our labour, and our oppression: ^8and the Lord brought us forth out of Egypt with a mighty hand, and with an outstretched arm, and with great terribleness, and with signs, and with wonders: ^9and he hath brought us into this place, and hath given us this land, even a land that floweth with milk and honey. ^10And now, behold, I have brought the firstfruits of the land, which thou, O Lord, hast given me. And thou shalt set it before the Lord thy God, and worship before the Lord thy God: ^11and thou shalt rejoice in every good thing which the Lord thy God hath given unto thee, and unto thine house, thou, and the Levite, and the stranger that is among you.

^12When thou hast made an end of tithing all the tithes of thine increase the third year, which is the year of tithing, and hast given it unto the Levite, the stranger, the fatherless, and the widow, that they may eat within thy gates, and be filled; ^13then thou shalt say before the Lord thy God, I have brought away the hallowed things out of mine house, and also have given them unto the Levite, and unto the stranger, to the fatherless, and to the widow, according to all thy commandments which thou hast commanded me: I have not transgressed thy commandments, neither have I forgotten them. ^14I have not eaten thereof in my mourning, neither have I taken away ought thereof for any unclean use, nor given ought thereof for the dead: but I have hearkened to the voice of the Lord my God, and have done according to all that thou hast commanded me. ^15Look down from thy holy habitation, from heaven, and bless thy people Israel, and the land which thou hast given us, as thou swarest unto our fathers, a land that floweth with milk and honey.

^16This day the Lord thy God hath commanded thee to do these statutes and judgments: thou shalt therefore keep and do them with all thine heart, and with all thy soul. ^17Thou hast avouched the Lord this day to be thy God, and to walk in his ways, and to keep his statutes, and his commandments, and his judgments, and to hearken unto his voice: ^18and the Lord hath avouched thee this day to be his peculiar people, as he hath promised thee, and that thou shouldest keep all his commandments; ^19and to make thee high above all nations which he hath made, in praise, and in name, and in honour; and that thou mayest be an holy people unto the Lord thy God, as he hath spoken.

XXVII

^1And Moses with the elders of Israel commanded the people, saying, Keep all the commandments which I command you this day. ^2And it shall be on the day when ye shall pass over Jordan unto the land which the Lord thy God giveth thee, that thou shalt set thee up great stones, and plaister them with plaister: ^3and thou shalt write upon them all the words of this law, when thou art passed over, that thou mayest go in unto the land which the Lord thy God giveth thee, a land that floweth with milk and honey; as the Lord God of thy fathers hath promised thee. ^4Therefore it shall be when ye be gone over Jordan, that ye shall set up these stones, which I command you this day, in mount Ebal, and thou shalt plaister them with plaister. ^5And there shalt thou build an altar unto the Lord thy God, an altar of stones: thou shalt not lift up any iron tool upon them. ^6Thou shalt build the altar of the Lord thy God of whole stones: and thou shalt offer burnt offerings thereon unto the Lord thy God: ^7and thou shalt offer peace offerings, and shalt eat there, and rejoice before the Lord thy God. ^8And thou shalt write upon the stones all the words of this law very plainly.

^9And Moses and the priests the Levites spake unto all Israel, saying, Take heed, and hearken, O Israel; this day thou art become the people of the Lord thy God. ^10Thou shalt therefore obey the voice of the Lord thy God, and do his commandments and his statutes, which I command thee this day.

^11And Moses charged the people the same day, saying, ^12These shall stand upon mount Gerizim to bless the people, when ye are come over Jordan; Simeon, and Levi, and Judah, and Issachar, and Joseph, and Benjamin: ^13and these shall stand upon mount Ebal to curse; Reuben, Gad, and Asher, and Zebulun, Dan, and Naphtali.

^14And the Levites shall speak, and say unto all the men of Israel with a loud voice,

^15Cursed be the man that maketh any graven or molten image, an abomination unto the Lord, the work of the hands of the craftsman, and putteth it in a secret place. And all the people shall answer and say, Amen.

^16Cursed be he that setteth light by his father or his mother. And all the people shall say, Amen.

^17Cursed be he that removeth his neighbour’s landmark. And all the people shall say, Amen.

^18Cursed be he that maketh the blind to wander out of the way. And all the people shall say, Amen.

^19Cursed be he that perverteth the judgment of the stranger, fatherless, and widow. And all the people shall say, Amen.

^20Cursed be he that lieth with his father’s wife; because he uncovereth his father’s skirt. And all the people shall say, Amen.

^21Cursed be he that lieth with any manner of beast. And all the people shall say, Amen.

^22Cursed be he that lieth with his sister, the daughter of his father, or the daughter of his mother. And all the people shall say, Amen.

^23Cursed be he that lieth with his mother in law. And all the people shall say, Amen.

^24Cursed be he that smiteth his neighbour secretly. And all the people shall say, Amen.

^25Cursed be he that taketh reward to slay an innocent person. And all the people shall say, Amen.

^26Cursed be he that confirmeth not all the words of this law to do them. And all the people shall say, Amen.

XXVIII

^1And it shall come to pass, if thou shalt hearken diligently unto the voice of the Lord thy God, to observe and to do all his commandments which I command thee this day, that the Lord thy God will set thee on high above all nations of the earth: ^2and all these blessings shall come on thee, and overtake thee, if thou shalt hearken unto the voice of the Lord thy God. ^3Blessed shalt thou be in the city, and blessed shalt thou be in the field. ^4Blessed shall be the fruit of thy body, and the fruit of thy ground, and the fruit of thy cattle, the increase of thy kine, and the flocks of thy sheep. ^5Blessed shall be thy basket and thy store. ^6Blessed shalt thou be when thou comest in, and blessed shalt thou be when thou goest out.

^7The Lord shall cause thine enemies that rise up against thee to be smitten before thy face: they shall come out against thee one way, and flee before thee seven ways. ^8The Lord shall command the blessing upon thee in thy storehouses, and in all that thou settest thine hand unto; and he shall bless thee in the land which the Lord thy God giveth thee. ^9The Lord shall establish thee an holy people unto himself, as he hath sworn unto thee, if thou shalt keep the commandments of the Lord thy God, and walk in his ways. ^10And all people of the earth shall see that thou art called by the name of the Lord; and they shall be afraid of thee. ^11And the Lord shall make thee plenteous in goods, in the fruit of thy body, and in the fruit of thy cattle, and in the fruit of thy ground, in the land which the Lord sware unto thy fathers to give thee. ^12The Lord shall open unto thee his good treasure, the heaven to give the rain unto thy land in his season, and to bless all the work of thine hand: and thou shalt lend unto many nations, and thou shalt not borrow. ^13And the Lord shall make thee the head, and not the tail; and thou shalt be above only, and thou shalt not be beneath; if that thou hearken unto the commandments of the Lord thy God, which I command thee this day, to observe and to do them: ^14and thou shalt not go aside from any of the words which I command thee this day, to the right hand, or to the left, to go after other gods to serve them.

^15But it shall come to pass, if thou wilt not hearken unto the voice of the Lord thy God, to observe to do all his commandments and his statutes which I command thee this day; that all these curses shall come upon thee, and overtake thee: ^16cursed shalt thou be in the city, and cursed shalt thou be in the field. ^17Cursed shall be thy basket and thy store. ^18Cursed shall be the fruit of thy body, and the fruit of thy land, the increase of thy kine, and the flocks of thy sheep. ^19Cursed shalt thou be when thou comest in, and cursed shalt thou be when thou goest out.

^20The Lord shall send upon thee cursing, vexation, and rebuke, in all that thou settest thine hand unto for to do, until thou be destroyed, and until thou perish quickly; because of the wickedness of thy doings, whereby thou hast forsaken me. ^21The Lord shall make the pestilence cleave unto thee, until he have consumed thee from off the land, whither thou goest to possess it. ^22The Lord shall smite thee with a consumption, and with a fever, and with an inflammation, and with an extreme burning, and with the sword, and with blasting, and with mildew; and they shall pursue thee until thou perish. ^23And thy heaven that is over thy head shall be brass, and the earth that is under thee shall be iron. ^24The Lord shall make the rain of thy land powder and dust: from heaven shall it come down upon thee, until thou be destroyed.

^25The Lord shall cause thee to be smitten before thine enemies: thou shalt go out one way against them, and flee seven ways before them: and shalt be removed into all the kingdoms of the earth. ^26And thy carcase shall be meat unto all fowls of the air, and unto the beasts of the earth, and no man shall fray them away. ^27The Lord will smite thee with the botch of Egypt, and with the emerods, and with the scab, and with the itch, whereof thou canst not be healed. ^28The Lord shall smite thee with madness, and blindness, and astonishment of heart: ^29and thou shalt grope at noonday, as the blind gropeth in darkness, and thou shalt not prosper in thy ways: and thou shalt be only oppressed and spoiled evermore, and no man shall save thee. ^30Thou shalt betroth a wife, and another man shall lie with her: thou shalt build an house, and thou shalt not dwell therein: thou shalt plant a vineyard, and shalt not gather the grapes thereof. ^31Thine ox shall be slain before thine eyes, and thou shalt not eat thereof: thine ass shall be violently taken away from before thy face, and shall not be restored to thee: thy sheep shall be given unto thine enemies, and thou shalt have none to rescue them. ^32Thy sons and thy daughters shall be given unto another people, and thine eyes shall look, and fail with longing for them all the day long; and there shall be no might in thine hand. ^33The fruit of thy land, and all thy labours, shall a nation which thou knowest not eat up; and thou shalt be only oppressed and crushed alway: ^34so that thou shalt be mad for the sight of thine eyes which thou shalt see. ^35The Lord shall smite thee in the knees, and in the legs, with a sore botch that cannot be healed, from the sole of thy foot unto the top of thy head.

^36The Lord shall bring thee, and thy king which thou shalt set over thee, unto a nation which neither thou nor thy fathers have known; and there shalt thou serve other gods, wood and stone. ^37And thou shalt become an astonishment, a proverb, and a byword, among all nations whither the Lord shall lead thee. ^38Thou shalt carry much seed out into the field, and shalt gather but little in; for the locust shall consume it. ^39Thou shalt plant vineyards, and dress them, but shalt neither drink of the wine, nor gather the grapes; for the worms shall eat them. ^40Thou shalt have olive trees throughout all thy coasts, but thou shalt not anoint thyself with the oil; for thine olive shall cast his fruit. ^41Thou shalt beget sons and daughters, but thou shalt not enjoy them; for they shall go into captivity. ^42All thy trees and fruit of thy land shall the locust consume. ^43The stranger that is within thee shall get up above thee very high; and thou shalt come down very low. ^44He shall lend to thee, and thou shalt not lend to him: he shall be the head, and thou shalt be the tail. ^45Moreover all these curses shall come upon thee, and shall pursue thee, and overtake thee, till thou be destroyed; because thou hearkenedst not unto the voice of the Lord thy God, to keep his commandments and his statutes which he commanded thee: ^46and they shall be upon thee for a sign and for a wonder, and upon thy seed for ever.

^47Because thou servedst not the Lord thy God with joyfulness, and with gladness of heart, for the abundance of all things; ^48therefore shalt thou serve thine enemies which the Lord shall send against thee, in hunger, and in thirst, and in nakedness, and in want of all things: and he shall put a yoke of iron upon thy neck, until he have destroyed thee. ^49The Lord shall bring a nation against thee from far, from the end of the earth, as swift as the eagle flieth; a nation whose tongue thou shalt not understand; ^50a nation of fierce countenance, which shall not regard the person of the old, nor shew favour to the young: ^51and he shall eat the fruit of thy cattle, and the fruit of thy land, until thou be destroyed: which also shall not leave thee either corn, wine, or oil, or the increase of thy kine, or flocks of thy sheep, until he have destroyed thee. ^52And he shall besiege thee in all thy gates, until thy high and fenced walls come down, wherein thou trustedst, throughout all thy land: and he shall besiege thee in all thy gates throughout all thy land, which the Lord thy God hath given thee. ^53And thou shalt eat the fruit of thine own body, the flesh of thy sons and of thy daughters, which the Lord thy God hath given thee, in the siege, and in the straitness, wherewith thine enemies shall distress thee: ^54so that the man that is tender among you, and very delicate, his eye shall be evil toward his brother, and toward the wife of his bosom, and toward the remnant of his children which he shall leave: ^55so that he will not give to any of them of the flesh of his children whom he shall eat: because he hath nothing left him in the siege, and in the straitness, wherewith thine enemies shall distress thee in all thy gates. ^56The tender and delicate woman among you, which would not adventure to set the sole of her foot upon the ground for delicateness and tenderness, her eye shall be evil toward the husband of her bosom, and toward her son, and toward her daughter, ^57and toward her young one that cometh out from between her feet, and toward her children which she shall bear: for she shall eat them for want of all things secretly in the siege and straitness, wherewith thine enemy shall distress thee in thy gates.

^58If thou wilt not observe to do all the words of this law that are written in this book, that thou mayest fear this glorious and fearful name, The Lord Thy God; ^59then the Lord will make thy plagues wonderful, and the plagues of thy seed, even great plagues, and of long continuance, and sore sicknesses, and of long continuance. ^60Moreover he will bring upon thee all the diseases of Egypt, which thou wast afraid of; and they shall cleave unto thee. ^61Also every sickness, and every plague, which is not written in the book of this law, them will the Lord bring upon thee, until thou be destroyed. ^62And ye shall be left few in number, whereas ye were as the stars of heaven for multitude; because thou wouldest not obey the voice of the Lord thy God. ^63And it shall come to pass, that as the Lord rejoiced over you to do you good, and to multiply you; so the Lord will rejoice over you to destroy you, and to bring you to nought; and ye shall be plucked from off the land whither thou goest to possess it. ^64And the Lord shall scatter thee among all people, from the one end of the earth even unto the other; and there thou shalt serve other gods, which neither thou nor thy fathers have known, even wood and stone. ^65And among these nations shalt thou find no ease, neither shall the sole of thy foot have rest: but the Lord shall give thee there a trembling heart, and failing of eyes, and sorrow of mind: ^66and thy life shall hang in doubt before thee; and thou shalt fear day and night, and shalt have none assurance of thy life: ^67in the morning thou shalt say, Would God it were even! and at even thou shalt say, Would God it were morning! for the fear of thine heart wherewith thou shalt fear, and for the sight of thine eyes which thou shalt see. ^68And the Lord shall bring thee into Egypt again with ships, by the way whereof I spake unto thee, Thou shalt see it no more again: and there ye shall be sold unto your enemies for bondmen and bondwomen, and no man shall buy you.

XXIX

^1These are the words of the covenant, which the Lord commanded Moses to make with the children of Israel in the land of Moab, beside the covenant which he made with them in Horeb.

^2And Moses called unto all Israel, and said unto them, Ye have seen all that the Lord did before your eyes in the land of Egypt unto Pharaoh, and unto all his servants, and unto all his land; ^3the great temptations which thine eyes have seen, the signs, and those great miracles: ^4yet the Lord hath not given you an heart to perceive, and eyes to see, and ears to hear, unto this day. ^5And I have led you forty years in the wilderness: your clothes are not waxen old upon you, and thy shoe is not waxen old upon thy foot. ^6Ye have not eaten bread, neither have ye drunk wine or strong drink: that ye might know that I am the Lord your God. ^7And when ye came unto this place, Sihon the king of Heshbon, and Og the king of Bashan, came out against us unto battle, and we smote them: ^8and we took their land, and gave it for an inheritance unto the Reubenites, and to the Gadites, and to the half tribe of Manasseh. ^9Keep therefore the words of this covenant, and do them, that ye may prosper in all that ye do.

^10Ye stand this day all of you before the Lord your God; your captains of your tribes, your elders, and your officers, with all the men of Israel, ^11your little ones, your wives, and thy stranger that is in thy camp, from the hewer of thy wood unto the drawer of thy water: ^12that thou shouldest enter into covenant with the Lord thy God, and into his oath, which the Lord thy God maketh with thee this day: ^13that he may establish thee to day for a people unto himself, and that he may be unto thee a God, as he hath said unto thee, and as he hath sworn unto thy fathers, to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob.

^14Neither with you only do I make this covenant and this oath; ^15but with him that standeth here with us this day before the Lord our God, and also with him that is not here with us this day: ^16(for ye know how we have dwelt in the land of Egypt; and how we came through the nations which ye passed by; ^17and ye have seen their abominations, and their idols, wood and stone, silver and gold, which were among them:) ^18lest there should be among you man, or woman, or family, or tribe, whose heart turneth away this day from the Lord our God, to go and serve the gods of these nations; lest there should be among you a root that beareth gall and wormwood; ^19and it come to pass, when he heareth the words of this curse, that he bless himself in his heart, saying, I shall have peace, though I walk in the imagination of mine heart, to add drunkenness to thirst: ^20the Lord will not spare him, but then the anger of the Lord and his jealousy shall smoke against that man, and all the curses that are written in this book shall lie upon him, and the Lord shall blot out his name from under heaven. ^21And the Lord shall separate him unto evil out of all the tribes of Israel, according to all the curses of the covenant that are written in this book of the law: ^22so that the generation to come of your children that shall rise up after you, and the stranger that shall come from a far land, shall say, when they see the plagues of that land, and the sicknesses which the Lord hath laid upon it; ^23and that the whole land thereof is brimstone, and salt, and burning, that it is not sown, nor beareth, nor any grass groweth therein, like the overthrow of Sodom, and Gomorrah, Admah, and Zeboim, which the Lord overthrew in his anger, and in his wrath: ^24even all nations shall say, Wherefore hath the Lord done thus unto this land? what meaneth the heat of this great anger? ^25Then men shall say, Because they have forsaken the covenant of the Lord God of their fathers, which he made with them when he brought them forth out of the land of Egypt: ^26for they went and served other gods, and worshipped them, gods whom they knew not, and whom he had not given unto them: ^27and the anger of the Lord was kindled against this land, to bring upon it all the curses that are written in this book: ^28and the Lord rooted them out of their land in anger, and in wrath, and in great indignation, and cast them into another land, as it is this day. ^29The secret things belong unto the Lord our God: but those things which are revealed belong unto us and to our children for ever, that we may do all the words of this law.

XXX

^1And it shall come to pass, when all these things are come upon thee, the blessing and the curse, which I have set before thee, and thou shalt call them to mind among all the nations, whither the Lord thy God hath driven thee, ^2and shalt return unto the Lord thy God, and shalt obey his voice according to all that I command thee this day, thou and thy children, with all thine heart, and with all thy soul; ^3that then the Lord thy God will turn thy captivity, and have compassion upon thee, and will return and gather thee from all the nations, whither the Lord thy God hath scattered thee. ^4If any of thine be driven out unto the outmost parts of heaven, from thence will the Lord thy God gather thee, and from thence will he fetch thee: ^5and the Lord thy God will bring thee into the land which thy fathers possessed, and thou shalt possess it; and he will do thee good, and multiply thee above thy fathers. ^6And the Lord thy God will circumcise thine heart, and the heart of thy seed, to love the Lord thy God with all thine heart, and with all thy soul, that thou mayest live. ^7And the Lord thy God will put all these curses upon thine enemies, and on them that hate thee, which persecuted thee. ^8And thou shalt return and obey the voice of the Lord, and do all his commandments which I command thee this day. ^9And the Lord thy God will make thee plenteous in every work of thine hand, in the fruit of thy body, and in the fruit of thy cattle, and in the fruit of thy land, for good: for the Lord will again rejoice over thee for good, as he rejoiced over thy fathers: ^10if thou shalt hearken unto the voice of the Lord thy God, to keep his commandments and his statutes which are written in this book of the law, and if thou turn unto the Lord thy God with all thine heart, and with all thy soul.

^11For this commandment which I command thee this day, it is not hidden from thee, neither is it far off. ^12It is not in heaven, that thou shouldest say, Who shall go up for us to heaven, and bring it unto us, that we may hear it, and do it? ^13Neither is it beyond the sea, that thou shouldest say, Who shall go over the sea for us, and bring it unto us, that we may hear it, and do it? ^14But the word is very nigh unto thee, in thy mouth, and in thy heart, that thou mayest do it.

^15See, I have set before thee this day life and good, and death and evil; ^16in that I command thee this day to love the Lord thy God, to walk in his ways, and to keep his commandments and his statutes and his judgments, that thou mayest live and multiply: and the Lord thy God shall bless thee in the land whither thou goest to possess it. ^17But if thine heart turn away, so that thou wilt not hear, but shalt be drawn away, and worship other gods, and serve them; ^18I denounce unto you this day, that ye shall surely perish, and that ye shall not prolong your days upon the land, whither thou passest over Jordan to go to possess it. ^19I call heaven and earth to record this day against you, that I have set before you life and death, blessing and cursing: therefore choose life, that both thou and thy seed may live: ^20that thou mayest love the Lord thy God, and that thou mayest obey his voice, and that thou mayest cleave unto him: for he is thy life, and the length of thy days: that thou mayest dwell in the land which the Lord sware unto thy fathers, to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob, to give them.

XXXI

^1And Moses went and spake these words unto all Israel. ^2And he said unto them, I am an hundred and twenty years old this day; I can no more go out and come in: also the Lord hath said unto me, Thou shalt not go over this Jordan. ^3The Lord thy God, he will go over before thee, and he will destroy these nations from before thee, and thou shalt possess them: and Joshua, he shall go over before thee, as the Lord hath said. ^4And the Lord shall do unto them as he did to Sihon and to Og, kings of the Amorites, and unto the land of them, whom he destroyed. ^5And the Lord shall give them up before your face, that ye may do unto them according unto all the commandments which I have commanded you. ^6Be strong and of a good courage, fear not, nor be afraid of them: for the Lord thy God, he it is that doth go with thee; he will not fail thee, nor forsake thee.

^7And Moses called unto Joshua, and said unto him in the sight of all Israel, Be strong and of a good courage: for thou must go with this people unto the land which the Lord hath sworn unto their fathers to give them; and thou shalt cause them to inherit it. ^8And the Lord, he it is that doth go before thee; he will be with thee, he will not fail thee, neither forsake thee: fear not, neither be dismayed.

^9And Moses wrote this law, and delivered it unto the priests the sons of Levi, which bare the ark of the covenant of the Lord, and unto all the elders of Israel. ^10And Moses commanded them, saying, At the end of every seven years, in the solemnity of the year of release, in the feast of tabernacles, ^11when all Israel is come to appear before the Lord thy God in the place which he shall choose, thou shalt read this law before all Israel in their hearing. ^12Gather the people together, men and women, and children, and thy stranger that is within thy gates, that they may hear, and that they may learn, and fear the Lord your God, and observe to do all the words of this law: ^13and that their children, which have not known any thing, may hear, and learn to fear the Lord your God, as long as ye live in the land whither ye go over Jordan to possess it.

^14And the Lord said unto Moses, Behold, thy days approach that thou must die: call Joshua, and present yourselves in the tabernacle of the congregation, that I may give him a charge. And Moses and Joshua went, and presented themselves in the tabernacle of the congregation. ^15And the Lord appeared in the tabernacle in a pillar of a cloud: and the pillar of the cloud stood over the door of the tabernacle. ^16And the Lord said unto Moses, Behold, thou shalt sleep with thy fathers; and this people will rise up, and go a whoring after the gods of the strangers of the land, whither they go to be among them, and will forsake me, and break my covenant which I have made with them. ^17Then my anger shall be kindled against them in that day, and I will forsake them, and I will hide my face from them, and they shall be devoured, and many evils and troubles shall befall them; so that they will say in that day, Are not these evils come upon us, because our God is not among us? ^18And I will surely hide my face in that day for all the evils which they shall have wrought, in that they are turned unto other gods. ^19Now therefore write ye this song for you, and teach it the children of Israel: put it in their mouths, that this song may be a witness for me against the children of Israel.

^20For when I shall have brought them into the land which I sware unto their fathers, that floweth with milk and honey; and they shall have eaten and filled themselves, and waxen fat; then will they turn unto other gods, and serve them, and provoke me, and break my covenant. ^21And it shall come to pass, when many evils and troubles are befallen them, that this song shall testify against them as a witness; for it shall not be forgotten out of the mouths of their seed: for I know their imagination which they go about, even now, before I have brought them into the land which I sware. ^22Moses therefore wrote this song the same day, and taught it the children of Israel. ^23And he gave Joshua the son of Nun a charge, and said, Be strong and of a good courage: for thou shalt bring the children of Israel into the land which I sware unto them: and I will be with thee.

^24And it came to pass, when Moses had made an end of writing the words of this law in a book, until they were finished, ^25that Moses commanded the Levites, which bare the ark of the covenant of the Lord, saying, ^26Take this book of the law, and put it in the side of the ark of the covenant of the Lord your God, that it may be there for a witness against thee. ^27For I know thy rebellion, and thy stiff neck: behold, while I am yet alive with you this day, ye have been rebellious against the Lord; and how much more after my death?

^28Gather unto me all the elders of your tribes, and your officers, that I may speak these words in their ears, and call heaven and earth to record against them. ^29For I know that after my death ye will utterly corrupt yourselves, and turn aside from the way which I have commanded you; and evil will befall you in the latter days; because ye will do evil in the sight of the Lord, to provoke him to anger through the work of your hands.

^30And Moses spake in the ears of all the congregation of Israel the words of this song, until they were ended.

XXXII

^1Give ear, O ye heavens, and I will speak;
And hear, O earth, the words of my mouth.
^2My doctrine shall drop as the rain,
My speech shall distil as the dew,
As the small rain upon the tender herb,
And as the showers upon the grass:
^3Because I will publish the name of the Lord:
Ascribe ye greatness unto our God.
^4He is the Rock, his work is perfect:
For all his ways are judgment:
A God of truth and without iniquity,
Just and right is he.
^5They have corrupted themselves, their spot is not the spot of his children:
They are a perverse and crooked generation.
^6Do ye thus requite the Lord,
O foolish people and unwise?
Is not he thy father that hath bought thee?
Hath he not made thee, and established thee?
^7Remember the days of old,
Consider the years of many generations:
Ask thy father, and he will shew thee;
Thy elders, and they will tell thee.
^8When the Most High divided to the nations their inheritance,
When he separated the sons of Adam,
He set the bounds of the people
According to the number of the children of Israel.
^9For the Lord’s portion is his people;
Jacob is the lot of his inheritance.
^10He found him in a desert land,
And in the waste howling wilderness;
He led him about, he instructed him,
He kept him as the apple of his eye.
^11As an eagle stirreth up her nest,
Fluttereth over her young,
Spreadeth abroad her wings, taketh them,
Beareth them on her wings:
^12So the Lord alone did lead him,
And there was no strange god with him.
^13He made him ride on the high places of the earth,
That he might eat the increase of the fields;
And he made him to suck honey out of the rock,
And oil out of the flinty rock;
^14Butter of kine, and milk of sheep,
With fat of lambs,
And rams of the breed of Bashan, and goats,
With the fat of kidneys of wheat;
And thou didst drink the pure blood of the grape.
^15But Jeshurun waxed fat, and kicked:
Thou art waxen fat, thou art grown thick, thou art covered with fatness;
Then he forsook God which made him,
And lightly esteemed the Rock of his salvation.
^16They provoked him to jealousy with strange gods,
With abominations provoked they him to anger.
^17They sacrificed unto devils, not to God;
To gods whom they knew not,
To new gods that came newly up,
Whom your fathers feared not.
^18Of the Rock that begat thee thou art unmindful,
And hast forgotten God that formed thee.
^19And when the Lord saw it, he abhorred them,
Because of the provoking of his sons, and of his daughters.
^20And he said, I will hide my face from them,
I will see what their end shall be:
For they are a very froward generation,
Children in whom is no faith.
^21They have moved me to jealousy with that which is not God;
They have provoked me to anger with their vanities:
And I will move them to jealousy with those which are not a people;
I will provoke them to anger with a foolish nation.
^22For a fire is kindled in mine anger,
And shall burn unto the lowest hell,
And shall consume the earth with her increase,
And set on fire the foundations of the mountains.
^23I will heap mischiefs upon them;
I will spend mine arrows upon them.
^24They shall be burnt with hunger, and devoured with burning heat,
And with bitter destruction:
I will also send the teeth of beasts upon them,
With the poison of serpents of the dust.
^25The sword without,
And terror within,
Shall destroy both the young man and the virgin,
The suckling also with the man of gray hairs.
^26I said, I would scatter them into corners,
I would make the remembrance of them to cease from among men:
^27Were it not that I feared the wrath of the enemy,
Lest their adversaries should behave themselves strangely,
And lest they should say, Our hand is high,
And the Lord hath not done all this.
^28For they are a nation void of counsel,
Neither is there any understanding in them.
^29O that they were wise, that they understood this,
That they would consider their latter end!
^30How should one chase a thousand,
And two put ten thousand to flight,
Except their Rock had sold them,
And the Lord had shut them up?
^31For their rock is not as our Rock,
Even our enemies themselves being judges.
^32For their vine is of the vine of Sodom,
And of the fields of Gomorrah:
Their grapes are grapes of gall,
Their clusters are bitter:
^33Their wine is the poison of dragons,
And the cruel venom of asps.
^34Is not this laid up in store with me,
And sealed up among my treasures?
^35To me belongeth vengeance and recompence;
Their foot shall slide in due time:
For the day of their calamity is at hand,
And the things that shall come upon them make haste.
^36For the Lord shall judge his people,
And repent himself for his servants,
When he seeth that their power is gone,
And there is none shut up, or left.
^37And he shall say, Where are their gods,
Their rock in whom they trusted,
^38Which did eat the fat of their sacrifices,
And drank the wine of their drink offerings?
Let them rise up and help you,
And be your protection.
^39See now that I, even I, am he,
And there is no god with me:
I kill, and I make alive;
I wound, and I heal:
Neither is there any that can deliver out of my hand.
^40For I lift up my hand to heaven,
And say, I live for ever.
^41If I whet my glittering sword,
And mine hand take hold on judgment;
I will render vengeance to mine enemies,
And will reward them that hate me.
^42I will make mine arrows drunk with blood,
And my sword shall devour flesh;
And that with the blood of the slain and of the captives,
From the beginning of revenges upon the enemy.
^43Rejoice, O ye nations, with his people:
For he will avenge the blood of his servants,
And will render vengeance to his adversaries,
And will be merciful unto his land, and to his people.

^44And Moses came and spake all the words of this song in the ears of the people, he, and Hoshea the son of Nun. ^45And Moses made an end of speaking all these words to all Israel: ^46and he said unto them, Set your hearts unto all the words which I testify among you this day, which ye shall command your children to observe to do, all the words of this law. ^47For it is not a vain thing for you; because it is your life: and through this thing ye shall prolong your days in the land, whither ye go over Jordan to possess it.

^48And the Lord spake unto Moses that selfsame day, saying, ^49Get thee up into this mountain Abarim, unto mount Nebo, which is in the land of Moab, that is over against Jericho; and behold the land of Canaan, which I give unto the children of Israel for a possession: ^50and die in the mount whither thou goest up, and be gathered unto thy people; as Aaron thy brother died in mount Hor, and was gathered unto his people: ^51because ye trespassed against me among the children of Israel at the waters of MeribahKadesh, in the wilderness of Zin; because ye sanctified me not in the midst of the children of Israel. ^52Yet thou shalt see the land before thee; but thou shalt not go thither unto the land which I give the children of Israel.

XXXIII

^1And this is the blessing, wherewith Moses the man of God blessed the children of Israel before his death. ^2And he said,

The Lord came from Sinai,
And rose up from Seir unto them;
He shined forth from mount Paran,
And he came with ten thousands of saints:
From his right hand went a fiery law for them.
^3Yea, he loved the people;
All his saints are in thy hand:
And they sat down at thy feet;
Every one shall receive of thy words.
^4Moses commanded us a law,
Even the inheritance of the congregation of Jacob.
^5And he was king in Jeshurun,
When the heads of the people
And the tribes of Israel were gathered together.
^6Let Reuben live, and not die;
And let not his men be few.
^7And this is the blessing of Judah: and he said,
Hear, Lord, the voice of Judah,
And bring him unto his people:
Let his hands be sufficient for him;
And be thou an help to him from his enemies.

^8And of Levi he said,

Let thy Thummim and thy Urim be with thy holy one,
Whom thou didst prove at Massah,
And with whom thou didst strive at the waters of Meribah;
^9Who said unto his father and to his mother, I have not seen him;
Neither did he acknowledge his brethren,
Nor knew his own children:
For they have observed thy word,
And kept thy covenant.
^10They shall teach Jacob thy judgments,
And Israel thy law:
They shall put incense before thee,
And whole burnt sacrifice upon thine altar.
^11Bless, Lord, his substance,
And accept the work of his hands;
Smite through the loins of them that rise against him,
And of them that hate him, that they rise not again.

^12And of Benjamin he said,

The beloved of the Lord shall dwell in safety by him;
And the Lord shall cover him all the day long,
And he shall dwell between his shoulders.

^13And of Joseph he said,

Blessed of the Lord be his land,
For the precious things of heaven, for the dew,
And for the deep that coucheth beneath,
^14And for the precious fruits brought forth by the sun,
And for the precious things put forth by the moon,
^15And for the chief things of the ancient mountains,
And for the precious things of the lasting hills,
^16And for the precious things of the earth and fulness thereof,
And for the good will of him that dwelt in the bush:
Let the blessing come upon the head of Joseph,
And upon the top of the head of him that was separated from his brethren.
^17His glory is like the firstling of his bullock,
And his horns are like the horns of unicorns:
With them he shall push the people together to the ends of the earth:
And they are the ten thousands of Ephraim,
And they are the thousands of Manasseh.

^18And of Zebulun he said,

Rejoice, Zebulun, in thy going out;
And, Issachar, in thy tents.
^19They shall call the people unto the mountain;
There they shall offer sacrifices of righteousness:
For they shall suck of the abundance of the seas,
And of treasures hid in the sand.

^20And of Gad he said,

Blessed be he that enlargeth Gad:
He dwelleth as a lion,
And teareth the arm with the crown of the head.
^21And he provided the first part for himself,
Because there, in a portion of the lawgiver, was he seated;
And he came with the heads of the people,
He executed the justice of the Lord,
And his judgments with Israel.

^22And of Dan he said,

Dan is a lion’s whelp:
He shall leap from Bashan.

^23And of Naphtali he said,

O Naphtali, satisfied with favour,
And full with the blessing of the Lord:
Possess thou the west and the south.

^24And of Asher he said,

Let Asher be blessed with children;
Let him be acceptable to his brethren,
And let him dip his foot in oil.
^25Thy shoes shall be iron and brass;
And as thy days, so shall thy strength be.
^26There is none like unto the God of Jeshurun,
Who rideth upon the heaven in thy help,
And in his excellency on the sky.
^27The eternal God is thy refuge,
And underneath are the everlasting arms:
And he shall thrust out the enemy from before thee;
And shall say, Destroy them.
^28Israel then shall dwell in safety alone:
The fountain of Jacob
Shall be upon a land of corn and wine;
Also his heavens shall drop down dew.
^29Happy art thou, O Israel:
Who is like unto thee, O people saved by the Lord,
The shield of thy help,
And who is the sword of thy excellency!
And thine enemies shall be found liars unto thee;
And thou shalt tread upon their high places.

XXXIV

^1And Moses went up from the plains of Moab unto the mountain of Nebo, to the top of Pisgah, that is over against Jericho. And the Lord shewed him all the land of Gilead, unto Dan, ^2and all Naphtali, and the land of Ephraim, and Manasseh, and all the land of Judah, unto the utmost sea, ^3and the south, and the plain of the valley of Jericho, the city of palm trees, unto Zoar. ^4And the Lord said unto him, This is the land which I sware unto Abraham, unto Isaac, and unto Jacob, saying, I will give it unto thy seed: I have caused thee to see it with thine eyes, but thou shalt not go over thither.

^5So Moses the servant of the Lord died there in the land of Moab, according to the word of the Lord. ^6And he buried him in a valley in the land of Moab, over against Bethpeor: but no man knoweth of his sepulchre unto this day. ^7And Moses was an hundred and twenty years old when he died: his eye was not dim, nor his natural force abated. ^8And the children of Israel wept for Moses in the plains of Moab thirty days: so the days of weeping and mourning for Moses were ended.

^9And Joshua the son of Nun was full of the spirit of wisdom; for Moses had laid his hands upon him: and the children of Israel hearkened unto him, and did as the Lord commanded Moses.

^10And there arose not a prophet since in Israel like unto Moses, whom the Lord knew face to face, ^11in all the signs and the wonders, which the Lord sent him to do in the land of Egypt to Pharaoh, and to all his servants, and to all his land, ^12and in all that mighty hand, and in all the great terror which Moses shewed in the sight of all Israel.

I Samuel

The First Book of

Samuel

I

^1Now there was a certain man of Ramathaimzophim, of mount Ephraim, and his name was Elkanah, the son of Jeroham, the son of Elihu, the son of Tohu, the son of Zuph, an Ephrathite:

^2And he had two wives; the name of the one was Hannah, and the name of the other Peninnah: and Peninnah had children, but Hannah had no children.

^3And this man went up out of his city yearly to worship and to sacrifice unto the Lord of hosts in Shiloh. And the two sons of Eli, Hophni and Phinehas, the priests of the Lord, were there.

^4And when the time was that Elkanah offered, he gave to Peninnah his wife, and to all her sons and her daughters, portions:

^5But unto Hannah he gave a worthy portion; for he loved Hannah: but the Lord had shut up her womb.

^6And her adversary also provoked her sore, for to make her fret, because the Lord had shut up her womb.

^7And as he did so year by year, when she went up to the house of the Lord, so she provoked her; therefore she wept, and did not eat.

^8Then said Elkanah her husband to her, Hannah, why weepest thou? and why eatest thou not? and why is thy heart grieved? am not I better to thee than ten sons?

^9So Hannah rose up after they had eaten in Shiloh, and after they had drunk. Now Eli the priest sat upon a seat by a post of the temple of the Lord.

^10And she was in bitterness of soul, and prayed unto the Lord, and wept sore.

^11And she vowed a vow, and said, O Lord of hosts, if thou wilt indeed look on the affliction of thine handmaid, and remember me, and not forget thine handmaid, but wilt give unto thine handmaid a man child, then I will give him unto the Lord all the days of his life, and there shall no razor come upon his head.

^12And it came to pass, as she continued praying before the Lord, that Eli marked her mouth.

^13Now Hannah, she spake in her heart; only her lips moved, but her voice was not heard: therefore Eli thought she had been drunken.

^14And Eli said unto her, How long wilt thou be drunken? put away thy wine from thee.

^15And Hannah answered and said, No, my lord, I am a woman of a sorrowful spirit: I have drunk neither wine nor strong drink, but have poured out my soul before the Lord.

^16Count not thine handmaid for a daughter of Belial: for out of the abundance of my complaint and grief have I spoken hitherto.

^17Then Eli answered and said, Go in peace: and the God of Israel grant thee thy petition that thou hast asked of him.

^18And she said, Let thine handmaid find grace in thy sight. So the woman went her way, and did eat, and her countenance was no more sad.

^19And they rose up in the morning early, and worshipped before the Lord, and returned, and came to their house to Ramah: and Elkanah knew Hannah his wife; and the Lord remembered her.

^20Wherefore it came to pass, when the time was come about after Hannah had conceived, that she bare a son, and called his name Samuel, saying, Because I have asked him of the Lord.

^21And the man Elkanah, and all his house, went up to offer unto the Lord the yearly sacrifice, and his vow.

^22But Hannah went not up; for she said unto her husband, I will not go up until the child be weaned, and then I will bring him, that he may appear before the Lord, and there abide for ever.

^23And Elkanah her husband said unto her, Do what seemeth thee good; tarry until thou have weaned him; only the Lord establish his word. So the woman abode, and gave her son suck until she weaned him.

^24And when she had weaned him, she took him up with her, with three bullocks, and one ephah of flour, and a bottle of wine, and brought him unto the house of the Lord in Shiloh: and the child was young.

^25And they slew a bullock, and brought the child to Eli.

^26And she said, Oh my lord, as thy soul liveth, my lord, I am the woman that stood by thee here, praying unto the Lord.

^27For this child I prayed; and the Lord hath given me my petition which I asked of him:

^28Therefore also I have lent him to the Lord; as long as he liveth he shall be lent to the Lord. And he worshipped the Lord there.

II

^1And Hannah prayed, and said, My heart rejoiceth in the Lord, mine horn is exalted in the Lord: my mouth is enlarged over mine enemies; because I rejoice in thy salvation.

^2There is none holy as the Lord: for there is none beside thee: neither is there any rock like our God.

^3Talk no more so exceeding proudly; let not arrogancy come out of your mouth: for the Lord is a God of knowledge, and by him actions are weighed.

^4The bows of the mighty men are broken, and they that stumbled are girded with strength.

^5They that were full have hired out themselves for bread; and they that were hungry ceased: so that the barren hath born seven; and she that hath many children is waxed feeble.

^6The Lord killeth, and maketh alive: he bringeth down to the grave, and bringeth up.

^7The Lord maketh poor, and maketh rich: he bringeth low, and lifteth up.

^8He raiseth up the poor out of the dust, and lifteth up the beggar from the dunghill, to set them among princes, and to make them inherit the throne of glory: for the pillars of the earth are the Lord’s, and he hath set the world upon them.

^9He will keep the feet of his saints, and the wicked shall be silent in darkness; for by strength shall no man prevail.

^10The adversaries of the Lord shall be broken to pieces; out of heaven shall he thunder upon them: the Lord shall judge the ends of the earth; and he shall give strength unto his king, and exalt the horn of his anointed.

^11And Elkanah went to Ramah to his house. And the child did minister unto the Lord before Eli the priest.

^12Now the sons of Eli were sons of Belial; they knew not the Lord.

^13And the priest’s custom with the people was, that, when any man offered sacrifice, the priest’s servant came, while the flesh was in seething, with a fleshhook of three teeth in his hand;

^14And he struck it into the pan, or kettle, or caldron, or pot; all that the fleshhook brought up the priest took for himself. So they did in Shiloh unto all the Israelites that came thither.

^15Also before they burnt the fat, the priest’s servant came, and said to the man that sacrificed, Give flesh to roast for the priest; for he will not have sodden flesh of thee, but raw.

^16And if any man said unto him, Let them not fail to burn the fat presently, and then take as much as thy soul desireth; then he would answer him, Nay; but thou shalt give it me now: and if not, I will take it by force.

^17Wherefore the sin of the young men was very great before the Lord: for men abhorred the offering of the Lord.

^18But Samuel ministered before the Lord, being a child, girded with a linen ephod.

^19Moreover his mother made him a little coat, and brought it to him from year to year, when she came up with her husband to offer the yearly sacrifice.

^20And Eli blessed Elkanah and his wife, and said, The Lord give thee seed of this woman for the loan which is lent to the Lord. And they went unto their own home.

^21And the Lord visited Hannah, so that she conceived, and bare three sons and two daughters. And the child Samuel grew before the Lord.

^22Now Eli was very old, and heard all that his sons did unto all Israel; and how they lay with the women that assembled at the door of the tabernacle of the congregation.

^23And he said unto them, Why do ye such things? for I hear of your evil dealings by all this people.

^24Nay, my sons; for it is no good report that I hear: ye make the Lord’s people to transgress.

^25If one man sin against another, the judge shall judge him: but if a man sin against the Lord, who shall intreat for him? Notwithstanding they hearkened not unto the voice of their father, because the Lord would slay them.

^26And the child Samuel grew on, and was in favour both with the Lord, and also with men.

^27And there came a man of God unto Eli, and said unto him, Thus saith the Lord, Did I plainly appear unto the house of thy father, when they were in Egypt in Pharaoh’s house?

^28And did I choose him out of all the tribes of Israel to be my priest, to offer upon mine altar, to burn incense, to wear an ephod before me? and did I give unto the house of thy father all the offerings made by fire of the children of Israel?

^29Wherefore kick ye at my sacrifice and at mine offering, which I have commanded in my habitation; and honourest thy sons above me, to make yourselves fat with the chiefest of all the offerings of Israel my people?

^30Wherefore the Lord God of Israel saith, I said indeed that thy house, and the house of thy father, should walk before me for ever: but now the Lord saith, Be it far from me; for them that honour me I will honour, and they that despise me shall be lightly esteemed.

^31Behold, the days come, that I will cut off thine arm, and the arm of thy father’s house, that there shall not be an old man in thine house.

^32And thou shalt see an enemy in my habitation, in all the wealth which God shall give Israel: and there shall not be an old man in thine house for ever.

^33And the man of thine, whom I shall not cut off from mine altar, shall be to consume thine eyes, and to grieve thine heart: and all the increase of thine house shall die in the flower of their age.

^34And this shall be a sign unto thee, that shall come upon thy two sons, on Hophni and Phinehas; in one day they shall die both of them.

^35And I will raise me up a faithful priest, that shall do according to that which is in mine heart and in my mind: and I will build him a sure house; and he shall walk before mine anointed for ever.

^36And it shall come to pass, that every one that is left in thine house shall come and crouch to him for a piece of silver and a morsel of bread, and shall say, Put me, I pray thee, into one of the priests’ offices, that I may eat a piece of bread.

III

^1And the child Samuel ministered unto the Lord before Eli. And the word of the Lord was precious in those days; there was no open vision.

^2And it came to pass at that time, when Eli was laid down in his place, and his eyes began to wax dim, that he could not see;

^3And ere the lamp of God went out in the temple of the Lord, where the ark of God was, and Samuel was laid down to sleep;

^4That the Lord called Samuel: and he answered, Here am I.

^5And he ran unto Eli, and said, Here am I; for thou calledst me. And he said, I called not; lie down again. And he went and lay down.

^6And the Lord called yet again, Samuel. And Samuel arose and went to Eli, and said, Here am I; for thou didst call me. And he answered, I called not, my son; lie down again.

^7Now Samuel did not yet know the Lord, neither was the word of the Lord yet revealed unto him.

^8And the Lord called Samuel again the third time. And he arose and went to Eli, and said, Here am I; for thou didst call me. And Eli perceived that the Lord had called the child.

^9Therefore Eli said unto Samuel, Go, lie down: and it shall be, if he call thee, that thou shalt say, Speak, Lord; for thy servant heareth. So Samuel went and lay down in his place.

^10And the Lord came, and stood, and called as at other times, Samuel, Samuel. Then Samuel answered, Speak; for thy servant heareth.

^11And the Lord said to Samuel, Behold, I will do a thing in Israel, at which both the ears of every one that heareth it shall tingle.

^12In that day I will perform against Eli all things which I have spoken concerning his house: when I begin, I will also make an end.

^13For I have told him that I will judge his house for ever for the iniquity which he knoweth; because his sons made themselves vile, and he restrained them not.

^14And therefore I have sworn unto the house of Eli, that the iniquity of Eli’s house shall not be purged with sacrifice nor offering for ever.

^15And Samuel lay until the morning, and opened the doors of the house of the Lord. And Samuel feared to shew Eli the vision.

^16Then Eli called Samuel, and said, Samuel, my son. And he answered, Here am I.

^17And he said, What is the thing that the Lord hath said unto thee? I pray thee hide it not from me: God do so to thee, and more also, if thou hide any thing from me of all the things that he said unto thee.

^18And Samuel told him every whit, and hid nothing from him. And he said, It is the Lord: let him do what seemeth him good.

^19And Samuel grew, and the Lord was with him, and did let none of his words fall to the ground.

^20And all Israel from Dan even to Beersheba knew that Samuel was established to be a prophet of the Lord.

^21And the Lord appeared again in Shiloh: for the Lord revealed himself to Samuel in Shiloh by the word of the Lord.

IV

^1And the word of Samuel came to all Israel. Now Israel went out against the Philistines to battle, and pitched beside Ebenezer: and the Philistines pitched in Aphek.

^2And the Philistines put themselves in array against Israel: and when they joined battle, Israel was smitten before the Philistines: and they slew of the army in the field about four thousand men.

^3And when the people were come into the camp, the elders of Israel said, Wherefore hath the Lord smitten us to day before the Philistines? Let us fetch the ark of the covenant of the Lord out of Shiloh unto us, that, when it cometh among us, it may save us out of the hand of our enemies.

^4So the people sent to Shiloh, that they might bring from thence the ark of the covenant of the Lord of hosts, which dwelleth between the cherubims: and the two sons of Eli, Hophni and Phinehas, were there with the ark of the covenant of God.

^5And when the ark of the covenant of the Lord came into the camp, all Israel shouted with a great shout, so that the earth rang again.

^6And when the Philistines heard the noise of the shout, they said, What meaneth the noise of this great shout in the camp of the Hebrews? And they understood that the ark of the Lord was come into the camp.

^7And the Philistines were afraid, for they said, God is come into the camp. And they said, Woe unto us! for there hath not been such a thing heretofore.

^8Woe unto us! who shall deliver us out of the hand of these mighty Gods? these are the Gods that smote the Egyptians with all the plagues in the wilderness.

^9Be strong and quit yourselves like men, O ye Philistines, that ye be not servants unto the Hebrews, as they have been to you: quit yourselves like men, and fight.

^10And the Philistines fought, and Israel was smitten, and they fled every man into his tent: and there was a very great slaughter; for there fell of Israel thirty thousand footmen.

^11And the ark of God was taken; and the two sons of Eli, Hophni and Phinehas, were slain.

^12And there ran a man of Benjamin out of the army, and came to Shiloh the same day with his clothes rent, and with earth upon his head.

^13And when he came, lo, Eli sat upon a seat by the wayside watching: for his heart trembled for the ark of God. And when the man came into the city, and told it, all the city cried out.

^14And when Eli heard the noise of the crying, he said, What meaneth the noise of this tumult? And the man came in hastily, and told Eli.

^15Now Eli was ninety and eight years old; and his eyes were dim, that he could not see.

^16And the man said unto Eli, I am he that came out of the army, and I fled to day out of the army. And he said, What is there done, my son?

^17And the messenger answered and said, Israel is fled before the Philistines, and there hath been also a great slaughter among the people, and thy two sons also, Hophni and Phinehas, are dead, and the ark of God is taken.

^18And it came to pass, when he made mention of the ark of God, that he fell from off the seat backward by the side of the gate, and his neck brake, and he died: for he was an old man, and heavy. And he had judged Israel forty years.

^19And his daughter in law, Phinehas’ wife, was with child, near to be delivered: and when she heard the tidings that the ark of God was taken, and that her father in law and her husband were dead, she bowed herself and travailed; for her pains came upon her.

^20And about the time of her death the women that stood by her said unto her, Fear not; for thou hast born a son. But she answered not, neither did she regard it.

^21And she named the child Ichabod, saying, The glory is departed from Israel: because the ark of God was taken, and because of her father in law and her husband.

^22And she said, The glory is departed from Israel: for the ark of God is taken.

V

^1And the Philistines took the ark of God, and brought it from Ebenezer unto Ashdod.

^2When the Philistines took the ark of God, they brought it into the house of Dagon, and set it by Dagon.

^3And when they of Ashdod arose early on the morrow, behold, Dagon was fallen upon his face to the earth before the ark of the Lord. And they took Dagon, and set him in his place again.

^4And when they arose early on the morrow morning, behold, Dagon was fallen upon his face to the ground before the ark of the Lord; and the head of Dagon and both the palms of his hands were cut off upon the threshold; only the stump of Dagon was left to him.

^5Therefore neither the priests of Dagon, nor any that come into Dagon’s house, tread on the threshold of Dagon in Ashdod unto this day.

^6But the hand of the Lord was heavy upon them of Ashdod, and he destroyed them, and smote them with emerods, even Ashdod and the coasts thereof.

^7And when the men of Ashdod saw that it was so, they said, The ark of the God of Israel shall not abide with us: for his hand is sore upon us, and upon Dagon our god.

^8They sent therefore and gathered all the lords of the Philistines unto them, and said, What shall we do with the ark of the God of Israel? And they answered, Let the ark of the God of Israel be carried about unto Gath. And they carried the ark of the God of Israel about thither.

^9And it was so, that, after they had carried it about, the hand of the Lord was against the city with a very great destruction: and he smote the men of the city, both small and great, and they had emerods in their secret parts.

^10Therefore they sent the ark of God to Ekron. And it came to pass, as the ark of God came to Ekron, that the Ekronites cried out, saying, They have brought about the ark of the God of Israel to us, to slay us and our people.

^11So they sent and gathered together all the lords of the Philistines, and said, Send away the ark of the God of Israel, and let it go again to his own place, that it slay us not, and our people: for there was a deadly destruction throughout all the city; the hand of God was very heavy there.

^12And the men that died not were smitten with the emerods: and the cry of the city went up to heaven.

VI

^1And the ark of the Lord was in the country of the Philistines seven months.

^2And the Philistines called for the priests and the diviners, saying, What shall we do to the ark of the Lord? tell us wherewith we shall send it to his place.

^3And they said, If ye send away the ark of the God of Israel, send it not empty; but in any wise return him a trespass offering: then ye shall be healed, and it shall be known to you why his hand is not removed from you.

^4Then said they, What shall be the trespass offering which we shall return to him? They answered, Five golden emerods, and five golden mice, according to the number of the lords of the Philistines: for one plague was on you all, and on your lords.

^5Wherefore ye shall make images of your emerods, and images of your mice that mar the land; and ye shall give glory unto the God of Israel: peradventure he will lighten his hand from off you, and from off your gods, and from off your land.

^6Wherefore then do ye harden your hearts, as the Egyptians and Pharaoh hardened their hearts? when he had wrought wonderfully among them, did they not let the people go, and they departed?

^7Now therefore make a new cart, and take two milch kine, on which there hath come no yoke, and tie the kine to the cart, and bring their calves home from them:

^8And take the ark of the Lord, and lay it upon the cart; and put the jewels of gold, which ye return him for a trespass offering, in a coffer by the side thereof; and send it away, that it may go.

^9And see, if it goeth up by the way of his own coast to Bethshemesh, then he hath done us this great evil: but if not, then we shall know that it is not his hand that smote us: it was a chance that happened to us.

^10And the men did so; and took two milch kine, and tied them to the cart, and shut up their calves at home:

^11And they laid the ark of the Lord upon the cart, and the coffer with the mice of gold and the images of their emerods.

^12And the kine took the straight way to the way of Bethshemesh, and went along the highway, lowing as they went, and turned not aside to the right hand or to the left; and the lords of the Philistines went after them unto the border of Bethshemesh.

^13And they of Bethshemesh were reaping their wheat harvest in the valley: and they lifted up their eyes, and saw the ark, and rejoiced to see it.

^14And the cart came into the field of Joshua, a Bethshemite, and stood there, where there was a great stone: and they clave the wood of the cart, and offered the kine a burnt offering unto the Lord.

^15And the Levites took down the ark of the Lord, and the coffer that was with it, wherein the jewels of gold were, and put them on the great stone: and the men of Bethshemesh offered burnt offerings and sacrificed sacrifices the same day unto the Lord.

^16And when the five lords of the Philistines had seen it, they returned to Ekron the same day.

^17And these are the golden emerods which the Philistines returned for a trespass offering unto the Lord; for Ashdod one, for Gaza one, for Askelon one, for Gath one, for Ekron one;

^18And the golden mice, according to the number of all the cities of the Philistines belonging to the five lords, both of fenced cities, and of country villages, even unto the great stone of Abel, whereon they set down the ark of the Lord: which stone remaineth unto this day in the field of Joshua, the Bethshemite.

^19And he smote the men of Bethshemesh, because they had looked into the ark of the Lord, even he smote of the people fifty thousand and threescore and ten men: and the people lamented, because the Lord had smitten many of the people with a great slaughter.

^20And the men of Bethshemesh said, Who is able to stand before this holy Lord God? and to whom shall he go up from us?

^21And they sent messengers to the inhabitants of Kirjathjearim, saying, The Philistines have brought again the ark of the Lord; come ye down, and fetch it up to you.

VII

^1And the men of Kirjathjearim came, and fetched up the ark of the Lord, and brought it into the house of Abinadab in the hill, and sanctified Eleazar his son to keep the ark of the Lord.

^2And it came to pass, while the ark abode in Kirjathjearim, that the time was long; for it was twenty years: and all the house of Israel lamented after the Lord.

^3And Samuel spake unto all the house of Israel, saying, If ye do return unto the Lord with all your hearts, then put away the strange gods and Ashtaroth from among you, and prepare your hearts unto the Lord, and serve him only: and he will deliver you out of the hand of the Philistines.

^4Then the children of Israel did put away Baalim and Ashtaroth, and served the Lord only.

^5And Samuel said, Gather all Israel to Mizpeh, and I will pray for you unto the Lord.

^6And they gathered together to Mizpeh, and drew water, and poured it out before the Lord, and fasted on that day, and said there, We have sinned against the Lord. And Samuel judged the children of Israel in Mizpeh.

^7And when the Philistines heard that the children of Israel were gathered together to Mizpeh, the lords of the Philistines went up against Israel. And when the children of Israel heard it, they were afraid of the Philistines.

^8And the children of Israel said to Samuel, Cease not to cry unto the Lord our God for us, that he will save us out of the hand of the Philistines.

^9And Samuel took a sucking lamb, and offered it for a burnt offering wholly unto the Lord: and Samuel cried unto the Lord for Israel; and the Lord heard him.

^10And as Samuel was offering up the burnt offering, the Philistines drew near to battle against Israel: but the Lord thundered with a great thunder on that day upon the Philistines, and discomfited them; and they were smitten before Israel.

^11And the men of Israel went out of Mizpeh, and pursued the Philistines, and smote them, until they came under Bethcar.

^12Then Samuel took a stone, and set it between Mizpeh and Shen, and called the name of it Ebenezer, saying, Hitherto hath the Lord helped us.

^13So the Philistines were subdued, and they came no more into the coast of Israel: and the hand of the Lord was against the Philistines all the days of Samuel.

^14And the cities which the Philistines had taken from Israel were restored to Israel, from Ekron even unto Gath; and the coasts thereof did Israel deliver out of the hands of the Philistines. And there was peace between Israel and the Amorites.

^15And Samuel judged Israel all the days of his life.

^16And he went from year to year in circuit to Bethel, and Gilgal, and Mizpeh, and judged Israel in all those places.

^17And his return was to Ramah; for there was his house; and there he judged Israel; and there he built an altar unto the Lord.

VIII

^1And it came to pass, when Samuel was old, that he made his sons judges over Israel.

^2Now the name of his firstborn was Joel; and the name of his second, Abiah: they were judges in Beersheba.

^3And his sons walked not in his ways, but turned aside after lucre, and took bribes, and perverted judgment.

^4Then all the elders of Israel gathered themselves together, and came to Samuel unto Ramah,

^5And said unto him, Behold, thou art old, and thy sons walk not in thy ways: now make us a king to judge us like all the nations.

^6But the thing displeased Samuel, when they said, Give us a king to judge us. And Samuel prayed unto the Lord.

^7And the Lord said unto Samuel, Hearken unto the voice of the people in all that they say unto thee: for they have not rejected thee, but they have rejected me, that I should not reign over them.

^8According to all the works which they have done since the day that I brought them up out of Egypt even unto this day, wherewith they have forsaken me, and served other gods, so do they also unto thee.

^9Now therefore hearken unto their voice: howbeit yet protest solemnly unto them, and shew them the manner of the king that shall reign over them.

^10And Samuel told all the words of the Lord unto the people that asked of him a king.

^11And he said, This will be the manner of the king that shall reign over you: He will take your sons, and appoint them for himself, for his chariots, and to be his horsemen; and some shall run before his chariots.

^12And he will appoint him captains over thousands, and captains over fifties; and will set them to ear his ground, and to reap his harvest, and to make his instruments of war, and instruments of his chariots.

^13And he will take your daughters to be confectionaries, and to be cooks, and to be bakers.

^14And he will take your fields, and your vineyards, and your oliveyards, even the best of them, and give them to his servants.

^15And he will take the tenth of your seed, and of your vineyards, and give to his officers, and to his servants.

^16And he will take your menservants, and your maidservants, and your goodliest young men, and your asses, and put them to his work.

^17He will take the tenth of your sheep: and ye shall be his servants.

^18And ye shall cry out in that day because of your king which ye shall have chosen you; and the Lord will not hear you in that day.

^19Nevertheless the people refused to obey the voice of Samuel; and they said, Nay; but we will have a king over us;

^20That we also may be like all the nations; and that our king may judge us, and go out before us, and fight our battles.

^21And Samuel heard all the words of the people, and he rehearsed them in the ears of the Lord.

^22And the Lord said to Samuel, Hearken unto their voice, and make them a king. And Samuel said unto the men of Israel, Go ye every man unto his city.

IX

^1Now there was a man of Benjamin, whose name was Kish, the son of Abiel, the son of Zeror, the son of Bechorath, the son of Aphiah, a Benjamite, a mighty man of power.

^2And he had a son, whose name was Saul, a choice young man, and a goodly: and there was not among the children of Israel a goodlier person than he: from his shoulders and upward he was higher than any of the people.

^3And the asses of Kish Saul’s father were lost. And Kish said to Saul his son, Take now one of the servants with thee, and arise, go seek the asses.

^4And he passed through mount Ephraim, and passed through the land of Shalisha, but they found them not: then they passed through the land of Shalim, and there they were not: and he passed through the land of the Benjamites, but they found them not.

^5And when they were come to the land of Zuph, Saul said to his servant that was with him, Come, and let us return; lest my father leave caring for the asses, and take thought for us.

^6And he said unto him, Behold now, there is in this city a man of God, and he is an honourable man; all that he saith cometh surely to pass: now let us go thither; peradventure he can shew us our way that we should go.

^7Then said Saul to his servant, But, behold, if we go, what shall we bring the man? for the bread is spent in our vessels, and there is not a present to bring to the man of God: what have we?

^8And the servant answered Saul again, and said, Behold, I have here at hand the fourth part of a shekel of silver: that will I give to the man of God, to tell us our way.

^9(Beforetime in Israel, when a man went to enquire of God, thus he spake, Come, and let us go to the seer: for he that is now called a Prophet was beforetime called a Seer.)

^10Then said Saul to his servant, Well said; come, let us go. So they went unto the city where the man of God was.

^11And as they went up the hill to the city, they found young maidens going out to draw water, and said unto them, Is the seer here?

^12And they answered them, and said, He is; behold, he is before you: make haste now, for he came to day to the city; for there is a sacrifice of the people to day in the high place:

^13As soon as ye be come into the city, ye shall straightway find him, before he go up to the high place to eat: for the people will not eat until he come, because he doth bless the sacrifice; and afterwards they eat that be bidden. Now therefore get you up; for about this time ye shall find him.

^14And they went up into the city: and when they were come into the city, behold, Samuel came out against them, for to go up to the high place.

^15Now the Lord had told Samuel in his ear a day before Saul came, saying,

^16To morrow about this time I will send thee a man out of the land of Benjamin, and thou shalt anoint him to be captain over my people Israel, that he may save my people out of the hand of the Philistines: for I have looked upon my people, because their cry is come unto me.

^17And when Samuel saw Saul, the Lord said unto him, Behold the man whom I spake to thee of! this same shall reign over my people.

^18Then Saul drew near to Samuel in the gate, and said, Tell me, I pray thee, where the seer’s house is.

^19And Samuel answered Saul, and said, I am the seer: go up before me unto the high place; for ye shall eat with me to day, and to morrow I will let thee go, and will tell thee all that is in thine heart.

^20And as for thine asses that were lost three days ago, set not thy mind on them; for they are found. And on whom is all the desire of Israel? Is it not on thee, and on all thy father’s house?

^21And Saul answered and said, Am not I a Benjamite, of the smallest of the tribes of Israel? and my family the least of all the families of the tribe of Benjamin? wherefore then speakest thou so to me?

^22And Samuel took Saul and his servant, and brought them into the parlour, and made them sit in the chiefest place among them that were bidden, which were about thirty persons.

^23And Samuel said unto the cook, Bring the portion which I gave thee, of which I said unto thee, Set it by thee.

^24And the cook took up the shoulder, and that which was upon it, and set it before Saul. And Samuel said, Behold that which is left! set it before thee, and eat: for unto this time hath it been kept for thee since I said, I have invited the people. So Saul did eat with Samuel that day.

^25And when they were come down from the high place into the city, Samuel communed with Saul upon the top of the house.

^26And they arose early: and it came to pass about the spring of the day, that Samuel called Saul to the top of the house, saying, Up, that I may send thee away. And Saul arose, and they went out both of them, he and Samuel, abroad.

^27And as they were going down to the end of the city, Samuel said to Saul, Bid the servant pass on before us, (and he passed on), but stand thou still a while, that I may shew thee the word of God.

X

^1Then Samuel took a vial of oil, and poured it upon his head, and kissed him, and said, Is it not because the Lord hath anointed thee to be captain over his inheritance?

^2When thou art departed from me to day, then thou shalt find two men by Rachel’s sepulchre in the border of Benjamin at Zelzah; and they will say unto thee, The asses which thou wentest to seek are found: and, lo, thy father hath left the care of the asses, and sorroweth for you, saying, What shall I do for my son?

^3Then shalt thou go on forward from thence, and thou shalt come to the plain of Tabor, and there shall meet thee three men going up to God to Bethel, one carrying three kids, and another carrying three loaves of bread, and another carrying a bottle of wine:

^4And they will salute thee, and give thee two loaves of bread; which thou shalt receive of their hands.

^5After that thou shalt come to the hill of God, where is the garrison of the Philistines: and it shall come to pass, when thou art come thither to the city, that thou shalt meet a company of prophets coming down from the high place with a psaltery, and a tabret, and a pipe, and a harp, before them; and they shall prophesy:

^6And the Spirit of the Lord will come upon thee, and thou shalt prophesy with them, and shalt be turned into another man.

^7And let it be, when these signs are come unto thee, that thou do as occasion serve thee; for God is with thee.

^8And thou shalt go down before me to Gilgal; and, behold, I will come down unto thee, to offer burnt offerings, and to sacrifice sacrifices of peace offerings: seven days shalt thou tarry, till I come to thee, and shew thee what thou shalt do.

^9And it was so, that when he had turned his back to go from Samuel, God gave him another heart: and all those signs came to pass that day.

^10And when they came thither to the hill, behold, a company of prophets met him; and the Spirit of God came upon him, and he prophesied among them.

^11And it came to pass, when all that knew him beforetime saw that, behold, he prophesied among the prophets, then the people said one to another, What is this that is come unto the son of Kish? Is Saul also among the prophets?

^12And one of the same place answered and said, But who is their father? Therefore it became a proverb, Is Saul also among the prophets?

^13And when he had made an end of prophesying, he came to the high place.

^14And Saul’s uncle said unto him and to his servant, Whither went ye? And he said, To seek the asses: and when we saw that they were no where, we came to Samuel.

^15And Saul’s uncle said, Tell me, I pray thee, what Samuel said unto you.

^16And Saul said unto his uncle, He told us plainly that the asses were found. But of the matter of the kingdom, whereof Samuel spake, he told him not.

^17And Samuel called the people together unto the Lord to Mizpeh;

^18And said unto the children of Israel, Thus saith the Lord God of Israel, I brought up Israel out of Egypt, and delivered you out of the hand of the Egyptians, and out of the hand of all kingdoms, and of them that oppressed you:

^19And ye have this day rejected your God, who himself saved you out of all your adversities and your tribulations; and ye have said unto him, Nay, but set a king over us. Now therefore present yourselves before the Lord by your tribes, and by your thousands.

^20And when Samuel had caused all the tribes of Israel to come near, the tribe of Benjamin was taken.

^21When he had caused the tribe of Benjamin to come near by their families, the family of Matri was taken, and Saul the son of Kish was taken: and when they sought him, he could not be found.

^22Therefore they enquired of the Lord further, if the man should yet come thither. And the Lord answered, Behold he hath hid himself among the stuff.

^23And they ran and fetched him thence: and when he stood among the people, he was higher than any of the people from his shoulders and upward.

^24And Samuel said to all the people, See ye him whom the Lord hath chosen, that there is none like him among all the people? And all the people shouted, and said, God save the king.

^25Then Samuel told the people the manner of the kingdom, and wrote it in a book, and laid it up before the Lord. And Samuel sent all the people away, every man to his house.

^26And Saul also went home to Gibeah; and there went with him a band of men, whose hearts God had touched.

^27But the children of Belial said, How shall this man save us? And they despised him, and brought no presents. But he held his peace.

XI

^1Then Nahash the Ammonite came up, and encamped against Jabeshgilead: and all the men of Jabesh said unto Nahash, Make a covenant with us, and we will serve thee.

^2And Nahash the Ammonite answered them, On this condition will I make a covenant with you, that I may thrust out all your right eyes, and lay it for a reproach upon all Israel.

^3And the elders of Jabesh said unto him, Give us seven days’ respite, that we may send messengers unto all the coasts of Israel: and then, if there be no man to save us, we will come out to thee.

^4Then came the messengers to Gibeah of Saul, and told the tidings in the ears of the people: and all the people lifted up their voices, and wept.

^5And, behold, Saul came after the herd out of the field; and Saul said, What aileth the people that they weep? And they told him the tidings of the men of Jabesh.

^6And the Spirit of God came upon Saul when he heard those tidings, and his anger was kindled greatly.

^7And he took a yoke of oxen, and hewed them in pieces, and sent them throughout all the coasts of Israel by the hands of messengers, saying, Whosoever cometh not forth after Saul and after Samuel, so shall it be done unto his oxen. And the fear of the Lord fell on the people, and they came out with one consent.

^8And when he numbered them in Bezek, the children of Israel were three hundred thousand, and the men of Judah thirty thousand.

^9And they said unto the messengers that came, Thus shall ye say unto the men of Jabeshgilead, To morrow, by that time the sun be hot, ye shall have help. And the messengers came and shewed it to the men of Jabesh; and they were glad.

^10Therefore the men of Jabesh said, To morrow we will come out unto you, and ye shall do with us all that seemeth good unto you.

^11And it was so on the morrow, that Saul put the people in three companies; and they came into the midst of the host in the morning watch, and slew the Ammonites until the heat of the day: and it came to pass, that they which remained were scattered, so that two of them were not left together.

^12And the people said unto Samuel, Who is he that said, Shall Saul reign over us? bring the men, that we may put them to death.

^13And Saul said, There shall not a man be put to death this day: for to day the Lord hath wrought salvation in Israel.

^14Then said Samuel to the people, Come, and let us go to Gilgal, and renew the kingdom there.

^15And all the people went to Gilgal; and there they made Saul king before the Lord in Gilgal; and there they sacrificed sacrifices of peace offerings before the Lord; and there Saul and all the men of Israel rejoiced greatly.

XII

^1And Samuel said unto all Israel, Behold, I have hearkened unto your voice in all that ye said unto me, and have made a king over you.

^2And now, behold, the king walketh before you: and I am old and grayheaded; and, behold, my sons are with you: and I have walked before you from my childhood unto this day.

^3Behold, here I am: witness against me before the Lord, and before his anointed: whose ox have I taken? or whose ass have I taken? or whom have I defrauded? whom have I oppressed? or of whose hand have I received any bribe to blind mine eyes therewith? and I will restore it you.

^4And they said, Thou hast not defrauded us, nor oppressed us, neither hast thou taken ought of any man’s hand.

^5And he said unto them, The Lord is witness against you, and his anointed is witness this day, that ye have not found ought in my hand. And they answered, He is witness.

^6And Samuel said unto the people, It is the Lord that advanced Moses and Aaron, and that brought your fathers up out of the land of Egypt.

^7Now therefore stand still, that I may reason with you before the Lord of all the righteous acts of the Lord, which he did to you and to your fathers.

^8When Jacob was come into Egypt, and your fathers cried unto the Lord, then the Lord sent Moses and Aaron, which brought forth your fathers out of Egypt, and made them dwell in this place.

^9And when they forgat the Lord their God, he sold them into the hand of Sisera, captain of the host of Hazor, and into the hand of the Philistines, and into the hand of the king of Moab, and they fought against them.

^10And they cried unto the Lord, and said, We have sinned, because we have forsaken the Lord, and have served Baalim and Ashtaroth: but now deliver us out of the hand of our enemies, and we will serve thee.

^11And the Lord sent Jerubbaal, and Bedan, and Jephthah, and Samuel, and delivered you out of the hand of your enemies on every side, and ye dwelled safe.

^12And when ye saw that Nahash the king of the children of Ammon came against you, ye said unto me, Nay; but a king shall reign over us: when the Lord your God was your king.

^13Now therefore behold the king whom ye have chosen, and whom ye have desired! and, behold, the Lord hath set a king over you.

^14If ye will fear the Lord, and serve him, and obey his voice, and not rebel against the commandment of the Lord, then shall both ye and also the king that reigneth over you continue following the Lord your God:

^15But if ye will not obey the voice of the Lord, but rebel against the commandment of the Lord, then shall the hand of the Lord be against you, as it was against your fathers.

^16Now therefore stand and see this great thing, which the Lord will do before your eyes.

^17Is it not wheat harvest to day? I will call unto the Lord, and he shall send thunder and rain; that ye may perceive and see that your wickedness is great, which ye have done in the sight of the Lord, in asking you a king.

^18So Samuel called unto the Lord; and the Lord sent thunder and rain that day: and all the people greatly feared the Lord and Samuel.

^19And all the people said unto Samuel, Pray for thy servants unto the Lord thy God, that we die not: for we have added unto all our sins this evil, to ask us a king.

^20And Samuel said unto the people, Fear not: ye have done all this wickedness: yet turn not aside from following the Lord, but serve the Lord with all your heart;

^21And turn ye not aside: for then should ye go after vain things, which cannot profit nor deliver; for they are vain.

^22For the Lord will not forsake his people for his great name’s sake: because it hath pleased the Lord to make you his people.

^23Moreover as for me, God forbid that I should sin against the Lord in ceasing to pray for you: but I will teach you the good and the right way:

^24Only fear the Lord, and serve him in truth with all your heart: for consider how great things he hath done for you.

^25But if ye shall still do wickedly, ye shall be consumed, both ye and your king.

XIII

^1Saul reigned one year; and when he had reigned two years over Israel,

^2Saul chose him three thousand men of Israel; whereof two thousand were with Saul in Michmash and in mount Bethel, and a thousand were with Jonathan in Gibeah of Benjamin: and the rest of the people he sent every man to his tent.

^3And Jonathan smote the garrison of the Philistines that was in Geba, and the Philistines heard of it. And Saul blew the trumpet throughout all the land, saying, Let the Hebrews hear.

^4And all Israel heard say that Saul had smitten a garrison of the Philistines, and that Israel also was had in abomination with the Philistines. And the people were called together after Saul to Gilgal.

^5And the Philistines gathered themselves together to fight with Israel, thirty thousand chariots, and six thousand horsemen, and people as the sand which is on the sea shore in multitude: and they came up, and pitched in Michmash, eastward from Bethaven.

^6When the men of Israel saw that they were in a strait, (for the people were distressed,) then the people did hide themselves in caves, and in thickets, and in rocks, and in high places, and in pits.

^7And some of the Hebrews went over Jordan to the land of Gad and Gilead. As for Saul, he was yet in Gilgal, and all the people followed him trembling.

^8And he tarried seven days, according to the set time that Samuel had appointed: but Samuel came not to Gilgal; and the people were scattered from him.

^9And Saul said, Bring hither a burnt offering to me, and peace offerings. And he offered the burnt offering.

^10And it came to pass, that as soon as he had made an end of offering the burnt offering, behold, Samuel came; and Saul went out to meet him, that he might salute him.

^11And Samuel said, What hast thou done? And Saul said, Because I saw that the people were scattered from me, and that thou camest not within the days appointed, and that the Philistines gathered themselves together at Michmash;

^12Therefore said I, The Philistines will come down now upon me to Gilgal, and I have not made supplication unto the Lord: I forced myself therefore, and offered a burnt offering.

^13And Samuel said to Saul, Thou hast done foolishly: thou hast not kept the commandment of the Lord thy God, which he commanded thee: for now would the Lord have established thy kingdom upon Israel for ever.

^14But now thy kingdom shall not continue: the Lord hath sought him a man after his own heart, and the Lord hath commanded him to be captain over his people, because thou hast not kept that which the Lord commanded thee.

^15And Samuel arose, and gat him up from Gilgal unto Gibeah of Benjamin. And Saul numbered the people that were present with him, about six hundred men.

^16And Saul, and Jonathan his son, and the people that were present with them, abode in Gibeah of Benjamin: but the Philistines encamped in Michmash.

^17And the spoilers came out of the camp of the Philistines in three companies: one company turned unto the way that leadeth to Ophrah, unto the land of Shual:

^18And another company turned the way to Bethhoron: and another company turned to the way of the border that looketh to the valley of Zeboim toward the wilderness.

^19Now there was no smith found throughout all the land of Israel: for the Philistines said, Lest the Hebrews make them swords or spears:

^20But all the Israelites went down to the Philistines, to sharpen every man his share, and his coulter, and his axe, and his mattock.

^21Yet they had a file for the mattocks, and for the coulters, and for the forks, and for the axes, and to sharpen the goads.

^22So it came to pass in the day of battle, that there was neither sword nor spear found in the hand of any of the people that were with Saul and Jonathan: but with Saul and with Jonathan his son was there found.

^23And the garrison of the Philistines went out to the passage of Michmash.

XIV

^1Now it came to pass upon a day, that Jonathan the son of Saul said unto the young man that bare his armour, Come, and let us go over to the Philistines’ garrison, that is on the other side. But he told not his father.

^2And Saul tarried in the uttermost part of Gibeah under a pomegranate tree which is in Migron: and the people that were with him were about six hundred men;

^3And Ahiah, the son of Ahitub, Ichabod’s brother, the son of Phinehas, the son of Eli, the Lord’s priest in Shiloh, wearing an ephod. And the people knew not that Jonathan was gone.

^4And between the passages, by which Jonathan sought to go over unto the Philistines’ garrison, there was a sharp rock on the one side, and a sharp rock on the other side: and the name of the one was Bozez, and the name of the other Seneh.

^5The forefront of the one was situate northward over against Michmash, and the other southward over against Gibeah.

^6And Jonathan said to the young man that bare his armour, Come, and let us go over unto the garrison of these uncircumcised: it may be that the Lord will work for us: for there is no restraint to the Lord to save by many or by few.

^7And his armourbearer said unto him, Do all that is in thine heart: turn thee; behold, I am with thee according to thy heart.

^8Then said Jonathan, Behold, we will pass over unto these men, and we will discover ourselves unto them.

^9If they say thus unto us, Tarry until we come to you; then we will stand still in our place, and will not go up unto them.

^10But if they say thus, Come up unto us; then we will go up: for the Lord hath delivered them into our hand: and this shall be a sign unto us.

^11And both of them discovered themselves unto the garrison of the Philistines: and the Philistines said, Behold, the Hebrews come forth out of the holes where they had hid themselves.

^12And the men of the garrison answered Jonathan and his armourbearer, and said, Come up to us, and we will shew you a thing. And Jonathan said unto his armourbearer, Come up after me: for the Lord hath delivered them into the hand of Israel.

^13And Jonathan climbed up upon his hands and upon his feet, and his armourbearer after him: and they fell before Jonathan; and his armourbearer slew after him.

^14And that first slaughter, which Jonathan and his armourbearer made, was about twenty men, within as it were an half acre of land, which a yoke of oxen might plow.

^15And there was trembling in the host, in the field, and among all the people: the garrison, and the spoilers, they also trembled, and the earth quaked: so it was a very great trembling.

^16And the watchmen of Saul in Gibeah of Benjamin looked; and, behold, the multitude melted away, and they went on beating down one another.

^17Then said Saul unto the people that were with him, Number now, and see who is gone from us. And when they had numbered, behold, Jonathan and his armourbearer were not there.

^18And Saul said unto Ahiah, Bring hither the ark of God. For the ark of God was at that time with the children of Israel.

^19And it came to pass, while Saul talked unto the priest, that the noise that was in the host of the Philistines went on and increased: and Saul said unto the priest, Withdraw thine hand.

^20And Saul and all the people that were with him assembled themselves, and they came to the battle: and, behold, every man’s sword was against his fellow, and there was a very great discomfiture.

^21Moreover the Hebrews that were with the Philistines before that time, which went up with them into the camp from the country round about, even they also turned to be with the Israelites that were with Saul and Jonathan.

^22Likewise all the men of Israel which had hid themselves in mount Ephraim, when they heard that the Philistines fled, even they also followed hard after them in the battle.

^23So the Lord saved Israel that day: and the battle passed over unto Bethaven.

^24And the men of Israel were distressed that day: for Saul had adjured the people, saying, Cursed be the man that eateth any food until evening, that I may be avenged on mine enemies. So none of the people tasted any food.

^25And all they of the land came to a wood; and there was honey upon the ground.

^26And when the people were come into the wood, behold, the honey dropped; but no man put his hand to his mouth: for the people feared the oath.

^27But Jonathan heard not when his father charged the people with the oath: wherefore he put forth the end of the rod that was in his hand, and dipped it in an honeycomb, and put his hand to his mouth; and his eyes were enlightened.

^28Then answered one of the people, and said, Thy father straitly charged the people with an oath, saying, Cursed be the man that eateth any food this day. And the people were faint.

^29Then said Jonathan, My father hath troubled the land: see, I pray you, how mine eyes have been enlightened, because I tasted a little of this honey.

^30How much more, if haply the people had eaten freely to day of the spoil of their enemies which they found? for had there not been now a much greater slaughter among the Philistines?

^31And they smote the Philistines that day from Michmash to Aijalon: and the people were very faint.

^32And the people flew upon the spoil, and took sheep, and oxen, and calves, and slew them on the ground: and the people did eat them with the blood.

^33Then they told Saul, saying, Behold, the people sin against the Lord, in that they eat with the blood. And he said, Ye have transgressed: roll a great stone unto me this day.

^34And Saul said, Disperse yourselves among the people, and say unto them, Bring me hither every man his ox, and every man his sheep, and slay them here, and eat; and sin not against the Lord in eating with the blood. And all the people brought every man his ox with him that night, and slew them there.

^35And Saul built an altar unto the Lord: the same was the first altar that he built unto the Lord.

^36And Saul said, Let us go down after the Philistines by night, and spoil them until the morning light, and let us not leave a man of them. And they said, Do whatsoever seemeth good unto thee. Then said the priest, Let us draw near hither unto God.

^37And Saul asked counsel of God, Shall I go down after the Philistines? wilt thou deliver them into the hand of Israel? But he answered him not that day.

^38And Saul said, Draw ye near hither, all the chief of the people: and know and see wherein this sin hath been this day.

^39For, as the Lord liveth, which saveth Israel, though it be in Jonathan my son, he shall surely die. But there was not a man among all the people that answered him.

^40Then said he unto all Israel, Be ye on one side, and I and Jonathan my son will be on the other side. And the people said unto Saul, Do what seemeth good unto thee.

^41Therefore Saul said unto the Lord God of Israel, Give a perfect lot. And Saul and Jonathan were taken: but the people escaped.

^42And Saul said, Cast lots between me and Jonathan my son. And Jonathan was taken.

^43Then Saul said to Jonathan, Tell me what thou hast done. And Jonathan told him, and said, I did but taste a little honey with the end of the rod that was in mine hand, and, lo, I must die.

^44And Saul answered, God do so and more also: for thou shalt surely die, Jonathan.

^45And the people said unto Saul, Shall Jonathan die, who hath wrought this great salvation in Israel? God forbid: as the Lord liveth, there shall not one hair of his head fall to the ground; for he hath wrought with God this day. So the people rescued Jonathan, that he died not.

^46Then Saul went up from following the Philistines: and the Philistines went to their own place.

^47So Saul took the kingdom over Israel, and fought against all his enemies on every side, against Moab, and against the children of Ammon, and against Edom, and against the kings of Zobah, and against the Philistines: and whithersoever he turned himself, he vexed them.

^48And he gathered an host, and smote the Amalekites, and delivered Israel out of the hands of them that spoiled them.

^49Now the sons of Saul were Jonathan, and Ishui, and Melchishua: and the names of his two daughters were these; the name of the firstborn Merab, and the name of the younger Michal:

^50And the name of Saul’s wife was Ahinoam, the daughter of Ahimaaz: and the name of the captain of his host was Abner, the son of Ner, Saul’s uncle.

^51And Kish was the father of Saul; and Ner the father of Abner was the son of Abiel.

^52And there was sore war against the Philistines all the days of Saul: and when Saul saw any strong man, or any valiant man, he took him unto him.

XV

^1Samuel also said unto Saul, The Lord sent me to anoint thee to be king over his people, over Israel: now therefore hearken thou unto the voice of the words of the Lord.

^2Thus saith the Lord of hosts, I remember that which Amalek did to Israel, how he laid wait for him in the way, when he came up from Egypt.

^3Now go and smite Amalek, and utterly destroy all that they have, and spare them not; but slay both man and woman, infant and suckling, ox and sheep, camel and ass.

^4And Saul gathered the people together, and numbered them in Telaim, two hundred thousand footmen, and ten thousand men of Judah.

^5And Saul came to a city of Amalek, and laid wait in the valley.

^6And Saul said unto the Kenites, Go, depart, get you down from among the Amalekites, lest I destroy you with them: for ye shewed kindness to all the children of Israel, when they came up out of Egypt. So the Kenites departed from among the Amalekites.

^7And Saul smote the Amalekites from Havilah until thou comest to Shur, that is over against Egypt.

^8And he took Agag the king of the Amalekites alive, and utterly destroyed all the people with the edge of the sword.

^9But Saul and the people spared Agag, and the best of the sheep, and of the oxen, and of the fatlings, and the lambs, and all that was good, and would not utterly destroy them: but every thing that was vile and refuse, that they destroyed utterly.

^10Then came the word of the Lord unto Samuel, saying,

^11It repenteth me that I have set up Saul to be king: for he is turned back from following me, and hath not performed my commandments. And it grieved Samuel; and he cried unto the Lord all night.

^12And when Samuel rose early to meet Saul in the morning, it was told Samuel, saying, Saul came to Carmel, and, behold, he set him up a place, and is gone about, and passed on, and gone down to Gilgal.

^13And Samuel came to Saul: and Saul said unto him, Blessed be thou of the Lord: I have performed the commandment of the Lord.

^14And Samuel said, What meaneth then this bleating of the sheep in mine ears, and the lowing of the oxen which I hear?

^15And Saul said, They have brought them from the Amalekites: for the people spared the best of the sheep and of the oxen, to sacrifice unto the Lord thy God; and the rest we have utterly destroyed.

^16Then Samuel said unto Saul, Stay, and I will tell thee what the Lord hath said to me this night. And he said unto him, Say on.

^17And Samuel said, When thou wast little in thine own sight, wast thou not made the head of the tribes of Israel, and the Lord anointed thee king over Israel?

^18And the Lord sent thee on a journey, and said, Go and utterly destroy the sinners the Amalekites, and fight against them until they be consumed.

^19Wherefore then didst thou not obey the voice of the Lord, but didst fly upon the spoil, and didst evil in the sight of the Lord?

^20And Saul said unto Samuel, Yea, I have obeyed the voice of the Lord, and have gone the way which the Lord sent me, and have brought Agag the king of Amalek, and have utterly destroyed the Amalekites.

^21But the people took of the spoil, sheep and oxen, the chief of the things which should have been utterly destroyed, to sacrifice unto the Lord thy God in Gilgal.

^22And Samuel said, Hath the Lord as great delight in burnt offerings and sacrifices, as in obeying the voice of the Lord? Behold, to obey is better than sacrifice, and to hearken than the fat of rams.

^23For rebellion is as the sin of witchcraft, and stubbornness is as iniquity and idolatry. Because thou hast rejected the word of the Lord, he hath also rejected thee from being king.

^24And Saul said unto Samuel, I have sinned: for I have transgressed the commandment of the Lord, and thy words: because I feared the people, and obeyed their voice.

^25Now therefore, I pray thee, pardon my sin, and turn again with me, that I may worship the Lord.

^26And Samuel said unto Saul, I will not return with thee: for thou hast rejected the word of the Lord, and the Lord hath rejected thee from being king over Israel.

^27And as Samuel turned about to go away, he laid hold upon the skirt of his mantle, and it rent.

^28And Samuel said unto him, The Lord hath rent the kingdom of Israel from thee this day, and hath given it to a neighbour of thine, that is better than thou.

^29And also the Strength of Israel will not lie nor repent: for he is not a man, that he should repent.

^30Then he said, I have sinned: yet honour me now, I pray thee, before the elders of my people, and before Israel, and turn again with me, that I may worship the Lord thy God.

^31So Samuel turned again after Saul; and Saul worshipped the Lord.

^32Then said Samuel, Bring ye hither to me Agag the king of the Amalekites. And Agag came unto him delicately. And Agag said, Surely the bitterness of death is past.

^33And Samuel said, As the sword hath made women childless, so shall thy mother be childless among women. And Samuel hewed Agag in pieces before the Lord in Gilgal.

^34Then Samuel went to Ramah; and Saul went up to his house to Gibeah of Saul.

^35And Samuel came no more to see Saul until the day of his death: nevertheless Samuel mourned for Saul: and the Lord repented that he had made Saul king over Israel.

XVI

^1And the Lord said unto Samuel, How long wilt thou mourn for Saul, seeing I have rejected him from reigning over Israel? fill thine horn with oil, and go, I will send thee to Jesse the Bethlehemite: for I have provided me a king among his sons.

^2And Samuel said, How can I go? if Saul hear it, he will kill me. And the Lord said, Take an heifer with thee, and say, I am come to sacrifice to the Lord.

^3And call Jesse to the sacrifice, and I will shew thee what thou shalt do: and thou shalt anoint unto me him whom I name unto thee.

^4And Samuel did that which the Lord spake, and came to Bethlehem. And the elders of the town trembled at his coming, and said, Comest thou peaceably?

^5And he said, Peaceably: I am come to sacrifice unto the Lord: sanctify yourselves, and come with me to the sacrifice. And he sanctified Jesse and his sons, and called them to the sacrifice.

^6And it came to pass, when they were come, that he looked on Eliab, and said, Surely the Lord’s anointed is before him.

^7But the Lord said unto Samuel, Look not on his countenance, or on the height of his stature; because I have refused him: for the Lord seeth not as man seeth; for man looketh on the outward appearance, but the Lord looketh on the heart.

^8Then Jesse called Abinadab, and made him pass before Samuel. And he said, Neither hath the Lord chosen this.

^9Then Jesse made Shammah to pass by. And he said, Neither hath the Lord chosen this.

^10Again, Jesse made seven of his sons to pass before Samuel. And Samuel said unto Jesse, The Lord hath not chosen these.

^11And Samuel said unto Jesse, Are here all thy children? And he said, There remaineth yet the youngest, and, behold, he keepeth the sheep. And Samuel said unto Jesse, Send and fetch him: for we will not sit down till he come hither.

^12And he sent, and brought him in. Now he was ruddy, and withal of a beautiful countenance, and goodly to look to. And the Lord said, Arise, anoint him: for this is he.

^13Then Samuel took the horn of oil, and anointed him in the midst of his brethren: and the Spirit of the Lord came upon David from that day forward. So Samuel rose up, and went to Ramah.

^14But the Spirit of the Lord departed from Saul, and an evil spirit from the Lord troubled him.

^15And Saul’s servants said unto him, Behold now, an evil spirit from God troubleth thee.

^16Let our lord now command thy servants, which are before thee, to seek out a man, who is a cunning player on an harp: and it shall come to pass, when the evil spirit from God is upon thee, that he shall play with his hand, and thou shalt be well.

^17And Saul said unto his servants, Provide me now a man that can play well, and bring him to me.

^18Then answered one of the servants, and said, Behold, I have seen a son of Jesse the Bethlehemite, that is cunning in playing, and a mighty valiant man, and a man of war, and prudent in matters, and a comely person, and the Lord is with him.

^19Wherefore Saul sent messengers unto Jesse, and said, Send me David thy son, which is with the sheep.

^20And Jesse took an ass laden with bread, and a bottle of wine, and a kid, and sent them by David his son unto Saul.

^21And David came to Saul, and stood before him: and he loved him greatly; and he became his armourbearer.

^22And Saul sent to Jesse, saying, Let David, I pray thee, stand before me; for he hath found favour in my sight.

^23And it came to pass, when the evil spirit from God was upon Saul, that David took an harp, and played with his hand: so Saul was refreshed, and was well, and the evil spirit departed from him.

XVII

^1Now the Philistines gathered together their armies to battle, and were gathered together at Shochoh, which belongeth to Judah, and pitched between Shochoh and Azekah, in Ephesdammim.

^2And Saul and the men of Israel were gathered together, and pitched by the valley of Elah, and set the battle in array against the Philistines.

^3And the Philistines stood on a mountain on the one side, and Israel stood on a mountain on the other side: and there was a valley between them.

^4And there went out a champion out of the camp of the Philistines, named Goliath, of Gath, whose height was six cubits and a span.

^5And he had an helmet of brass upon his head, and he was armed with a coat of mail; and the weight of the coat was five thousand shekels of brass.

^6And he had greaves of brass upon his legs, and a target of brass between his shoulders.

^7And the staff of his spear was like a weaver’s beam; and his spear’s head weighed six hundred shekels of iron: and one bearing a shield went before him.

^8And he stood and cried unto the armies of Israel, and said unto them, Why are ye come out to set your battle in array? am not I a Philistine, and ye servants to Saul? choose you a man for you, and let him come down to me.

^9If he be able to fight with me, and to kill me, then will we be your servants: but if I prevail against him, and kill him, then shall ye be our servants, and serve us.

^10And the Philistine said, I defy the armies of Israel this day; give me a man, that we may fight together.

^11When Saul and all Israel heard those words of the Philistine, they were dismayed, and greatly afraid.

^12Now David was the son of that Ephrathite of Bethlehemjudah, whose name was Jesse; and he had eight sons: and the man went among men for an old man in the days of Saul.

^13And the three eldest sons of Jesse went and followed Saul to the battle: and the names of his three sons that went to the battle were Eliab the firstborn, and next unto him Abinadab, and the third Shammah.

^14And David was the youngest: and the three eldest followed Saul.

^15But David went and returned from Saul to feed his father’s sheep at Bethlehem.

^16And the Philistine drew near morning and evening, and presented himself forty days.

^17And Jesse said unto David his son, Take now for thy brethren an ephah of this parched corn, and these ten loaves, and run to the camp of thy brethren;

^18And carry these ten cheeses unto the captain of their thousand, and look how thy brethren fare, and take their pledge.

^19Now Saul, and they, and all the men of Israel, were in the valley of Elah, fighting with the Philistines.

^20And David rose up early in the morning, and left the sheep with a keeper, and took, and went, as Jesse had commanded him; and he came to the trench, as the host was going forth to the fight, and shouted for the battle.

^21For Israel and the Philistines had put the battle in array, army against army.

^22And David left his carriage in the hand of the keeper of the carriage, and ran into the army, and came and saluted his brethren.

^23And as he talked with them, behold, there came up the champion, the Philistine of Gath, Goliath by name, out of the armies of the Philistines, and spake according to the same words: and David heard them.

^24And all the men of Israel, when they saw the man, fled from him, and were sore afraid.

^25And the men of Israel said, Have ye seen this man that is come up? surely to defy Israel is he come up: and it shall be, that the man who killeth him, the king will enrich him with great riches, and will give him his daughter, and make his father’s house free in Israel.

^26And David spake to the men that stood by him, saying, What shall be done to the man that killeth this Philistine, and taketh away the reproach from Israel? for who is this uncircumcised Philistine, that he should defy the armies of the living God?

^27And the people answered him after this manner, saying, So shall it be done to the man that killeth him.

^28And Eliab his eldest brother heard when he spake unto the men; and Eliab’s anger was kindled against David, and he said, Why camest thou down hither? and with whom hast thou left those few sheep in the wilderness? I know thy pride, and the naughtiness of thine heart; for thou art come down that thou mightest see the battle.

^29And David said, What have I now done? Is there not a cause?

^30And he turned from him toward another, and spake after the same manner: and the people answered him again after the former manner.

^31And when the words were heard which David spake, they rehearsed them before Saul: and he sent for him.

^32And David said to Saul, Let no man’s heart fail because of him; thy servant will go and fight with this Philistine.

^33And Saul said to David, Thou art not able to go against this Philistine to fight with him: for thou art but a youth, and he a man of war from his youth.

^34And David said unto Saul, Thy servant kept his father’s sheep, and there came a lion, and a bear, and took a lamb out of the flock:

^35And I went out after him, and smote him, and delivered it out of his mouth: and when he arose against me, I caught him by his beard, and smote him, and slew him.

^36Thy servant slew both the lion and the bear: and this uncircumcised Philistine shall be as one of them, seeing he hath defied the armies of the living God.

^37David said moreover, The Lord that delivered me out of the paw of the lion, and out of the paw of the bear, he will deliver me out of the hand of this Philistine. And Saul said unto David, Go, and the Lord be with thee.

^38And Saul armed David with his armour, and he put an helmet of brass upon his head; also he armed him with a coat of mail.

^39And David girded his sword upon his armour, and he assayed to go; for he had not proved it. And David said unto Saul, I cannot go with these; for I have not proved them. And David put them off him.

^40And he took his staff in his hand, and chose him five smooth stones out of the brook, and put them in a shepherd’s bag which he had, even in a scrip; and his sling was in his hand: and he drew near to the Philistine.

^41And the Philistine came on and drew near unto David; and the man that bare the shield went before him.

^42And when the Philistine looked about, and saw David, he disdained him: for he was but a youth, and ruddy, and of a fair countenance.

^43And the Philistine said unto David, Am I a dog, that thou comest to me with staves? And the Philistine cursed David by his gods.

^44And the Philistine said to David, Come to me, and I will give thy flesh unto the fowls of the air, and to the beasts of the field.

^45Then said David to the Philistine, Thou comest to me with a sword, and with a spear, and with a shield: but I come to thee in the name of the Lord of hosts, the God of the armies of Israel, whom thou hast defied.

^46This day will the Lord deliver thee into mine hand; and I will smite thee, and take thine head from thee; and I will give the carcases of the host of the Philistines this day unto the fowls of the air, and to the wild beasts of the earth; that all the earth may know that there is a God in Israel.

^47And all this assembly shall know that the Lord saveth not with sword and spear: for the battle is the Lord’s, and he will give you into our hands.

^48And it came to pass, when the Philistine arose, and came, and drew nigh to meet David, that David hastened, and ran toward the army to meet the Philistine.

^49And David put his hand in his bag, and took thence a stone, and slang it, and smote the Philistine in his forehead, that the stone sunk into his forehead; and he fell upon his face to the earth.

^50So David prevailed over the Philistine with a sling and with a stone, and smote the Philistine, and slew him; but there was no sword in the hand of David.

^51Therefore David ran, and stood upon the Philistine, and took his sword, and drew it out of the sheath thereof, and slew him, and cut off his head therewith. And when the Philistines saw their champion was dead, they fled.

^52And the men of Israel and of Judah arose, and shouted, and pursued the Philistines, until thou come to the valley, and to the gates of Ekron. And the wounded of the Philistines fell down by the way to Shaaraim, even unto Gath, and unto Ekron.

^53And the children of Israel returned from chasing after the Philistines, and they spoiled their tents.

^54And David took the head of the Philistine, and brought it to Jerusalem; but he put his armour in his tent.

^55And when Saul saw David go forth against the Philistine, he said unto Abner, the captain of the host, Abner, whose son is this youth? And Abner said, As thy soul liveth, O king, I cannot tell.

^56And the king said, Enquire thou whose son the stripling is.

^57And as David returned from the slaughter of the Philistine, Abner took him, and brought him before Saul with the head of the Philistine in his hand.

^58And Saul said to him, Whose son art thou, thou young man? And David answered, I am the son of thy servant Jesse the Bethlehemite.

XVIII

^1And it came to pass, when he had made an end of speaking unto Saul, that the soul of Jonathan was knit with the soul of David, and Jonathan loved him as his own soul.

^2And Saul took him that day, and would let him go no more home to his father’s house.

^3Then Jonathan and David made a covenant, because he loved him as his own soul.

^4And Jonathan stripped himself of the robe that was upon him, and gave it to David, and his garments, even to his sword, and to his bow, and to his girdle.

^5And David went out whithersoever Saul sent him, and behaved himself wisely: and Saul set him over the men of war, and he was accepted in the sight of all the people, and also in the sight of Saul’s servants.

^6And it came to pass as they came, when David was returned from the slaughter of the Philistine, that the women came out of all cities of Israel, singing and dancing, to meet king Saul, with tabrets, with joy, and with instruments of musick.

^7And the women answered one another as they played, and said, Saul hath slain his thousands, and David his ten thousands.

^8And Saul was very wroth, and the saying displeased him; and he said, They have ascribed unto David ten thousands, and to me they have ascribed but thousands: and what can he have more but the kingdom?

^9And Saul eyed David from that day and forward.

^10And it came to pass on the morrow, that the evil spirit from God came upon Saul, and he prophesied in the midst of the house: and David played with his hand, as at other times: and there was a javelin in Saul’s hand.

^11And Saul cast the javelin; for he said, I will smite David even to the wall with it. And David avoided out of his presence twice.

^12And Saul was afraid of David, because the Lord was with him, and was departed from Saul.

^13Therefore Saul removed him from him, and made him his captain over a thousand; and he went out and came in before the people.

^14And David behaved himself wisely in all his ways; and the Lord was with him.

^15Wherefore when Saul saw that he behaved himself very wisely, he was afraid of him.

^16But all Israel and Judah loved David, because he went out and came in before them.

^17And Saul said to David, Behold my elder daughter Merab, her will I give thee to wife: only be thou valiant for me, and fight the Lord’s battles. For Saul said, Let not mine hand be upon him, but let the hand of the Philistines be upon him.

^18And David said unto Saul, Who am I? and what is my life, or my father’s family in Israel, that I should be son in law to the king?

^19But it came to pass at the time when Merab Saul’s daughter should have been given to David, that she was given unto Adriel the Meholathite to wife.

^20And Michal Saul’s daughter loved David: and they told Saul, and the thing pleased him.

^21And Saul said, I will give him her, that she may be a snare to him, and that the hand of the Philistines may be against him. Wherefore Saul said to David, Thou shalt this day be my son in law in the one of the twain.

^22And Saul commanded his servants, saying, Commune with David secretly, and say, Behold, the king hath delight in thee, and all his servants love thee: now therefore be the king’s son in law.

^23And Saul’s servants spake those words in the ears of David. And David said, Seemeth it to you a light thing to be a king’s son in law, seeing that I am a poor man, and lightly esteemed?

^24And the servants of Saul told him, saying, On this manner spake David.

^25And Saul said, Thus shall ye say to David, The king desireth not any dowry, but an hundred foreskins of the Philistines, to be avenged of the king’s enemies. But Saul thought to make David fall by the hand of the Philistines.

^26And when his servants told David these words, it pleased David well to be the king’s son in law: and the days were not expired.

^27Wherefore David arose and went, he and his men, and slew of the Philistines two hundred men; and David brought their foreskins, and they gave them in full tale to the king, that he might be the king’s son in law. And Saul gave him Michal his daughter to wife.

^28And Saul saw and knew that the Lord was with David, and that Michal Saul’s daughter loved him.

^29And Saul was yet the more afraid of David; and Saul became David’s enemy continually.

^30Then the princes of the Philistines went forth: and it came to pass, after they went forth, that David behaved himself more wisely than all the servants of Saul; so that his name was much set by.

XIX

^1And Saul spake to Jonathan his son, and to all his servants, that they should kill David.

^2But Jonathan Saul’s son delighted much in David: and Jonathan told David, saying, Saul my father seeketh to kill thee: now therefore, I pray thee, take heed to thyself until the morning, and abide in a secret place, and hide thyself:

^3And I will go out and stand beside my father in the field where thou art, and I will commune with my father of thee; and what I see, that I will tell thee.

^4And Jonathan spake good of David unto Saul his father, and said unto him, Let not the king sin against his servant, against David; because he hath not sinned against thee, and because his works have been to thee-ward very good:

^5For he did put his life in his hand, and slew the Philistine, and the Lord wrought a great salvation for all Israel: thou sawest it, and didst rejoice: wherefore then wilt thou sin against innocent blood, to slay David without a cause?

^6And Saul hearkened unto the voice of Jonathan: and Saul sware, As the Lord liveth, he shall not be slain.

^7And Jonathan called David, and Jonathan shewed him all those things. And Jonathan brought David to Saul, and he was in his presence, as in times past.

^8And there was war again: and David went out, and fought with the Philistines, and slew them with a great slaughter; and they fled from him.

^9And the evil spirit from the Lord was upon Saul, as he sat in his house with his javelin in his hand: and David played with his hand.

^10And Saul sought to smite David even to the wall with the javelin: but he slipped away out of Saul’s presence, and he smote the javelin into the wall: and David fled, and escaped that night.

^11Saul also sent messengers unto David’s house, to watch him, and to slay him in the morning: and Michal David’s wife told him, saying, If thou save not thy life to night, to morrow thou shalt be slain.

^12So Michal let David down through a window: and he went, and fled, and escaped.

^13And Michal took an image, and laid it in the bed, and put a pillow of goats’ hair for his bolster, and covered it with a cloth.

^14And when Saul sent messengers to take David, she said, He is sick.

^15And Saul sent the messengers again to see David, saying, Bring him up to me in the bed, that I may slay him.

^16And when the messengers were come in, behold, there was an image in the bed, with a pillow of goats’ hair for his bolster.

^17And Saul said unto Michal, Why hast thou deceived me so, and sent away mine enemy, that he is escaped? And Michal answered Saul, He said unto me, Let me go; why should I kill thee?

^18So David fled, and escaped, and came to Samuel to Ramah, and told him all that Saul had done to him. And he and Samuel went and dwelt in Naioth.

^19And it was told Saul, saying, Behold, David is at Naioth in Ramah.

^20And Saul sent messengers to take David: and when they saw the company of the prophets prophesying, and Samuel standing as appointed over them, the Spirit of God was upon the messengers of Saul, and they also prophesied.

^21And when it was told Saul, he sent other messengers, and they prophesied likewise. And Saul sent messengers again the third time, and they prophesied also.

^22Then went he also to Ramah, and came to a great well that is in Sechu: and he asked and said, Where are Samuel and David? And one said, Behold, they be at Naioth in Ramah.

^23And he went thither to Naioth in Ramah: and the Spirit of God was upon him also, and he went on, and prophesied, until he came to Naioth in Ramah.

^24And he stripped off his clothes also, and prophesied before Samuel in like manner, and lay down naked all that day and all that night. Wherefore they say, Is Saul also among the prophets?

XX

^1And David fled from Naioth in Ramah, and came and said before Jonathan, What have I done? what is mine iniquity? and what is my sin before thy father, that he seeketh my life?

^2And he said unto him, God forbid; thou shalt not die: behold, my father will do nothing either great or small, but that he will shew it me: and why should my father hide this thing from me? it is not so.

^3And David sware moreover, and said, Thy father certainly knoweth that I have found grace in thine eyes; and he saith, Let not Jonathan know this, lest he be grieved: but truly as the Lord liveth, and as thy soul liveth, there is but a step between me and death.

^4Then said Jonathan unto David, Whatsoever thy soul desireth, I will even do it for thee.

^5And David said unto Jonathan, Behold, to morrow is the new moon, and I should not fail to sit with the king at meat: but let me go, that I may hide myself in the field unto the third day at even.

^6If thy father at all miss me, then say, David earnestly asked leave of me that he might run to Bethlehem his city: for there is a yearly sacrifice there for all the family.

^7If he say thus, It is well; thy servant shall have peace: but if he be very wroth, then be sure that evil is determined by him.

^8Therefore thou shalt deal kindly with thy servant; for thou hast brought thy servant into a covenant of the Lord with thee: notwithstanding, if there be in me iniquity, slay me thyself; for why shouldest thou bring me to thy father?

^9And Jonathan said, Far be it from thee: for if I knew certainly that evil were determined by my father to come upon thee, then would not I tell it thee?

^10Then said David to Jonathan, Who shall tell me? or what if thy father answer thee roughly?

^11And Jonathan said unto David, Come, and let us go out into the field. And they went out both of them into the field.

^12And Jonathan said unto David, O Lord God of Israel, when I have sounded my father about to morrow any time, or the third day, and, behold, if there be good toward David, and I then send not unto thee, and shew it thee;

^13The Lord do so and much more to Jonathan: but if it please my father to do thee evil, then I will shew it thee, and send thee away, that thou mayest go in peace: and the Lord be with thee, as he hath been with my father.

^14And thou shalt not only while yet I live shew me the kindness of the Lord, that I die not:

^15But also thou shalt not cut off thy kindness from my house for ever: no, not when the Lord hath cut off the enemies of David every one from the face of the earth.

^16So Jonathan made a covenant with the house of David, saying, Let the Lord even require it at the hand of David’s enemies.

^17And Jonathan caused David to swear again, because he loved him: for he loved him as he loved his own soul.

^18Then Jonathan said to David, To morrow is the new moon: and thou shalt be missed, because thy seat will be empty.

^19And when thou hast stayed three days, then thou shalt go down quickly, and come to the place where thou didst hide thyself when the business was in hand, and shalt remain by the stone Ezel.

^20And I will shoot three arrows on the side thereof, as though I shot at a mark.

^21And, behold, I will send a lad, saying, Go, find out the arrows. If I expressly say unto the lad, Behold, the arrows are on this side of thee, take them; then come thou: for there is peace to thee, and no hurt; as the Lord liveth.

^22But if I say thus unto the young man, Behold, the arrows are beyond thee; go thy way: for the Lord hath sent thee away.

^23And as touching the matter which thou and I have spoken of, behold, the Lord be between thee and me for ever.

^24So David hid himself in the field: and when the new moon was come, the king sat him down to eat meat.

^25And the king sat upon his seat, as at other times, even upon a seat by the wall: and Jonathan arose, and Abner sat by Saul’s side, and David’s place was empty.

^26Nevertheless Saul spake not any thing that day: for he thought, Something hath befallen him, he is not clean; surely he is not clean.

^27And it came to pass on the morrow, which was the second day of the month, that David’s place was empty: and Saul said unto Jonathan his son, Wherefore cometh not the son of Jesse to meat, neither yesterday, nor to day?

^28And Jonathan answered Saul, David earnestly asked leave of me to go to Bethlehem:

^29And he said, Let me go, I pray thee; for our family hath a sacrifice in the city; and my brother, he hath commanded me to be there: and now, if I have found favour in thine eyes, let me get away, I pray thee, and see my brethren. Therefore he cometh not unto the king’s table.

^30Then Saul’s anger was kindled against Jonathan, and he said unto him, Thou son of the perverse rebellious woman, do not I know that thou hast chosen the son of Jesse to thine own confusion, and unto the confusion of thy mother’s nakedness?

^31For as long as the son of Jesse liveth upon the ground, thou shalt not be established, nor thy kingdom. Wherefore now send and fetch him unto me, for he shall surely die.

^32And Jonathan answered Saul his father, and said unto him, Wherefore shall he be slain? what hath he done?

^33And Saul cast a javelin at him to smite him: whereby Jonathan knew that it was determined of his father to slay David.

^34So Jonathan arose from the table in fierce anger, and did eat no meat the second day of the month: for he was grieved for David, because his father had done him shame.

^35And it came to pass in the morning, that Jonathan went out into the field at the time appointed with David, and a little lad with him.

^36And he said unto his lad, Run, find out now the arrows which I shoot. And as the lad ran, he shot an arrow beyond him.

^37And when the lad was come to the place of the arrow which Jonathan had shot, Jonathan cried after the lad, and said, Is not the arrow beyond thee?

^38And Jonathan cried after the lad, Make speed, haste, stay not. And Jonathan’s lad gathered up the arrows, and came to his master.

^39But the lad knew not any thing: only Jonathan and David knew the matter.

^40And Jonathan gave his artillery unto his lad, and said unto him, Go, carry them to the city.

^41And as soon as the lad was gone, David arose out of a place toward the south, and fell on his face to the ground, and bowed himself three times: and they kissed one another, and wept one with another, until David exceeded.

^42And Jonathan said to David, Go in peace, forasmuch as we have sworn both of us in the name of the Lord, saying, The Lord be between me and thee, and between my seed and thy seed for ever. And he arose and departed: and Jonathan went into the city.

XXI

^1Then came David to Nob to Ahimelech the priest: and Ahimelech was afraid at the meeting of David, and said unto him, Why art thou alone, and no man with thee?

^2And David said unto Ahimelech the priest, The king hath commanded me a business, and hath said unto me, Let no man know any thing of the business whereabout I send thee, and what I have commanded thee: and I have appointed my servants to such and such a place.

^3Now therefore what is under thine hand? give me five loaves of bread in mine hand, or what there is present.

^4And the priest answered David, and said, There is no common bread under mine hand, but there is hallowed bread; if the young men have kept themselves at least from women.

^5And David answered the priest, and said unto him, Of a truth women have been kept from us about these three days, since I came out, and the vessels of the young men are holy, and the bread is in a manner common, yea, though it were sanctified this day in the vessel.

^6So the priest gave him hallowed bread: for there was no bread there but the shewbread, that was taken from before the Lord, to put hot bread in the day when it was taken away.

^7Now a certain man of the servants of Saul was there that day, detained before the Lord; and his name was Doeg, an Edomite, the chiefest of the herdmen that belonged to Saul.

^8And David said unto Ahimelech, And is there not here under thine hand spear or sword? for I have neither brought my sword nor my weapons with me, because the king’s business required haste.

^9And the priest said, The sword of Goliath the Philistine, whom thou slewest in the valley of Elah, behold, it is here wrapped in a cloth behind the ephod: if thou wilt take that, take it: for there is no other save that here. And David said, There is none like that; give it me.

^10And David arose and fled that day for fear of Saul, and went to Achish the king of Gath.

^11And the servants of Achish said unto him, Is not this David the king of the land? did they not sing one to another of him in dances, saying, Saul hath slain his thousands, and David his ten thousands?

^12And David laid up these words in his heart, and was sore afraid of Achish the king of Gath.

^13And he changed his behaviour before them, and feigned himself mad in their hands, and scrabbled on the doors of the gate, and let his spittle fall down upon his beard.

^14Then said Achish unto his servants, Lo, ye see the man is mad: wherefore then have ye brought him to me?

^15Have I need of mad men, that ye have brought this fellow to play the mad man in my presence? shall this fellow come into my house?

XXII

^1David therefore departed thence, and escaped to the cave Adullam: and when his brethren and all his father’s house heard it, they went down thither to him.

^2And every one that was in distress, and every one that was in debt, and every one that was discontented, gathered themselves unto him; and he became a captain over them: and there were with him about four hundred men.

^3And David went thence to Mizpeh of Moab: and he said unto the king of Moab, Let my father and my mother, I pray thee, come forth, and be with you, till I know what God will do for me.

^4And he brought them before the king of Moab: and they dwelt with him all the while that David was in the hold.

^5And the prophet Gad said unto David, Abide not in the hold; depart, and get thee into the land of Judah. Then David departed, and came into the forest of Hareth.

^6When Saul heard that David was discovered, and the men that were with him, (now Saul abode in Gibeah under a tree in Ramah, having his spear in his hand, and all his servants were standing about him;)

^7Then Saul said unto his servants that stood about him, Hear now, ye Benjamites; will the son of Jesse give every one of you fields and vineyards, and make you all captains of thousands, and captains of hundreds;

^8That all of you have conspired against me, and there is none that sheweth me that my son hath made a league with the son of Jesse, and there is none of you that is sorry for me, or sheweth unto me that my son hath stirred up my servant against me, to lie in wait, as at this day?

^9Then answered Doeg the Edomite, which was set over the servants of Saul, and said, I saw the son of Jesse coming to Nob, to Ahimelech the son of Ahitub.

^10And he enquired of the Lord for him, and gave him victuals, and gave him the sword of Goliath the Philistine.

^11Then the king sent to call Ahimelech the priest, the son of Ahitub, and all his father’s house, the priests that were in Nob: and they came all of them to the king.

^12And Saul said, Hear now, thou son of Ahitub. And he answered, Here I am, my lord.

^13And Saul said unto him, Why have ye conspired against me, thou and the son of Jesse, in that thou hast given him bread, and a sword, and hast enquired of God for him, that he should rise against me, to lie in wait, as at this day?

^14Then Ahimelech answered the king, and said, And who is so faithful among all thy servants as David, which is the king’s son in law, and goeth at thy bidding, and is honourable in thine house?

^15Did I then begin to enquire of God for him? be it far from me: let not the king impute any thing unto his servant, nor to all the house of my father: for thy servant knew nothing of all this, less or more.

^16And the king said, Thou shalt surely die, Ahimelech, thou, and all thy father’s house.

^17And the king said unto the footmen that stood about him, Turn, and slay the priests of the Lord: because their hand also is with David, and because they knew when he fled, and did not shew it to me. But the servants of the king would not put forth their hand to fall upon the priests of the Lord.

^18And the king said to Doeg, Turn thou, and fall upon the priests. And Doeg the Edomite turned, and he fell upon the priests, and slew on that day fourscore and five persons that did wear a linen ephod.

^19And Nob, the city of the priests, smote he with the edge of the sword, both men and women, children and sucklings, and oxen, and asses, and sheep, with the edge of the sword.

^20And one of the sons of Ahimelech the son of Ahitub, named Abiathar, escaped, and fled after David.

^21And Abiathar shewed David that Saul had slain the Lord’s priests.

^22And David said unto Abiathar, I knew it that day, when Doeg the Edomite was there, that he would surely tell Saul: I have occasioned the death of all the persons of thy father’s house.

^23Abide thou with me, fear not: for he that seeketh my life seeketh thy life: but with me thou shalt be in safeguard.

XXIII

^1Then they told David, saying, Behold, the Philistines fight against Keilah, and they rob the threshingfloors.

^2Therefore David enquired of the Lord, saying, Shall I go and smite these Philistines? And the Lord said unto David, Go, and smite the Philistines, and save Keilah.

^3And David’s men said unto him, Behold, we be afraid here in Judah: how much more then if we come to Keilah against the armies of the Philistines?

^4Then David enquired of the Lord yet again. And the Lord answered him and said, Arise, go down to Keilah; for I will deliver the Philistines into thine hand.

^5So David and his men went to Keilah, and fought with the Philistines, and brought away their cattle, and smote them with a great slaughter. So David saved the inhabitants of Keilah.

^6And it came to pass, when Abiathar the son of Ahimelech fled to David to Keilah, that he came down with an ephod in his hand.

^7And it was told Saul that David was come to Keilah. And Saul said, God hath delivered him into mine hand; for he is shut in, by entering into a town that hath gates and bars.

^8And Saul called all the people together to war, to go down to Keilah, to besiege David and his men.

^9And David knew that Saul secretly practised mischief against him; and he said to Abiathar the priest, Bring hither the ephod.

^10Then said David, O Lord God of Israel, thy servant hath certainly heard that Saul seeketh to come to Keilah, to destroy the city for my sake.

^11Will the men of Keilah deliver me up into his hand? will Saul come down, as thy servant hath heard? O Lord God of Israel, I beseech thee, tell thy servant. And the Lord said, He will come down.

^12Then said David, Will the men of Keilah deliver me and my men into the hand of Saul? And the Lord said, They will deliver thee up.

^13Then David and his men, which were about six hundred, arose and departed out of Keilah, and went whithersoever they could go. And it was told Saul that David was escaped from Keilah; and he forbare to go forth.

^14And David abode in the wilderness in strong holds, and remained in a mountain in the wilderness of Ziph. And Saul sought him every day, but God delivered him not into his hand.

^15And David saw that Saul was come out to seek his life: and David was in the wilderness of Ziph in a wood.

^16And Jonathan Saul’s son arose, and went to David into the wood, and strengthened his hand in God.

^17And he said unto him, Fear not: for the hand of Saul my father shall not find thee; and thou shalt be king over Israel, and I shall be next unto thee; and that also Saul my father knoweth.

^18And they two made a covenant before the Lord: and David abode in the wood, and Jonathan went to his house.

^19Then came up the Ziphites to Saul to Gibeah, saying, Doth not David hide himself with us in strong holds in the wood, in the hill of Hachilah, which is on the south of Jeshimon?

^20Now therefore, O king, come down according to all the desire of thy soul to come down; and our part shall be to deliver him into the king’s hand.

^21And Saul said, Blessed be ye of the Lord; for ye have compassion on me.

^22Go, I pray you, prepare yet, and know and see his place where his haunt is, and who hath seen him there: for it is told me that he dealeth very subtilly.

^23See therefore, and take knowledge of all the lurking places where he hideth himself, and come ye again to me with the certainty, and I will go with you: and it shall come to pass, if he be in the land, that I will search him out throughout all the thousands of Judah.

^24And they arose, and went to Ziph before Saul: but David and his men were in the wilderness of Maon, in the plain on the south of Jeshimon.

^25Saul also and his men went to seek him. And they told David; wherefore he came down into a rock, and abode in the wilderness of Maon. And when Saul heard that, he pursued after David in the wilderness of Maon.

^26And Saul went on this side of the mountain, and David and his men on that side of the mountain: and David made haste to get away for fear of Saul; for Saul and his men compassed David and his men round about to take them.

^27But there came a messenger unto Saul, saying, Haste thee, and come; for the Philistines have invaded the land.

^28Wherefore Saul returned from pursuing after David, and went against the Philistines: therefore they called that place Selahammahlekoth.

^29And David went up from thence, and dwelt in strong holds at Engedi.

XXIV

^1And it came to pass, when Saul was returned from following the Philistines, that it was told him, saying, Behold, David is in the wilderness of Engedi.

^2Then Saul took three thousand chosen men out of all Israel, and went to seek David and his men upon the rocks of the wild goats.

^3And he came to the sheepcotes by the way, where was a cave; and Saul went in to cover his feet: and David and his men remained in the sides of the cave.

^4And the men of David said unto him, Behold the day of which the Lord said unto thee, Behold, I will deliver thine enemy into thine hand, that thou mayest do to him as it shall seem good unto thee. Then David arose, and cut off the skirt of Saul’s robe privily.

^5And it came to pass afterward, that David’s heart smote him, because he had cut off Saul’s skirt.

^6And he said unto his men, The Lord forbid that I should do this thing unto my master, the Lord’s anointed, to stretch forth mine hand against him, seeing he is the anointed of the Lord.

^7So David stayed his servants with these words, and suffered them not to rise against Saul. But Saul rose up out of the cave, and went on his way.

^8David also arose afterward, and went out of the cave, and cried after Saul, saying, My lord the king. And when Saul looked behind him, David stooped with his face to the earth, and bowed himself.

^9And David said to Saul, Wherefore hearest thou men’s words, saying, Behold, David seeketh thy hurt?

^10Behold, this day thine eyes have seen how that the Lord had delivered thee to day into mine hand in the cave: and some bade me kill thee: but mine eye spared thee; and I said, I will not put forth mine hand against my lord; for he is the Lord’s anointed.

^11Moreover, my father, see, yea, see the skirt of thy robe in my hand: for in that I cut off the skirt of thy robe, and killed thee not, know thou and see that there is neither evil nor transgression in mine hand, and I have not sinned against thee; yet thou huntest my soul to take it.

^12The Lord judge between me and thee, and the Lord avenge me of thee: but mine hand shall not be upon thee.

^13As saith the proverb of the ancients, Wickedness proceedeth from the wicked: but mine hand shall not be upon thee.

^14After whom is the king of Israel come out? after whom dost thou pursue? after a dead dog, after a flea.

^15The Lord therefore be judge, and judge between me and thee, and see, and plead my cause, and deliver me out of thine hand.

^16And it came to pass, when David had made an end of speaking these words unto Saul, that Saul said, Is this thy voice, my son David? And Saul lifted up his voice, and wept.

^17And he said to David, Thou art more righteous than I: for thou hast rewarded me good, whereas I have rewarded thee evil.

^18And thou hast shewed this day how that thou hast dealt well with me: forasmuch as when the Lord had delivered me into thine hand, thou killedst me not.

^19For if a man find his enemy, will he let him go well away? wherefore the Lord reward thee good for that thou hast done unto me this day.

^20And now, behold, I know well that thou shalt surely be king, and that the kingdom of Israel shall be established in thine hand.

^21Swear now therefore unto me by the Lord, that thou wilt not cut off my seed after me, and that thou wilt not destroy my name out of my father’s house.

^22And David sware unto Saul. And Saul went home; but David and his men gat them up unto the hold.

XXV

^1And Samuel died; and all the Israelites were gathered together, and lamented him, and buried him in his house at Ramah. And David arose, and went down to the wilderness of Paran.

^2And there was a man in Maon, whose possessions were in Carmel; and the man was very great, and he had three thousand sheep, and a thousand goats: and he was shearing his sheep in Carmel.

^3Now the name of the man was Nabal; and the name of his wife Abigail: and she was a woman of good understanding, and of a beautiful countenance: but the man was churlish and evil in his doings; and he was of the house of Caleb.

^4And David heard in the wilderness that Nabal did shear his sheep.

^5And David sent out ten young men, and David said unto the young men, Get you up to Carmel, and go to Nabal, and greet him in my name:

^6And thus shall ye say to him that liveth in prosperity, Peace be both to thee, and peace be to thine house, and peace be unto all that thou hast.

^7And now I have heard that thou hast shearers: now thy shepherds which were with us, we hurt them not, neither was there ought missing unto them, all the while they were in Carmel.

^8Ask thy young men, and they will shew thee. Wherefore let the young men find favour in thine eyes: for we come in a good day: give, I pray thee, whatsoever cometh to thine hand unto thy servants, and to thy son David.

^9And when David’s young men came, they spake to Nabal according to all those words in the name of David, and ceased.

^10And Nabal answered David’s servants, and said, Who is David? and who is the son of Jesse? there be many servants now a days that break away every man from his master.

^11Shall I then take my bread, and my water, and my flesh that I have killed for my shearers, and give it unto men, whom I know not whence they be?

^12So David’s young men turned their way, and went again, and came and told him all those sayings.

^13And David said unto his men, Gird ye on every man his sword. And they girded on every man his sword; and David also girded on his sword: and there went up after David about four hundred men; and two hundred abode by the stuff.

^14But one of the young men told Abigail, Nabal’s wife, saying, Behold, David sent messengers out of the wilderness to salute our master; and he railed on them.

^15But the men were very good unto us, and we were not hurt, neither missed we any thing, as long as we were conversant with them, when we were in the fields:

^16They were a wall unto us both by night and day, all the while we were with them keeping the sheep.

^17Now therefore know and consider what thou wilt do; for evil is determined against our master, and against all his household: for he is such a son of Belial, that a man cannot speak to him.

^18Then Abigail made haste, and took two hundred loaves, and two bottles of wine, and five sheep ready dressed, and five measures of parched corn, and an hundred clusters of raisins, and two hundred cakes of figs, and laid them on asses.

^19And she said unto her servants, Go on before me; behold, I come after you. But she told not her husband Nabal.

^20And it was so, as she rode on the ass, that she came down by the covert on the hill, and, behold, David and his men came down against her; and she met them.

^21Now David had said, Surely in vain have I kept all that this fellow hath in the wilderness, so that nothing was missed of all that pertained unto him: and he hath requited me evil for good.

^22So and more also do God unto the enemies of David, if I leave of all that pertain to him by the morning light any that pisseth against the wall.

^23And when Abigail saw David, she hasted, and lighted off the ass, and fell before David on her face, and bowed herself to the ground,

^24And fell at his feet, and said, Upon me, my lord, upon me let this iniquity be: and let thine handmaid, I pray thee, speak in thine audience, and hear the words of thine handmaid.

^25Let not my lord, I pray thee, regard this man of Belial, even Nabal: for as his name is, so is he; Nabal is his name, and folly is with him: but I thine handmaid saw not the young men of my lord, whom thou didst send.

^26Now therefore, my lord, as the Lord liveth, and as thy soul liveth, seeing the Lord hath withholden thee from coming to shed blood, and from avenging thyself with thine own hand, now let thine enemies, and they that seek evil to my lord, be as Nabal.

^27And now this blessing which thine handmaid hath brought unto my lord, let it even be given unto the young men that follow my lord.

^28I pray thee, forgive the trespass of thine handmaid: for the Lord will certainly make my lord a sure house; because my lord fighteth the battles of the Lord, and evil hath not been found in thee all thy days.

^29Yet a man is risen to pursue thee, and to seek thy soul: but the soul of my lord shall be bound in the bundle of life with the Lord thy God; and the souls of thine enemies, them shall he sling out, as out of the middle of a sling.

^30And it shall come to pass, when the Lord shall have done to my lord according to all the good that he hath spoken concerning thee, and shall have appointed thee ruler over Israel;

^31That this shall be no grief unto thee, nor offence of heart unto my lord, either that thou hast shed blood causeless, or that my lord hath avenged himself: but when the Lord shall have dealt well with my lord, then remember thine handmaid.

^32And David said to Abigail, Blessed be the Lord God of Israel, which sent thee this day to meet me:

^33And blessed be thy advice, and blessed be thou, which hast kept me this day from coming to shed blood, and from avenging myself with mine own hand.

^34For in very deed, as the Lord God of Israel liveth, which hath kept me back from hurting thee, except thou hadst hasted and come to meet me, surely there had not been left unto Nabal by the morning light any that pisseth against the wall.

^35So David received of her hand that which she had brought him, and said unto her, Go up in peace to thine house; see, I have hearkened to thy voice, and have accepted thy person.

^36And Abigail came to Nabal; and, behold, he held a feast in his house, like the feast of a king; and Nabal’s heart was merry within him, for he was very drunken: wherefore she told him nothing, less or more, until the morning light.

^37But it came to pass in the morning, when the wine was gone out of Nabal, and his wife had told him these things, that his heart died within him, and he became as a stone.

^38And it came to pass about ten days after, that the Lord smote Nabal, that he died.

^39And when David heard that Nabal was dead, he said, Blessed be the Lord, that hath pleaded the cause of my reproach from the hand of Nabal, and hath kept his servant from evil: for the Lord hath returned the wickedness of Nabal upon his own head. And David sent and communed with Abigail, to take her to him to wife.

^40And when the servants of David were come to Abigail to Carmel, they spake unto her, saying, David sent us unto thee, to take thee to him to wife.

^41And she arose, and bowed herself on her face to the earth, and said, Behold, let thine handmaid be a servant to wash the feet of the servants of my lord.

^42And Abigail hasted, and arose and rode upon an ass, with five damsels of hers that went after her; and she went after the messengers of David, and became his wife.

^43David also took Ahinoam of Jezreel; and they were also both of them his wives.

^44But Saul had given Michal his daughter, David’s wife, to Phalti the son of Laish, which was of Gallim.

XXVI

^1And the Ziphites came unto Saul to Gibeah, saying, Doth not David hide himself in the hill of Hachilah, which is before Jeshimon?

^2Then Saul arose, and went down to the wilderness of Ziph, having three thousand chosen men of Israel with him, to seek David in the wilderness of Ziph.

^3And Saul pitched in the hill of Hachilah, which is before Jeshimon, by the way. But David abode in the wilderness, and he saw that Saul came after him into the wilderness.

^4David therefore sent out spies, and understood that Saul was come in very deed.

^5And David arose, and came to the place where Saul had pitched: and David beheld the place where Saul lay, and Abner the son of Ner, the captain of his host: and Saul lay in the trench, and the people pitched round about him.

^6Then answered David and said to Ahimelech the Hittite, and to Abishai the son of Zeruiah, brother to Joab, saying, Who will go down with me to Saul to the camp? And Abishai said, I will go down with thee.

^7So David and Abishai came to the people by night: and, behold, Saul lay sleeping within the trench, and his spear stuck in the ground at his bolster: but Abner and the people lay round about him.

^8Then said Abishai to David, God hath delivered thine enemy into thine hand this day: now therefore let me smite him, I pray thee, with the spear even to the earth at once, and I will not smite him the second time.

^9And David said to Abishai, Destroy him not: for who can stretch forth his hand against the Lord’s anointed, and be guiltless?

^10David said furthermore, As the Lord liveth, the Lord shall smite him; or his day shall come to die; or he shall descend into battle, and perish.

^11The Lord forbid that I should stretch forth mine hand against the Lord’s anointed: but, I pray thee, take thou now the spear that is at his bolster, and the cruse of water, and let us go.

^12So David took the spear and the cruse of water from Saul’s bolster; and they gat them away, and no man saw it, nor knew it, neither awaked: for they were all asleep; because a deep sleep from the Lord was fallen upon them.

^13Then David went over to the other side, and stood on the top of an hill afar off; a great space being between them:

^14And David cried to the people, and to Abner the son of Ner, saying, Answerest thou not, Abner? Then Abner answered and said, Who art thou that criest to the king?

^15And David said to Abner, Art not thou a valiant man? and who is like to thee in Israel? wherefore then hast thou not kept thy lord the king? for there came one of the people in to destroy the king thy lord.

^16This thing is not good that thou hast done. As the Lord liveth, ye are worthy to die, because ye have not kept your master, the Lord’s anointed. And now see where the king’s spear is, and the cruse of water that was at his bolster.

^17And Saul knew David’s voice, and said, Is this thy voice, my son David? And David said, It is my voice, my lord, O king.

^18And he said, Wherefore doth my lord thus pursue after his servant? for what have I done? or what evil is in mine hand?

^19Now therefore, I pray thee, let my lord the king hear the words of his servant. If the Lord have stirred thee up against me, let him accept an offering: but if they be the children of men, cursed be they before the Lord; for they have driven me out this day from abiding in the inheritance of the Lord, saying, Go, serve other gods.

^20Now therefore, let not my blood fall to the earth before the face of the Lord: for the king of Israel is come out to seek a flea, as when one doth hunt a partridge in the mountains.

^21Then said Saul, I have sinned: return, my son David: for I will no more do thee harm, because my soul was precious in thine eyes this day: behold, I have played the fool, and have erred exceedingly.

^22And David answered and said, Behold the king’s spear! and let one of the young men come over and fetch it.

^23The Lord render to every man his righteousness and his faithfulness; for the Lord delivered thee into my hand to day, but I would not stretch forth mine hand against the Lord’s anointed.

^24And, behold, as thy life was much set by this day in mine eyes, so let my life be much set by in the eyes of the Lord, and let him deliver me out of all tribulation.

^25Then Saul said to David, Blessed be thou, my son David: thou shalt both do great things, and also shalt still prevail. So David went on his way, and Saul returned to his place.

XXVII

^1And David said in his heart, I shall now perish one day by the hand of Saul: there is nothing better for me than that I should speedily escape into the land of the Philistines; and Saul shall despair of me, to seek me any more in any coast of Israel: so shall I escape out of his hand.

^2And David arose, and he passed over with the six hundred men that were with him unto Achish, the son of Maoch, king of Gath.

^3And David dwelt with Achish at Gath, he and his men, every man with his household, even David with his two wives, Ahinoam the Jezreelitess, and Abigail the Carmelitess, Nabal’s wife.

^4And it was told Saul that David was fled to Gath: and he sought no more again for him.

^5And David said unto Achish, If I have now found grace in thine eyes, let them give me a place in some town in the country, that I may dwell there: for why should thy servant dwell in the royal city with thee?

^6Then Achish gave him Ziklag that day: wherefore Ziklag pertaineth unto the kings of Judah unto this day.

^7And the time that David dwelt in the country of the Philistines was a full year and four months.

^8And David and his men went up, and invaded the Geshurites, and the Gezrites, and the Amalekites: for those nations were of old the inhabitants of the land, as thou goest to Shur, even unto the land of Egypt.

^9And David smote the land, and left neither man nor woman alive, and took away the sheep, and the oxen, and the asses, and the camels, and the apparel, and returned, and came to Achish.

^10And Achish said, Whither have ye made a road to day? And David said, Against the south of Judah, and against the south of the Jerahmeelites, and against the south of the Kenites.

^11And David saved neither man nor woman alive, to bring tidings to Gath, saying, Lest they should tell on us, saying, So did David, and so will be his manner all the while he dwelleth in the country of the Philistines.

^12And Achish believed David, saying, He hath made his people Israel utterly to abhor him; therefore he shall be my servant for ever.

XXVIII

^1And it came to pass in those days, that the Philistines gathered their armies together for warfare, to fight with Israel. And Achish said unto David, Know thou assuredly, that thou shalt go out with me to battle, thou and thy men.

^2And David said to Achish, Surely thou shalt know what thy servant can do. And Achish said to David, Therefore will I make thee keeper of mine head for ever.

^3Now Samuel was dead, and all Israel had lamented him, and buried him in Ramah, even in his own city. And Saul had put away those that had familiar spirits, and the wizards, out of the land.

^4And the Philistines gathered themselves together, and came and pitched in Shunem: and Saul gathered all Israel together, and they pitched in Gilboa.

^5And when Saul saw the host of the Philistines, he was afraid, and his heart greatly trembled.

^6And when Saul enquired of the Lord, the Lord answered him not, neither by dreams, nor by Urim, nor by prophets.

^7Then said Saul unto his servants, Seek me a woman that hath a familiar spirit, that I may go to her, and enquire of her. And his servants said to him, Behold, there is a woman that hath a familiar spirit at Endor.

^8And Saul disguised himself, and put on other raiment, and he went, and two men with him, and they came to the woman by night: and he said, I pray thee, divine unto me by the familiar spirit, and bring me him up, whom I shall name unto thee.

^9And the woman said unto him, Behold, thou knowest what Saul hath done, how he hath cut off those that have familiar spirits, and the wizards, out of the land: wherefore then layest thou a snare for my life, to cause me to die?

^10And Saul sware to her by the Lord, saying, As the Lord liveth, there shall no punishment happen to thee for this thing.

^11Then said the woman, Whom shall I bring up unto thee? And he said, Bring me up Samuel.

^12And when the woman saw Samuel, she cried with a loud voice: and the woman spake to Saul, saying, Why hast thou deceived me? for thou art Saul.

^13And the king said unto her, Be not afraid: for what sawest thou? And the woman said unto Saul, I saw gods ascending out of the earth.

^14And he said unto her, What form is he of? And she said, An old man cometh up; and he is covered with a mantle. And Saul perceived that it was Samuel, and he stooped with his face to the ground, and bowed himself.

^15And Samuel said to Saul, Why hast thou disquieted me, to bring me up? And Saul answered, I am sore distressed; for the Philistines make war against me, and God is departed from me, and answereth me no more, neither by prophets, nor by dreams: therefore I have called thee, that thou mayest make known unto me what I shall do.

^16Then said Samuel, Wherefore then dost thou ask of me, seeing the Lord is departed from thee, and is become thine enemy?

^17And the Lord hath done to him, as he spake by me: for the Lord hath rent the kingdom out of thine hand, and given it to thy neighbour, even to David:

^18Because thou obeyedst not the voice of the Lord, nor executedst his fierce wrath upon Amalek, therefore hath the Lord done this thing unto thee this day.

^19Moreover the Lord will also deliver Israel with thee into the hand of the Philistines: and to morrow shalt thou and thy sons be with me: the Lord also shall deliver the host of Israel into the hand of the Philistines.

^20Then Saul fell straightway all along on the earth, and was sore afraid, because of the words of Samuel: and there was no strength in him; for he had eaten no bread all the day, nor all the night.

^21And the woman came unto Saul, and saw that he was sore troubled, and said unto him, Behold, thine handmaid hath obeyed thy voice, and I have put my life in my hand, and have hearkened unto thy words which thou spakest unto me.

^22Now therefore, I pray thee, hearken thou also unto the voice of thine handmaid, and let me set a morsel of bread before thee; and eat, that thou mayest have strength, when thou goest on thy way.

^23But he refused, and said, I will not eat. But his servants, together with the woman, compelled him; and he hearkened unto their voice. So he arose from the earth, and sat upon the bed.

^24And the woman had a fat calf in the house; and she hasted, and killed it, and took flour, and kneaded it, and did bake unleavened bread thereof:

^25And she brought it before Saul, and before his servants; and they did eat. Then they rose up, and went away that night.

XXIX

^1Now the Philistines gathered together all their armies to Aphek: and the Israelites pitched by a fountain which is in Jezreel.

^2And the lords of the Philistines passed on by hundreds, and by thousands: but David and his men passed on in the rereward with Achish.

^3Then said the princes of the Philistines, What do these Hebrews here? And Achish said unto the princes of the Philistines, Is not this David, the servant of Saul the king of Israel, which hath been with me these days, or these years, and I have found no fault in him since he fell unto me unto this day?

^4And the princes of the Philistines were wroth with him; and the princes of the Philistines said unto him, Make this fellow return, that he may go again to his place which thou hast appointed him, and let him not go down with us to battle, lest in the battle he be an adversary to us: for wherewith should he reconcile himself unto his master? should it not be with the heads of these men?

^5Is not this David, of whom they sang one to another in dances, saying, Saul slew his thousands, and David his ten thousands?

^6Then Achish called David, and said unto him, Surely, as the Lord liveth, thou hast been upright, and thy going out and thy coming in with me in the host is good in my sight: for I have not found evil in thee since the day of thy coming unto me unto this day: nevertheless the lords favour thee not.

^7Wherefore now return, and go in peace, that thou displease not the lords of the Philistines.

^8And David said unto Achish, But what have I done? and what hast thou found in thy servant so long as I have been with thee unto this day, that I may not go fight against the enemies of my lord the king?

^9And Achish answered and said to David, I know that thou art good in my sight, as an angel of God: notwithstanding the princes of the Philistines have said, He shall not go up with us to the battle.

^10Wherefore now rise up early in the morning with thy master’s servants that are come with thee: and as soon as ye be up early in the morning, and have light, depart.

^11So David and his men rose up early to depart in the morning, to return into the land of the Philistines. And the Philistines went up to Jezreel.

XXX

^1And it came to pass, when David and his men were come to Ziklag on the third day, that the Amalekites had invaded the south, and Ziklag, and smitten Ziklag, and burned it with fire;

^2And had taken the women captives, that were therein: they slew not any, either great or small, but carried them away, and went on their way.

^3So David and his men came to the city, and, behold, it was burned with fire; and their wives, and their sons, and their daughters, were taken captives.

^4Then David and the people that were with him lifted up their voice and wept, until they had no more power to weep.

^5And David’s two wives were taken captives, Ahinoam the Jezreelitess, and Abigail the wife of Nabal the Carmelite.

^6And David was greatly distressed; for the people spake of stoning him, because the soul of all the people was grieved, every man for his sons and for his daughters: but David encouraged himself in the Lord his God.

^7And David said to Abiathar the priest, Ahimelech’s son, I pray thee, bring me hither the ephod. And Abiathar brought thither the ephod to David.

^8And David enquired at the Lord, saying, Shall I pursue after this troop? shall I overtake them? And he answered him, Pursue: for thou shalt surely overtake them, and without fail recover all.

^9So David went, he and the six hundred men that were with him, and came to the brook Besor, where those that were left behind stayed.

^10But David pursued, he and four hundred men: for two hundred abode behind, which were so faint that they could not go over the brook Besor.

^11And they found an Egyptian in the field, and brought him to David, and gave him bread, and he did eat; and they made him drink water;

^12And they gave him a piece of a cake of figs, and two clusters of raisins: and when he had eaten, his spirit came again to him: for he had eaten no bread, nor drunk any water, three days and three nights.

^13And David said unto him, To whom belongest thou? and whence art thou? And he said, I am a young man of Egypt, servant to an Amalekite; and my master left me, because three days agone I fell sick.

^14We made an invasion upon the south of the Cherethites, and upon the coast which belongeth to Judah, and upon the south of Caleb; and we burned Ziklag with fire.

^15And David said to him, Canst thou bring me down to this company? And he said, Swear unto me by God, that thou wilt neither kill me, nor deliver me into the hands of my master, and I will bring thee down to this company.

^16And when he had brought him down, behold, they were spread abroad upon all the earth, eating and drinking, and dancing, because of all the great spoil that they had taken out of the land of the Philistines, and out of the land of Judah.

^17And David smote them from the twilight even unto the evening of the next day: and there escaped not a man of them, save four hundred young men, which rode upon camels, and fled.

^18And David recovered all that the Amalekites had carried away: and David rescued his two wives.

^19And there was nothing lacking to them, neither small nor great, neither sons nor daughters, neither spoil, nor any thing that they had taken to them: David recovered all.

^20And David took all the flocks and the herds, which they drave before those other cattle, and said, This is David’s spoil.

^21And David came to the two hundred men, which were so faint that they could not follow David, whom they had made also to abide at the brook Besor: and they went forth to meet David, and to meet the people that were with him: and when David came near to the people, he saluted them.

^22Then answered all the wicked men and men of Belial, of those that went with David, and said, Because they went not with us, we will not give them ought of the spoil that we have recovered, save to every man his wife and his children, that they may lead them away, and depart.

^23Then said David, Ye shall not do so, my brethren, with that which the Lord hath given us, who hath preserved us, and delivered the company that came against us into our hand.

^24For who will hearken unto you in this matter? but as his part is that goeth down to the battle, so shall his part be that tarrieth by the stuff: they shall part alike.

^25And it was so from that day forward, that he made it a statute and an ordinance for Israel unto this day.

^26And when David came to Ziklag, he sent of the spoil unto the elders of Judah, even to his friends, saying, Behold a present for you of the spoil of the enemies of the Lord;

^27To them which were in Bethel, and to them which were in south Ramoth, and to them which were in Jattir,

^28And to them which were in Aroer, and to them which were in Siphmoth, and to them which were in Eshtemoa,

^29And to them which were in Rachal, and to them which were in the cities of the Jerahmeelites, and to them which were in the cities of the Kenites,

^30And to them which were in Hormah, and to them which were in Chorashan, and to them which were in Athach,

^31And to them which were in Hebron, and to all the places where David himself and his men were wont to haunt.

XXXI

^1Now the Philistines fought against Israel: and the men of Israel fled from before the Philistines, and fell down slain in mount Gilboa.

^2And the Philistines followed hard upon Saul and upon his sons; and the Philistines slew Jonathan, and Abinadab, and Melchishua, Saul’s sons.

^3And the battle went sore against Saul, and the archers hit him; and he was sore wounded of the archers.

^4Then said Saul unto his armourbearer, Draw thy sword, and thrust me through therewith; lest these uncircumcised come and thrust me through, and abuse me. But his armourbearer would not; for he was sore afraid. Therefore Saul took a sword, and fell upon it.

^5And when his armourbearer saw that Saul was dead, he fell likewise upon his sword, and died with him.

^6So Saul died, and his three sons, and his armourbearer, and all his men, that same day together.

^7And when the men of Israel that were on the other side of the valley, and they that were on the other side Jordan, saw that the men of Israel fled, and that Saul and his sons were dead, they forsook the cities, and fled; and the Philistines came and dwelt in them.

^8And it came to pass on the morrow, when the Philistines came to strip the slain, that they found Saul and his three sons fallen in mount Gilboa.

^9And they cut off his head, and stripped off his armour, and sent into the land of the Philistines round about, to publish it in the house of their idols, and among the people.

^10And they put his armour in the house of Ashtaroth: and they fastened his body to the wall of Bethshan.

^11And when the inhabitants of Jabeshgilead heard of that which the Philistines had done to Saul;

^12All the valiant men arose, and went all night, and took the body of Saul and the bodies of his sons from the wall of Bethshan, and came to Jabesh, and burnt them there.

^13And they took their bones, and buried them under a tree at Jabesh, and fasted seven days.

II Chronicles

The Second Book of

Chronicles

I

^1And Solomon the son of David was strengthened in his kingdom, and the Lord his God was with him, and magnified him exceedingly.

^2Then Solomon spake unto all Israel, to the captains of thousands and of hundreds, and to the judges, and to every governor in all Israel, the chief of the fathers.

^3So Solomon, and all the congregation with him, went to the high place that was at Gibeon; for there was the tabernacle of the congregation of God, which Moses the servant of the Lord had made in the wilderness.

^4But the ark of God had David brought up from Kirjathjearim to the place which David had prepared for it: for he had pitched a tent for it at Jerusalem.

^5Moreover the brasen altar, that Bezaleel the son of Uri, the son of Hur, had made, he put before the tabernacle of the Lord: and Solomon and the congregation sought unto it.

^6And Solomon went up thither to the brasen altar before the Lord, which was at the tabernacle of the congregation, and offered a thousand burnt offerings upon it.

^7In that night did God appear unto Solomon, and said unto him, Ask what I shall give thee.

^8And Solomon said unto God, Thou hast shewed great mercy unto David my father, and hast made me to reign in his stead.

^9Now, O Lord God, let thy promise unto David my father be established: for thou hast made me king over a people like the dust of the earth in multitude.

^10Give me now wisdom and knowledge, that I may go out and come in before this people: for who can judge this thy people, that is so great?

^11And God said to Solomon, Because this was in thine heart, and thou hast not asked riches, wealth, or honour, nor the life of thine enemies, neither yet hast asked long life; but hast asked wisdom and knowledge for thyself, that thou mayest judge my people, over whom I have made thee king:

^12Wisdom and knowledge is granted unto thee; and I will give thee riches, and wealth, and honour, such as none of the kings have had that have been before thee, neither shall there any after thee have the like.

^13Then Solomon came from his journey to the high place that was at Gibeon to Jerusalem, from before the tabernacle of the congregation, and reigned over Israel.

^14And Solomon gathered chariots and horsemen: and he had a thousand and four hundred chariots, and twelve thousand horsemen, which he placed in the chariot cities, and with the king at Jerusalem.

^15And the king made silver and gold at Jerusalem as plenteous as stones, and cedar trees made he as the sycomore trees that are in the vale for abundance.

^16And Solomon had horses brought out of Egypt, and linen yarn: the king’s merchants received the linen yarn at a price.

^17And they fetched up, and brought forth out of Egypt a chariot for six hundred shekels of silver, and an horse for an hundred and fifty: and so brought they out horses for all the kings of the Hittites, and for the kings of Syria, by their means.

II

^1And Solomon determined to build an house for the name of the Lord, and an house for his kingdom.

^2And Solomon told out threescore and ten thousand men to bear burdens, and fourscore thousand to hew in the mountain, and three thousand and six hundred to oversee them.

^3And Solomon sent to Huram the king of Tyre, saying, As thou didst deal with David my father, and didst send him cedars to build him an house to dwell therein, even so deal with me.

^4Behold, I build an house to the name of the Lord my God, to dedicate it to him, and to burn before him sweet incense, and for the continual shewbread, and for the burnt offerings morning and evening, on the sabbaths, and on the new moons, and on the solemn feasts of the Lord our God. This is an ordinance for ever to Israel.

^5And the house which I build is great: for great is our God above all gods.

^6But who is able to build him an house, seeing the heaven and heaven of heavens cannot contain him? who am I then, that I should build him an house, save only to burn sacrifice before him?

^7Send me now therefore a man cunning to work in gold, and in silver, and in brass, and in iron, and in purple, and crimson, and blue, and that can skill to grave with the cunning men that are with me in Judah and in Jerusalem, whom David my father did provide.

^8Send me also cedar trees, fir trees, and algum trees, out of Lebanon: for I know that thy servants can skill to cut timber in Lebanon; and, behold, my servants shall be with thy servants,

^9Even to prepare me timber in abundance: for the house which I am about to build shall be wonderful great.

^10And, behold, I will give to thy servants, the hewers that cut timber, twenty thousand measures of beaten wheat, and twenty thousand measures of barley, and twenty thousand baths of wine, and twenty thousand baths of oil.

^11Then Huram the king of Tyre answered in writing, which he sent to Solomon, Because the Lord hath loved his people, he hath made thee king over them.

^12Huram said moreover, Blessed be the Lord God of Israel, that made heaven and earth, who hath given to David the king a wise son, endued with prudence and understanding, that might build an house for the Lord, and an house for his kingdom.

^13And now I have sent a cunning man, endued with understanding, of Huram my father’s,

^14The son of a woman of the daughters of Dan, and his father was a man of Tyre, skilful to work in gold, and in silver, in brass, in iron, in stone, and in timber, in purple, in blue, and in fine linen, and in crimson; also to grave any manner of graving, and to find out every device which shall be put to him, with thy cunning men, and with the cunning men of my lord David thy father.

^15Now therefore the wheat, and the barley, the oil, and the wine, which my lord hath spoken of, let him send unto his servants:

^16And we will cut wood out of Lebanon, as much as thou shalt need: and we will bring it to thee in floats by sea to Joppa; and thou shalt carry it up to Jerusalem.

^17And Solomon numbered all the strangers that were in the land of Israel, after the numbering wherewith David his father had numbered them; and they were found an hundred and fifty thousand and three thousand and six hundred.

^18And he set threescore and ten thousand of them to be bearers of burdens, and fourscore thousand to be hewers in the mountain, and three thousand and six hundred overseers to set the people a work.

III

^1Then Solomon began to build the house of the Lord at Jerusalem in mount Moriah, where the Lord appeared unto David his father, in the place that David had prepared in the threshingfloor of Ornan the Jebusite.

^2And he began to build in the second day of the second month, in the fourth year of his reign.

^3Now these are the things wherein Solomon was instructed for the building of the house of God. The length by cubits after the first measure was threescore cubits, and the breadth twenty cubits.

^4And the porch that was in the front of the house, the length of it was according to the breadth of the house, twenty cubits, and the height was an hundred and twenty: and he overlaid it within with pure gold.

^5And the greater house he cieled with fir tree, which he overlaid with fine gold, and set thereon palm trees and chains.

^6And he garnished the house with precious stones for beauty: and the gold was gold of Parvaim.

^7He overlaid also the house, the beams, the posts, and the walls thereof, and the doors thereof, with gold; and graved cherubims on the walls.

^8And he made the most holy house, the length whereof was according to the breadth of the house, twenty cubits, and the breadth thereof twenty cubits: and he overlaid it with fine gold, amounting to six hundred talents.

^9And the weight of the nails was fifty shekels of gold. And he overlaid the upper chambers with gold.

^10And in the most holy house he made two cherubims of image work, and overlaid them with gold.

^11And the wings of the cherubims were twenty cubits long: one wing of the one cherub was five cubits, reaching to the wall of the house: and the other wing was likewise five cubits, reaching to the wing of the other cherub.

^12And one wing of the other cherub was five cubits, reaching to the wall of the house: and the other wing was five cubits also, joining to the wing of the other cherub.

^13The wings of these cherubims spread themselves forth twenty cubits: and they stood on their feet, and their faces were inward.

^14And he made the vail of blue, and purple, and crimson, and fine linen, and wrought cherubims thereon.

^15Also he made before the house two pillars of thirty and five cubits high, and the chapiter that was on the top of each of them was five cubits.

^16And he made chains, as in the oracle, and put them on the heads of the pillars; and made an hundred pomegranates, and put them on the chains.

^17And he reared up the pillars before the temple, one on the right hand, and the other on the left; and called the name of that on the right hand Jachin, and the name of that on the left Boaz.

IV

^1Moreover he made an altar of brass, twenty cubits the length thereof, and twenty cubits the breadth thereof, and ten cubits the height thereof.

^2Also he made a molten sea of ten cubits from brim to brim, round in compass, and five cubits the height thereof; and a line of thirty cubits did compass it round about.

^3And under it was the similitude of oxen, which did compass it round about: ten in a cubit, compassing the sea round about. Two rows of oxen were cast, when it was cast.

^4It stood upon twelve oxen, three looking toward the north, and three looking toward the west, and three looking toward the south, and three looking toward the east: and the sea was set above upon them, and all their hinder parts were inward.

^5And the thickness of it was an handbreadth, and the brim of it like the work of the brim of a cup, with flowers of lilies; and it received and held three thousand baths.

^6He made also ten lavers, and put five on the right hand, and five on the left, to wash in them: such things as they offered for the burnt offering they washed in them; but the sea was for the priests to wash in.

^7And he made ten candlesticks of gold according to their form, and set them in the temple, five on the right hand, and five on the left.

^8He made also ten tables, and placed them in the temple, five on the right side, and five on the left. And he made an hundred basons of gold.

^9Furthermore he made the court of the priests, and the great court, and doors for the court, and overlaid the doors of them with brass.

^10And he set the sea on the right side of the east end, over against the south.

^11And Huram made the pots, and the shovels, and the basons. And Huram finished the work that he was to make for king Solomon for the house of God;

^12To wit, the two pillars, and the pommels, and the chapiters which were on the top of the two pillars, and the two wreaths to cover the two pommels of the chapiters which were on the top of the pillars;

^13And four hundred pomegranates on the two wreaths; two rows of pomegranates on each wreath, to cover the two pommels of the chapiters which were upon the pillars.

^14He made also bases, and lavers made he upon the bases;

^15One sea, and twelve oxen under it.

^16The pots also, and the shovels, and the fleshhooks, and all their instruments, did Huram his father make to king Solomon for the house of the Lord of bright brass.

^17In the plain of Jordan did the king cast them, in the clay ground between Succoth and Zeredathah.

^18Thus Solomon made all these vessels in great abundance: for the weight of the brass could not be found out.

^19And Solomon made all the vessels that were for the house of God, the golden altar also, and the tables whereon the shewbread was set;

^20Moreover the candlesticks with their lamps, that they should burn after the manner before the oracle, of pure gold;

^21And the flowers, and the lamps, and the tongs, made he of gold, and that perfect gold;

^22And the snuffers, and the basons, and the spoons, and the censers, of pure gold: and the entry of the house, the inner doors thereof for the most holy place, and the doors of the house of the temple, were of gold.

V

^1Thus all the work that Solomon made for the house of the Lord was finished: and Solomon brought in all the things that David his father had dedicated; and the silver, and the gold, and all the instruments, put he among the treasures of the house of God.

^2Then Solomon assembled the elders of Israel, and all the heads of the tribes, the chief of the fathers of the children of Israel, unto Jerusalem, to bring up the ark of the covenant of the Lord out of the city of David, which is Zion.

^3Wherefore all the men of Israel assembled themselves unto the king in the feast which was in the seventh month.

^4And all the elders of Israel came; and the Levites took up the ark.

^5And they brought up the ark, and the tabernacle of the congregation, and all the holy vessels that were in the tabernacle, these did the priests and the Levites bring up.

^6Also king Solomon, and all the congregation of Israel that were assembled unto him before the ark, sacrificed sheep and oxen, which could not be told nor numbered for multitude.

^7And the priests brought in the ark of the covenant of the Lord unto his place, to the oracle of the house, into the most holy place, even under the wings of the cherubims:

^8For the cherubims spread forth their wings over the place of the ark, and the cherubims covered the ark and the staves thereof above.

^9And they drew out the staves of the ark, that the ends of the staves were seen from the ark before the oracle; but they were not seen without. And there it is unto this day.

^10There was nothing in the ark save the two tables which Moses put therein at Horeb, when the Lord made a covenant with the children of Israel, when they came out of Egypt.

^11And it came to pass, when the priests were come out of the holy place: (for all the priests that were present were sanctified, and did not then wait by course:

^12Also the Levites which were the singers, all of them of Asaph, of Heman, of Jeduthun, with their sons and their brethren, being arrayed in white linen, having cymbals and psalteries and harps, stood at the east end of the altar, and with them an hundred and twenty priests sounding with trumpets:)

^13It came even to pass, as the trumpeters and singers were as one, to make one sound to be heard in praising and thanking the Lord; and when they lifted up their voice with the trumpets and cymbals and instruments of musick, and praised the Lord, saying, For he is good; for his mercy endureth for ever: that then the house was filled with a cloud, even the house of the Lord;

^14So that the priests could not stand to minister by reason of the cloud: for the glory of the Lord had filled the house of God.

VI

^1Then said Solomon, The Lord hath said that he would dwell in the thick darkness.

^2But I have built an house of habitation for thee, and a place for thy dwelling for ever.

^3And the king turned his face, and blessed the whole congregation of Israel: and all the congregation of Israel stood.

^4And he said, Blessed be the Lord God of Israel, who hath with his hands fulfilled that which he spake with his mouth to my father David, saying,

^5Since the day that I brought forth my people out of the land of Egypt I chose no city among all the tribes of Israel to build an house in, that my name might be there; neither chose I any man to be a ruler over my people Israel:

^6But I have chosen Jerusalem, that my name might be there; and have chosen David to be over my people Israel.

^7Now it was in the heart of David my father to build an house for the name of the Lord God of Israel.

^8But the Lord said to David my father, Forasmuch as it was in thine heart to build an house for my name, thou didst well in that it was in thine heart:

^9Notwithstanding thou shalt not build the house; but thy son which shall come forth out of thy loins, he shall build the house for my name.

^10The Lord therefore hath performed his word that he hath spoken: for I am risen up in the room of David my father, and am set on the throne of Israel, as the Lord promised, and have built the house for the name of the Lord God of Israel.

^11And in it have I put the ark, wherein is the covenant of the Lord, that he made with the children of Israel.

^12And he stood before the altar of the Lord in the presence of all the congregation of Israel, and spread forth his hands:

^13For Solomon had made a brasen scaffold of five cubits long, and five cubits broad, and three cubits high, and had set it in the midst of the court: and upon it he stood, and kneeled down upon his knees before all the congregation of Israel, and spread forth his hands toward heaven.

^14And said, O Lord God of Israel, there is no God like thee in the heaven, nor in the earth; which keepest covenant, and shewest mercy unto thy servants, that walk before thee with all their hearts:

^15Thou which hast kept with thy servant David my father that which thou hast promised him; and spakest with thy mouth, and hast fulfilled it with thine hand, as it is this day.

^16Now therefore, O Lord God of Israel, keep with thy servant David my father that which thou hast promised him, saying, There shall not fail thee a man in my sight to sit upon the throne of Israel; yet so that thy children take heed to their way to walk in my law, as thou hast walked before me.

^17Now then, O Lord God of Israel, let thy word be verified, which thou hast spoken unto thy servant David.

^18But will God in very deed dwell with men on the earth? behold, heaven and the heaven of heavens cannot contain thee; how much less this house which I have built!

^19Have respect therefore to the prayer of thy servant, and to his supplication, O Lord my God, to hearken unto the cry and the prayer which thy servant prayeth before thee:

^20That thine eyes may be open upon this house day and night, upon the place whereof thou hast said that thou wouldest put thy name there; to hearken unto the prayer which thy servant prayeth toward this place.

^21Hearken therefore unto the supplications of thy servant, and of thy people Israel, which they shall make toward this place: hear thou from thy dwelling place, even from heaven; and when thou hearest, forgive.

^22If a man sin against his neighbour, and an oath be laid upon him to make him swear, and the oath come before thine altar in this house;

^23Then hear thou from heaven, and do, and judge thy servants, by requiting the wicked, by recompensing his way upon his own head; and by justifying the righteous, by giving him according to his righteousness.

^24And if thy people Israel be put to the worse before the enemy, because they have sinned against thee; and shall return and confess thy name, and pray and make supplication before thee in this house;

^25Then hear thou from the heavens, and forgive the sin of thy people Israel, and bring them again unto the land which thou gavest to them and to their fathers.

^26When the heaven is shut up, and there is no rain, because they have sinned against thee; yet if they pray toward this place, and confess thy name, and turn from their sin, when thou dost afflict them;

^27Then hear thou from heaven, and forgive the sin of thy servants, and of thy people Israel, when thou hast taught them the good way, wherein they should walk; and send rain upon thy land, which thou hast given unto thy people for an inheritance.

^28If there be dearth in the land, if there be pestilence, if there be blasting, or mildew, locusts, or caterpillers; if their enemies besiege them in the cities of their land; whatsoever sore or whatsoever sickness there be:

^29Then what prayer or what supplication soever shall be made of any man, or of all thy people Israel, when every one shall know his own sore and his own grief, and shall spread forth his hands in this house:

^30Then hear thou from heaven thy dwelling place, and forgive, and render unto every man according unto all his ways, whose heart thou knowest; (for thou only knowest the hearts of the children of men:)

^31That they may fear thee, to walk in thy ways, so long as they live in the land which thou gavest unto our fathers.

^32Moreover concerning the stranger, which is not of thy people Israel, but is come from a far country for thy great name’s sake, and thy mighty hand, and thy stretched out arm; if they come and pray in this house;

^33Then hear thou from the heavens, even from thy dwelling place, and do according to all that the stranger calleth to thee for; that all people of the earth may know thy name, and fear thee, as doth thy people Israel, and may know that this house which I have built is called by thy name.

^34If thy people go out to war against their enemies by the way that thou shalt send them, and they pray unto thee toward this city which thou hast chosen, and the house which I have built for thy name;

^35Then hear thou from the heavens their prayer and their supplication, and maintain their cause.

^36If they sin against thee, (for there is no man which sinneth not,) and thou be angry with them, and deliver them over before their enemies, and they carry them away captives unto a land far off or near;

^37Yet if they bethink themselves in the land whither they are carried captive, and turn and pray unto thee in the land of their captivity, saying, We have sinned, we have done amiss, and have dealt wickedly;

^38If they return to thee with all their heart and with all their soul in the land of their captivity, whither they have carried them captives, and pray toward their land, which thou gavest unto their fathers, and toward the city which thou hast chosen, and toward the house which I have built for thy name:

^39Then hear thou from the heavens, even from thy dwelling place, their prayer and their supplications, and maintain their cause, and forgive thy people which have sinned against thee.

^40Now, my God, let, I beseech thee, thine eyes be open, and let thine ears be attent unto the prayer that is made in this place.

^41Now therefore arise, O Lord God, into thy resting place, thou, and the ark of thy strength: let thy priests, O Lord God, be clothed with salvation, and let thy saints rejoice in goodness.

^42O Lord God, turn not away the face of thine anointed: remember the mercies of David thy servant.

VII

^1Now when Solomon had made an end of praying, the fire came down from heaven, and consumed the burnt offering and the sacrifices; and the glory of the Lord filled the house.

^2And the priests could not enter into the house of the Lord, because the glory of the Lord had filled the Lord’s house.

^3And when all the children of Israel saw how the fire came down, and the glory of the Lord upon the house, they bowed themselves with their faces to the ground upon the pavement, and worshipped, and praised the Lord, saying, For he is good; for his mercy endureth for ever.

^4Then the king and all the people offered sacrifices before the Lord.

^5And king Solomon offered a sacrifice of twenty and two thousand oxen, and an hundred and twenty thousand sheep: so the king and all the people dedicated the house of God.

^6And the priests waited on their offices: the Levites also with instruments of musick of the Lord, which David the king had made to praise the Lord, because his mercy endureth for ever, when David praised by their ministry; and the priests sounded trumpets before them, and all Israel stood.

^7Moreover Solomon hallowed the middle of the court that was before the house of the Lord: for there he offered burnt offerings, and the fat of the peace offerings, because the brasen altar which Solomon had made was not able to receive the burnt offerings, and the meat offerings, and the fat.

^8Also at the same time Solomon kept the feast seven days, and all Israel with him, a very great congregation, from the entering in of Hamath unto the river of Egypt.

^9And in the eighth day they made a solemn assembly: for they kept the dedication of the altar seven days, and the feast seven days.

^10And on the three and twentieth day of the seventh month he sent the people away into their tents, glad and merry in heart for the goodness that the Lord had shewed unto David, and to Solomon, and to Israel his people.

^11Thus Solomon finished the house of the Lord, and the king’s house: and all that came into Solomon’s heart to make in the house of the Lord, and in his own house, he prosperously effected.

^12And the Lord appeared to Solomon by night, and said unto him, I have heard thy prayer, and have chosen this place to myself for an house of sacrifice.

^13If I shut up heaven that there be no rain, or if I command the locusts to devour the land, or if I send pestilence among my people;

^14If my people, which are called by my name, shall humble themselves, and pray, and seek my face, and turn from their wicked ways; then will I hear from heaven, and will forgive their sin, and will heal their land.

^15Now mine eyes shall be open, and mine ears attent unto the prayer that is made in this place.

^16For now have I chosen and sanctified this house, that my name may be there for ever: and mine eyes and mine heart shall be there perpetually.

^17And as for thee, if thou wilt walk before me, as David thy father walked, and do according to all that I have commanded thee, and shalt observe my statutes and my judgments;

^18Then will I stablish the throne of thy kingdom, according as I have covenanted with David thy father, saying, There shall not fail thee a man to be ruler in Israel.

^19But if ye turn away, and forsake my statutes and my commandments, which I have set before you, and shall go and serve other gods, and worship them;

^20Then will I pluck them up by the roots out of my land which I have given them; and this house, which I have sanctified for my name, will I cast out of my sight, and will make it to be a proverb and a byword among all nations.

^21And this house, which is high, shall be an astonishment to every one that passeth by it; so that he shall say, Why hath the Lord done thus unto this land, and unto this house?

^22And it shall be answered, Because they forsook the Lord God of their fathers, which brought them forth out of the land of Egypt, and laid hold on other gods, and worshipped them, and served them: therefore hath he brought all this evil upon them.

VIII

^1And it came to pass at the end of twenty years, wherein Solomon had built the house of the Lord, and his own house,

^2That the cities which Huram had restored to Solomon, Solomon built them, and caused the children of Israel to dwell there.

^3And Solomon went to Hamathzobah, and prevailed against it.

^4And he built Tadmor in the wilderness, and all the store cities, which he built in Hamath.

^5Also he built Bethhoron the upper, and Bethhoron the nether, fenced cities, with walls, gates, and bars;

^6And Baalath, and all the store cities that Solomon had, and all the chariot cities, and the cities of the horsemen, and all that Solomon desired to build in Jerusalem, and in Lebanon, and throughout all the land of his dominion.

^7As for all the people that were left of the Hittites, and the Amorites, and the Perizzites, and the Hivites, and the Jebusites, which were not of Israel,

^8But of their children, who were left after them in the land, whom the children of Israel consumed not, them did Solomon make to pay tribute until this day.

^9But of the children of Israel did Solomon make no servants for his work; but they were men of war, and chief of his captains, and captains of his chariots and horsemen.

^10And these were the chief of king Solomon’s officers, even two hundred and fifty, that bare rule over the people.

^11And Solomon brought up the daughter of Pharaoh out of the city of David unto the house that he had built for her: for he said, My wife shall not dwell in the house of David king of Israel, because the places are holy, whereunto the ark of the Lord hath come.

^12Then Solomon offered burnt offerings unto the Lord on the altar of the Lord, which he had built before the porch,

^13Even after a certain rate every day, offering according to the commandment of Moses, on the sabbaths, and on the new moons, and on the solemn feasts, three times in the year, even in the feast of unleavened bread, and in the feast of weeks, and in the feast of tabernacles.

^14And he appointed, according to the order of David his father, the courses of the priests to their service, and the Levites to their charges, to praise and minister before the priests, as the duty of every day required: the porters also by their courses at every gate: for so had David the man of God commanded.

^15And they departed not from the commandment of the king unto the priests and Levites concerning any matter, or concerning the treasures.

^16Now all the work of Solomon was prepared unto the day of the foundation of the house of the Lord, and until it was finished. So the house of the Lord was perfected.

^17Then went Solomon to Eziongeber, and to Eloth, at the sea side in the land of Edom.

^18And Huram sent him by the hands of his servants ships, and servants that had knowledge of the sea; and they went with the servants of Solomon to Ophir, and took thence four hundred and fifty talents of gold, and brought them to king Solomon.

IX

^1And when the queen of Sheba heard of the fame of Solomon, she came to prove Solomon with hard questions at Jerusalem, with a very great company, and camels that bare spices, and gold in abundance, and precious stones: and when she was come to Solomon, she communed with him of all that was in her heart.

^2And Solomon told her all her questions: and there was nothing hid from Solomon which he told her not.

^3And when the queen of Sheba had seen the wisdom of Solomon, and the house that he had built,

^4And the meat of his table, and the sitting of his servants, and the attendance of his ministers, and their apparel; his cupbearers also, and their apparel; and his ascent by which he went up into the house of the Lord; there was no more spirit in her.

^5And she said to the king, It was a true report which I heard in mine own land of thine acts, and of thy wisdom:

^6Howbeit I believed not their words, until I came, and mine eyes had seen it: and, behold, the one half of the greatness of thy wisdom was not told me: for thou exceedest the fame that I heard.

^7Happy are thy men, and happy are these thy servants, which stand continually before thee, and hear thy wisdom.

^8Blessed be the Lord thy God, which delighted in thee to set thee on his throne, to be king for the Lord thy God: because thy God loved Israel, to establish them for ever, therefore made he thee king over them, to do judgment and justice.

^9And she gave the king an hundred and twenty talents of gold, and of spices great abundance, and precious stones: neither was there any such spice as the queen of Sheba gave king Solomon.

^10And the servants also of Huram, and the servants of Solomon, which brought gold from Ophir, brought algum trees and precious stones.

^11And the king made of the algum trees terraces to the house of the Lord, and to the king’s palace, and harps and psalteries for singers: and there were none such seen before in the land of Judah.

^12And king Solomon gave to the queen of Sheba all her desire, whatsoever she asked, beside that which she had brought unto the king. So she turned, and went away to her own land, she and her servants.

^13Now the weight of gold that came to Solomon in one year was six hundred and threescore and six talents of gold;

^14Beside that which chapmen and merchants brought. And all the kings of Arabia and governors of the country brought gold and silver to Solomon.

^15And king Solomon made two hundred targets of beaten gold: six hundred shekels of beaten gold went to one target.

^16And three hundred shields made he of beaten gold: three hundred shekels of gold went to one shield. And the king put them in the house of the forest of Lebanon.

^17Moreover the king made a great throne of ivory, and overlaid it with pure gold.

^18And there were six steps to the throne, with a footstool of gold, which were fastened to the throne, and stays on each side of the sitting place, and two lions standing by the stays:

^19And twelve lions stood there on the one side and on the other upon the six steps. There was not the like made in any kingdom.

^20And all the drinking vessels of king Solomon were of gold, and all the vessels of the house of the forest of Lebanon were of pure gold: none were of silver; it was not any thing accounted of in the days of Solomon.

^21For the king’s ships went to Tarshish with the servants of Huram: every three years once came the ships of Tarshish bringing gold, and silver, ivory, and apes, and peacocks.

^22And king Solomon passed all the kings of the earth in riches and wisdom.

^23And all the kings of the earth sought the presence of Solomon, to hear his wisdom, that God had put in his heart.

^24And they brought every man his present, vessels of silver, and vessels of gold, and raiment, harness, and spices, horses, and mules, a rate year by year.

^25And Solomon had four thousand stalls for horses and chariots, and twelve thousand horsemen; whom he bestowed in the chariot cities, and with the king at Jerusalem.

^26And he reigned over all the kings from the river even unto the land of the Philistines, and to the border of Egypt.

^27And the king made silver in Jerusalem as stones, and cedar trees made he as the sycomore trees that are in the low plains in abundance.

^28And they brought unto Solomon horses out of Egypt, and out of all lands.

^29Now the rest of the acts of Solomon, first and last, are they not written in the book of Nathan the prophet, and in the prophecy of Ahijah the Shilonite, and in the visions of Iddo the seer against Jeroboam the son of Nebat?

^30And Solomon reigned in Jerusalem over all Israel forty years.

^31And Solomon slept with his fathers, and he was buried in the city of David his father: and Rehoboam his son reigned in his stead.

X

^1And Rehoboam went to Shechem: for to Shechem were all Israel come to make him king.

^2And it came to pass, when Jeroboam the son of Nebat, who was in Egypt, whither he fled from the presence of Solomon the king, heard it, that Jeroboam returned out of Egypt.

^3And they sent and called him. So Jeroboam and all Israel came and spake to Rehoboam, saying,

^4Thy father made our yoke grievous: now therefore ease thou somewhat the grievous servitude of thy father, and his heavy yoke that he put upon us, and we will serve thee.

^5And he said unto them, Come again unto me after three days. And the people departed.

^6And king Rehoboam took counsel with the old men that had stood before Solomon his father while he yet lived, saying, What counsel give ye me to return answer to this people?

^7And they spake unto him, saying, If thou be kind to this people, and please them, and speak good words to them, they will be thy servants for ever.

^8But he forsook the counsel which the old men gave him, and took counsel with the young men that were brought up with him, that stood before him.

^9And he said unto them, What advice give ye that we may return answer to this people, which have spoken to me, saying, Ease somewhat the yoke that thy father did put upon us?

^10And the young men that were brought up with him spake unto him, saying, Thus shalt thou answer the people that spake unto thee, saying, Thy father made our yoke heavy, but make thou it somewhat lighter for us; thus shalt thou say unto them, My little finger shall be thicker than my father’s loins.

^11For whereas my father put a heavy yoke upon you, I will put more to your yoke: my father chastised you with whips, but I will chastise you with scorpions.

^12So Jeroboam and all the people came to Rehoboam on the third day, as the king bade, saying, Come again to me on the third day.

^13And the king answered them roughly; and king Rehoboam forsook the counsel of the old men,

^14And answered them after the advice of the young men, saying, My father made your yoke heavy, but I will add thereto: my father chastised you with whips, but I will chastise you with scorpions.

^15So the king hearkened not unto the people: for the cause was of God, that the Lord might perform his word, which he spake by the hand of Ahijah the Shilonite to Jeroboam the son of Nebat.

^16And when all Israel saw that the king would not hearken unto them, the people answered the king, saying, What portion have we in David? and we have none inheritance in the son of Jesse: every man to your tents, O Israel: and now, David, see to thine own house. So all Israel went to their tents.

^17But as for the children of Israel that dwelt in the cities of Judah, Rehoboam reigned over them.

^18Then king Rehoboam sent Hadoram that was over the tribute; and the children of Israel stoned him with stones, that he died. But king Rehoboam made speed to get him up to his chariot, to flee to Jerusalem.

^19And Israel rebelled against the house of David unto this day.

XI

^1And when Rehoboam was come to Jerusalem, he gathered of the house of Judah and Benjamin an hundred and fourscore thousand chosen men, which were warriors, to fight against Israel, that he might bring the kingdom again to Rehoboam.

^2But the word of the Lord came to Shemaiah the man of God, saying,

^3Speak unto Rehoboam the son of Solomon, king of Judah, and to all Israel in Judah and Benjamin, saying,

^4Thus saith the Lord, Ye shall not go up, nor fight against your brethren: return every man to his house: for this thing is done of me. And they obeyed the words of the Lord, and returned from going against Jeroboam.

^5And Rehoboam dwelt in Jerusalem, and built cities for defence in Judah.

^6He built even Bethlehem, and Etam, and Tekoa,

^7And Bethzur, and Shoco, and Adullam,

^8And Gath, and Mareshah, and Ziph,

^9And Adoraim, and Lachish, and Azekah,

^10And Zorah, and Aijalon, and Hebron, which are in Judah and in Benjamin fenced cities.

^11And he fortified the strong holds, and put captains in them, and store of victual, and of oil and wine.

^12And in every several city he put shields and spears, and made them exceeding strong, having Judah and Benjamin on his side.

^13And the priests and the Levites that were in all Israel resorted to him out of all their coasts.

^14For the Levites left their suburbs and their possession, and came to Judah and Jerusalem: for Jeroboam and his sons had cast them off from executing the priest’s office unto the Lord:

^15And he ordained him priests for the high places, and for the devils, and for the calves which he had made.

^16And after them out of all the tribes of Israel such as set their hearts to seek the Lord God of Israel came to Jerusalem, to sacrifice unto the Lord God of their fathers.

^17So they strengthened the kingdom of Judah, and made Rehoboam the son of Solomon strong, three years: for three years they walked in the way of David and Solomon.

^18And Rehoboam took him Mahalath the daughter of Jerimoth the son of David to wife, and Abihail the daughter of Eliab the son of Jesse;

^19Which bare him children; Jeush, and Shamariah, and Zaham.

^20And after her he took Maachah the daughter of Absalom; which bare him Abijah, and Attai, and Ziza, and Shelomith.

^21And Rehoboam loved Maachah the daughter of Absalom above all his wives and his concubines: (for he took eighteen wives, and threescore concubines; and begat twenty and eight sons, and threescore daughters.)

^22And Rehoboam made Abijah the son of Maachah the chief, to be ruler among his brethren: for he thought to make him king.

^23And he dealt wisely, and dispersed of all his children throughout all the countries of Judah and Benjamin, unto every fenced city: and he gave them victual in abundance. And he desired many wives.

XII

^1And it came to pass, when Rehoboam had established the kingdom, and had strengthened himself, he forsook the law of the Lord, and all Israel with him.

^2And it came to pass, that in the fifth year of king Rehoboam Shishak king of Egypt came up against Jerusalem, because they had transgressed against the Lord,

^3With twelve hundred chariots, and threescore thousand horsemen: and the people were without number that came with him out of Egypt; the Lubims, the Sukkiims, and the Ethiopians.

^4And he took the fenced cities which pertained to Judah, and came to Jerusalem.

^5Then came Shemaiah the prophet to Rehoboam, and to the princes of Judah, that were gathered together to Jerusalem because of Shishak, and said unto them, Thus saith the Lord, Ye have forsaken me, and therefore have I also left you in the hand of Shishak.

^6Whereupon the princes of Israel and the king humbled themselves; and they said, The Lord is righteous.

^7And when the Lord saw that they humbled themselves, the word of the Lord came to Shemaiah, saying, They have humbled themselves; therefore I will not destroy them, but I will grant them some deliverance; and my wrath shall not be poured out upon Jerusalem by the hand of Shishak.

^8Nevertheless they shall be his servants; that they may know my service, and the service of the kingdoms of the countries.

^9So Shishak king of Egypt came up against Jerusalem, and took away the treasures of the house of the Lord, and the treasures of the king’s house; he took all: he carried away also the shields of gold which Solomon had made.

^10Instead of which king Rehoboam made shields of brass, and committed them to the hands of the chief of the guard, that kept the entrance of the king’s house.

^11And when the king entered into the house of the Lord, the guard came and fetched them, and brought them again into the guard chamber.

^12And when he humbled himself, the wrath of the Lord turned from him, that he would not destroy him altogether: and also in Judah things went well.

^13So king Rehoboam strengthened himself in Jerusalem, and reigned: for Rehoboam was one and forty years old when he began to reign, and he reigned seventeen years in Jerusalem, the city which the Lord had chosen out of all the tribes of Israel, to put his name there. And his mother’s name was Naamah an Ammonitess.

^14And he did evil, because he prepared not his heart to seek the Lord.

^15Now the acts of Rehoboam, first and last, are they not written in the book of Shemaiah the prophet, and of Iddo the seer concerning genealogies? And there were wars between Rehoboam and Jeroboam continually.

^16And Rehoboam slept with his fathers, and was buried in the city of David: and Abijah his son reigned in his stead.

XIII

^1Now in the eighteenth year of king Jeroboam began Abijah to reign over Judah.

^2He reigned three years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name also was Michaiah the daughter of Uriel of Gibeah. And there was war between Abijah and Jeroboam.

^3And Abijah set the battle in array with an army of valiant men of war, even four hundred thousand chosen men: Jeroboam also set the battle in array against him with eight hundred thousand chosen men, being mighty men of valour.

^4And Abijah stood up upon mount Zemaraim, which is in mount Ephraim, and said, Hear me, thou Jeroboam, and all Israel;

^5Ought ye not to know that the Lord God of Israel gave the kingdom over Israel to David for ever, even to him and to his sons by a covenant of salt?

^6Yet Jeroboam the son of Nebat, the servant of Solomon the son of David, is risen up, and hath rebelled against his lord.

^7And there are gathered unto him vain men, the children of Belial, and have strengthened themselves against Rehoboam the son of Solomon, when Rehoboam was young and tenderhearted, and could not withstand them.

^8And now ye think to withstand the kingdom of the Lord in the hand of the sons of David; and ye be a great multitude, and there are with your golden calves, which Jeroboam made you for gods.

^9Have ye not cast out the priests of the Lord, the sons of Aaron, and the Levites, and have made you priests after the manner of the nations of other lands? so that whosoever cometh to consecrate himself with a young bullock and seven rams, the same may be a priest of them that are no gods.

^10But as for us, the Lord is our God, and we have not forsaken him; and the priests, which minister unto the Lord, are the sons of Aaron, and the Levites wait upon their business:

^11And they burn unto the Lord every morning and every evening burnt sacrifices and sweet incense: the shewbread also set they in order upon the pure table; and the candlestick of gold with the lamps thereof, to burn every evening: for we keep the charge of the Lord our God; but ye have forsaken him.

^12And, behold, God himself is with us for our captain, and his priests with sounding trumpets to cry alarm against you. O children of Israel, fight ye not against the Lord God of your fathers; for ye shall not prosper.

^13But Jeroboam caused an ambushment to come about behind them: so they were before Judah, and the ambushment was behind them.

^14And when Judah looked back, behold, the battle was before and behind: and they cried unto the Lord, and the priests sounded with the trumpets.

^15Then the men of Judah gave a shout: and as the men of Judah shouted, it came to pass, that God smote Jeroboam and all Israel before Abijah and Judah.

^16And the children of Israel fled before Judah: and God delivered them into their hand.

^17And Abijah and his people slew them with a great slaughter: so there fell down slain of Israel five hundred thousand chosen men.

^18Thus the children of Israel were brought under at that time, and the children of Judah prevailed, because they relied upon the Lord God of their fathers.

^19And Abijah pursued after Jeroboam, and took cities from him, Bethel with the towns thereof, and Jeshanah with the towns thereof, and Ephraim with the towns thereof.

^20Neither did Jeroboam recover strength again in the days of Abijah: and the Lord struck him, and he died.

^21But Abijah waxed mighty, and married fourteen wives, and begat twenty and two sons, and sixteen daughters.

^22And the rest of the acts of Abijah, and his ways, and his sayings, are written in the story of the prophet Iddo.

XIV

^1So Abijah slept with his fathers, and they buried him in the city of David: and Asa his son reigned in his stead. In his days the land was quiet ten years.

^2And Asa did that which was good and right in the eyes of the Lord his God:

^3For he took away the altars of the strange gods, and the high places, and brake down the images, and cut down the groves:

^4And commanded Judah to seek the Lord God of their fathers, and to do the law and the commandment.

^5Also he took away out of all the cities of Judah the high places and the images: and the kingdom was quiet before him.

^6And he built fenced cities in Judah: for the land had rest, and he had no war in those years; because the Lord had given him rest.

^7Therefore he said unto Judah, Let us build these cities, and make about them walls, and towers, gates, and bars, while the land is yet before us; because we have sought the Lord our God, we have sought him, and he hath given us rest on every side. So they built and prospered.

^8And Asa had an army of men that bare targets and spears, out of Judah three hundred thousand; and out of Benjamin, that bare shields and drew bows, two hundred and fourscore thousand: all these were mighty men of valour.

^9And there came out against them Zerah the Ethiopian with an host of a thousand thousand, and three hundred chariots; and came unto Mareshah.

^10Then Asa went out against him, and they set the battle in array in the valley of Zephathah at Mareshah.

^11And Asa cried unto the Lord his God, and said, Lord, it is nothing with thee to help, whether with many, or with them that have no power: help us, O Lord our God; for we rest on thee, and in thy name we go against this multitude. O Lord, thou art our God; let no man prevail against thee.

^12So the Lord smote the Ethiopians before Asa, and before Judah; and the Ethiopians fled.

^13And Asa and the people that were with him pursued them unto Gerar: and the Ethiopians were overthrown, that they could not recover themselves; for they were destroyed before the Lord, and before his host; and they carried away very much spoil.

^14And they smote all the cities round about Gerar; for the fear of the Lord came upon them: and they spoiled all the cities; for there was exceeding much spoil in them.

^15They smote also the tents of cattle, and carried away sheep and camels in abundance, and returned to Jerusalem.

XV

^1And the Spirit of God came upon Azariah the son of Oded:

^2And he went out to meet Asa, and said unto him, Hear ye me, Asa, and all Judah and Benjamin; The Lord is with you, while ye be with him; and if ye seek him, he will be found of you; but if ye forsake him, he will forsake you.

^3Now for a long season Israel hath been without the true God, and without a teaching priest, and without law.

^4But when they in their trouble did turn unto the Lord God of Israel, and sought him, he was found of them.

^5And in those times there was no peace to him that went out, nor to him that came in, but great vexations were upon all the inhabitants of the countries.

^6And nation was destroyed of nation, and city of city: for God did vex them with all adversity.

^7Be ye strong therefore, and let not your hands be weak: for your work shall be rewarded.

^8And when Asa heard these words, and the prophecy of Oded the prophet, he took courage, and put away the abominable idols out of all the land of Judah and Benjamin, and out of the cities which he had taken from mount Ephraim, and renewed the altar of the Lord, that was before the porch of the Lord.

^9And he gathered all Judah and Benjamin, and the strangers with them out of Ephraim and Manasseh, and out of Simeon: for they fell to him out of Israel in abundance, when they saw that the Lord his God was with him.

^10So they gathered themselves together at Jerusalem in the third month, in the fifteenth year of the reign of Asa.

^11And they offered unto the Lord the same time, of the spoil which they had brought, seven hundred oxen and seven thousand sheep.

^12And they entered into a covenant to seek the Lord God of their fathers with all their heart and with all their soul;

^13That whosoever would not seek the Lord God of Israel should be put to death, whether small or great, whether man or woman.

^14And they sware unto the Lord with a loud voice, and with shouting, and with trumpets, and with cornets.

^15And all Judah rejoiced at the oath: for they had sworn with all their heart, and sought him with their whole desire; and he was found of them: and the Lord gave them rest round about.

^16And also concerning Maachah the mother of Asa the king, he removed her from being queen, because she had made an idol in a grove: and Asa cut down her idol, and stamped it, and burnt it at the brook Kidron.

^17But the high places were not taken away out of Israel: nevertheless the heart of Asa was perfect all his days.

^18And he brought into the house of God the things that his father had dedicated, and that he himself had dedicated, silver, and gold, and vessels.

^19And there was no more war unto the five and thirtieth year of the reign of Asa.

XVI

^1In the six and thirtieth year of the reign of Asa Baasha king of Israel came up against Judah, and built Ramah, to the intent that he might let none go out or come in to Asa king of Judah.

^2Then Asa brought out silver and gold out of the treasures of the house of the Lord and of the king’s house, and sent to Benhadad king of Syria, that dwelt at Damascus, saying,

^3There is a league between me and thee, as there was between my father and thy father: behold, I have sent thee silver and gold; go, break thy league with Baasha king of Israel, that he may depart from me.

^4And Benhadad hearkened unto king Asa, and sent the captains of his armies against the cities of Israel; and they smote Ijon, and Dan, and Abelmaim, and all the store cities of Naphtali.

^5And it came to pass, when Baasha heard it, that he left off building of Ramah, and let his work cease.

^6Then Asa the king took all Judah; and they carried away the stones of Ramah, and the timber thereof, wherewith Baasha was building; and he built therewith Geba and Mizpah.

^7And at that time Hanani the seer came to Asa king of Judah, and said unto him, Because thou hast relied on the king of Syria, and not relied on the Lord thy God, therefore is the host of the king of Syria escaped out of thine hand.

^8Were not the Ethiopians and the Lubims a huge host, with very many chariots and horsemen? yet, because thou didst rely on the Lord, he delivered them into thine hand.

^9For the eyes of the Lord run to and fro throughout the whole earth, to shew himself strong in the behalf of them whose heart is perfect toward him. Herein thou hast done foolishly: therefore from henceforth thou shalt have wars.

^10Then Asa was wroth with the seer, and put him in a prison house; for he was in a rage with him because of this thing. And Asa oppressed some of the people the same time.

^11And, behold, the acts of Asa, first and last, lo, they are written in the book of the kings of Judah and Israel.

^12And Asa in the thirty and ninth year of his reign was diseased in his feet, until his disease was exceeding great: yet in his disease he sought not to the Lord, but to the physicians.

^13And Asa slept with his fathers, and died in the one and fortieth year of his reign.

^14And they buried him in his own sepulchres, which he had made for himself in the city of David, and laid him in the bed which was filled with sweet odours and divers kinds of spices prepared by the apothecaries’ art: and they made a very great burning for him.

XVII

^1And Jehoshaphat his son reigned in his stead, and strengthened himself against Israel.

^2And he placed forces in all the fenced cities of Judah, and set garrisons in the land of Judah, and in the cities of Ephraim, which Asa his father had taken.

^3And the Lord was with Jehoshaphat, because he walked in the first ways of his father David, and sought not unto Baalim;

^4But sought to the Lord God of his father, and walked in his commandments, and not after the doings of Israel.

^5Therefore the Lord stablished the kingdom in his hand; and all Judah brought to Jehoshaphat presents; and he had riches and honour in abundance.

^6And his heart was lifted up in the ways of the Lord: moreover he took away the high places and groves out of Judah.

^7Also in the third year of his reign he sent to his princes, even to Benhail, and to Obadiah, and to Zechariah, and to Nethaneel, and to Michaiah, to teach in the cities of Judah.

^8And with them he sent Levites, even Shemaiah, and Nethaniah, and Zebadiah, and Asahel, and Shemiramoth, and Jehonathan, and Adonijah, and Tobijah, and Tobadonijah, Levites; and with them Elishama and Jehoram, priests.

^9And they taught in Judah, and had the book of the law of the Lord with them, and went about throughout all the cities of Judah, and taught the people.

^10And the fear of the Lord fell upon all the kingdoms of the lands that were round about Judah, so that they made no war against Jehoshaphat.

^11Also some of the Philistines brought Jehoshaphat presents, and tribute silver; and the Arabians brought him flocks, seven thousand and seven hundred rams, and seven thousand and seven hundred he goats.

^12And Jehoshaphat waxed great exceedingly; and he built in Judah castles, and cities of store.

^13And he had much business in the cities of Judah: and the men of war, mighty men of valour, were in Jerusalem.

^14And these are the numbers of them according to the house of their fathers: Of Judah, the captains of thousands; Adnah the chief, and with him mighty men of valour three hundred thousand.

^15And next to him was Jehohanan the captain, and with him two hundred and fourscore thousand.

^16And next him was Amasiah the son of Zichri, who willingly offered himself unto the Lord; and with him two hundred thousand mighty men of valour.

^17And of Benjamin; Eliada a mighty man of valour, and with him armed men with bow and shield two hundred thousand.

^18And next him was Jehozabad, and with him an hundred and fourscore thousand ready prepared for the war.

^19These waited on the king, beside those whom the king put in the fenced cities throughout all Judah.

XVIII

^1Now Jehoshaphat had riches and honour in abundance, and joined affinity with Ahab.

^2And after certain years he went down to Ahab to Samaria. And Ahab killed sheep and oxen for him in abundance, and for the people that he had with him, and persuaded him to go up with him to Ramothgilead.

^3And Ahab king of Israel said unto Jehoshaphat king of Judah, Wilt thou go with me to Ramothgilead? And he answered him, I am as thou art, and my people as thy people; and we will be with thee in the war.

^4And Jehoshaphat said unto the king of Israel, Enquire, I pray thee, at the word of the Lord to day.

^5Therefore the king of Israel gathered together of prophets four hundred men, and said unto them, Shall we go to Ramothgilead to battle, or shall I forbear? And they said, Go up; for God will deliver it into the king’s hand.

^6But Jehoshaphat said, Is there not here a prophet of the Lord besides, that we might enquire of him?

^7And the king of Israel said unto Jehoshaphat, There is yet one man, by whom we may enquire of the Lord: but I hate him; for he never prophesied good unto me, but always evil: the same is Micaiah the son of Imla. And Jehoshaphat said, Let not the king say so.

^8And the king of Israel called for one of his officers, and said, Fetch quickly Micaiah the son of Imla.

^9And the king of Israel and Jehoshaphat king of Judah sat either of them on his throne, clothed in their robes, and they sat in a void place at the entering in of the gate of Samaria; and all the prophets prophesied before them.

^10And Zedekiah the son of Chenaanah had made him horns of iron, and said, Thus saith the Lord, With these thou shalt push Syria until they be consumed.

^11And all the prophets prophesied so, saying, Go up to Ramothgilead, and prosper: for the Lord shall deliver it into the hand of the king.

^12And the messenger that went to call Micaiah spake to him, saying, Behold, the words of the prophets declare good to the king with one assent; let thy word therefore, I pray thee, be like one of their’s, and speak thou good.

^13And Micaiah said, As the Lord liveth, even what my God saith, that will I speak.

^14And when he was come to the king, the king said unto him, Micaiah, shall we go to Ramothgilead to battle, or shall I forbear? And he said, Go ye up, and prosper, and they shall be delivered into your hand.

^15And the king said to him, How many times shall I adjure thee that thou say nothing but the truth to me in the name of the Lord?

^16Then he said, I did see all Israel scattered upon the mountains, as sheep that have no shepherd: and the Lord said, These have no master; let them return therefore every man to his house in peace.

^17And the king of Israel said to Jehoshaphat, Did I not tell thee that he would not prophesy good unto me, but evil?

^18Again he said, Therefore hear the word of the Lord; I saw the Lord sitting upon his throne, and all the host of heaven standing on his right hand and on his left.

^19And the Lord said, Who shall entice Ahab king of Israel, that he may go up and fall at Ramothgilead? And one spake saying after this manner, and another saying after that manner.

^20Then there came out a spirit, and stood before the Lord, and said, I will entice him. And the Lord said unto him, Wherewith?

^21And he said, I will go out, and be a lying spirit in the mouth of all his prophets. And the Lord said, Thou shalt entice him, and thou shalt also prevail: go out, and do even so.

^22Now therefore, behold, the Lord hath put a lying spirit in the mouth of these thy prophets, and the Lord hath spoken evil against thee.

^23Then Zedekiah the son of Chenaanah came near, and smote Micaiah upon the cheek, and said, Which way went the Spirit of the Lord from me to speak unto thee?

^24And Micaiah said, Behold, thou shalt see on that day when thou shalt go into an inner chamber to hide thyself.

^25Then the king of Israel said, Take ye Micaiah, and carry him back to Amon the governor of the city, and to Joash the king’s son;

^26And say, Thus saith the king, Put this fellow in the prison, and feed him with bread of affliction and with water of affliction, until I return in peace.

^27And Micaiah said, If thou certainly return in peace, then hath not the Lord spoken by me. And he said, Hearken, all ye people.

^28So the king of Israel and Jehoshaphat the king of Judah went up to Ramothgilead.

^29And the king of Israel said unto Jehoshaphat, I will disguise myself, and I will go to the battle; but put thou on thy robes. So the king of Israel disguised himself; and they went to the battle.

^30Now the king of Syria had commanded the captains of the chariots that were with him, saying, Fight ye not with small or great, save only with the king of Israel.

^31And it came to pass, when the captains of the chariots saw Jehoshaphat, that they said, It is the king of Israel. Therefore they compassed about him to fight: but Jehoshaphat cried out, and the Lord helped him; and God moved them to depart from him.

^32For it came to pass, that, when the captains of the chariots perceived that it was not the king of Israel, they turned back again from pursuing him.

^33And a certain man drew a bow at a venture, and smote the king of Israel between the joints of the harness: therefore he said to his chariot man, Turn thine hand, that thou mayest carry me out of the host; for I am wounded.

^34And the battle increased that day: howbeit the king of Israel stayed himself up in his chariot against the Syrians until the even: and about the time of the sun going down he died.

XIX

^1And Jehoshaphat the king of Judah returned to his house in peace to Jerusalem.

^2And Jehu the son of Hanani the seer went out to meet him, and said to king Jehoshaphat, Shouldest thou help the ungodly, and love them that hate the Lord? therefore is wrath upon thee from before the Lord.

^3Nevertheless there are good things found in thee, in that thou hast taken away the groves out of the land, and hast prepared thine heart to seek God.

^4And Jehoshaphat dwelt at Jerusalem: and he went out again through the people from Beersheba to mount Ephraim, and brought them back unto the Lord God of their fathers.

^5And he set judges in the land throughout all the fenced cities of Judah, city by city,

^6And said to the judges, Take heed what ye do: for ye judge not for man, but for the Lord, who is with you in the judgment.

^7Wherefore now let the fear of the Lord be upon you; take heed and do it: for there is no iniquity with the Lord our God, nor respect of persons, nor taking of gifts.

^8Moreover in Jerusalem did Jehoshaphat set of the Levites, and of the priests, and of the chief of the fathers of Israel, for the judgment of the Lord, and for controversies, when they returned to Jerusalem.

^9And he charged them, saying, Thus shall ye do in the fear of the Lord, faithfully, and with a perfect heart.

^10And what cause soever shall come to you of your brethren that dwell in your cities, between blood and blood, between law and commandment, statutes and judgments, ye shall even warn them that they trespass not against the Lord, and so wrath come upon you, and upon your brethren: this do, and ye shall not trespass.

^11And, behold, Amariah the chief priest is over you in all matters of the Lord; and Zebadiah the son of Ishmael, the ruler of the house of Judah, for all the king’s matters: also the Levites shall be officers before you. Deal courageously, and the Lord shall be with the good.

XX

^1It came to pass after this also, that the children of Moab, and the children of Ammon, and with them other beside the Ammonites, came against Jehoshaphat to battle.

^2Then there came some that told Jehoshaphat, saying, There cometh a great multitude against thee from beyond the sea on this side Syria; and, behold, they be in Hazazontamar, which is Engedi.

^3And Jehoshaphat feared, and set himself to seek the Lord, and proclaimed a fast throughout all Judah.

^4And Judah gathered themselves together, to ask help of the Lord: even out of all the cities of Judah they came to seek the Lord.

^5And Jehoshaphat stood in the congregation of Judah and Jerusalem, in the house of the Lord, before the new court,

^6And said, O Lord God of our fathers, art not thou God in heaven? and rulest not thou over all the kingdoms of the heathen? and in thine hand is there not power and might, so that none is able to withstand thee?

^7Art not thou our God, who didst drive out the inhabitants of this land before thy people Israel, and gavest it to the seed of Abraham thy friend for ever?

^8And they dwelt therein, and have built thee a sanctuary therein for thy name, saying,

^9If, when evil cometh upon us, as the sword, judgment, or pestilence, or famine, we stand before this house, and in thy presence, (for thy name is in this house,) and cry unto thee in our affliction, then thou wilt hear and help.

^10And now, behold, the children of Ammon and Moab and mount Seir, whom thou wouldest not let Israel invade, when they came out of the land of Egypt, but they turned from them, and destroyed them not;

^11Behold, I say, how they reward us, to come to cast us out of thy possession, which thou hast given us to inherit.

^12O our God, wilt thou not judge them? for we have no might against this great company that cometh against us; neither know we what to do: but our eyes are upon thee.

^13And all Judah stood before the Lord, with their little ones, their wives, and their children.

^14Then upon Jahaziel the son of Zechariah, the son of Benaiah, the son of Jeiel, the son of Mattaniah, a Levite of the sons of Asaph, came the Spirit of the Lord in the midst of the congregation;

^15And he said, Hearken ye, all Judah, and ye inhabitants of Jerusalem, and thou king Jehoshaphat, Thus saith the Lord unto you, Be not afraid nor dismayed by reason of this great multitude; for the battle is not yours, but God’s.

^16To morrow go ye down against them: behold, they come up by the cliff of Ziz; and ye shall find them at the end of the brook, before the wilderness of Jeruel.

^17Ye shall not need to fight in this battle: set yourselves, stand ye still, and see the salvation of the Lord with you, O Judah and Jerusalem: fear not, nor be dismayed; to morrow go out against them: for the Lord will be with you.

^18And Jehoshaphat bowed his head with his face to the ground: and all Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem fell before the Lord, worshipping the Lord.

^19And the Levites, of the children of the Kohathites, and of the children of the Korhites, stood up to praise the Lord God of Israel with a loud voice on high.

^20And they rose early in the morning, and went forth into the wilderness of Tekoa: and as they went forth, Jehoshaphat stood and said, Hear me, O Judah, and ye inhabitants of Jerusalem; Believe in the Lord your God, so shall ye be established; believe his prophets, so shall ye prosper.

^21And when he had consulted with the people, he appointed singers unto the Lord, and that should praise the beauty of holiness, as they went out before the army, and to say, Praise the Lord; for his mercy endureth for ever.

^22And when they began to sing and to praise, the Lord set ambushments against the children of Ammon, Moab, and mount Seir, which were come against Judah; and they were smitten.

^23For the children of Ammon and Moab stood up against the inhabitants of mount Seir, utterly to slay and destroy them: and when they had made an end of the inhabitants of Seir, every one helped to destroy another.

^24And when Judah came toward the watch tower in the wilderness, they looked unto the multitude, and, behold, they were dead bodies fallen to the earth, and none escaped.

^25And when Jehoshaphat and his people came to take away the spoil of them, they found among them in abundance both riches with the dead bodies, and precious jewels, which they stripped off for themselves, more than they could carry away: and they were three days in gathering of the spoil, it was so much.

^26And on the fourth day they assembled themselves in the valley of Berachah; for there they blessed the Lord: therefore the name of the same place was called, The valley of Berachah, unto this day.

^27Then they returned, every man of Judah and Jerusalem, and Jehoshaphat in the forefront of them, to go again to Jerusalem with joy; for the Lord had made them to rejoice over their enemies.

^28And they came to Jerusalem with psalteries and harps and trumpets unto the house of the Lord.

^29And the fear of God was on all the kingdoms of those countries, when they had heard that the Lord fought against the enemies of Israel.

^30So the realm of Jehoshaphat was quiet: for his God gave him rest round about.

^31And Jehoshaphat reigned over Judah: he was thirty and five years old when he began to reign, and he reigned twenty and five years in Jerusalem. And his mother’s name was Azubah the daughter of Shilhi.

^32And he walked in the way of Asa his father, and departed not from it, doing that which was right in the sight of the Lord.

^33Howbeit the high places were not taken away: for as yet the people had not prepared their hearts unto the God of their fathers.

^34Now the rest of the acts of Jehoshaphat, first and last, behold, they are written in the book of Jehu the son of Hanani, who is mentioned in the book of the kings of Israel.

^35And after this did Jehoshaphat king of Judah join himself with Ahaziah king of Israel, who did very wickedly:

^36And he joined himself with him to make ships to go to Tarshish: and they made the ships in Eziongaber.

^37Then Eliezer the son of Dodavah of Mareshah prophesied against Jehoshaphat, saying, Because thou hast joined thyself with Ahaziah, the Lord hath broken thy works. And the ships were broken, that they were not able to go to Tarshish.

XXI

^1Now Jehoshaphat slept with his fathers, and was buried with his fathers in the city of David. And Jehoram his son reigned in his stead.

^2And he had brethren the sons of Jehoshaphat, Azariah, and Jehiel, and Zechariah, and Azariah, and Michael, and Shephatiah: all these were the sons of Jehoshaphat king of Israel.

^3And their father gave them great gifts of silver, and of gold, and of precious things, with fenced cities in Judah: but the kingdom gave he to Jehoram; because he was the firstborn.

^4Now when Jehoram was risen up to the kingdom of his father, he strengthened himself, and slew all his brethren with the sword, and divers also of the princes of Israel.

^5Jehoram was thirty and two years old when he began to reign, and he reigned eight years in Jerusalem.

^6And he walked in the way of the kings of Israel, like as did the house of Ahab: for he had the daughter of Ahab to wife: and he wrought that which was evil in the eyes of the Lord.

^7Howbeit the Lord would not destroy the house of David, because of the covenant that he had made with David, and as he promised to give a light to him and to his sons for ever.

^8In his days the Edomites revolted from under the dominion of Judah, and made themselves a king.

^9Then Jehoram went forth with his princes, and all his chariots with him: and he rose up by night, and smote the Edomites which compassed him in, and the captains of the chariots.

^10So the Edomites revolted from under the hand of Judah unto this day. The same time also did Libnah revolt from under his hand; because he had forsaken the Lord God of his fathers.

^11Moreover he made high places in the mountains of Judah and caused the inhabitants of Jerusalem to commit fornication, and compelled Judah thereto.

^12And there came a writing to him from Elijah the prophet, saying, Thus saith the Lord God of David thy father, Because thou hast not walked in the ways of Jehoshaphat thy father, nor in the ways of Asa king of Judah,

^13But hast walked in the way of the kings of Israel, and hast made Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem to go a whoring, like to the whoredoms of the house of Ahab, and also hast slain thy brethren of thy father’s house, which were better than thyself:

^14Behold, with a great plague will the Lord smite thy people, and thy children, and thy wives, and all thy goods:

^15And thou shalt have great sickness by disease of thy bowels, until thy bowels fall out by reason of the sickness day by day.

^16Moreover the Lord stirred up against Jehoram the spirit of the Philistines, and of the Arabians, that were near the Ethiopians:

^17And they came up into Judah, and brake into it, and carried away all the substance that was found in the king’s house, and his sons also, and his wives; so that there was never a son left him, save Jehoahaz, the youngest of his sons.

^18And after all this the Lord smote him in his bowels with an incurable disease.

^19And it came to pass, that in process of time, after the end of two years, his bowels fell out by reason of his sickness: so he died of sore diseases. And his people made no burning for him, like the burning of his fathers.

^20Thirty and two years old was he when he began to reign, and he reigned in Jerusalem eight years, and departed without being desired. Howbeit they buried him in the city of David, but not in the sepulchres of the kings.

XXII

^1And the inhabitants of Jerusalem made Ahaziah his youngest son king in his stead: for the band of men that came with the Arabians to the camp had slain all the eldest. So Ahaziah the son of Jehoram king of Judah reigned.

^2Forty and two years old was Ahaziah when he began to reign, and he reigned one year in Jerusalem. His mother’s name also was Athaliah the daughter of Omri.

^3He also walked in the ways of the house of Ahab: for his mother was his counsellor to do wickedly.

^4Wherefore he did evil in the sight of the Lord like the house of Ahab: for they were his counsellors after the death of his father to his destruction.

^5He walked also after their counsel, and went with Jehoram the son of Ahab king of Israel to war against Hazael king of Syria at Ramothgilead: and the Syrians smote Joram.

^6And he returned to be healed in Jezreel because of the wounds which were given him at Ramah, when he fought with Hazael king of Syria. And Azariah the son of Jehoram king of Judah went down to see Jehoram the son of Ahab at Jezreel, because he was sick.

^7And the destruction of Ahaziah was of God by coming to Joram: for when he was come, he went out with Jehoram against Jehu the son of Nimshi, whom the Lord had anointed to cut off the house of Ahab.

^8And it came to pass, that, when Jehu was executing judgment upon the house of Ahab, and found the princes of Judah, and the sons of the brethren of Ahaziah, that ministered to Ahaziah, he slew them.

^9And he sought Ahaziah: and they caught him, (for he was hid in Samaria,) and brought him to Jehu: and when they had slain him, they buried him: Because, said they, he is the son of Jehoshaphat, who sought the Lord with all his heart. So the house of Ahaziah had no power to keep still the kingdom.

^10But when Athaliah the mother of Ahaziah saw that her son was dead, she arose and destroyed all the seed royal of the house of Judah.

^11But Jehoshabeath, the daughter of the king, took Joash the son of Ahaziah, and stole him from among the king’s sons that were slain, and put him and his nurse in a bedchamber. So Jehoshabeath, the daughter of king Jehoram, the wife of Jehoiada the priest, (for she was the sister of Ahaziah,) hid him from Athaliah, so that she slew him not.

^12And he was with them hid in the house of God six years: and Athaliah reigned over the land.

XXIII

^1And in the seventh year Jehoiada strengthened himself, and took the captains of hundreds, Azariah the son of Jeroham, and Ishmael the son of Jehohanan, and Azariah the son of Obed, and Maaseiah the son of Adaiah, and Elishaphat the son of Zichri, into covenant with him.

^2And they went about in Judah, and gathered the Levites out of all the cities of Judah, and the chief of the fathers of Israel, and they came to Jerusalem.

^3And all the congregation made a covenant with the king in the house of God. And he said unto them, Behold, the king’s son shall reign, as the Lord hath said of the sons of David.

^4This is the thing that ye shall do; A third part of you entering on the sabbath, of the priests and of the Levites, shall be porters of the doors;

^5And a third part shall be at the king’s house; and a third part at the gate of the foundation: and all the people shall be in the courts of the house of the Lord.

^6But let none come into the house of the Lord, save the priests, and they that minister of the Levites; they shall go in, for they are holy: but all the people shall keep the watch of the Lord.

^7And the Levites shall compass the king round about, every man with his weapons in his hand; and whosoever else cometh into the house, he shall be put to death: but be ye with the king when he cometh in, and when he goeth out.

^8So the Levites and all Judah did according to all things that Jehoiada the priest had commanded, and took every man his men that were to come in on the sabbath, with them that were to go out on the sabbath: for Jehoiada the priest dismissed not the courses.

^9Moreover Jehoiada the priest delivered to the captains of hundreds spears, and bucklers, and shields, that had been king David’s, which were in the house of God.

^10And he set all the people, every man having his weapon in his hand, from the right side of the temple to the left side of the temple, along by the altar and the temple, by the king round about.

^11Then they brought out the king’s son, and put upon him the crown, and gave him the testimony, and made him king. And Jehoiada and his sons anointed him, and said, God save the king.

^12Now when Athaliah heard the noise of the people running and praising the king, she came to the people into the house of the Lord:

^13And she looked, and, behold, the king stood at his pillar at the entering in, and the princes and the trumpets by the king: and all the people of the land rejoiced, and sounded with trumpets, also the singers with instruments of musick, and such as taught to sing praise. Then Athaliah rent her clothes, and said, Treason, Treason.

^14Then Jehoiada the priest brought out the captains of hundreds that were set over the host, and said unto them, Have her forth of the ranges: and whoso followeth her, let him be slain with the sword. For the priest said, Slay her not in the house of the Lord.

^15So they laid hands on her; and when she was come to the entering of the horse gate by the king’s house, they slew her there.

^16And Jehoiada made a covenant between him, and between all the people, and between the king, that they should be the Lord’s people.

^17Then all the people went to the house of Baal, and brake it down, and brake his altars and his images in pieces, and slew Mattan the priest of Baal before the altars.

^18Also Jehoiada appointed the offices of the house of the Lord by the hand of the priests the Levites, whom David had distributed in the house of the Lord, to offer the burnt offerings of the Lord, as it is written in the law of Moses, with rejoicing and with singing, as it was ordained by David.

^19And he set the porters at the gates of the house of the Lord, that none which was unclean in any thing should enter in.

^20And he took the captains of hundreds, and the nobles, and the governors of the people, and all the people of the land, and brought down the king from the house of the Lord: and they came through the high gate into the king’s house, and set the king upon the throne of the kingdom.

^21And all the people of the land rejoiced: and the city was quiet, after that they had slain Athaliah with the sword.

XXIV

^1Joash was seven years old when he began to reign, and he reigned forty years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name also was Zibiah of Beersheba.

^2And Joash did that which was right in the sight of the Lord all the days of Jehoiada the priest.

^3And Jehoiada took for him two wives; and he begat sons and daughters.

^4And it came to pass after this, that Joash was minded to repair the house of the Lord.

^5And he gathered together the priests and the Levites, and said to them, Go out unto the cities of Judah, and gather of all Israel money to repair the house of your God from year to year, and see that ye hasten the matter. Howbeit the Levites hastened it not.

^6And the king called for Jehoiada the chief, and said unto him, Why hast thou not required of the Levites to bring in out of Judah and out of Jerusalem the collection, according to the commandment of Moses the servant of the Lord, and of the congregation of Israel, for the tabernacle of witness?

^7For the sons of Athaliah, that wicked woman, had broken up the house of God; and also all the dedicated things of the house of the Lord did they bestow upon Baalim.

^8And at the king’s commandment they made a chest, and set it without at the gate of the house of the Lord.

^9And they made a proclamation through Judah and Jerusalem, to bring in to the Lord the collection that Moses the servant of God laid upon Israel in the wilderness.

^10And all the princes and all the people rejoiced, and brought in, and cast into the chest, until they had made an end.

^11Now it came to pass, that at what time the chest was brought unto the king’s office by the hand of the Levites, and when they saw that there was much money, the king’s scribe and the high priest’s officer came and emptied the chest, and took it, and carried it to his place again. Thus they did day by day, and gathered money in abundance.

^12And the king and Jehoiada gave it to such as did the work of the service of the house of the Lord, and hired masons and carpenters to repair the house of the Lord, and also such as wrought iron and brass to mend the house of the Lord.

^13So the workmen wrought, and the work was perfected by them, and they set the house of God in his state, and strengthened it.

^14And when they had finished it, they brought the rest of the money before the king and Jehoiada, whereof were made vessels for the house of the Lord, even vessels to minister, and to offer withal, and spoons, and vessels of gold and silver. And they offered burnt offerings in the house of the Lord continually all the days of Jehoiada.

^15But Jehoiada waxed old, and was full of days when he died; an hundred and thirty years old was he when he died.

^16And they buried him in the city of David among the kings, because he had done good in Israel, both toward God, and toward his house.

^17Now after the death of Jehoiada came the princes of Judah, and made obeisance to the king. Then the king hearkened unto them.

^18And they left the house of the Lord God of their fathers, and served groves and idols: and wrath came upon Judah and Jerusalem for this their trespass.

^19Yet he sent prophets to them, to bring them again unto the Lord; and they testified against them: but they would not give ear.

^20And the Spirit of God came upon Zechariah the son of Jehoiada the priest, which stood above the people, and said unto them, Thus saith God, Why transgress ye the commandments of the Lord, that ye cannot prosper? because ye have forsaken the Lord, he hath also forsaken you.

^21And they conspired against him, and stoned him with stones at the commandment of the king in the court of the house of the Lord.

^22Thus Joash the king remembered not the kindness which Jehoiada his father had done to him, but slew his son. And when he died, he said, The Lord look upon it, and require it.

^23And it came to pass at the end of the year, that the host of Syria came up against him: and they came to Judah and Jerusalem, and destroyed all the princes of the people from among the people, and sent all the spoil of them unto the king of Damascus.

^24For the army of the Syrians came with a small company of men, and the Lord delivered a very great host into their hand, because they had forsaken the Lord God of their fathers. So they executed judgment against Joash.

^25And when they were departed from him, (for they left him in great diseases,) his own servants conspired against him for the blood of the sons of Jehoiada the priest, and slew him on his bed, and he died: and they buried him in the city of David, but they buried him not in the sepulchres of the kings.

^26And these are they that conspired against him; Zabad the son of Shimeath an Ammonitess, and Jehozabad the son of Shimrith a Moabitess.

^27Now concerning his sons, and the greatness of the burdens laid upon him, and the repairing of the house of God, behold, they are written in the story of the book of the kings. And Amaziah his son reigned in his stead.

XXV

^1Amaziah was twenty and five years old when he began to reign, and he reigned twenty and nine years in Jerusalem. And his mother’s name was Jehoaddan of Jerusalem.

^2And he did that which was right in the sight of the Lord, but not with a perfect heart.

^3Now it came to pass, when the kingdom was established to him, that he slew his servants that had killed the king his father.

^4But he slew not their children, but did as it is written in the law in the book of Moses, where the Lord commanded, saying, The fathers shall not die for the children, neither shall the children die for the fathers, but every man shall die for his own sin.

^5Moreover Amaziah gathered Judah together, and made them captains over thousands, and captains over hundreds, according to the houses of their fathers, throughout all Judah and Benjamin: and he numbered them from twenty years old and above, and found them three hundred thousand choice men, able to go forth to war, that could handle spear and shield.

^6He hired also an hundred thousand mighty men of valour out of Israel for an hundred talents of silver.

^7But there came a man of God to him, saying, O king, let not the army of Israel go with thee; for the Lord is not with Israel, to wit, with all the children of Ephraim.

^8But if thou wilt go, do it; be strong for the battle: God shall make thee fall before the enemy: for God hath power to help, and to cast down.

^9And Amaziah said to the man of God, But what shall we do for the hundred talents which I have given to the army of Israel? And the man of God answered, The Lord is able to give thee much more than this.

^10Then Amaziah separated them, to wit, the army that was come to him out of Ephraim, to go home again: wherefore their anger was greatly kindled against Judah, and they returned home in great anger.

^11And Amaziah strengthened himself, and led forth his people, and went to the valley of salt, and smote of the children of Seir ten thousand.

^12And other ten thousand left alive did the children of Judah carry away captive, and brought them unto the top of the rock, and cast them down from the top of the rock, that they all were broken in pieces.

^13But the soldiers of the army which Amaziah sent back, that they should not go with him to battle, fell upon the cities of Judah, from Samaria even unto Bethhoron, and smote three thousand of them, and took much spoil.

^14Now it came to pass, after that Amaziah was come from the slaughter of the Edomites, that he brought the gods of the children of Seir, and set them up to be his gods, and bowed down himself before them, and burned incense unto them.

^15Wherefore the anger of the Lord was kindled against Amaziah, and he sent unto him a prophet, which said unto him, Why hast thou sought after the gods of the people, which could not deliver their own people out of thine hand?

^16And it came to pass, as he talked with him, that the king said unto him, Art thou made of the king’s counsel? forbear; why shouldest thou be smitten? Then the prophet forbare, and said, I know that God hath determined to destroy thee, because thou hast done this, and hast not hearkened unto my counsel.

^17Then Amaziah king of Judah took advice, and sent to Joash, the son of Jehoahaz, the son of Jehu, king of Israel, saying, Come, let us see one another in the face.

^18And Joash king of Israel sent to Amaziah king of Judah, saying, The thistle that was in Lebanon sent to the cedar that was in Lebanon, saying, Give thy daughter to my son to wife: and there passed by a wild beast that was in Lebanon, and trode down the thistle.

^19Thou sayest, Lo, thou hast smitten the Edomites; and thine heart lifteth thee up to boast: abide now at home; why shouldest thou meddle to thine hurt, that thou shouldest fall, even thou, and Judah with thee?

^20But Amaziah would not hear; for it came of God, that he might deliver them into the hand of their enemies, because they sought after the gods of Edom.

^21So Joash the king of Israel went up; and they saw one another in the face, both he and Amaziah king of Judah, at Bethshemesh, which belongeth to Judah.

^22And Judah was put to the worse before Israel, and they fled every man to his tent.

^23And Joash the king of Israel took Amaziah king of Judah, the son of Joash, the son of Jehoahaz, at Bethshemesh, and brought him to Jerusalem, and brake down the wall of Jerusalem from the gate of Ephraim to the corner gate, four hundred cubits.

^24And he took all the gold and the silver, and all the vessels that were found in the house of God with Obededom, and the treasures of the king’s house, the hostages also, and returned to Samaria.

^25And Amaziah the son of Joash king of Judah lived after the death of Joash son of Jehoahaz king of Israel fifteen years.

^26Now the rest of the acts of Amaziah, first and last, behold, are they not written in the book of the kings of Judah and Israel?

^27Now after the time that Amaziah did turn away from following the Lord they made a conspiracy against him in Jerusalem; and he fled to Lachish: but they sent to Lachish after him, and slew him there.

^28And they brought him upon horses, and buried him with his fathers in the city of Judah.

XXVI

^1Then all the people of Judah took Uzziah, who was sixteen years old, and made him king in the room of his father Amaziah.

^2He built Eloth, and restored it to Judah, after that the king slept with his fathers.

^3Sixteen years old was Uzziah when he began to reign, and he reigned fifty and two years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name also was Jecoliah of Jerusalem.

^4And he did that which was right in the sight of the Lord, according to all that his father Amaziah did.

^5And he sought God in the days of Zechariah, who had understanding in the visions of God: and as long as he sought the Lord, God made him to prosper.

^6And he went forth and warred against the Philistines, and brake down the wall of Gath, and the wall of Jabneh, and the wall of Ashdod, and built cities about Ashdod, and among the Philistines.

^7And God helped him against the Philistines, and against the Arabians that dwelt in Gurbaal, and the Mehunims.

^8And the Ammonites gave gifts to Uzziah: and his name spread abroad even to the entering in of Egypt; for he strengthened himself exceedingly.

^9Moreover Uzziah built towers in Jerusalem at the corner gate, and at the valley gate, and at the turning of the wall, and fortified them.

^10Also he built towers in the desert, and digged many wells: for he had much cattle, both in the low country, and in the plains: husbandmen also, and vine dressers in the mountains, and in Carmel: for he loved husbandry.

^11Moreover Uzziah had an host of fighting men, that went out to war by bands, according to the number of their account by the hand of Jeiel the scribe and Maaseiah the ruler, under the hand of Hananiah, one of the king’s captains.

^12The whole number of the chief of the fathers of the mighty men of valour were two thousand and six hundred.

^13And under their hand was an army, three hundred thousand and seven thousand and five hundred, that made war with mighty power, to help the king against the enemy.

^14And Uzziah prepared for them throughout all the host shields, and spears, and helmets, and habergeons, and bows, and slings to cast stones.

^15And he made in Jerusalem engines, invented by cunning men, to be on the towers and upon the bulwarks, to shoot arrows and great stones withal. And his name spread far abroad; for he was marvellously helped, till he was strong.

^16But when he was strong, his heart was lifted up to his destruction: for he transgressed against the Lord his God, and went into the temple of the Lord to burn incense upon the altar of incense.

^17And Azariah the priest went in after him, and with him fourscore priests of the Lord, that were valiant men:

^18And they withstood Uzziah the king, and said unto him, It appertaineth not unto thee, Uzziah, to burn incense unto the Lord, but to the priests the sons of Aaron, that are consecrated to burn incense: go out of the sanctuary; for thou hast trespassed; neither shall it be for thine honour from the Lord God.

^19Then Uzziah was wroth, and had a censer in his hand to burn incense: and while he was wroth with the priests, the leprosy even rose up in his forehead before the priests in the house of the Lord, from beside the incense altar.

^20And Azariah the chief priest, and all the priests, looked upon him, and, behold, he was leprous in his forehead, and they thrust him out from thence; yea, himself hasted also to go out, because the Lord had smitten him.

^21And Uzziah the king was a leper unto the day of his death, and dwelt in a several house, being a leper; for he was cut off from the house of the Lord: and Jotham his son was over the king’s house, judging the people of the land.

^22Now the rest of the acts of Uzziah, first and last, did Isaiah the prophet, the son of Amoz, write.

^23So Uzziah slept with his fathers, and they buried him with his fathers in the field of the burial which belonged to the kings; for they said, He is a leper: and Jotham his son reigned in his stead.

XXVII

^1Jotham was twenty and five years old when he began to reign, and he reigned sixteen years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name also was Jerushah, the daughter of Zadok.

^2And he did that which was right in the sight of the Lord, according to all that his father Uzziah did: howbeit he entered not into the temple of the Lord. And the people did yet corruptly.

^3He built the high gate of the house of the Lord, and on the wall of Ophel he built much.

^4Moreover he built cities in the mountains of Judah, and in the forests he built castles and towers.

^5He fought also with the king of the Ammonites, and prevailed against them. And the children of Ammon gave him the same year an hundred talents of silver, and ten thousand measures of wheat, and ten thousand of barley. So much did the children of Ammon pay unto him, both the second year, and the third.

^6So Jotham became mighty, because he prepared his ways before the Lord his God.

^7Now the rest of the acts of Jotham, and all his wars, and his ways, lo, they are written in the book of the kings of Israel and Judah.

^8He was five and twenty years old when he began to reign, and reigned sixteen years in Jerusalem.

^9And Jotham slept with his fathers, and they buried him in the city of David: and Ahaz his son reigned in his stead.

XXVIII

^1Ahaz was twenty years old when he began to reign, and he reigned sixteen years in Jerusalem: but he did not that which was right in the sight of the Lord, like David his father:

^2For he walked in the ways of the kings of Israel, and made also molten images for Baalim.

^3Moreover he burnt incense in the valley of the son of Hinnom, and burnt his children in the fire, after the abominations of the heathen whom the Lord had cast out before the children of Israel.

^4He sacrificed also and burnt incense in the high places, and on the hills, and under every green tree.

^5Wherefore the Lord his God delivered him into the hand of the king of Syria; and they smote him, and carried away a great multitude of them captives, and brought them to Damascus. And he was also delivered into the hand of the king of Israel, who smote him with a great slaughter.

^6For Pekah the son of Remaliah slew in Judah an hundred and twenty thousand in one day, which were all valiant men; because they had forsaken the Lord God of their fathers.

^7And Zichri, a mighty man of Ephraim, slew Maaseiah the king’s son, and Azrikam the governor of the house, and Elkanah that was next to the king.

^8And the children of Israel carried away captive of their brethren two hundred thousand, women, sons, and daughters, and took also away much spoil from them, and brought the spoil to Samaria.

^9But a prophet of the Lord was there, whose name was Oded: and he went out before the host that came to Samaria, and said unto them, Behold, because the Lord God of your fathers was wroth with Judah, he hath delivered them into your hand, and ye have slain them in a rage that reacheth up unto heaven.

^10And now ye purpose to keep under the children of Judah and Jerusalem for bondmen and bondwomen unto you: but are there not with you, even with you, sins against the Lord your God?

^11Now hear me therefore, and deliver the captives again, which ye have taken captive of your brethren: for the fierce wrath of the Lord is upon you.

^12Then certain of the heads of the children of Ephraim, Azariah the son of Johanan, Berechiah the son of Meshillemoth, and Jehizkiah the son of Shallum, and Amasa the son of Hadlai, stood up against them that came from the war,

^13And said unto them, Ye shall not bring in the captives hither: for whereas we have offended against the Lord already, ye intend to add more to our sins and to our trespass: for our trespass is great, and there is fierce wrath against Israel.

^14So the armed men left the captives and the spoil before the princes and all the congregation.

^15And the men which were expressed by name rose up, and took the captives, and with the spoil clothed all that were naked among them, and arrayed them, and shod them, and gave them to eat and to drink, and anointed them, and carried all the feeble of them upon asses, and brought them to Jericho, the city of palm trees, to their brethren: then they returned to Samaria.

^16At that time did king Ahaz send unto the kings of Assyria to help him.

^17For again the Edomites had come and smitten Judah, and carried away captives.

^18The Philistines also had invaded the cities of the low country, and of the south of Judah, and had taken Bethshemesh, and Ajalon, and Gederoth, and Shocho with the villages thereof, and Timnah with the villages thereof, Gimzo also and the villages thereof: and they dwelt there.

^19For the Lord brought Judah low because of Ahaz king of Israel; for he made Judah naked, and transgressed sore against the Lord.

^20And Tilgathpilneser king of Assyria came unto him, and distressed him, but strengthened him not.

^21For Ahaz took away a portion out of the house of the Lord, and out of the house of the king, and of the princes, and gave it unto the king of Assyria: but he helped him not.

^22And in the time of his distress did he trespass yet more against the Lord: this is that king Ahaz.

^23For he sacrificed unto the gods of Damascus, which smote him: and he said, Because the gods of the kings of Syria help them, therefore will I sacrifice to them, that they may help me. But they were the ruin of him, and of all Israel.

^24And Ahaz gathered together the vessels of the house of God, and cut in pieces the vessels of the house of God, and shut up the doors of the house of the Lord, and he made him altars in every corner of Jerusalem.

^25And in every several city of Judah he made high places to burn incense unto other gods, and provoked to anger the Lord God of his fathers.

^26Now the rest of his acts and of all his ways, first and last, behold, they are written in the book of the kings of Judah and Israel.

^27And Ahaz slept with his fathers, and they buried him in the city, even in Jerusalem: but they brought him not into the sepulchres of the kings of Israel: and Hezekiah his son reigned in his stead.

XXIX

^1Hezekiah began to reign when he was five and twenty years old, and he reigned nine and twenty years in Jerusalem. And his mother’s name was Abijah, the daughter of Zechariah.

^2And he did that which was right in the sight of the Lord, according to all that David his father had done.

^3He in the first year of his reign, in the first month, opened the doors of the house of the Lord, and repaired them.

^4And he brought in the priests and the Levites, and gathered them together into the east street,

^5And said unto them, Hear me, ye Levites, sanctify now yourselves, and sanctify the house of the Lord God of your fathers, and carry forth the filthiness out of the holy place.

^6For our fathers have trespassed, and done that which was evil in the eyes of the Lord our God, and have forsaken him, and have turned away their faces from the habitation of the Lord, and turned their backs.

^7Also they have shut up the doors of the porch, and put out the lamps, and have not burned incense nor offered burnt offerings in the holy place unto the God of Israel.

^8Wherefore the wrath of the Lord was upon Judah and Jerusalem, and he hath delivered them to trouble, to astonishment, and to hissing, as ye see with your eyes.

^9For, lo, our fathers have fallen by the sword, and our sons and our daughters and our wives are in captivity for this.

^10Now it is in mine heart to make a covenant with the Lord God of Israel, that his fierce wrath may turn away from us.

^11My sons, be not now negligent: for the Lord hath chosen you to stand before him, to serve him, and that ye should minister unto him, and burn incense.

^12Then the Levites arose, Mahath the son of Amasai, and Joel the son of Azariah, of the sons of the Kohathites: and of the sons of Merari, Kish the son of Abdi, and Azariah the son of Jehalelel: and of the Gershonites; Joah the son of Zimmah, and Eden the son of Joah:

^13And of the sons of Elizaphan; Shimri, and Jeiel: and of the sons of Asaph; Zechariah, and Mattaniah:

^14And of the sons of Heman; Jehiel, and Shimei: and of the sons of Jeduthun; Shemaiah, and Uzziel.

^15And they gathered their brethren, and sanctified themselves, and came, according to the commandment of the king, by the words of the Lord, to cleanse the house of the Lord.

^16And the priests went into the inner part of the house of the Lord, to cleanse it, and brought out all the uncleanness that they found in the temple of the Lord into the court of the house of the Lord. And the Levites took it, to carry it out abroad into the brook Kidron.

^17Now they began on the first day of the first month to sanctify, and on the eighth day of the month came they to the porch of the Lord: so they sanctified the house of the Lord in eight days; and in the sixteenth day of the first month they made an end.

^18Then they went in to Hezekiah the king, and said, We have cleansed all the house of the Lord, and the altar of burnt offering, with all the vessels thereof, and the shewbread table, with all the vessels thereof.

^19Moreover all the vessels, which king Ahaz in his reign did cast away in his transgression, have we prepared and sanctified, and, behold, they are before the altar of the Lord.

^20Then Hezekiah the king rose early, and gathered the rulers of the city, and went up to the house of the Lord.

^21And they brought seven bullocks, and seven rams, and seven lambs, and seven he goats, for a sin offering for the kingdom, and for the sanctuary, and for Judah. And he commanded the priests the sons of Aaron to offer them on the altar of the Lord.

^22So they killed the bullocks, and the priests received the blood, and sprinkled it on the altar: likewise, when they had killed the rams, they sprinkled the blood upon the altar: they killed also the lambs, and they sprinkled the blood upon the altar.

^23And they brought forth the he goats for the sin offering before the king and the congregation; and they laid their hands upon them:

^24And the priests killed them, and they made reconciliation with their blood upon the altar, to make an atonement for all Israel: for the king commanded that the burnt offering and the sin offering should be made for all Israel.

^25And he set the Levites in the house of the Lord with cymbals, with psalteries, and with harps, according to the commandment of David, and of Gad the king’s seer, and Nathan the prophet: for so was the commandment of the Lord by his prophets.

^26And the Levites stood with the instruments of David, and the priests with the trumpets.

^27And Hezekiah commanded to offer the burnt offering upon the altar. And when the burnt offering began, the song of the Lord began also with the trumpets, and with the instruments ordained by David king of Israel.

^28And all the congregation worshipped, and the singers sang, and the trumpeters sounded: and all this continued until the burnt offering was finished.

^29And when they had made an end of offering, the king and all that were present with him bowed themselves, and worshipped.

^30Moreover Hezekiah the king and the princes commanded the Levites to sing praise unto the Lord with the words of David, and of Asaph the seer. And they sang praises with gladness, and they bowed their heads and worshipped.

^31Then Hezekiah answered and said, Now ye have consecrated yourselves unto the Lord, come near and bring sacrifices and thank offerings into the house of the Lord. And the congregation brought in sacrifices and thank offerings; and as many as were of a free heart burnt offerings.

^32And the number of the burnt offerings, which the congregation brought, was threescore and ten bullocks, an hundred rams, and two hundred lambs: all these were for a burnt offering to the Lord.

^33And the consecrated things were six hundred oxen and three thousand sheep.

^34But the priests were too few, so that they could not flay all the burnt offerings: wherefore their brethren the Levites did help them, till the work was ended, and until the other priests had sanctified themselves: for the Levites were more upright in heart to sanctify themselves than the priests.

^35And also the burnt offerings were in abundance, with the fat of the peace offerings, and the drink offerings for every burnt offering. So the service of the house of the Lord was set in order.

^36And Hezekiah rejoiced, and all the people, that God had prepared the people: for the thing was done suddenly.

XXX

^1And Hezekiah sent to all Israel and Judah, and wrote letters also to Ephraim and Manasseh, that they should come to the house of the Lord at Jerusalem, to keep the passover unto the Lord God of Israel.

^2For the king had taken counsel, and his princes, and all the congregation in Jerusalem, to keep the passover in the second month.

^3For they could not keep it at that time, because the priests had not sanctified themselves sufficiently, neither had the people gathered themselves together to Jerusalem.

^4And the thing pleased the king and all the congregation.

^5So they established a decree to make proclamation throughout all Israel, from Beersheba even to Dan, that they should come to keep the passover unto the Lord God of Israel at Jerusalem: for they had not done it of a long time in such sort as it was written.

^6So the posts went with the letters from the king and his princes throughout all Israel and Judah, and according to the commandment of the king, saying, Ye children of Israel, turn again unto the Lord God of Abraham, Isaac, and Israel, and he will return to the remnant of you, that are escaped out of the hand of the kings of Assyria.

^7And be not ye like your fathers, and like your brethren, which trespassed against the Lord God of their fathers, who therefore gave them up to desolation, as ye see.

^8Now be ye not stiffnecked, as your fathers were, but yield yourselves unto the Lord, and enter into his sanctuary, which he hath sanctified for ever: and serve the Lord your God, that the fierceness of his wrath may turn away from you.

^9For if ye turn again unto the Lord, your brethren and your children shall find compassion before them that lead them captive, so that they shall come again into this land: for the Lord your God is gracious and merciful, and will not turn away his face from you, if ye return unto him.

^10So the posts passed from city to city through the country of Ephraim and Manasseh even unto Zebulun: but they laughed them to scorn, and mocked them.

^11Nevertheless divers of Asher and Manasseh and of Zebulun humbled themselves, and came to Jerusalem.

^12Also in Judah the hand of God was to give them one heart to do the commandment of the king and of the princes, by the word of the Lord.

^13And there assembled at Jerusalem much people to keep the feast of unleavened bread in the second month, a very great congregation.

^14And they arose and took away the altars that were in Jerusalem, and all the altars for incense took they away, and cast them into the brook Kidron.

^15Then they killed the passover on the fourteenth day of the second month: and the priests and the Levites were ashamed, and sanctified themselves, and brought in the burnt offerings into the house of the Lord.

^16And they stood in their place after their manner, according to the law of Moses the man of God: the priests sprinkled the blood, which they received of the hand of the Levites.

^17For there were many in the congregation that were not sanctified: therefore the Levites had the charge of the killing of the passovers for every one that was not clean, to sanctify them unto the Lord.

^18For a multitude of the people, even many of Ephraim, and Manasseh, Issachar, and Zebulun, had not cleansed themselves, yet did they eat the passover otherwise than it was written. But Hezekiah prayed for them, saying, The good Lord pardon every one

^19That prepareth his heart to seek God, the Lord God of his fathers, though he be not cleansed according to the purification of the sanctuary.

^20And the Lord hearkened to Hezekiah, and healed the people.

^21And the children of Israel that were present at Jerusalem kept the feast of unleavened bread seven days with great gladness: and the Levites and the priests praised the Lord day by day, singing with loud instruments unto the Lord.

^22And Hezekiah spake comfortably unto all the Levites that taught the good knowledge of the Lord: and they did eat throughout the feast seven days, offering peace offerings, and making confession to the Lord God of their fathers.

^23And the whole assembly took counsel to keep other seven days: and they kept other seven days with gladness.

^24For Hezekiah king of Judah did give to the congregation a thousand bullocks and seven thousand sheep; and the princes gave to the congregation a thousand bullocks and ten thousand sheep: and a great number of priests sanctified themselves.

^25And all the congregation of Judah, with the priests and the Levites, and all the congregation that came out of Israel, and the strangers that came out of the land of Israel, and that dwelt in Judah, rejoiced.

^26So there was great joy in Jerusalem: for since the time of Solomon the son of David king of Israel there was not the like in Jerusalem.

^27Then the priests the Levites arose and blessed the people: and their voice was heard, and their prayer came up to his holy dwelling place, even unto heaven.

XXXI

^1Now when all this was finished, all Israel that were present went out to the cities of Judah, and brake the images in pieces, and cut down the groves, and threw down the high places and the altars out of all Judah and Benjamin, in Ephraim also and Manasseh, until they had utterly destroyed them all. Then all the children of Israel returned, every man to his possession, into their own cities.

^2And Hezekiah appointed the courses of the priests and the Levites after their courses, every man according to his service, the priests and Levites for burnt offerings and for peace offerings, to minister, and to give thanks, and to praise in the gates of the tents of the Lord.

^3He appointed also the king’s portion of his substance for the burnt offerings, to wit, for the morning and evening burnt offerings, and the burnt offerings for the sabbaths, and for the new moons, and for the set feasts, as it is written in the law of the Lord.

^4Moreover he commanded the people that dwelt in Jerusalem to give the portion of the priests and the Levites, that they might be encouraged in the law of the Lord.

^5And as soon as the commandment came abroad, the children of Israel brought in abundance the firstfruits of corn, wine, and oil, and honey, and of all the increase of the field; and the tithe of all things brought they in abundantly.

^6And concerning the children of Israel and Judah, that dwelt in the cities of Judah, they also brought in the tithe of oxen and sheep, and the tithe of holy things which were consecrated unto the Lord their God, and laid them by heaps.

^7In the third month they began to lay the foundation of the heaps, and finished them in the seventh month.

^8And when Hezekiah and the princes came and saw the heaps, they blessed the Lord, and his people Israel.

^9Then Hezekiah questioned with the priests and the Levites concerning the heaps.

^10And Azariah the chief priest of the house of Zadok answered him, and said, Since the people began to bring the offerings into the house of the Lord, we have had enough to eat, and have left plenty: for the Lord hath blessed his people; and that which is left is this great store.

^11Then Hezekiah commanded to prepare chambers in the house of the Lord; and they prepared them,

^12And brought in the offerings and the tithes and the dedicated things faithfully: over which Cononiah the Levite was ruler, and Shimei his brother was the next.

^13And Jehiel, and Azaziah, and Nahath, and Asahel, and Jerimoth, and Jozabad, and Eliel, and Ismachiah, and Mahath, and Benaiah, were overseers under the hand of Cononiah and Shimei his brother, at the commandment of Hezekiah the king, and Azariah the ruler of the house of God.

^14And Kore the son of Imnah the Levite, the porter toward the east, was over the freewill offerings of God, to distribute the oblations of the Lord, and the most holy things.

^15And next him were Eden, and Miniamin, and Jeshua, and Shemaiah, Amariah, and Shecaniah, in the cities of the priests, in their set office, to give to their brethren by courses, as well to the great as to the small:

^16Beside their genealogy of males, from three years old and upward, even unto every one that entereth into the house of the Lord, his daily portion for their service in their charges according to their courses;

^17Both to the genealogy of the priests by the house of their fathers, and the Levites from twenty years old and upward, in their charges by their courses;

^18And to the genealogy of all their little ones, their wives, and their sons, and their daughters, through all the congregation: for in their set office they sanctified themselves in holiness:

^19Also of the sons of Aaron the priests, which were in the fields of the suburbs of their cities, in every several city, the men that were expressed by name, to give portions to all the males among the priests, and to all that were reckoned by genealogies among the Levites.

^20And thus did Hezekiah throughout all Judah, and wrought that which was good and right and truth before the Lord his God.

^21And in every work that he began in the service of the house of God, and in the law, and in the commandments, to seek his God, he did it with all his heart, and prospered.

XXXII

^1After these things, and the establishment thereof, Sennacherib king of Assyria came, and entered into Judah, and encamped against the fenced cities, and thought to win them for himself.

^2And when Hezekiah saw that Sennacherib was come, and that he was purposed to fight against Jerusalem,

^3He took counsel with his princes and his mighty men to stop the waters of the fountains which were without the city: and they did help him.

^4So there was gathered much people together, who stopped all the fountains, and the brook that ran through the midst of the land, saying, Why should the kings of Assyria come, and find much water?

^5Also he strengthened himself, and built up all the wall that was broken, and raised it up to the towers, and another wall without, and repaired Millo in the city of David, and made darts and shields in abundance.

^6And he set captains of war over the people, and gathered them together to him in the street of the gate of the city, and spake comfortably to them, saying,

^7Be strong and courageous, be not afraid nor dismayed for the king of Assyria, nor for all the multitude that is with him: for there be more with us than with him:

^8With him is an arm of flesh; but with us is the Lord our God to help us, and to fight our battles. And the people rested themselves upon the words of Hezekiah king of Judah.

^9After this did Sennacherib king of Assyria send his servants to Jerusalem, (but he himself laid siege against Lachish, and all his power with him,) unto Hezekiah king of Judah, and unto all Judah that were at Jerusalem, saying,

^10Thus saith Sennacherib king of Assyria, Whereon do ye trust, that ye abide in the siege in Jerusalem?

^11Doth not Hezekiah persuade you to give over yourselves to die by famine and by thirst, saying, The Lord our God shall deliver us out of the hand of the king of Assyria?

^12Hath not the same Hezekiah taken away his high places and his altars, and commanded Judah and Jerusalem, saying, Ye shall worship before one altar, and burn incense upon it?

^13Know ye not what I and my fathers have done unto all the people of other lands? were the gods of the nations of those lands any ways able to deliver their lands out of mine hand?

^14Who was there among all the gods of those nations that my fathers utterly destroyed, that could deliver his people out of mine hand, that your God should be able to deliver you out of mine hand?

^15Now therefore let not Hezekiah deceive you, nor persuade you on this manner, neither yet believe him: for no god of any nation or kingdom was able to deliver his people out of mine hand, and out of the hand of my fathers: how much less shall your God deliver you out of mine hand?

^16And his servants spake yet more against the Lord God, and against his servant Hezekiah.

^17He wrote also letters to rail on the Lord God of Israel, and to speak against him, saying, As the gods of the nations of other lands have not delivered their people out of mine hand, so shall not the God of Hezekiah deliver his people out of mine hand.

^18Then they cried with a loud voice in the Jews’ speech unto the people of Jerusalem that were on the wall, to affright them, and to trouble them; that they might take the city.

^19And they spake against the God of Jerusalem, as against the gods of the people of the earth, which were the work of the hands of man.

^20And for this cause Hezekiah the king, and the prophet Isaiah the son of Amoz, prayed and cried to heaven.

^21And the Lord sent an angel, which cut off all the mighty men of valour, and the leaders and captains in the camp of the king of Assyria. So he returned with shame of face to his own land. And when he was come into the house of his god, they that came forth of his own bowels slew him there with the sword.

^22Thus the Lord saved Hezekiah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem from the hand of Sennacherib the king of Assyria, and from the hand of all other, and guided them on every side.

^23And many brought gifts unto the Lord to Jerusalem, and presents to Hezekiah king of Judah: so that he was magnified in the sight of all nations from thenceforth.

^24In those days Hezekiah was sick to the death, and prayed unto the Lord: and he spake unto him, and he gave him a sign.

^25But Hezekiah rendered not again according to the benefit done unto him; for his heart was lifted up: therefore there was wrath upon him, and upon Judah and Jerusalem.

^26Notwithstanding Hezekiah humbled himself for the pride of his heart, both he and the inhabitants of Jerusalem, so that the wrath of the Lord came not upon them in the days of Hezekiah.

^27And Hezekiah had exceeding much riches and honour: and he made himself treasuries for silver, and for gold, and for precious stones, and for spices, and for shields, and for all manner of pleasant jewels;

^28Storehouses also for the increase of corn, and wine, and oil; and stalls for all manner of beasts, and cotes for flocks.

^29Moreover he provided him cities, and possessions of flocks and herds in abundance: for God had given him substance very much.

^30This same Hezekiah also stopped the upper watercourse of Gihon, and brought it straight down to the west side of the city of David. And Hezekiah prospered in all his works.

^31Howbeit in the business of the ambassadors of the princes of Babylon, who sent unto him to enquire of the wonder that was done in the land, God left him, to try him, that he might know all that was in his heart.

^32Now the rest of the acts of Hezekiah, and his goodness, behold, they are written in the vision of Isaiah the prophet, the son of Amoz, and in the book of the kings of Judah and Israel.

^33And Hezekiah slept with his fathers, and they buried him in the chiefest of the sepulchres of the sons of David: and all Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem did him honour at his death. And Manasseh his son reigned in his stead.

XXXIII

^1Manasseh was twelve years old when he began to reign, and he reigned fifty and five years in Jerusalem:

^2But did that which was evil in the sight of the Lord, like unto the abominations of the heathen, whom the Lord had cast out before the children of Israel.

^3For he built again the high places which Hezekiah his father had broken down, and he reared up altars for Baalim, and made groves, and worshipped all the host of heaven, and served them.

^4Also he built altars in the house of the Lord, whereof the Lord had said, In Jerusalem shall my name be for ever.

^5And he built altars for all the host of heaven in the two courts of the house of the Lord.

^6And he caused his children to pass through the fire in the valley of the son of Hinnom: also he observed times, and used enchantments, and used witchcraft, and dealt with a familiar spirit, and with wizards: he wrought much evil in the sight of the Lord, to provoke him to anger.

^7And he set a carved image, the idol which he had made, in the house of God, of which God had said to David and to Solomon his son, In this house, and in Jerusalem, which I have chosen before all the tribes of Israel, will I put my name for ever:

^8Neither will I any more remove the foot of Israel from out of the land which I have appointed for your fathers; so that they will take heed to do all that I have commanded them, according to the whole law and the statutes and the ordinances by the hand of Moses.

^9So Manasseh made Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem to err, and to do worse than the heathen, whom the Lord had destroyed before the children of Israel.

^10And the Lord spake to Manasseh, and to his people: but they would not hearken.

^11Wherefore the Lord brought upon them the captains of the host of the king of Assyria, which took Manasseh among the thorns, and bound him with fetters, and carried him to Babylon.

^12And when he was in affliction, he besought the Lord his God, and humbled himself greatly before the God of his fathers,

^13And prayed unto him: and he was intreated of him, and heard his supplication, and brought him again to Jerusalem into his kingdom. Then Manasseh knew that the Lord he was God.

^14Now after this he built a wall without the city of David, on the west side of Gihon, in the valley, even to the entering in at the fish gate, and compassed about Ophel, and raised it up a very great height, and put captains of war in all the fenced cities of Judah.

^15And he took away the strange gods, and the idol out of the house of the Lord, and all the altars that he had built in the mount of the house of the Lord, and in Jerusalem, and cast them out of the city.

^16And he repaired the altar of the Lord, and sacrificed thereon peace offerings and thank offerings, and commanded Judah to serve the Lord God of Israel.

^17Nevertheless the people did sacrifice still in the high places, yet unto the Lord their God only.

^18Now the rest of the acts of Manasseh, and his prayer unto his God, and the words of the seers that spake to him in the name of the Lord God of Israel, behold, they are written in the book of the kings of Israel.

^19His prayer also, and how God was intreated of him, and all his sins, and his trespass, and the places wherein he built high places, and set up groves and graven images, before he was humbled: behold, they are written among the sayings of the seers.

^20So Manasseh slept with his fathers, and they buried him in his own house: and Amon his son reigned in his stead.

^21Amon was two and twenty years old when he began to reign, and reigned two years in Jerusalem.

^22But he did that which was evil in the sight of the Lord, as did Manasseh his father: for Amon sacrificed unto all the carved images which Manasseh his father had made, and served them;

^23And humbled not himself before the Lord, as Manasseh his father had humbled himself; but Amon trespassed more and more.

^24And his servants conspired against him, and slew him in his own house.

^25But the people of the land slew all them that had conspired against king Amon; and the people of the land made Josiah his son king in his stead.

XXXIV

^1Josiah was eight years old when he began to reign, and he reigned in Jerusalem one and thirty years.

^2And he did that which was right in the sight of the Lord, and walked in the ways of David his father, and declined neither to the right hand, nor to the left.

^3For in the eighth year of his reign, while he was yet young, he began to seek after the God of David his father: and in the twelfth year he began to purge Judah and Jerusalem from the high places, and the groves, and the carved images, and the molten images.

^4And they brake down the altars of Baalim in his presence; and the images, that were on high above them, he cut down; and the groves, and the carved images, and the molten images, he brake in pieces, and made dust of them, and strowed it upon the graves of them that had sacrificed unto them.

^5And he burnt the bones of the priests upon their altars, and cleansed Judah and Jerusalem.

^6And so did he in the cities of Manasseh, and Ephraim, and Simeon, even unto Naphtali, with their mattocks round about.

^7And when he had broken down the altars and the groves, and had beaten the graven images into powder, and cut down all the idols throughout all the land of Israel, he returned to Jerusalem.

^8Now in the eighteenth year of his reign, when he had purged the land, and the house, he sent Shaphan the son of Azaliah, and Maaseiah the governor of the city, and Joah the son of Joahaz the recorder, to repair the house of the Lord his God.

^9And when they came to Hilkiah the high priest, they delivered the money that was brought into the house of God, which the Levites that kept the doors had gathered of the hand of Manasseh and Ephraim, and of all the remnant of Israel, and of all Judah and Benjamin; and they returned to Jerusalem.

^10And they put it in the hand of the workmen that had the oversight of the house of the Lord, and they gave it to the workmen that wrought in the house of the Lord, to repair and amend the house:

^11Even to the artificers and builders gave they it, to buy hewn stone, and timber for couplings, and to floor the houses which the kings of Judah had destroyed.

^12And the men did the work faithfully: and the overseers of them were Jahath and Obadiah, the Levites, of the sons of Merari; and Zechariah and Meshullam, of the sons of the Kohathites, to set it forward; and other of the Levites, all that could skill of instruments of musick.

^13Also they were over the bearers of burdens, and were overseers of all that wrought the work in any manner of service: and of the Levites there were scribes, and officers, and porters.

^14And when they brought out the money that was brought into the house of the Lord, Hilkiah the priest found a book of the law of the Lord given by Moses.

^15And Hilkiah answered and said to Shaphan the scribe, I have found the book of the law in the house of the Lord. And Hilkiah delivered the book to Shaphan.

^16And Shaphan carried the book to the king, and brought the king word back again, saying, All that was committed to thy servants, they do it.

^17And they have gathered together the money that was found in the house of the Lord, and have delivered it into the hand of the overseers, and to the hand of the workmen.

^18Then Shaphan the scribe told the king, saying, Hilkiah the priest hath given me a book. And Shaphan read it before the king.

^19And it came to pass, when the king had heard the words of the law, that he rent his clothes.

^20And the king commanded Hilkiah, and Ahikam the son of Shaphan, and Abdon the son of Micah, and Shaphan the scribe, and Asaiah a servant of the king’s, saying,

^21Go, enquire of the Lord for me, and for them that are left in Israel and in Judah, concerning the words of the book that is found: for great is the wrath of the Lord that is poured out upon us, because our fathers have not kept the word of the Lord, to do after all that is written in this book.

^22And Hilkiah, and they that the king had appointed, went to Huldah the prophetess, the wife of Shallum the son of Tikvath, the son of Hasrah, keeper of the wardrobe; (now she dwelt in Jerusalem in the college:) and they spake to her to that effect.

^23And she answered them, Thus saith the Lord God of Israel, Tell ye the man that sent you to me,

^24Thus saith the Lord, Behold, I will bring evil upon this place, and upon the inhabitants thereof, even all the curses that are written in the book which they have read before the king of Judah:

^25Because they have forsaken me, and have burned incense unto other gods, that they might provoke me to anger with all the works of their hands; therefore my wrath shall be poured out upon this place, and shall not be quenched.

^26And as for the king of Judah, who sent you to enquire of the Lord, so shall ye say unto him, Thus saith the Lord God of Israel concerning the words which thou hast heard;

^27Because thine heart was tender, and thou didst humble thyself before God, when thou heardest his words against this place, and against the inhabitants thereof, and humbledst thyself before me, and didst rend thy clothes, and weep before me; I have even heard thee also, saith the Lord.

^28Behold, I will gather thee to thy fathers, and thou shalt be gathered to thy grave in peace, neither shall thine eyes see all the evil that I will bring upon this place, and upon the inhabitants of the same. So they brought the king word again.

^29Then the king sent and gathered together all the elders of Judah and Jerusalem.

^30And the king went up into the house of the Lord, and all the men of Judah, and the inhabitants of Jerusalem, and the priests, and the Levites, and all the people, great and small: and he read in their ears all the words of the book of the covenant that was found in the house of the Lord.

^31And the king stood in his place, and made a covenant before the Lord, to walk after the Lord, and to keep his commandments, and his testimonies, and his statutes, with all his heart, and with all his soul, to perform the words of the covenant which are written in this book.

^32And he caused all that were present in Jerusalem and Benjamin to stand to it. And the inhabitants of Jerusalem did according to the covenant of God, the God of their fathers.

^33And Josiah took away all the abominations out of all the countries that pertained to the children of Israel, and made all that were present in Israel to serve, even to serve the Lord their God. And all his days they departed not from following the Lord, the God of their fathers.

XXXV

^1Moreover Josiah kept a passover unto the Lord in Jerusalem: and they killed the passover on the fourteenth day of the first month.

^2And he set the priests in their charges, and encouraged them to the service of the house of the Lord,

^3And said unto the Levites that taught all Israel, which were holy unto the Lord, Put the holy ark in the house which Solomon the son of David king of Israel did build; it shall not be a burden upon your shoulders: serve now the Lord your God, and his people Israel,

^4And prepare yourselves by the houses of your fathers, after your courses, according to the writing of David king of Israel, and according to the writing of Solomon his son.

^5And stand in the holy place according to the divisions of the families of the fathers of your brethren the people, and after the division of the families of the Levites.

^6So kill the passover, and sanctify yourselves, and prepare your brethren, that they may do according to the word of the Lord by the hand of Moses.

^7And Josiah gave to the people, of the flock, lambs and kids, all for the passover offerings, for all that were present, to the number of thirty thousand, and three thousand bullocks: these were of the king’s substance.

^8And his princes gave willingly unto the people, to the priests, and to the Levites: Hilkiah and Zechariah and Jehiel, rulers of the house of God, gave unto the priests for the passover offerings two thousand and six hundred small cattle and three hundred oxen.

^9Conaniah also, and Shemaiah and Nethaneel, his brethren, and Hashabiah and Jeiel and Jozabad, chief of the Levites, gave unto the Levites for passover offerings five thousand small cattle, and five hundred oxen.

^10So the service was prepared, and the priests stood in their place, and the Levites in their courses, according to the king’s commandment.

^11And they killed the passover, and the priests sprinkled the blood from their hands, and the Levites flayed them.

^12And they removed the burnt offerings, that they might give according to the divisions of the families of the people, to offer unto the Lord, as it is written in the book of Moses. And so did they with the oxen.

^13And they roasted the passover with fire according to the ordinance: but the other holy offerings sod they in pots, and in caldrons, and in pans, and divided them speedily among all the people.

^14And afterward they made ready for themselves, and for the priests: because the priests the sons of Aaron were busied in offering of burnt offerings and the fat until night; therefore the Levites prepared for themselves, and for the priests the sons of Aaron.

^15And the singers the sons of Asaph were in their place, according to the commandment of David, and Asaph, and Heman, and Jeduthun the king’s seer; and the porters waited at every gate; they might not depart from their service; for their brethren the Levites prepared for them.

^16So all the service of the Lord was prepared the same day, to keep the passover, and to offer burnt offerings upon the altar of the Lord, according to the commandment of king Josiah.

^17And the children of Israel that were present kept the passover at that time, and the feast of unleavened bread seven days.

^18And there was no passover like to that kept in Israel from the days of Samuel the prophet; neither did all the kings of Israel keep such a passover as Josiah kept, and the priests, and the Levites, and all Judah and Israel that were present, and the inhabitants of Jerusalem.

^19In the eighteenth year of the reign of Josiah was this passover kept.

^20After all this, when Josiah had prepared the temple, Necho king of Egypt came up to fight against Charchemish by Euphrates: and Josiah went out against him.

^21But he sent ambassadors to him, saying, What have I to do with thee, thou king of Judah? I come not against thee this day, but against the house wherewith I have war: for God commanded me to make haste: forbear thee from meddling with God, who is with me, that he destroy thee not.

^22Nevertheless Josiah would not turn his face from him, but disguised himself, that he might fight with him, and hearkened not unto the words of Necho from the mouth of God, and came to fight in the valley of Megiddo.

^23And the archers shot at king Josiah; and the king said to his servants, Have me away; for I am sore wounded.

^24His servants therefore took him out of that chariot, and put him in the second chariot that he had; and they brought him to Jerusalem, and he died, and was buried in one of the sepulchres of his fathers. And all Judah and Jerusalem mourned for Josiah.

^25And Jeremiah lamented for Josiah: and all the singing men and the singing women spake of Josiah in their lamentations to this day, and made them an ordinance in Israel: and, behold, they are written in the lamentations.

^26Now the rest of the acts of Josiah, and his goodness, according to that which was written in the law of the Lord,

^27And his deeds, first and last, behold, they are written in the book of the kings of Israel and Judah.

XXXVI

^1Then the people of the land took Jehoahaz the son of Josiah, and made him king in his father’s stead in Jerusalem.

^2Jehoahaz was twenty and three years old when he began to reign, and he reigned three months in Jerusalem.

^3And the king of Egypt put him down at Jerusalem, and condemned the land in an hundred talents of silver and a talent of gold.

^4And the king of Egypt made Eliakim his brother king over Judah and Jerusalem, and turned his name to Jehoiakim. And Necho took Jehoahaz his brother, and carried him to Egypt.

^5Jehoiakim was twenty and five years old when he began to reign, and he reigned eleven years in Jerusalem: and he did that which was evil in the sight of the Lord his God.

^6Against him came up Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon, and bound him in fetters, to carry him to Babylon.

^7Nebuchadnezzar also carried of the vessels of the house of the Lord to Babylon, and put them in his temple at Babylon.

^8Now the rest of the acts of Jehoiakim, and his abominations which he did, and that which was found in him, behold, they are written in the book of the kings of Israel and Judah: and Jehoiachin his son reigned in his stead.

^9Jehoiachin was eight years old when he began to reign, and he reigned three months and ten days in Jerusalem: and he did that which was evil in the sight of the Lord.

^10And when the year was expired, king Nebuchadnezzar sent, and brought him to Babylon, with the goodly vessels of the house of the Lord, and made Zedekiah his brother king over Judah and Jerusalem.

^11Zedekiah was one and twenty years old when he began to reign, and reigned eleven years in Jerusalem.

^12And he did that which was evil in the sight of the Lord his God, and humbled not himself before Jeremiah the prophet speaking from the mouth of the Lord.

^13And he also rebelled against king Nebuchadnezzar, who had made him swear by God: but he stiffened his neck, and hardened his heart from turning unto the Lord God of Israel.

^14Moreover all the chief of the priests, and the people, transgressed very much after all the abominations of the heathen; and polluted the house of the Lord which he had hallowed in Jerusalem.

^15And the Lord God of their fathers sent to them by his messengers, rising up betimes, and sending; because he had compassion on his people, and on his dwelling place:

^16But they mocked the messengers of God, and despised his words, and misused his prophets, until the wrath of the Lord arose against his people, till there was no remedy.

^17Therefore he brought upon them the king of the Chaldees, who slew their young men with the sword in the house of their sanctuary, and had no compassion upon young man or maiden, old man, or him that stooped for age: he gave them all into his hand.

^18And all the vessels of the house of God, great and small, and the treasures of the house of the Lord, and the treasures of the king, and of his princes; all these he brought to Babylon.

^19And they burnt the house of God, and brake down the wall of Jerusalem, and burnt all the palaces thereof with fire, and destroyed all the goodly vessels thereof.

^20And them that had escaped from the sword carried he away to Babylon; where they were servants to him and his sons until the reign of the kingdom of Persia:

^21To fulfil the word of the Lord by the mouth of Jeremiah, until the land had enjoyed her sabbaths: for as long as she lay desolate she kept sabbath, to fulfil threescore and ten years.

^22Now in the first year of Cyrus king of Persia, that the word of the Lord spoken by the mouth of Jeremiah might be accomplished, the Lord stirred up the spirit of Cyrus king of Persia, that he made a proclamation throughout all his kingdom, and put it also in writing, saying,

^23Thus saith Cyrus king of Persia, All the kingdoms of the earth hath the Lord God of heaven given me; and he hath charged me to build him an house in Jerusalem, which is in Judah. Who is there among you of all his people? The Lord his God be with him, and let him go up.

Ezra

The Book of

Ezra

I

^1Now in the first year of Cyrus king of Persia, that the word of the Lord by the mouth of Jeremiah might be fulfilled, the Lord stirred up the spirit of Cyrus king of Persia, that he made a proclamation throughout all his kingdom, and put it also in writing, saying,

^2Thus saith Cyrus king of Persia, The Lord God of heaven hath given me all the kingdoms of the earth; and he hath charged me to build him an house at Jerusalem, which is in Judah.

^3Who is there among you of all his people? his God be with him, and let him go up to Jerusalem, which is in Judah, and build the house of the Lord God of Israel, (he is the God,) which is in Jerusalem.

^4And whosoever remaineth in any place where he sojourneth, let the men of his place help him with silver, and with gold, and with goods, and with beasts, beside the freewill offering for the house of God that is in Jerusalem.

^5Then rose up the chief of the fathers of Judah and Benjamin, and the priests, and the Levites, with all them whose spirit God had raised, to go up to build the house of the Lord which is in Jerusalem.

^6And all they that were about them strengthened their hands with vessels of silver, with gold, with goods, and with beasts, and with precious things, beside all that was willingly offered.

^7Also Cyrus the king brought forth the vessels of the house of the Lord, which Nebuchadnezzar had brought forth out of Jerusalem, and had put them in the house of his gods;

^8Even those did Cyrus king of Persia bring forth by the hand of Mithredath the treasurer, and numbered them unto Sheshbazzar, the prince of Judah.

^9And this is the number of them: thirty chargers of gold, a thousand chargers of silver, nine and twenty knives,

^10Thirty basons of gold, silver basons of a second sort four hundred and ten, and other vessels a thousand.

^11All the vessels of gold and of silver were five thousand and four hundred. All these did Sheshbazzar bring up with them of the captivity that were brought up from Babylon unto Jerusalem.

II

^1Now these are the children of the province that went up out of the captivity, of those which had been carried away, whom Nebuchadnezzar the king of Babylon had carried away unto Babylon, and came again unto Jerusalem and Judah, every one unto his city;

^2Which came with Zerubbabel: Jeshua, Nehemiah, Seraiah, Reelaiah, Mordecai, Bilshan, Mizpar, Bigvai, Rehum, Baanah. The number of the men of the people of Israel:

^3The children of Parosh, two thousand an hundred seventy and two.

^4The children of Shephatiah, three hundred seventy and two.

^5The children of Arah, seven hundred seventy and five.

^6The children of Pahathmoab, of the children of Jeshua and Joab, two thousand eight hundred and twelve.

^7The children of Elam, a thousand two hundred fifty and four.

^8The children of Zattu, nine hundred forty and five.

^9The children of Zaccai, seven hundred and threescore.

^10The children of Bani, six hundred forty and two.

^11The children of Bebai, six hundred twenty and three.

^12The children of Azgad, a thousand two hundred twenty and two.

^13The children of Adonikam, six hundred sixty and six.

^14The children of Bigvai, two thousand fifty and six.

^15The children of Adin, four hundred fifty and four.

^16The children of Ater of Hezekiah, ninety and eight.

^17The children of Bezai, three hundred twenty and three.

^18The children of Jorah, an hundred and twelve.

^19The children of Hashum, two hundred twenty and three.

^20The children of Gibbar, ninety and five.

^21The children of Bethlehem, an hundred twenty and three.

^22The men of Netophah, fifty and six.

^23The men of Anathoth, an hundred twenty and eight.

^24The children of Azmaveth, forty and two.

^25The children of Kirjatharim, Chephirah, and Beeroth, seven hundred and forty and three.

^26The children of Ramah and Gaba, six hundred twenty and one.

^27The men of Michmas, an hundred twenty and two.

^28The men of Bethel and Ai, two hundred twenty and three.

^29The children of Nebo, fifty and two.

^30The children of Magbish, an hundred fifty and six.

^31The children of the other Elam, a thousand two hundred fifty and four.

^32The children of Harim, three hundred and twenty.

^33The children of Lod, Hadid, and Ono, seven hundred twenty and five.

^34The children of Jericho, three hundred forty and five.

^35The children of Senaah, three thousand and six hundred and thirty.

^36The priests: the children of Jedaiah, of the house of Jeshua, nine hundred seventy and three.

^37The children of Immer, a thousand fifty and two.

^38The children of Pashur, a thousand two hundred forty and seven.

^39The children of Harim, a thousand and seventeen.

^40The Levites: the children of Jeshua and Kadmiel, of the children of Hodaviah, seventy and four.

^41The singers: the children of Asaph, an hundred twenty and eight.

^42The children of the porters: the children of Shallum, the children of Ater, the children of Talmon, the children of Akkub, the children of Hatita, the children of Shobai, in all an hundred thirty and nine.

^43The Nethinims: the children of Ziha, the children of Hasupha, the children of Tabbaoth,

^44The children of Keros, the children of Siaha, the children of Padon,

^45The children of Lebanah, the children of Hagabah, the children of Akkub,

^46The children of Hagab, the children of Shalmai, the children of Hanan,

^47The children of Giddel, the children of Gahar, the children of Reaiah,

^48The children of Rezin, the children of Nekoda, the children of Gazzam,

^49The children of Uzza, the children of Paseah, the children of Besai,

^50The children of Asnah, the children of Mehunim, the children of Nephusim,

^51The children of Bakbuk, the children of Hakupha, the children of Harhur,

^52The children of Bazluth, the children of Mehida, the children of Harsha,

^53The children of Barkos, the children of Sisera, the children of Thamah,

^54The children of Neziah, the children of Hatipha.

^55The children of Solomon’s servants: the children of Sotai, the children of Sophereth, the children of Peruda,

^56The children of Jaalah, the children of Darkon, the children of Giddel,

^57The children of Shephatiah, the children of Hattil, the children of Pochereth of Zebaim, the children of Ami.

^58All the Nethinims, and the children of Solomon’s servants, were three hundred ninety and two.

^59And these were they which went up from Telmelah, Telharsa, Cherub, Addan, and Immer: but they could not shew their father’s house, and their seed, whether they were of Israel:

^60The children of Delaiah, the children of Tobiah, the children of Nekoda, six hundred fifty and two.

^61And of the children of the priests: the children of Habaiah, the children of Koz, the children of Barzillai; which took a wife of the daughters of Barzillai the Gileadite, and was called after their name:

^62These sought their register among those that were reckoned by genealogy, but they were not found: therefore were they, as polluted, put from the priesthood.

^63And the Tirshatha said unto them, that they should not eat of the most holy things, till there stood up a priest with Urim and with Thummim.

^64The whole congregation together was forty and two thousand three hundred and threescore,

^65Beside their servants and their maids, of whom there were seven thousand three hundred thirty and seven: and there were among them two hundred singing men and singing women.

^66Their horses were seven hundred thirty and six; their mules, two hundred forty and five;

^67Their camels, four hundred thirty and five; their asses, six thousand seven hundred and twenty.

^68And some of the chief of the fathers, when they came to the house of the Lord which is at Jerusalem, offered freely for the house of God to set it up in his place:

^69They gave after their ability unto the treasure of the work threescore and one thousand drams of gold, and five thousand pound of silver, and one hundred priests’ garments.

^70So the priests, and the Levites, and some of the people, and the singers, and the porters, and the Nethinims, dwelt in their cities, and all Israel in their cities.

III

^1And when the seventh month was come, and the children of Israel were in the cities, the people gathered themselves together as one man to Jerusalem.

^2Then stood up Jeshua the son of Jozadak, and his brethren the priests, and Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, and his brethren, and builded the altar of the God of Israel, to offer burnt offerings thereon, as it is written in the law of Moses the man of God.

^3And they set the altar upon his bases; for fear was upon them because of the people of those countries: and they offered burnt offerings thereon unto the Lord, even burnt offerings morning and evening.

^4They kept also the feast of tabernacles, as it is written, and offered the daily burnt offerings by number, according to the custom, as the duty of every day required;

^5And afterward offered the continual burnt offering, both of the new moons, and of all the set feasts of the Lord that were consecrated, and of every one that willingly offered a freewill offering unto the Lord.

^6From the first day of the seventh month began they to offer burnt offerings unto the Lord. But the foundation of the temple of the Lord was not yet laid.

^7They gave money also unto the masons, and to the carpenters; and meat, and drink, and oil, unto them of Zidon, and to them of Tyre, to bring cedar trees from Lebanon to the sea of Joppa, according to the grant that they had of Cyrus king of Persia.

^8Now in the second year of their coming unto the house of God at Jerusalem, in the second month, began Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, and Jeshua the son of Jozadak, and the remnant of their brethren the priests and the Levites, and all they that were come out of the captivity unto Jerusalem; and appointed the Levites, from twenty years old and upward, to set forward the work of the house of the Lord.

^9Then stood Jeshua with his sons and his brethren, Kadmiel and his sons, the sons of Judah, together, to set forward the workmen in the house of God: the sons of Henadad, with their sons and their brethren the Levites.

^10And when the builders laid the foundation of the temple of the Lord, they set the priests in their apparel with trumpets, and the Levites the sons of Asaph with cymbals, to praise the Lord, after the ordinance of David king of Israel.

^11And they sang together by course in praising and giving thanks unto the Lord; because he is good, for his mercy endureth for ever toward Israel. And all the people shouted with a great shout, when they praised the Lord, because the foundation of the house of the Lord was laid.

^12But many of the priests and Levites and chief of the fathers, who were ancient men, that had seen the first house, when the foundation of this house was laid before their eyes, wept with a loud voice; and many shouted aloud for joy:

^13So that the people could not discern the noise of the shout of joy from the noise of the weeping of the people: for the people shouted with a loud shout, and the noise was heard afar off.

IV

^1Now when the adversaries of Judah and Benjamin heard that the children of the captivity builded the temple unto the Lord God of Israel;

^2Then they came to Zerubbabel, and to the chief of the fathers, and said unto them, Let us build with you: for we seek your God, as ye do; and we do sacrifice unto him since the days of Esarhaddon king of Assur, which brought us up hither.

^3But Zerubbabel, and Jeshua, and the rest of the chief of the fathers of Israel, said unto them, Ye have nothing to do with us to build an house unto our God; but we ourselves together will build unto the Lord God of Israel, as king Cyrus the king of Persia hath commanded us.

^4Then the people of the land weakened the hands of the people of Judah, and troubled them in building,

^5And hired counsellors against them, to frustrate their purpose, all the days of Cyrus king of Persia, even until the reign of Darius king of Persia.

^6And in the reign of Ahasuerus, in the beginning of his reign, wrote they unto him an accusation against the inhabitants of Judah and Jerusalem.

^7And in the days of Artaxerxes wrote Bishlam, Mithredath, Tabeel, and the rest of their companions, unto Artaxerxes king of Persia; and the writing of the letter was written in the Syrian tongue, and interpreted in the Syrian tongue.

^8Rehum the chancellor and Shimshai the scribe wrote a letter against Jerusalem to Artaxerxes the king in this sort:

^9Then wrote Rehum the chancellor, and Shimshai the scribe, and the rest of their companions; the Dinaites, the Apharsathchites, the Tarpelites, the Apharsites, the Archevites, the Babylonians, the Susanchites, the Dehavites, and the Elamites,

^10And the rest of the nations whom the great and noble Asnapper brought over, and set in the cities of Samaria, and the rest that are on this side the river, and at such a time.

^11This is the copy of the letter that they sent unto him, even unto Artaxerxes the king; Thy servants the men on this side the river, and at such a time.

^12Be it known unto the king, that the Jews which came up from thee to us are come unto Jerusalem, building the rebellious and the bad city, and have set up the walls thereof, and joined the foundations.

^13Be it known now unto the king, that, if this city be builded, and the walls set up again, then will they not pay toll, tribute, and custom, and so thou shalt endamage the revenue of the kings.

^14Now because we have maintenance from the king’s palace, and it was not meet for us to see the king’s dishonour, therefore have we sent and certified the king;

^15That search may be made in the book of the records of thy fathers: so shalt thou find in the book of the records, and know that this city is a rebellious city, and hurtful unto kings and provinces, and that they have moved sedition within the same of old time: for which cause was this city destroyed.

^16We certify the king that, if this city be builded again, and the walls thereof set up, by this means thou shalt have no portion on this side the river.

^17Then sent the king an answer unto Rehum the chancellor, and to Shimshai the scribe, and to the rest of their companions that dwell in Samaria, and unto the rest beyond the river, Peace, and at such a time.

^18The letter which ye sent unto us hath been plainly read before me.

^19And I commanded, and search hath been made, and it is found that this city of old time hath made insurrection against kings, and that rebellion and sedition have been made therein.

^20There have been mighty kings also over Jerusalem, which have ruled over all countries beyond the river; and toll, tribute, and custom, was paid unto them.

^21Give ye now commandment to cause these men to cease, and that this city be not builded, until another commandment shall be given from me.

^22Take heed now that ye fail not to do this: why should damage grow to the hurt of the kings?

^23Now when the copy of king Artaxerxes’ letter was read before Rehum, and Shimshai the scribe, and their companions, they went up in haste to Jerusalem unto the Jews, and made them to cease by force and power.

^24Then ceased the work of the house of God which is at Jerusalem. So it ceased unto the second year of the reign of Darius king of Persia.

V

^1Then the prophets, Haggai the prophet, and Zechariah the son of Iddo, prophesied unto the Jews that were in Judah and Jerusalem in the name of the God of Israel, even unto them.

^2Then rose up Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, and Jeshua the son of Jozadak, and began to build the house of God which is at Jerusalem: and with them were the prophets of God helping them.

^3At the same time came to them Tatnai, governor on this side the river, and Shetharboznai and their companions, and said thus unto them, Who hath commanded you to build this house, and to make up this wall?

^4Then said we unto them after this manner, What are the names of the men that make this building?

^5But the eye of their God was upon the elders of the Jews, that they could not cause them to cease, till the matter came to Darius: and then they returned answer by letter concerning this matter.

^6The copy of the letter that Tatnai, governor on this side the river, and Shetharboznai and his companions the Apharsachites, which were on this side the river, sent unto Darius the king:

^7They sent a letter unto him, wherein was written thus; Unto Darius the king, all peace.

^8Be it known unto the king, that we went into the province of Judea, to the house of the great God, which is builded with great stones, and timber is laid in the walls, and this work goeth fast on, and prospereth in their hands.

^9Then asked we those elders, and said unto them thus, Who commanded you to build this house, and to make up these walls?

^10We asked their names also, to certify thee, that we might write the names of the men that were the chief of them.

^11And thus they returned us answer, saying, We are the servants of the God of heaven and earth, and build the house that was builded these many years ago, which a great king of Israel builded and set up.

^12But after that our fathers had provoked the God of heaven unto wrath, he gave them into the hand of Nebuchadnezzar the king of Babylon, the Chaldean, who destroyed this house, and carried the people away into Babylon.

^13But in the first year of Cyrus the king of Babylon the same king Cyrus made a decree to build this house of God.

^14And the vessels also of gold and silver of the house of God, which Nebuchadnezzar took out of the temple that was in Jerusalem, and brought them into the temple of Babylon, those did Cyrus the king take out of the temple of Babylon, and they were delivered unto one, whose name was Sheshbazzar, whom he had made governor;

^15And said unto him, Take these vessels, go, carry them into the temple that is in Jerusalem, and let the house of God be builded in his place.

^16Then came the same Sheshbazzar, and laid the foundation of the house of God which is in Jerusalem: and since that time even until now hath it been in building, and yet it is not finished.

^17Now therefore, if it seem good to the king, let there be search made in the king’s treasure house, which is there at Babylon, whether it be so, that a decree was made of Cyrus the king to build this house of God at Jerusalem, and let the king send his pleasure to us concerning this matter.

VI

^1Then Darius the king made a decree, and search was made in the house of the rolls, where the treasures were laid up in Babylon.

^2And there was found at Achmetha, in the palace that is in the province of the Medes, a roll, and therein was a record thus written:

^3In the first year of Cyrus the king the same Cyrus the king made a decree concerning the house of God at Jerusalem, Let the house be builded, the place where they offered sacrifices, and let the foundations thereof be strongly laid; the height thereof threescore cubits, and the breadth thereof threescore cubits;

^4With three rows of great stones, and a row of new timber: and let the expenses be given out of the king’s house:

^5And also let the golden and silver vessels of the house of God, which Nebuchadnezzar took forth out of the temple which is at Jerusalem, and brought unto Babylon, be restored, and brought again unto the temple which is at Jerusalem, every one to his place, and place them in the house of God.

^6Now therefore, Tatnai, governor beyond the river, Shetharboznai, and your companions the Apharsachites, which are beyond the river, be ye far from thence:

^7Let the work of this house of God alone; let the governor of the Jews and the elders of the Jews build this house of God in his place.

^8Moreover I make a decree what ye shall do to the elders of these Jews for the building of this house of God: that of the king’s goods, even of the tribute beyond the river, forthwith expenses be given unto these men, that they be not hindered.

^9And that which they have need of, both young bullocks, and rams, and lambs, for the burnt offerings of the God of heaven, wheat, salt, wine, and oil, according to the appointment of the priests which are at Jerusalem, let it be given them day by day without fail:

^10That they may offer sacrifices of sweet savours unto the God of heaven, and pray for the life of the king, and of his sons.

^11Also I have made a decree, that whosoever shall alter this word, let timber be pulled down from his house, and being set up, let him be hanged thereon; and let his house be made a dunghill for this.

^12And the God that hath caused his name to dwell there destroy all kings and people, that shall put to their hand to alter and to destroy this house of God which is at Jerusalem. I Darius have made a decree; let it be done with speed.

^13Then Tatnai, governor on this side the river, Shetharboznai, and their companions, according to that which Darius the king had sent, so they did speedily.

^14And the elders of the Jews builded, and they prospered through the prophesying of Haggai the prophet and Zechariah the son of Iddo. And they builded, and finished it, according to the commandment of the God of Israel, and according to the commandment of Cyrus, and Darius, and Artaxerxes king of Persia.

^15And this house was finished on the third day of the month Adar, which was in the sixth year of the reign of Darius the king.

^16And the children of Israel, the priests, and the Levites, and the rest of the children of the captivity, kept the dedication of this house of God with joy.

^17And offered at the dedication of this house of God an hundred bullocks, two hundred rams, four hundred lambs; and for a sin offering for all Israel, twelve he goats, according to the number of the tribes of Israel.

^18And they set the priests in their divisions, and the Levites in their courses, for the service of God, which is at Jerusalem; as it is written in the book of Moses.

^19And the children of the captivity kept the passover upon the fourteenth day of the first month.

^20For the priests and the Levites were purified together, all of them were pure, and killed the passover for all the children of the captivity, and for their brethren the priests, and for themselves.

^21And the children of Israel, which were come again out of captivity, and all such as had separated themselves unto them from the filthiness of the heathen of the land, to seek the Lord God of Israel, did eat,

^22And kept the feast of unleavened bread seven days with joy: for the Lord had made them joyful, and turned the heart of the king of Assyria unto them, to strengthen their hands in the work of the house of God, the God of Israel.

VII

^1Now after these things, in the reign of Artaxerxes king of Persia, Ezra the son of Seraiah, the son of Azariah, the son of Hilkiah,

^2The son of Shallum, the son of Zadok, the son of Ahitub,

^3The son of Amariah, the son of Azariah, the son of Meraioth,

^4The son of Zerahiah, the son of Uzzi, the son of Bukki,

^5The son of Abishua, the son of Phinehas, the son of Eleazar, the son of Aaron the chief priest:

^6This Ezra went up from Babylon; and he was a ready scribe in the law of Moses, which the Lord God of Israel had given: and the king granted him all his request, according to the hand of the Lord his God upon him.

^7And there went up some of the children of Israel, and of the priests, and the Levites, and the singers, and the porters, and the Nethinims, unto Jerusalem, in the seventh year of Artaxerxes the king.

^8And he came to Jerusalem in the fifth month, which was in the seventh year of the king.

^9For upon the first day of the first month began he to go up from Babylon, and on the first day of the fifth month came he to Jerusalem, according to the good hand of his God upon him.

^10For Ezra had prepared his heart to seek the law of the Lord, and to do it, and to teach in Israel statutes and judgments.

^11Now this is the copy of the letter that the king Artaxerxes gave unto Ezra the priest, the scribe, even a scribe of the words of the commandments of the Lord, and of his statutes to Israel.

^12Artaxerxes, king of kings, unto Ezra the priest, a scribe of the law of the God of heaven, perfect peace, and at such a time.

^13I make a decree, that all they of the people of Israel, and of his priests and Levites, in my realm, which are minded of their own freewill to go up to Jerusalem, go with thee.

^14Forasmuch as thou art sent of the king, and of his seven counsellors, to enquire concerning Judah and Jerusalem, according to the law of thy God which is in thine hand;

^15And to carry the silver and gold, which the king and his counsellors have freely offered unto the God of Israel, whose habitation is in Jerusalem,

^16And all the silver and gold that thou canst find in all the province of Babylon, with the freewill offering of the people, and of the priests, offering willingly for the house of their God which is in Jerusalem:

^17That thou mayest buy speedily with this money bullocks, rams, lambs, with their meat offerings and their drink offerings, and offer them upon the altar of the house of your God which is in Jerusalem.

^18And whatsoever shall seem good to thee, and to thy brethren, to do with the rest of the silver and the gold, that do after the will of your God.

^19The vessels also that are given thee for the service of the house of thy God, those deliver thou before the God of Jerusalem.

^20And whatsoever more shall be needful for the house of thy God, which thou shalt have occasion to bestow, bestow it out of the king’s treasure house.

^21And I, even I Artaxerxes the king, do make a decree to all the treasurers which are beyond the river, that whatsoever Ezra the priest, the scribe of the law of the God of heaven, shall require of you, it be done speedily,

^22Unto an hundred talents of silver, and to an hundred measures of wheat, and to an hundred baths of wine, and to an hundred baths of oil, and salt without prescribing how much.

^23Whatsoever is commanded by the God of heaven, let it be diligently done for the house of the God of heaven: for why should there be wrath against the realm of the king and his sons?

^24Also we certify you, that touching any of the priests and Levites, singers, porters, Nethinims, or ministers of this house of God, it shall not be lawful to impose toll, tribute, or custom, upon them.

^25And thou, Ezra, after the wisdom of thy God, that is in thine hand, set magistrates and judges, which may judge all the people that are beyond the river, all such as know the laws of thy God; and teach ye them that know them not.

^26And whosoever will not do the law of thy God, and the law of the king, let judgment be executed speedily upon him, whether it be unto death, or to banishment, or to confiscation of goods, or to imprisonment.

^27Blessed be the Lord God of our fathers, which hath put such a thing as this in the king’s heart, to beautify the house of the Lord which is in Jerusalem:

^28And hath extended mercy unto me before the king, and his counsellors, and before all the king’s mighty princes. And I was strengthened as the hand of the Lord my God was upon me, and I gathered together out of Israel chief men to go up with me.

VIII

^1These are now the chief of their fathers, and this is the genealogy of them that went up with me from Babylon, in the reign of Artaxerxes the king.

^2Of the sons of Phinehas; Gershom: of the sons of Ithamar; Daniel: of the sons of David; Hattush.

^3Of the sons of Shechaniah, of the sons of Pharosh; Zechariah: and with him were reckoned by genealogy of the males an hundred and fifty.

^4Of the sons of Pahathmoab; Elihoenai the son of Zerahiah, and with him two hundred males.

^5Of the sons of Shechaniah; the son of Jahaziel, and with him three hundred males.

^6Of the sons also of Adin; Ebed the son of Jonathan, and with him fifty males.

^7And of the sons of Elam; Jeshaiah the son of Athaliah, and with him seventy males.

^8And of the sons of Shephatiah; Zebadiah the son of Michael, and with him fourscore males.

^9Of the sons of Joab; Obadiah the son of Jehiel, and with him two hundred and eighteen males.

^10And of the sons of Shelomith; the son of Josiphiah, and with him an hundred and threescore males.

^11And of the sons of Bebai; Zechariah the son of Bebai, and with him twenty and eight males.

^12And of the sons of Azgad; Johanan the son of Hakkatan, and with him an hundred and ten males.

^13And of the last sons of Adonikam, whose names are these, Eliphelet, Jeiel, and Shemaiah, and with them threescore males.

^14Of the sons also of Bigvai; Uthai, and Zabbud, and with them seventy males.

^15And I gathered them together to the river that runneth to Ahava; and there abode we in tents three days: and I viewed the people, and the priests, and found there none of the sons of Levi.

^16Then sent I for Eliezer, for Ariel, for Shemaiah, and for Elnathan, and for Jarib, and for Elnathan, and for Nathan, and for Zechariah, and for Meshullam, chief men; also for Joiarib, and for Elnathan, men of understanding.

^17And I sent them with commandment unto Iddo the chief at the place Casiphia, and I told them what they should say unto Iddo, and to his brethren the Nethinims, at the place Casiphia, that they should bring unto us ministers for the house of our God.

^18And by the good hand of our God upon us they brought us a man of understanding, of the sons of Mahli, the son of Levi, the son of Israel; and Sherebiah, with his sons and his brethren, eighteen;

^19And Hashabiah, and with him Jeshaiah of the sons of Merari, his brethren and their sons, twenty;

^20Also of the Nethinims, whom David and the princes had appointed for the service of the Levites, two hundred and twenty Nethinims: all of them were expressed by name.

^21Then I proclaimed a fast there, at the river of Ahava, that we might afflict ourselves before our God, to seek of him a right way for us, and for our little ones, and for all our substance.

^22For I was ashamed to require of the king a band of soldiers and horsemen to help us against the enemy in the way: because we had spoken unto the king, saying, The hand of our God is upon all them for good that seek him; but his power and his wrath is against all them that forsake him.

^23So we fasted and besought our God for this: and he was intreated of us.

^24Then I separated twelve of the chief of the priests, Sherebiah, Hashabiah, and ten of their brethren with them,

^25And weighed unto them the silver, and the gold, and the vessels, even the offering of the house of our God, which the king, and his counsellors, and his lords, and all Israel there present, had offered:

^26I even weighed unto their hand six hundred and fifty talents of silver, and silver vessels an hundred talents, and of gold an hundred talents;

^27Also twenty basons of gold, of a thousand drams; and two vessels of fine copper, precious as gold.

^28And I said unto them, Ye are holy unto the Lord; the vessels are holy also; and the silver and the gold are a freewill offering unto the Lord God of your fathers.

^29Watch ye, and keep them, until ye weigh them before the chief of the priests and the Levites, and chief of the fathers of Israel, at Jerusalem, in the chambers of the house of the Lord.

^30So took the priests and the Levites the weight of the silver, and the gold, and the vessels, to bring them to Jerusalem unto the house of our God.

^31Then we departed from the river of Ahava on the twelfth day of the first month, to go unto Jerusalem: and the hand of our God was upon us, and he delivered us from the hand of the enemy, and of such as lay in wait by the way.

^32And we came to Jerusalem, and abode there three days.

^33Now on the fourth day was the silver and the gold and the vessels weighed in the house of our God by the hand of Meremoth the son of Uriah the priest; and with him was Eleazar the son of Phinehas; and with them was Jozabad the son of Jeshua, and Noadiah the son of Binnui, Levites;

^34By number and by weight of every one: and all the weight was written at that time.

^35Also the children of those that had been carried away, which were come out of the captivity, offered burnt offerings unto the God of Israel, twelve bullocks for all Israel, ninety and six rams, seventy and seven lambs, twelve he goats for a sin offering: all this was a burnt offering unto the Lord.

^36And they delivered the king’s commissions unto the king’s lieutenants, and to the governors on this side the river: and they furthered the people, and the house of God.

IX

^1Now when these things were done, the princes came to me, saying, The people of Israel, and the priests, and the Levites, have not separated themselves from the people of the lands, doing according to their abominations, even of the Canaanites, the Hittites, the Perizzites, the Jebusites, the Ammonites, the Moabites, the Egyptians, and the Amorites.

^2For they have taken of their daughters for themselves, and for their sons: so that the holy seed have mingled themselves with the people of those lands: yea, the hand of the princes and rulers hath been chief in this trespass.

^3And when I heard this thing, I rent my garment and my mantle, and plucked off the hair of my head and of my beard, and sat down astonied.

^4Then were assembled unto me every one that trembled at the words of the God of Israel, because of the transgression of those that had been carried away; and I sat astonied until the evening sacrifice.

^5And at the evening sacrifice I arose up from my heaviness; and having rent my garment and my mantle, I fell upon my knees, and spread out my hands unto the Lord my God,

^6And said, O my God, I am ashamed and blush to lift up my face to thee, my God: for our iniquities are increased over our head, and our trespass is grown up unto the heavens.

^7Since the days of our fathers have we been in a great trespass unto this day; and for our iniquities have we, our kings, and our priests, been delivered into the hand of the kings of the lands, to the sword, to captivity, and to a spoil, and to confusion of face, as it is this day.

^8And now for a little space grace hath been shewed from the Lord our God, to leave us a remnant to escape, and to give us a nail in his holy place, that our God may lighten our eyes, and give us a little reviving in our bondage.

^9For we were bondmen; yet our God hath not forsaken us in our bondage, but hath extended mercy unto us in the sight of the kings of Persia, to give us a reviving, to set up the house of our God, and to repair the desolations thereof, and to give us a wall in Judah and in Jerusalem.

^10And now, O our God, what shall we say after this? for we have forsaken thy commandments,

^11Which thou hast commanded by thy servants the prophets, saying, The land, unto which ye go to possess it, is an unclean land with the filthiness of the people of the lands, with their abominations, which have filled it from one end to another with their uncleanness.

^12Now therefore give not your daughters unto their sons, neither take their daughters unto your sons, nor seek their peace or their wealth for ever: that ye may be strong, and eat the good of the land, and leave it for an inheritance to your children for ever.

^13And after all that is come upon us for our evil deeds, and for our great trespass, seeing that thou our God hast punished us less than our iniquities deserve, and hast given us such deliverance as this;

^14Should we again break thy commandments, and join in affinity with the people of these abominations? wouldest not thou be angry with us till thou hadst consumed us, so that there should be no remnant nor escaping?

^15O Lord God of Israel, thou art righteous: for we remain yet escaped, as it is this day: behold, we are before thee in our trespasses: for we cannot stand before thee because of this.

X

^1Now when Ezra had prayed, and when he had confessed, weeping and casting himself down before the house of God, there assembled unto him out of Israel a very great congregation of men and women and children: for the people wept very sore.

^2And Shechaniah the son of Jehiel, one of the sons of Elam, answered and said unto Ezra, We have trespassed against our God, and have taken strange wives of the people of the land: yet now there is hope in Israel concerning this thing.

^3Now therefore let us make a covenant with our God to put away all the wives, and such as are born of them, according to the counsel of my lord, and of those that tremble at the commandment of our God; and let it be done according to the law.

^4Arise; for this matter belongeth unto thee: we also will be with thee: be of good courage, and do it.

^5Then arose Ezra, and made the chief priests, the Levites, and all Israel, to swear that they should do according to this word. And they sware.

^6Then Ezra rose up from before the house of God, and went into the chamber of Johanan the son of Eliashib: and when he came thither, he did eat no bread, nor drink water: for he mourned because of the transgression of them that had been carried away.

^7And they made proclamation throughout Judah and Jerusalem unto all the children of the captivity, that they should gather themselves together unto Jerusalem;

^8And that whosoever would not come within three days, according to the counsel of the princes and the elders, all his substance should be forfeited, and himself separated from the congregation of those that had been carried away.

^9Then all the men of Judah and Benjamin gathered themselves together unto Jerusalem within three days. It was the ninth month, on the twentieth day of the month; and all the people sat in the street of the house of God, trembling because of this matter, and for the great rain.

^10And Ezra the priest stood up, and said unto them, Ye have transgressed, and have taken strange wives, to increase the trespass of Israel.

^11Now therefore make confession unto the Lord God of your fathers, and do his pleasure: and separate yourselves from the people of the land, and from the strange wives.

^12Then all the congregation answered and said with a loud voice, As thou hast said, so must we do.

^13But the people are many, and it is a time of much rain, and we are not able to stand without, neither is this a work of one day or two: for we are many that have transgressed in this thing.

^14Let now our rulers of all the congregation stand, and let all them which have taken strange wives in our cities come at appointed times, and with them the elders of every city, and the judges thereof, until the fierce wrath of our God for this matter be turned from us.

^15Only Jonathan the son of Asahel and Jahaziah the son of Tikvah were employed about this matter: and Meshullam and Shabbethai the Levite helped them.

^16And the children of the captivity did so. And Ezra the priest, with certain chief of the fathers, after the house of their fathers, and all of them by their names, were separated, and sat down in the first day of the tenth month to examine the matter.

^17And they made an end with all the men that had taken strange wives by the first day of the first month.

^18And among the sons of the priests there were found that had taken strange wives: namely, of the sons of Jeshua the son of Jozadak, and his brethren; Maaseiah, and Eliezer, and Jarib, and Gedaliah.

^19And they gave their hands that they would put away their wives; and being guilty, they offered a ram of the flock for their trespass.

^20And of the sons of Immer; Hanani, and Zebadiah.

^21And of the sons of Harim; Maaseiah, and Elijah, and Shemaiah, and Jehiel, and Uzziah.

^22And of the sons of Pashur; Elioenai, Maaseiah, Ishmael, Nethaneel, Jozabad, and Elasah.

^23Also of the Levites; Jozabad, and Shimei, and Kelaiah, (the same is Kelita,) Pethahiah, Judah, and Eliezer.

^24Of the singers also; Eliashib: and of the porters; Shallum, and Telem, and Uri.

^25Moreover of Israel: of the sons of Parosh; Ramiah, and Jeziah, and Malchiah, and Miamin, and Eleazar, and Malchijah, and Benaiah.

^26And of the sons of Elam; Mattaniah, Zechariah, and Jehiel, and Abdi, and Jeremoth, and Eliah.

^27And of the sons of Zattu; Elioenai, Eliashib, Mattaniah, and Jeremoth, and Zabad, and Aziza.

^28Of the sons also of Bebai; Jehohanan, Hananiah, Zabbai, and Athlai.

^29And of the sons of Bani; Meshullam, Malluch, and Adaiah, Jashub, and Sheal, and Ramoth.

^30And of the sons of Pahathmoab; Adna, and Chelal, Benaiah, Maaseiah, Mattaniah, Bezaleel, and Binnui, and Manasseh.

^31And of the sons of Harim; Eliezer, Ishijah, Malchiah, Shemaiah, Shimeon,

^32Benjamin, Malluch, and Shemariah.

^33Of the sons of Hashum; Mattenai, Mattathah, Zabad, Eliphelet, Jeremai, Manasseh, and Shimei.

^34Of the sons of Bani; Maadai, Amram, and Uel,

^35Benaiah, Bedeiah, Chelluh,

^36Vaniah, Meremoth, Eliashib,

^37Mattaniah, Mattenai, and Jaasau,

^38And Bani, and Binnui, Shimei,

^39And Shelemiah, and Nathan, and Adaiah,

^40Machnadebai, Shashai, Sharai,

^41Azareel, and Shelemiah, Shemariah,

^42Shallum, Amariah, and Joseph.

^43Of the sons of Nebo; Jeiel, Mattithiah, Zabad, Zebina, Jadau, and Joel, Benaiah.

^44All these had taken strange wives: and some of them had wives by whom they had children.

Job

The Book of

Job

I

^1There was a man in the land of Uz, whose name was Job; and that man was perfect and upright, and one that feared God, and eschewed evil. ^2And there were born unto him seven sons and three daughters. ^3His substance also was seven thousand sheep, and three thousand camels, and five hundred yoke of oxen, and five hundred she asses, and a very great household; so that this man was the greatest of all the men of the east. ^4And his sons went and feasted in their houses, every one his day; and sent and called for their three sisters to eat and to drink with them. ^5And it was so, when the days of their feasting were gone about, that Job sent and sanctified them, and rose up early in the morning, and offered burnt offerings according to the number of them all: for Job said, It may be that my sons have sinned, and cursed God in their hearts. Thus did Job continually.

^6Now there was a day when the sons of God came to present themselves before the Lord, and Satan came also among them. ^7And the Lord said unto Satan, Whence comest thou? Then Satan answered the Lord, and said, From going to and fro in the earth, and from walking up and down in it. ^8And the Lord said unto Satan, Hast thou considered my servant Job, that there is none like him in the earth, a perfect and an upright man, one that feareth God, and escheweth evil? ^9Then Satan answered the Lord, and said, Doth Job fear God for nought? ^10Hast not thou made an hedge about him, and about his house, and about all that he hath on every side? thou hast blessed the work of his hands, and his substance is increased in the land. ^11But put forth thine hand now, and touch all that he hath, and he will curse thee to thy face. ^12And the Lord said unto Satan, Behold, all that he hath is in thy power; only upon himself put not forth thine hand. So Satan went forth from the presence of the Lord.

^13And there was a day when his sons and his daughters were eating and drinking wine in their eldest brother’s house: ^14and there came a messenger unto Job, and said, The oxen were plowing, and the asses feeding beside them: ^15and the Sabeans fell upon them, and took them away; yea, they have slain the servants with the edge of the sword; and I only am escaped alone to tell thee. ^16While he was yet speaking, there came also another, and said, The fire of God is fallen from heaven, and hath burned up the sheep, and the servants, and consumed them; and I only am escaped alone to tell thee. ^17While he was yet speaking, there came also another, and said, The Chaldeans made out three bands, and fell upon the camels, and have carried them away, yea, and slain the servants with the edge of the sword; and I only am escaped alone to tell thee. ^18While he was yet speaking, there came also another, and said, Thy sons and thy daughters were eating and drinking wine in their eldest brother’s house: ^19and, behold, there came a great wind from the wilderness, and smote the four corners of the house, and it fell upon the young men, and they are dead; and I only am escaped alone to tell thee.

^20Then Job arose, and rent his mantle, and shaved his head, and fell down upon the ground, and worshipped, ^21and said, Naked came I out of my mother’s womb, and naked shall I return thither: the Lord gave, and the Lord hath taken away; blessed be the name of the Lord. ^22In all this Job sinned not, nor charged God foolishly.

II

^1Again there was a day when the sons of God came to present themselves before the Lord, and Satan came also among them to present himself before the Lord. ^2And the Lord said unto Satan, From whence comest thou? And Satan answered the Lord, and said, From going to and fro in the earth, and from walking up and down in it. ^3And the Lord said unto Satan, Hast thou considered my servant Job, that there is none like him in the earth, a perfect and an upright man, one that feareth God, and escheweth evil? and still he holdeth fast his integrity, although thou movedst me against him, to destroy him without cause. ^4And Satan answered the Lord, and said, Skin for skin, yea, all that a man hath will he give for his life. ^5But put forth thine hand now, and touch his bone and his flesh, and he will curse thee to thy face. ^6And the Lord said unto Satan, Behold, he is in thine hand; but save his life.

^7So went Satan forth from the presence of the Lord, and smote Job with sore boils from the sole of his foot unto his crown. ^8And he took him a potsherd to scrape himself withal; and he sat down among the ashes. ^9Then said his wife unto him, Dost thou still retain thine integrity? curse God, and die. ^10But he said unto her, Thou speakest as one of the foolish women speaketh. What? shall we receive good at the hand of God, and shall we not receive evil? In all this did not Job sin with his lips.

^11Now when Job’s three friends heard of all this evil that was come upon him, they came every one from his own place; Eliphaz the Temanite, and Bildad the Shuhite, and Zophar the Naamathite: for they had made an appointment together to come to mourn with him and to comfort him. ^12And when they lifted up their eyes afar off, and knew him not, they lifted up their voice, and wept; and they rent every one his mantle, and sprinkled dust upon their heads toward heaven. ^13So they sat down with him upon the ground seven days and seven nights, and none spake a word unto him: for they saw that his grief was very great.

III

^1After this opened Job his mouth, and cursed his day. ^2And Job spake, and said,

^3Let the day perish wherein I was born,
And the night in which it was said,
There is a man child conceived.
^4Let that day be darkness;
Let not God regard it from above,
Neither let the light shine upon it.
^5Let darkness and the shadow of death stain it;
Let a cloud dwell upon it;
Let the blackness of the day terrify it.
^6As for that night, let darkness seize upon it;
Let it not be joined unto the days of the year,
Let it not come into the number of the months.
^7Lo, let that night be solitary,
Let no joyful voice come therein.
^8Let them curse it that curse the day,
Who are ready to raise up their mourning.
^9Let the stars of the twilight thereof be dark;
Let it look for light, but have none;
Neither let it see the dawning of the day:
^10Because it shut not up the doors of my mother’s womb,
Nor hid sorrow from mine eyes.

^11Why died I not from the womb?
Why did I not give up the ghost
When I came out of the belly?
^12Why did the knees prevent me?
Or why the breasts that I should suck?
^13For now should I have lain still and been quiet,
I should have slept: then had I been at rest,
^14With kings and counsellors of the earth,
Which build desolate places for themselves;
^15Or with princes that had gold,
Who filled their houses with silver:
^16Or as an hidden untimely birth I had not been;
As infants which never saw light.
^17There the wicked cease from troubling;
And there the weary be at rest.
^18There the prisoners rest together;
They hear not the voice of the oppressor.
^19The small and great are there;
And the servant is free from his master.

^20Wherefore is light given to him that is in misery,
And life unto the bitter in soul;
^21Which long for death, but it cometh not;
And dig for it more than for hid treasures;
^22Which rejoice exceedingly,
And are glad, when they can find the grave?
^23Why is light given to a man whose way is hid,
And whom God hath hedged in?
^24For my sighing cometh before I eat,
And my roarings are poured out like the waters.
^25For the thing which I greatly feared is come upon me,
And that which I was afraid of is come unto me.
^26I was not in safety, neither had I rest,
Neither was I quiet; yet trouble came.

IV

^1Then Eliphaz the Temanite answered and said,

^2If we assay to commune with thee, wilt thou be grieved?
But who can withhold himself from speaking?
^3Behold, thou hast instructed many,
And thou hast strengthened the weak hands.
^4Thy words have upholden him that was falling,
And thou hast strengthened the feeble knees.
^5But now it is come upon thee, and thou faintest;
It toucheth thee, and thou art troubled.
^6Is not this thy fear, thy confidence,
Thy hope, and the uprightness of thy ways?

^7Remember, I pray thee, who ever perished, being innocent?
Or where were the righteous cut off?
^8Even as I have seen, they that plow iniquity,
And sow wickedness, reap the same.
^9By the blast of God they perish,
And by the breath of his nostrils are they consumed.
^10The roaring of the lion, and the voice of the fierce lion,
And the teeth of the young lions, are broken.
^11The old lion perisheth for lack of prey,
And the stout lion’s whelps are scattered abroad.

^12Now a thing was secretly brought to me,
And mine ear received a little thereof.
^13In thoughts from the visions of the night,
When deep sleep falleth on men,
^14Fear came upon me, and trembling,
Which made all my bones to shake.
^15Then a spirit passed before my face;
The hair of my flesh stood up:
^16It stood still,
But I could not discern the form thereof:
An image was before mine eyes,
There was silence, and I heard a voice, saying,
^17Shall mortal man be more just than God?
Shall a man be more pure than his maker?
^18Behold, he put no trust in his servants;
And his angels he charged with folly:
^19How much less in them that dwell in houses of clay,
Whose foundation is in the dust,
Which are crushed before the moth?
^20They are destroyed from morning to evening:
They perish for ever without any regarding it.
^21Doth not their excellency which is in them go away?
They die, even without wisdom.

V

^1Call now, if there be any that will answer thee;
And to which of the saints wilt thou turn?
^2For wrath killeth the foolish man,
And envy slayeth the silly one.
^3I have seen the foolish taking root:
But suddenly I cursed his habitation.
^4His children are far from safety,
And they are crushed in the gate,
Neither is there any to deliver them.
^5Whose harvest the hungry eateth up,
And taketh it even out of the thorns,
And the robber swalloweth up their substance.
^6Although affliction cometh not forth of the dust,
Neither doth trouble spring out of the ground;
^7Yet man is born unto trouble,
As the sparks fly upward.

^8I would seek unto God,
And unto God would I commit my cause:
^9Which doeth great things and unsearchable;
Marvellous things without number:
^10Who giveth rain upon the earth,
And sendeth waters upon the fields:
^11To set up on high those that be low;
That those which mourn may be exalted to safety.
^12He disappointeth the devices of the crafty,
So that their hands cannot perform their enterprise.
^13He taketh the wise in their own craftiness:
And the counsel of the froward is carried headlong.
^14They meet with darkness in the day time,
And grope in the noonday as in the night.
^15But he saveth the poor from the sword, from their mouth,
And from the hand of the mighty.
^16So the poor hath hope,
And iniquity stoppeth her mouth.

^17Behold, happy is the man whom God correcteth:
Therefore despise not thou the chastening of the Almighty:
^18For he maketh sore, and bindeth up:
He woundeth, and his hands make whole.
^19He shall deliver thee in six troubles:
Yea, in seven there shall no evil touch thee.
^20In famine he shall redeem thee from death:
And in war from the power of the sword.
^21Thou shalt be hid from the scourge of the tongue:
Neither shalt thou be afraid of destruction when it cometh.
^22At destruction and famine thou shalt laugh:
Neither shalt thou be afraid of the beasts of the earth.
^23For thou shalt be in league with the stones of the field:
And the beasts of the field shall be at peace with thee.
^24And thou shalt know that thy tabernacle shall be in peace;
And thou shalt visit thy habitation, and shalt not sin.
^25Thou shalt know also that thy seed shall be great,
And thine offspring as the grass of the earth.
^26Thou shalt come to thy grave in a full age,
Like as a shock of corn cometh in in his season.
^27Lo this, we have searched it, so it is;
Hear it, and know thou it for thy good.

VI

^1But Job answered and said,

^2Oh that my grief were throughly weighed,
And my calamity laid in the balances together!
^3For now it would be heavier than the sand of the sea:
Therefore my words are swallowed up.
^4For the arrows of the Almighty are within me,
The poison whereof drinketh up my spirit:
The terrors of God do set themselves in array against me.
^5Doth the wild ass bray when he hath grass?
Or loweth the ox over his fodder?
^6Can that which is unsavoury be eaten without salt?
Or is there any taste in the white of an egg?
^7The things that my soul refused to touch
Are as my sorrowful meat.

^8Oh that I might have my request;
And that God would grant me the thing that I long for!
^9Even that it would please God to destroy me;
That he would let loose his hand, and cut me off!
^10Then should I yet have comfort;
Yea, I would harden myself in sorrow: let him not spare;
For I have not concealed the words of the Holy One.
^11What is my strength, that I should hope?
And what is mine end, that I should prolong my life?
^12Is my strength the strength of stones?
Or is my flesh of brass?
^13Is not my help in me?
And is wisdom driven quite from me?

^14To him that is afflicted pity should be shewed from his friend;
But he forsaketh the fear of the Almighty.
^15My brethren have dealt deceitfully as a brook,
And as the stream of brooks they pass away;
^16Which are blackish by reason of the ice,
And wherein the snow is hid:
^17What time they wax warm, they vanish:
When it is hot, they are consumed out of their place.
^18The paths of their way are turned aside;
They go to nothing, and perish.
^19The troops of Tema looked,
The companies of Sheba waited for them.
^20They were confounded because they had hoped;
They came thither, and were ashamed.
^21For now ye are nothing;
Ye see my casting down, and are afraid.
^22Did I say, Bring unto me?
Or, Give a reward for me of your substance?
^23Or, Deliver me from the enemy’s hand?
Or, Redeem me from the hand of the mighty?

^24Teach me, and I will hold my tongue:
And cause me to understand wherein I have erred.
^25How forcible are right words!
But what doth your arguing reprove?
^26Do ye imagine to reprove words,
And the speeches of one that is desperate, which are as wind?
^27Yea, ye overwhelm the fatherless,
And ye dig a pit for your friend.

^28Now therefore be content, look upon me;
For it is evident unto you if I lie.
^29Return, I pray you, let it not be iniquity;
Yea, return again, my righteousness is in it.
^30Is there iniquity in my tongue?
Cannot my taste discern perverse things?

VII

^1Is there not an appointed time to man upon earth?
Are not his days also like the days of an hireling?
^2As a servant earnestly desireth the shadow,
And as an hireling looketh for the reward of his work:
^3So am I made to possess months of vanity,
And wearisome nights are appointed to me.
^4When I lie down, I say,
When shall I arise, and the night be gone?
And I am full of tossings to and fro unto the dawning of the day.
^5My flesh is clothed with worms and clods of dust;
My skin is broken, and become loathsome.
^6My days are swifter than a weaver’s shuttle,
And are spent without hope.

^7O remember that my life is wind:
Mine eye shall no more see good.
^8The eye of him that hath seen me shall see me no more:
Thine eyes are upon me, and I am not.
^9As the cloud is consumed and vanisheth away:
So he that goeth down to the grave shall come up no more.
^10He shall return no more to his house,
Neither shall his place know him any more.

^11Therefore I will not refrain my mouth;
I will speak in the anguish of my spirit;
I will complain in the bitterness of my soul.
^12Am I a sea, or a whale,
That thou settest a watch over me?
^13When I say, My bed shall comfort me,
My couch shall ease my complaints;
^14Then thou scarest me with dreams,
And terrifiest me through visions:
^15So that my soul chooseth strangling,
And death rather than my life.
^16I loathe it; I would not live alway:
Let me alone; for my days are vanity.
^17What is man, that thou shouldest magnify him?
And that thou shouldest set thine heart upon him?
^18And that thou shouldest visit him every morning,
And try him every moment?
^19How long wilt thou not depart from me,
Nor let me alone till I swallow down my spittle?
^20I have sinned; what shall I do unto thee, O thou preserver of men?
Why hast thou set me as a mark against thee,
So that I am a burden to myself?
^21And why dost thou not pardon my transgression,
And take away my iniquity?
For now shall I sleep in the dust;
And thou shalt seek me in the morning,
But I shall not be.

VIII

^1Then answered Bildad the Shuhite, and said,

^2How long wilt thou speak these things?
And how long shall the words of thy mouth be like a strong wind?
^3Doth God pervert judgment?
Or doth the Almighty pervert justice?
^4If thy children have sinned against him,
And he have cast them away for their transgression;
^5If thou wouldest seek unto God betimes,
And make thy supplication to the Almighty;
^6If thou wert pure and upright;
Surely now he would awake for thee,
And make the habitation of thy righteousness prosperous.
^7Though thy beginning was small,
Yet thy latter end should greatly increase.

^8For enquire, I pray thee, of the former age,
And prepare thyself to the search of their fathers:
^9(For we are but of yesterday, and know nothing,
Because our days upon earth are a shadow:)
^10Shall not they teach thee, and tell thee,
And utter words out of their heart?

^11Can the rush grow up without mire?
Can the flag grow without water?
^12Whilst it is yet in his greenness, and not cut down,
It withereth before any other herb.
^13So are the paths of all that forget God;
And the hypocrite’s hope shall perish:
^14Whose hope shall be cut off,
And whose trust shall be a spider’s web.
^15He shall lean upon his house, but it shall not stand:
He shall hold it fast, but it shall not endure.
^16He is green before the sun,
And his branch shooteth forth in his garden.
^17His roots are wrapped about the heap,
And seeth the place of stones.
^18If he destroy him from his place,
Then it shall deny him, saying,
I have not seen thee.
^19Behold, this is the joy of his way,
And out of the earth shall others grow.

^20Behold, God will not cast away a perfect man,
Neither will he help the evil doers:
^21Till he fill thy mouth with laughing,
And thy lips with rejoicing.
^22They that hate thee shall be clothed with shame;
And the dwelling place of the wicked shall come to nought.

IX

^1Then Job answered and said,

^2I know it is so of a truth:
But how should man be just with God?
^3If he will contend with him,
He cannot answer him one of a thousand.
^4He is wise in heart, and mighty in strength:
Who hath hardened himself against him, and hath prospered?
^5Which removeth the mountains, and they know not:
Which overturneth them in his anger.
^6Which shaketh the earth out of her place,
And the pillars thereof tremble.
^7Which commandeth the sun, and it riseth not;
And sealeth up the stars.
^8Which alone spreadeth out the heavens,
And treadeth upon the waves of the sea.
^9Which maketh Arcturus, Orion, and Pleiades,
And the chambers of the south.
^10Which doeth great things past finding out;
Yea, and wonders without number.
^11Lo, he goeth by me, and I see him not:
He passeth on also, but I perceive him not.
^12Behold, he taketh away, who can hinder him?
Who will say unto him, What doest thou?

^13If God will not withdraw his anger,
The proud helpers do stoop under him.
^14How much less shall I answer him,
And choose out my words to reason with him?
^15Whom, though I were righteous, yet would I not answer,
But I would make supplication to my judge.
^16If I had called, and he had answered me;
Yet would I not believe that he had hearkened unto my voice.
^17For he breaketh me with a tempest,
And multiplieth my wounds without cause.
^18He will not suffer me to take my breath,
But filleth me with bitterness.
^19If I speak of strength, lo, he is strong:
And if of judgment, who shall set me a time to plead?
^20If I justify myself, mine own mouth shall condemn me:
If I say, I am perfect, it shall also prove me perverse.
^21Though I were perfect, yet would I not know my soul:
I would despise my life.
^22This is one thing, therefore I said it,
He destroyeth the perfect and the wicked.
^23If the scourge slay suddenly,
He will laugh at the trial of the innocent.
^24The earth is given into the hand of the wicked:
He covereth the faces of the judges thereof;
If not, where, and who is he?

^25Now my days are swifter than a post:
They flee away, they see no good.
^26They are passed away as the swift ships:
As the eagle that hasteth to the prey.
^27If I say, I will forget my complaint,
I will leave off my heaviness, and comfort myself:
^28I am afraid of all my sorrows,
I know that thou wilt not hold me innocent.
^29If I be wicked,
Why then labour I in vain?
^30If I wash myself with snow water,
And make my hands never so clean;
^31Yet shalt thou plunge me in the ditch,
And mine own clothes shall abhor me.
^32For he is not a man, as I am, that I should answer him,
And we should come together in judgment.
^33Neither is there any daysman betwixt us,
That might lay his hand upon us both.
^34Let him take his rod away from me,
And let not his fear terrify me:
^35Then would I speak, and not fear him;
But it is not so with me.

X

^1My soul is weary of my life;
I will leave my complaint upon myself;
I will speak in the bitterness of my soul.
^2I will say unto God, Do not condemn me;
Shew me wherefore thou contendest with me.
^3Is it good unto thee that thou shouldest oppress,
That thou shouldest despise the work of thine hands,
And shine upon the counsel of the wicked?
^4Hast thou eyes of flesh?
Or seest thou as man seeth?
^5Are thy days as the days of man?
Are thy years as man’s days,
^6That thou enquirest after mine iniquity,
And searchest after my sin?
^7Thou knowest that I am not wicked;
And there is none that can deliver out of thine hand.
^8Thine hands have made me and fashioned me together round about;
Yet thou dost destroy me.
^9Remember, I beseech thee, that thou hast made me as the clay;
And wilt thou bring me into dust again?
^10Hast thou not poured me out as milk,
And curdled me like cheese?
^11Thou hast clothed me with skin and flesh,
And hast fenced me with bones and sinews.
^12Thou hast granted me life and favour,
And thy visitation hath preserved my spirit.
^13And these things hast thou hid in thine heart:
I know that this is with thee.
^14If I sin, then thou markest me,
And thou wilt not acquit me from mine iniquity.
^15If I be wicked, woe unto me;
And if I be righteous, yet will I not lift up my head.
I am full of confusion;
Therefore see thou mine affliction;
^16For it increaseth. Thou huntest me as a fierce lion:
And again thou shewest thyself marvellous upon me.
^17Thou renewest thy witnesses against me,
And increasest thine indignation upon me;
Changes and war are against me.

^18Wherefore then hast thou brought me forth out of the womb?
Oh that I had given up the ghost, and no eye had seen me!
^19I should have been as though I had not been;
I should have been carried from the womb to the grave.
^20Are not my days few? cease then,
And let me alone, that I may take comfort a little,
^21Before I go whence I shall not return,
Even to the land of darkness and the shadow of death;
^22A land of darkness, as darkness itself;
And of the shadow of death, without any order,
And where the light is as darkness.

XI

^1Then answered Zophar the Naamathite, and said,

^2Should not the multitude of words be answered?
And should a man full of talk be justified?
^3Should thy lies make men hold their peace?
And when thou mockest, shall no man make thee ashamed?
^4For thou hast said, My doctrine is pure,
And I am clean in thine eyes.
^5But oh that God would speak,
And open his lips against thee;
^6And that he would shew thee the secrets of wisdom,
That they are double to that which is!
Know therefore that God exacteth of thee less than thine iniquity deserveth.

^7Canst thou by searching find out God?
Canst thou find out the Almighty unto perfection?
^8It is as high as heaven; what canst thou do?
Deeper than hell; what canst thou know?
^9The measure thereof is longer than the earth,
And broader than the sea.
^10If he cut off, and shut up,
Or gather together, then who can hinder him?
^11For he knoweth vain men:
He seeth wickedness also; will he not then consider it?
^12For vain men would be wise,
Though man be born like a wild ass’s colt.

^13If thou prepare thine heart,
And stretch out thine hands toward him;
^14If iniquity be in thine hand, put it far away,
And let not wickedness dwell in thy tabernacles.
^15For then shalt thou lift up thy face without spot;
Yea, thou shalt be stedfast, and shalt not fear:
^16Because thou shalt forget thy misery,
And remember it as waters that pass away:
^17And thine age shall be clearer than the noonday:
Thou shalt shine forth, thou shalt be as the morning.
^18And thou shalt be secure, because there is hope;
Yea, thou shalt dig about thee, and thou shalt take thy rest in safety.
^19Also thou shalt lie down, and none shall make thee afraid;
Yea, many shall make suit unto thee.
^20But the eyes of the wicked shall fail,
And they shall not escape,
And their hope shall be as the giving up of the ghost.

XII

^1And Job answered and said,

^2No doubt but ye are the people,
And wisdom shall die with you.
^3But I have understanding as well as you;
I am not inferior to you:
Yea, who knoweth not such things as these?
^4I am as one mocked of his neighbour,
Who calleth upon God, and he answereth him:
The just upright man is laughed to scorn.
^5He that is ready to slip with his feet
Is as a lamp despised in the thought of him that is at ease.
^6The tabernacles of robbers prosper,
And they that provoke God are secure;
Into whose hand God bringeth abundantly.

^7But ask now the beasts, and they shall teach thee;
And the fowls of the air, and they shall tell thee:
^8Or speak to the earth, and it shall teach thee:
And the fishes of the sea shall declare unto thee.
^9Who knoweth not in all these
That the hand of the Lord hath wrought this?
^10In whose hand is the soul of every living thing,
And the breath of all mankind.
^11Doth not the ear try words?
And the mouth taste his meat?
^12With the ancient is wisdom;
And in length of days understanding.

^13With him is wisdom and strength,
He hath counsel and understanding.
^14Behold, he breaketh down, and it cannot be built again:
He shutteth up a man, and there can be no opening.
^15Behold, he withholdeth the waters, and they dry up:
Also he sendeth them out, and they overturn the earth.
^16With him is strength and wisdom:
The deceived and the deceiver are his.
^17He leadeth counsellors away spoiled,
And maketh the judges fools.
^18He looseth the bond of kings,
And girdeth their loins with a girdle.
^19He leadeth princes away spoiled,
And overthroweth the mighty.
^20He removeth away the speech of the trusty,
And taketh away the understanding of the aged.
^21He poureth contempt upon princes,
And weakeneth the strength of the mighty.
^22He discovereth deep things out of darkness,
And bringeth out to light the shadow of death.
^23He increaseth the nations, and destroyeth them:
He enlargeth the nations, and straiteneth them again.
^24He taketh away the heart of the chief of the people of the earth,
And causeth them to wander in a wilderness where there is no way.
^25They grope in the dark without light,
And he maketh them to stagger like a drunken man.

XIII

^1Lo, mine eye hath seen all this,
Mine ear hath heard and understood it.
^2What ye know, the same do I know also:
I am not inferior unto you.
^3Surely I would speak to the Almighty,
And I desire to reason with God.
^4But ye are forgers of lies,
Ye are all physicians of no value.
^5O that ye would altogether hold your peace!
And it should be your wisdom.
^6Hear now my reasoning,
And hearken to the pleadings of my lips.
^7Will ye speak wickedly for God?
And talk deceitfully for him?
^8Will ye accept his person?
Will ye contend for God?
^9Is it good that he should search you out?
Or as one man mocketh another, do ye so mock him?
^10He will surely reprove you,
If ye do secretly accept persons.
^11Shall not his excellency make you afraid?
And his dread fall upon you?
^12Your remembrances are like unto ashes,
Your bodies to bodies of clay.

^13Hold your peace, let me alone, that I may speak,
And let come on me what will.
^14Wherefore do I take my flesh in my teeth,
And put my life in mine hand?
^15Though he slay me, yet will I trust in him:
But I will maintain mine own ways before him.
^16He also shall be my salvation:
For an hypocrite shall not come before him.
^17Hear diligently my speech,
And my declaration with your ears.
^18Behold now, I have ordered my cause;
I know that I shall be justified.
^19Who is he that will plead with me?
For now, if I hold my tongue, I shall give up the ghost.
^20Only do not two things unto me:
Then will I not hide myself from thee.
^21Withdraw thine hand far from me:
And let not thy dread make me afraid.
^22Then call thou, and I will answer:
Or let me speak, and answer thou me.
^23How many are mine iniquities and sins?
Make me to know my transgression and my sin.
^24Wherefore hidest thou thy face,
And holdest me for thine enemy?
^25Wilt thou break a leaf driven to and fro?
And wilt thou pursue the dry stubble?
^26For thou writest bitter things against me,
And makest me to possess the iniquities of my youth.
^27Thou puttest my feet also in the stocks,
And lookest narrowly unto all my paths;
Thou settest a print upon the heels of my feet.
^28And he, as a rotten thing, consumeth,
As a garment that is moth eaten.

XIV

^1Man that is born of a woman
Is of few days and full of trouble.
^2He cometh forth like a flower, and is cut down:
He fleeth also as a shadow, and continueth not.
^3And doth thou open thine eyes upon such an one,
And bringest me into judgment with thee?
^4Who can bring a clean thing out of an unclean?
Not one.
^5Seeing his days are determined, the number of his months are with thee,
Thou hast appointed his bounds that he cannot pass;
^6Turn from him, that he may rest,
Till he shall accomplish, as an hireling, his day.
^7For there is hope of a tree,
If it be cut down, that it will sprout again,
And that the tender branch thereof will not cease.
^8Though the root thereof wax old in the earth,
And the stock thereof die in the ground;
^9Yet through the scent of water it will bud,
And bring forth boughs like a plant.
^10But man dieth, and wasteth away:
Yea, man giveth up the ghost, and where is he?
^11As the waters fail from the sea,
And the flood decayeth and drieth up:
^12So man lieth down, and riseth not:
Till the heavens be no more, they shall not awake,
Nor be raised out of their sleep.
^13O that thou wouldest hide me in the grave,
That thou wouldest keep me secret, until thy wrath be past,
That thou wouldest appoint me a set time, and remember me!
^14If a man die, shall he live again?
All the days of my appointed time will I wait,
Till my change come.
^15Thou shalt call, and I will answer thee:
Thou wilt have a desire to the work of thine hands.
^16For now thou numberest my steps:
Dost thou not watch over my sin?
^17My transgression is sealed up in a bag,
And thou sewest up mine iniquity.

^18And surely the mountains falling cometh to nought,
And the rock is removed out of his place.
^19The waters wear the stones:
Thou washest away the things which grow out of the dust of the earth;
And thou destroyest the hope of man.
^20Thou prevailest for ever against him, and he passeth:
Thou changest his countenance, and sendest him away.
^21His sons come to honour, and he knoweth it not;
And they are brought low, but he perceiveth it not of them.
^22But his flesh upon him shall have pain,
And his soul within him shall mourn.

XV

^1Then answered Eliphaz the Temanite, and said,

^2Should a wise man utter vain knowledge,
And fill his belly with the east wind?
^3Should he reason with unprofitable talk?
Or with speeches wherewith he can do no good?
^4Yea, thou castest off fear,
And restrainest prayer before God.
^5For thy mouth uttereth thine iniquity,
And thou choosest the tongue of the crafty.
^6Thine own mouth condemneth thee, and not I:
Yea, thine own lips testify against thee.

^7Art thou the first man that was born?
Or wast thou made before the hills?
^8Hast thou heard the secret of God?
And dost thou restrain wisdom to thyself?
^9What knowest thou, that we know not?
What understandest thou, which is not in us?
^10With us are both the grayheaded and very aged men,
Much elder than thy father.
^11Are the consolations of God small with thee?
Is there any secret thing with thee?
^12Why doth thine heart carry thee away?
And what do thy eyes wink at,
^13That thou turnest thy spirit against God,
And lettest such words go out of thy mouth?
^14What is man, that he should be clean?
And he which is born of a woman, that he should be righteous?
^15Behold, he putteth no trust in his saints;
Yea, the heavens are not clean in his sight.
^16How much more abominable and filthy is man,
Which drinketh iniquity like water?

^17I will shew thee, hear me;
And that which I have seen I will declare;
^18Which wise men have told from their fathers,
And have not hid it:
^19Unto whom alone the earth was given,
And no stranger passed among them.
^20The wicked man travaileth with pain all his days,
And the number of years is hidden to the oppressor.
^21A dreadful sound is in his ears:
In prosperity the destroyer shall come upon him.
^22He believeth not that he shall return out of darkness,
And he is waited for of the sword.
^23He wandereth abroad for bread, saying, Where is it?
He knoweth that the day of darkness is ready at his hand.
^24Trouble and anguish shall make him afraid;
They shall prevail against him, as a king ready to the battle.
^25For he stretcheth out his hand against God,
And strengtheneth himself against the Almighty.
^26He runneth upon him, even on his neck,
Upon the thick bosses of his bucklers:
^27Because he covereth his face with his fatness,
And maketh collops of fat on his flanks.
^28And he dwelleth in desolate cities,
And in houses which no man inhabiteth,
Which are ready to become heaps.
^29He shall not be rich, neither shall his substance continue,
Neither shall he prolong the perfection thereof upon the earth.
^30He shall not depart out of darkness;
The flame shall dry up his branches,
And by the breath of his mouth shall he go away.
^31Let not him that is deceived trust in vanity:
For vanity shall be his recompence.
^32It shall be accomplished before his time,
And his branch shall not be green.
^33He shall shake off his unripe grape as the vine,
And shall cast off his flower as the olive.
^34For the congregation of hypocrites shall be desolate,
And fire shall consume the tabernacles of bribery.
^35They conceive mischief, and bring forth vanity,
And their belly prepareth deceit.

XVI

^1Then Job answered and said,

^2I have heard many such things:
Miserable comforters are ye all.
^3Shall vain words have an end?
Or what emboldeneth thee that thou answerest?
^4I also could speak as ye do:
If your soul were in my soul’s stead,
I could heap up words against you,
And shake mine head at you.
^5But I would strengthen you with my mouth,
And the moving of my lips should asswage your grief.

^6Though I speak, my grief is not asswaged:
And though I forbear, what am I eased?
^7But now he hath made me weary:
Thou hast made desolate all my company.
^8And thou hast filled me with wrinkles, which is a witness against me:
And my leanness rising up in me beareth witness to my face.
^9He teareth me in his wrath, who hateth me:
He gnasheth upon me with his teeth;
Mine enemy sharpeneth his eyes upon me.
^10They have gaped upon me with their mouth;
They have smitten me upon the cheek reproachfully;
They have gathered themselves together against me.
^11God hath delivered me to the ungodly,
And turned me over into the hands of the wicked.
^12I was at ease, but he hath broken me asunder:
He hath also taken me by my neck, and shaken me to pieces,
And set me up for his mark.
^13His archers compass me round about,
He cleaveth my reins asunder, and doth not spare;
He poureth out my gall upon the ground.
^14He breaketh me with breach upon breach,
He runneth upon me like a giant.
^15I have sewed sackcloth upon my skin,
And defiled my horn in the dust.
^16My face is foul with weeping,
And on my eyelids is the shadow of death;
^17Not for any injustice in mine hands:
Also my prayer is pure.

^18O earth, cover not thou my blood,
And let my cry have no place.
^19Also now, behold, my witness is in heaven,
And my record is on high.
^20My friends scorn me:
But mine eye poureth out tears unto God.
^21O that one might plead for a man with God,
As a man pleadeth for his neighbour!
^22When a few years are come,
Then I shall go the way whence I shall not return.

XVII

^1My breath is corrupt, my days are extinct,
The graves are ready for me.
^2Are there not mockers with me?
And doth not mine eye continue in their provocation?

^3Lay down now, put me in a surety with thee;
Who is he that will strike hands with me?
^4For thou hast hid their heart from understanding:
Therefore shalt thou not exalt them.
^5He that speaketh flattery to his friends,
Even the eyes of his children shall fail.

^6He hath made me also a byword of the people;
And aforetime I was as a tabret.
^7Mine eye also is dim by reason of sorrow,
And all my members are as a shadow.
^8Upright men shall be astonied at this,
And the innocent shall stir up himself against the hypocrite.
^9The righteous also shall hold on his way,
And he that hath clean hands shall be stronger and stronger.
^10But as for you all, do ye return, and come now:
For I cannot find one wise man among you.
^11My days are past, my purposes are broken off,
Even the thoughts of my heart.
^12They change the night into day:
The light is short because of darkness.
^13If I wait, the grave is mine house:
I have made my bed in the darkness.
^14I have said to corruption, Thou art my father:
To the worm, Thou art my mother, and my sister.
^15And where is now my hope?
As for my hope, who shall see it?
^16They shall go down to the bars of the pit,
When our rest together is in the dust.

XVIII

^1Then answered Bildad the Shuhite, and said,

^2How long will it be ere ye make an end of words?
Mark, and afterwards we will speak.
^3Wherefore are we counted as beasts,
And reputed vile in your sight?
^4He teareth himself in his anger:
Shall the earth be forsaken for thee?
And shall the rock be removed out of his place?

^5Yea, the light of the wicked shall be put out,
And the spark of his fire shall not shine.
^6The light shall be dark in his tabernacle,
And his candle shall be put out with him.
^7The steps of his strength shall be straitened,
And his own counsel shall cast him down.
^8For he is cast into a net by his own feet,
And he walketh upon a snare.
^9The gin shall take him by the heel,
And the robber shall prevail against him.
^10The snare is laid for him in the ground,
And a trap for him in the way.
^11Terrors shall make him afraid on every side,
And shall drive him to his feet.
^12His strength shall be hungerbitten,
And destruction shall be ready at his side.
^13It shall devour the strength of his skin:
Even the firstborn of death shall devour his strength.
^14His confidence shall be rooted out of his tabernacle,
And it shall bring him to the king of terrors.
^15It shall dwell in his tabernacle, because it is none of his:
Brimstone shall be scattered upon his habitation.
^16His roots shall be dried up beneath,
And above shall his branch be cut off.
^17His remembrance shall perish from the earth,
And he shall have no name in the street.
^18He shall be driven from light into darkness,
And chased out of the world.
^19He shall neither have son nor nephew among his people,
Nor any remaining in his dwellings.
^20They that come after him shall be astonied at his day,
As they that went before were affrighted.
^21Surely such are the dwellings of the wicked,
And this is the place of him that knoweth not God.

XIX

^1Then Job answered and said,

^2How long will ye vex my soul,
And break me in pieces with words?
^3These ten times have ye reproached me:
Ye are not ashamed that ye make yourselves strange to me.
^4And be it indeed that I have erred,
Mine error remaineth with myself.
^5If indeed ye will magnify yourselves against me,
And plead against me my reproach:
^6Know now that God hath overthrown me,
And hath compassed me with his net.
^7Behold, I cry out of wrong, but I am not heard:
I cry aloud, but there is no judgment.
^8He hath fenced up my way that I cannot pass,
And he hath set darkness in my paths.
^9He hath stripped me of my glory,
And taken the crown from my head.
^10He hath destroyed me on every side, and I am gone:
And mine hope hath he removed like a tree.
^11He hath also kindled his wrath against me,
And he counteth me unto him as one of his enemies.
^12His troops come together,
And raise up their way against me,
And encamp round about my tabernacle.

^13He hath put my brethren far from me,
And mine acquaintance are verily estranged from me.
^14My kinsfolk have failed, and my familiar friends have forgotten me.
^15They that dwell in mine house,
And my maids, count me for a stranger:
I am an alien in their sight.
^16I called my servant, and he gave me no answer;
I intreated him with my mouth.
^17My breath is strange to my wife,
Though I intreated for the children’s sake of mine own body.
^18Yea, young children despised me;
I arose, and they spake against me.
^19All my inward friends abhorred me:
And they whom I loved are turned against me.
^20My bone cleaveth to my skin and to my flesh,
And I am escaped with the skin of my teeth.
^21Have pity upon me, have pity upon me, O ye my friends;
For the hand of God hath touched me.
^22Why do ye persecute me as God,
And are not satisfied with my flesh?

^23Oh that my words were now written!
Oh that they were printed in a book!
^24That they were graven with an iron pen and lead
In the rock for ever!
^25For I know that my redeemer liveth,
And that he shall stand at the latter day upon the earth:
^26And though after my skin worms destroy this body,
Yet in my flesh shall I see God:
^27Whom I shall see for myself,
And mine eyes shall behold, and not another;
Though my reins be consumed within me.
^28But ye should say, Why persecute we him,
Seeing the root of the matter is found in me?
^29Be ye afraid of the sword:
For wrath bringeth the punishments of the sword,
That ye may know there is a judgment.

XX

^1Then answered Zophar the Naamathite, and said,

^2Therefore do my thoughts cause me to answer,
And for this I make haste.
^3I have heard the check of my reproach,
And the spirit of my understanding causeth me to answer.
^4Knowest thou not this of old,
Since man was placed upon earth,
^5That the triumphing of the wicked is short,
And the joy of the hypocrite but for a moment?
^6Though his excellency mount up to the heavens,
And his head reach unto the clouds;
^7Yet he shall perish for ever like his own dung:
They which have seen him shall say, Where is he?
^8He shall fly away as a dream, and shall not be found:
Yea, he shall be chased away as a vision of the night.
^9The eye also which saw him shall see him no more;
Neither shall his place any more behold him.
^10His children shall seek to please the poor,
And his hands shall restore their goods.
^11His bones are full of the sin of his youth,
Which shall lie down with him in the dust.

^12Though wickedness be sweet in his mouth,
Though he hide it under his tongue;
^13Though he spare it, and forsake it not;
But keep it still within his mouth:
^14Yet his meat in his bowels is turned,
It is the gall of asps within him.
^15He hath swallowed down riches, and he shall vomit them up again:
God shall cast them out of his belly.
^16He shall suck the poison of asps:
The viper’s tongue shall slay him.
^17He shall not see the rivers,
The floods, the brooks of honey and butter.
^18That which he laboured for shall he restore,
And shall not swallow it down:
According to his substance shall the restitution be,
And he shall not rejoice therein.
^19Because he hath oppressed and hath forsaken the poor;
Because he hath violently taken away an house which he builded not;

^20Surely he shall not feel quietness in his belly,
He shall not save of that which he desired.
^21There shall none of his meat be left;
Therefore shall no man look for his goods.
^22In the fulness of his sufficiency he shall be in straits:
Every hand of the wicked shall come upon him.
^23When he is about to fill his belly,
God shall cast the fury of his wrath upon him,
And shall rain it upon him while he is eating.
^24He shall flee from the iron weapon,
And the bow of steel shall strike him through.
^25It is drawn, and cometh out of the body;
Yea, the glittering sword cometh out of his gall:
Terrors are upon him.
^26All darkness shall be hid in his secret places:
A fire not blown shall consume him;
It shall go ill with him that is left in his tabernacle.
^27The heaven shall reveal his iniquity;
And the earth shall rise up against him.
^28The increase of his house shall depart,
And his goods shall flow away in the day of his wrath.
^29This is the portion of a wicked man from God,
And the heritage appointed unto him by God.

XXI

^1But Job answered and said,

^2Hear diligently my speech,
And let this be your consolations.
^3Suffer me that I may speak;
And after that I have spoken, mock on.
^4As for me, is my complaint to man?
And if it were so, why should not my spirit be troubled?
^5Mark me, and be astonished,
And lay your hand upon your mouth.
^6Even when I remember I am afraid,
And trembling taketh hold on my flesh.
^7Wherefore do the wicked live,
Become old, yea, are mighty in power?
^8Their seed is established in their sight with them,
And their offspring before their eyes.
^9Their houses are safe from fear,
Neither is the rod of God upon them.
^10Their bull gendereth, and faileth not;
Their cow calveth, and casteth not her calf.
^11They send forth their little ones like a flock,
And their children dance.
^12They take the timbrel and harp,
And rejoice at the sound of the organ.
^13They spend their days in wealth,
And in a moment go down to the grave.
^14Therefore they say unto God, Depart from us;
For we desire not the knowledge of thy ways.
^15What is the Almighty, that we should serve him?
And what profit should we have, if we pray unto him?
^16Lo, their good is not in their hand:
The counsel of the wicked is far from me.

^17How oft is the candle of the wicked put out!
And how oft cometh their destruction upon them!
God distributeth sorrows in his anger.
^18They are as stubble before the wind,
And as chaff that the storm carrieth away.
^19God layeth up his iniquity for his children:
He rewardeth him, and he shall know it.
^20His eyes shall see his destruction,
And he shall drink of the wrath of the Almighty.
^21For what pleasure hath he in his house after him,
When the number of his months is cut off in the midst?
^22Shall any teach God knowledge?
Seeing he judgeth those that are high.
^23One dieth in his full strength,
Being wholly at ease and quiet.
^24His breasts are full of milk,
And his bones are moistened with marrow.
^25And another dieth in the bitterness of his soul,
And never eateth with pleasure.
^26They shall lie down alike in the dust,
And the worms shall cover them.

^27Behold, I know your thoughts,
And the devices which ye wrongfully imagine against me.
^28For ye say, Where is the house of the prince?
And where are the dwelling places of the wicked?
^29Have ye not asked them that go by the way?
And do ye not know their tokens,
^30That the wicked is reserved to the day of destruction?
They shall be brought forth to the day of wrath.
^31Who shall declare his way to his face?
And who shall repay him what he hath done?
^32Yet shall he be brought to the grave, and shall remain in the tomb.
^33The clods of the valley shall be sweet unto him, and every man shall draw after him, as there are innumerable before him.
^34How then comfort ye me in vain, seeing in your answers there remaineth falsehood?

XXII

^1Then Eliphaz the Temanite answered and said,

^2Can a man be profitable unto God,
As he that is wise may be profitable unto himself?
^3Is it any pleasure to the Almighty, that thou art righteous?
Or is it gain to him, that thou makest thy ways perfect?
^4Will he reprove thee for fear of thee?
Will he enter with thee into judgment?
^5Is not thy wickedness great?
And thine iniquities infinite?
^6For thou hast taken a pledge from thy brother for nought,
And stripped the naked of their clothing.
^7Thou hast not given water to the weary to drink,
And thou hast withholden bread from the hungry.
^8But as for the mighty man, he had the earth;
And the honourable man dwelt in it.
^9Thou hast sent widows away empty,
And the arms of the fatherless have been broken.
^10Therefore snares are round about thee,
And sudden fear troubleth thee;
^11Or darkness, that thou canst not see;
And abundance of waters cover thee.

^12Is not God in the height of heaven?
And behold the height of the stars, how high they are!
^13And thou sayest, How doth God know?
Can he judge through the dark cloud?
^14Thick clouds are a covering to him, that he seeth not;
And he walketh in the circuit of heaven.
^15Hast thou marked the old way
Which wicked men have trodden?
^16Which were cut down out of time,
Whose foundation was overflown with a flood:
^17Which said unto God, Depart from us:
And what can the Almighty do for them?
^18Yet he filled their houses with good things:
But the counsel of the wicked is far from me.
^19The righteous see it, and are glad:
And the innocent laugh them to scorn.
^20Whereas our substance is not cut down,
But the remnant of them the fire consumeth.

^21Acquaint now thyself with him, and be at peace:
Thereby good shall come unto thee.
^22Receive, I pray thee, the law from his mouth,
And lay up his words in thine heart.
^23If thou return to the Almighty, thou shalt be built up,
Thou shalt put away iniquity far from thy tabernacles.
^24Then shalt thou lay up gold as dust,
And the gold of Ophir as the stones of the brooks.
^25Yea, the Almighty shall be thy defence,
And thou shalt have plenty of silver.
^26For then shalt thou have thy delight in the Almighty,
And shalt lift up thy face unto God.
^27Thou shalt make thy prayer unto him, and he shall hear thee,
And thou shalt pay thy vows.
^28Thou shalt also decree a thing, and it shall be established unto thee:
And the light shall shine upon thy ways.
^29When men are cast down, then thou shalt say, There is lifting up;
And he shall save the humble person.
^30He shall deliver the island of the innocent:
And it is delivered by the pureness of thine hands.

XXIII

^1Then Job answered and said,

^2Even to day is my complaint bitter:
My stroke is heavier than my groaning.
^3Oh that I knew where I might find him!
That I might come even to his seat!
^4I would order my cause before him,
And fill my mouth with arguments.
^5I would know the words which he would answer me,
And understand what he would say unto me.
^6Will he plead against me with his great power?
No; but he would put strength in me.
^7There the righteous might dispute with him;
So should I be delivered for ever from my judge.

^8Behold, I go forward, but he is not there;
And backward, but I cannot perceive him:
^9On the left hand, where he doth work, but I cannot behold him:
He hideth himself on the right hand, that I cannot see him:
^10But he knoweth the way that I take:
When he hath tried me, I shall come forth as gold.
^11My foot hath held his steps,
His way have I kept, and not declined.
^12Neither have I gone back from the commandment of his lips;
I have esteemed the words of his mouth more than my necessary food.
^13But he is in one mind, and who can turn him?
And what his soul desireth, even that he doeth.
^14For he performeth the thing that is appointed for me:
And many such things are with him.
^15Therefore am I troubled at his presence:
When I consider, I am afraid of him.
^16For God maketh my heart soft,
And the Almighty troubleth me:
^17Because I was not cut off before the darkness,
Neither hath he covered the darkness from my face.

XXIV

^1Why, seeing times are not hidden from the Almighty,
Do they that know him not see his days?
^2Some remove the landmarks;
They violently take away flocks, and feed thereof.
^3They drive away the ass of the fatherless,
They take the widow’s ox for a pledge.
^4They turn the needy out of the way:
The poor of the earth hide themselves together.
^5Behold, as wild asses in the desert,
Go they forth to their work; rising betimes for a prey:
The wilderness yieldeth food for them and for their children.
^6They reap every one his corn in the field:
And they gather the vintage of the wicked.
^7They cause the naked to lodge without clothing,
That they have no covering in the cold.
^8They are wet with the showers of the mountains,
And embrace the rock for want of a shelter.
^9They pluck the fatherless from the breast,
And take a pledge of the poor.
^10They cause him to go naked without clothing,
And they take away the sheaf from the hungry;
^11Which make oil within their walls,
And tread their winepresses, and suffer thirst.
^12Men groan from out of the city,
And the soul of the wounded crieth out:
Yet God layeth not folly to them.

^13They are of those that rebel against the light;
They know not the ways thereof,
Nor abide in the paths thereof.
^14The murderer rising with the light killeth the poor and needy,
And in the night is as a thief.
^15The eye also of the adulterer waiteth for the twilight,
Saying, No eye shall see me:
And disguiseth his face.
^16In the dark they dig through houses,
Which they had marked for themselves in the daytime:
They know not the light.
^17For the morning is to them even as the shadow of death:
If one know them, they are in the terrors of the shadow of death.

^18He is swift as the waters;
Their portion is cursed in the earth:
He beholdeth not the way of the vineyards.
^19Drought and heat consume the snow waters:
So doth the grave those which have sinned.
^20The womb shall forget him; the worm shall feed sweetly on him;
He shall be no more remembered;
And wickedness shall be broken as a tree.

^21He evil entreateth the barren that beareth not:
And doeth not good to the widow.
^22He draweth also the mighty with his power:
He riseth up, and no man is sure of life.
^23Though it be given him to be in safety, whereon he resteth;
Yet his eyes are upon their ways.
^24They are exalted for a little while, but are gone and brought low;
They are taken out of the way as all other,
And cut off as the tops of the ears of corn.
^25And if it be not so now, who will make me a liar,
And make my speech nothing worth?

XXV

^1Then answered Bildad the Shuhite, and said,

^2Dominion and fear are with him,
He maketh peace in his high places.
^3Is there any number of his armies?
And upon whom doth not his light arise?
^4How then can man be justified with God?
Or how can he be clean that is born of a woman?
^5Behold even to the moon, and it shineth not;
Yea, the stars are not pure in his sight.
^6How much less man, that is a worm?
And the son of man, which is a worm?

XXVI

^1But Job answered and said,

^2How hast thou helped him that is without power?
How savest thou the arm that hath no strength?
^3How hast thou counselled him that hath no wisdom?
And how hast thou plentifully declared the thing as it is?
^4To whom hast thou uttered words?
And whose spirit came from thee?
^5Dead things are formed from under the waters,
And the inhabitants thereof.
^6Hell is naked before him,
And destruction hath no covering.
^7He stretcheth out the north over the empty place,
And hangeth the earth upon nothing.
^8He bindeth up the waters in his thick clouds;
And the cloud is not rent under them.
^9He holdeth back the face of his throne,
And spreadeth his cloud upon it.
^10He hath compassed the waters with bounds,
Until the day and night come to an end.
^11The pillars of heaven tremble
And are astonished at his reproof.
^12He divideth the sea with his power,
And by his understanding he smiteth through the proud.
^13By his spirit he hath garnished the heavens;
His hand hath formed the crooked serpent.
^14Lo, these are parts of his ways:
But how little a portion is heard of him?
But the thunder of his power who can understand?

XXVII

^1Moreover Job continued his parable, and said,

^2As God liveth, who hath taken away my judgment;
And the Almighty, who hath vexed my soul;
^3All the while my breath is in me,
And the spirit of God is in my nostrils;
^4My lips shall not speak wickedness,
Nor my tongue utter deceit.
^5God forbid that I should justify you:
Till I die I will not remove mine integrity from me.
^6My righteousness I hold fast, and will not let it go:
My heart shall not reproach me so long as I live.
^7Let mine enemy be as the wicked,
And he that riseth up against me as the unrighteous.

^8For what is the hope of the hypocrite, though he hath gained,
When God taketh away his soul?
^9Will God hear his cry
When trouble cometh upon him?
^10Will he delight himself in the Almighty?
Will he always call upon God?
^11I will teach you by the hand of God:
That which is with the Almighty will I not conceal.
^12Behold, all ye yourselves have seen it;
Why then are ye thus altogether vain?

^13This is the portion of a wicked man with God,
And the heritage of oppressors, which they shall receive of the Almighty.
^14If his children be multiplied, it is for the sword:
And his offspring shall not be satisfied with bread.
^15Those that remain of him shall be buried in death:
And his widows shall not weep.
^16Though he heap up silver as the dust,
And prepare raiment as the clay;
^17He may prepare it, but the just shall put it on,
And the innocent shall divide the silver.
^18He buildeth his house as a moth,
And as a booth that the keeper maketh.
^19The rich man shall lie down, but he shall not be gathered:
He openeth his eyes, and he is not.
^20Terrors take hold on him as waters,
A tempest stealeth him away in the night.
^21The east wind carrieth him away, and he departeth:
And as a storm hurleth him out of his place.
^22For God shall cast upon him, and not spare:
He would fain flee out of his hand.
^23Men shall clap their hands at him,
And shall hiss him out of his place.

XXVIII

^1Surely there is a vein for the silver,
And a place for gold where they fine it.
^2Iron is taken out of the earth,
And brass is molten out of the stone.
^3He setteth an end to darkness,
And searcheth out all perfection:
The stones of darkness, and the shadow of death.
^4The flood breaketh out from the inhabitant;
Even the waters forgotten of the foot:
They are dried up, they are gone away from men.
^5As for the earth, out of it cometh bread:
And under it is turned up as it were fire.
^6The stones of it are the place of sapphires:
And it hath dust of gold.

^7There is a path which no fowl knoweth,
And which the vulture’s eye hath not seen:
^8The lion’s whelps have not trodden it,
Nor the fierce lion passed by it.
^9He putteth forth his hand upon the rock;
He overturneth the mountains by the roots.
^10He cutteth out rivers among the rocks;
And his eye seeth every precious thing.
^11He bindeth the floods from overflowing;
And the thing that is hid bringeth he forth to light.

^12But where shall wisdom be found?
And where is the place of understanding?
^13Man knoweth not the price thereof;
Neither is it found in the land of the living.
^14The depth saith, It is not in me:
And the sea saith, It is not with me.
^15It cannot be gotten for gold,
Neither shall silver be weighed for the price thereof.
^16It cannot be valued with the gold of Ophir,
With the precious onyx, or the sapphire.
^17The gold and the crystal cannot equal it:
And the exchange of it shall not be for jewels of fine gold.
^18No mention shall be made of coral, or of pearls:
For the price of wisdom is above rubies.
^19The topaz of Ethiopia shall not equal it,
Neither shall it be valued with pure gold.

^20Whence then cometh wisdom?
And where is the place of understanding?
^21Seeing it is hid from the eyes of all living,
And kept close from the fowls of the air.
^22Destruction and death say,
We have heard the fame thereof with our ears.

^23God understandeth the way thereof,
And he knoweth the place thereof.
^24For he looketh to the ends of the earth,
And seeth under the whole heaven;
^25To make the weight for the winds;
And he weigheth the waters by measure.
^26When he made a decree for the rain,
And a way for the lightning of the thunder:
^27Then did he see it, and declare it;
He prepared it, yea, and searched it out.
^28And unto man he said,
Behold, the fear of the Lord, that is wisdom;
And to depart from evil is understanding.

XXIX

^1Moreover Job continued his parable, and said,

^2Oh that I were as in months past,
As in the days when God preserved me;
^3When his candle shined upon my head,
And when by his light I walked through darkness;
^4As I was in the days of my youth,
When the secret of God was upon my tabernacle;
^5When the Almighty was yet with me,
When my children were about me;
^6When I washed my steps with butter,
And the rock poured me out rivers of oil;

^7When I went out to the gate through the city,
When I prepared my seat in the street!
^8The young men saw me, and hid themselves:
And the aged arose, and stood up.
^9The princes refrained talking,
And laid their hand on their mouth.
^10The nobles held their peace,
And their tongue cleaved to the roof of their mouth.
^11When the ear heard me, then it blessed me;
And when the eye saw me, it gave witness to me:
^12Because I delivered the poor that cried,
And the fatherless, and him that had none to help him.
^13The blessing of him that was ready to perish came upon me:
And I caused the widow’s heart to sing for joy.
^14I put on righteousness, and it clothed me:
My judgment was as a robe and a diadem.
^15I was eyes to the blind,
And feet was I to the lame.
^16I was a father to the poor:
And the cause which I knew not I searched out.
^17And I brake the jaws of the wicked,
And plucked the spoil out of his teeth.
^18Then I said, I shall die in my nest,
And I shall multiply my days as the sand.
^19My root was spread out by the waters,
And the dew lay all night upon my branch.
^20My glory was fresh in me,
And my bow was renewed in my hand.

^21Unto me men gave ear, and waited,
And kept silence at my counsel.
^22After my words they spake not again;
And my speech dropped upon them.
^23And they waited for me as for the rain;
And they opened their mouth wide as for the latter rain.
^24If I laughed on them, they believed it not;
And the light of my countenance they cast not down.
^25I chose out their way, and sat chief,
And dwelt as a king in the army,
As one that comforteth the mourners.

XXX

^1But now they that are younger than I have me in derision,
Whose fathers I would have disdained to have set with the dogs of my flock.
^2Yea, whereto might the strength of their hands profit me,
In whom old age was perished?
^3For want and famine they were solitary;
Fleeing into the wilderness in former time desolate and waste.
^4Who cut up mallows by the bushes,
And juniper roots for their meat.
^5They were driven forth from among men,
(They cried after them as after a thief;)
^6To dwell in the cliffs of the valleys,
In caves of the earth, and in the rocks.
^7Among the bushes they brayed;
Under the nettles they were gathered together.
^8They were children of fools, yea, children of base men:
They were viler than the earth.

^9And now am I their song,
Yea, I am their byword.
^10They abhor me, they flee far from me,
And spare not to spit in my face.
^11Because he hath loosed my cord, and afflicted me,
They have also let loose the bridle before me.
^12Upon my right hand rise the youth;
They push away my feet,
And they raise up against me the ways of their destruction.
^13They mar my path,
They set forward my calamity,
They have no helper.
^14They came upon me as a wide breaking in of waters:
In the desolation they rolled themselves upon me.
^15Terrors are turned upon me:
They pursue my soul as the wind:
And my welfare passeth away as a cloud.

^16And now my soul is poured out upon me;
The days of affliction have taken hold upon me.
^17My bones are pierced in me in the night season:
And my sinews take no rest.
^18By the great force of my disease is my garment changed:
It bindeth me about as the collar of my coat.
^19He hath cast me into the mire,
And I am become like dust and ashes.
^20I cry unto thee, and thou dost not hear me:
I stand up, and thou regardest me not.
^21Thou art become cruel to me:
With thy strong hand thou opposest thyself against me.
^22Thou liftest me up to the wind;
Thou causest me to ride upon it, and dissolvest my substance.
^23For I know that thou wilt bring me to death,
And to the house appointed for all living.

^24Howbeit he will not stretch out his hand to the grave,
Though they cry in his destruction.
^25Did not I weep for him that was in trouble?
Was not my soul grieved for the poor?
^26When I looked for good, then evil came unto me:
And when I waited for light, there came darkness.
^27My bowels boiled, and rested not:
The days of affliction prevented me.
^28I went mourning without the sun:
I stood up, and I cried in the congregation.
^29I am a brother to dragons,
And a companion to owls.
^30My skin is black upon me,
And my bones are burned with heat.
^31My harp also is turned to mourning,
And my organ into the voice of them that weep.

XXXI

^1I made a covenant with mine eyes;
Why then should I think upon a maid?
^2For what portion of God is there from above?
And what inheritance of the Almighty from on high?
^3Is not destruction to the wicked?
And a strange punishment to the workers of iniquity?
^4Doth not he see my ways,
And count all my steps?

^5If I have walked with vanity,
Or if my foot hath hasted to deceit;
^6Let me be weighed in an even balance,
That God may know mine integrity.
^7If my step hath turned out of the way,
And mine heart walked after mine eyes,
And if any blot hath cleaved to mine hands;
^8Then let me sow, and let another eat;
Yea, let my offspring be rooted out.

^9If mine heart have been deceived by a woman,
Or if I have laid wait at my neighbour’s door;
^10Then let my wife grind unto another,
And let others bow down upon her.
^11For this is an heinous crime;
Yea, it is an iniquity to be punished by the judges.
^12For it is a fire that consumeth to destruction,
And would root out all mine increase.

^13If I did despise the cause of my manservant or of my maidservant,
When they contended with me;
^14What then shall I do when God riseth up?
And when he visiteth, what shall I answer him?
^15Did not he that made me in the womb make him?
And did not one fashion us in the womb?

^16If I have withheld the poor from their desire,
Or have caused the eyes of the widow to fail;
^17Or have eaten my morsel myself alone,
And the fatherless hath not eaten thereof;
^18(For from my youth he was brought up with me, as with a father,
And I have guided her from my mother’s womb;)
^19If I have seen any perish for want of clothing,
Or any poor without covering;
^20If his loins have not blessed me,
And if he were not warmed with the fleece of my sheep;
^21If I have lifted up my hand against the fatherless,
When I saw my help in the gate:
^22Then let mine arm fall from my shoulder blade,
And mine arm be broken from the bone.

^23For destruction from God was a terror to me,
And by reason of his highness I could not endure.
^24If I have made gold my hope,
Or have said to the fine gold, Thou art my confidence;
^25If I rejoice because my wealth was great,
And because mine hand had gotten much;
^26If I beheld the sun when it shined,
Or the moon walking in brightness;
^27And my heart hath been secretly enticed,
Or my mouth hath kissed my hand:
^28This also were an iniquity to be punished by the judge:
For I should have denied the God that is above.

^29If I rejoice at the destruction of him that hated me,
Or lifted up myself when evil found him:
^30Neither have I suffered my mouth to sin
By wishing a curse to his soul.
^31If the men of my tabernacle said not,
Oh that we had of his flesh! we cannot be satisfied.
^32The stranger did not lodge in the street:
But I opened my doors to the traveller.
^33If I covered my transgressions as Adam,
By hiding mine iniquity in my bosom:
^34Did I fear a great multitude,
Or did the contempt of families terrify me,
That I kept silence, and went not out of the door?
^35Oh that one would hear me!
Behold, my desire is, that the Almighty would answer me,
And that mine adversary had written a book.
^36Surely I would take it upon my shoulder,
And bind it as a crown to me.
^37I would declare unto him the number of my steps;
As a prince would I go near unto him.

^38If my land cry against me,
Or that the furrows likewise thereof complain;
^39If I have eaten the fruits thereof without money,
Or have caused the owners thereof to lose their life:
^40Let thistles grow instead of wheat,
And cockle instead of barley.

The words of Job are ended.

XXXII

^1So these three men ceased to answer Job, because he was righteous in his own eyes. ^2Then was kindled the wrath of Elihu the son of Barachel the Buzite, of the kindred of Ram: against Job was his wrath kindled, because he justified himself rather than God. ^3Also against his three friends was his wrath kindled, because they had found no answer, and yet had condemned Job. ^4Now Elihu had waited till Job had spoken, because they were elder than he. ^5When Elihu saw that there was no answer in the mouth of these three men, then his wrath was kindled.

^6And Elihu the son of Barachel the Buzite answered and said,

I am young, and ye are very old;
Wherefore I was afraid, and durst not shew you mine opinion.
^7I said, Days should speak,
And multitude of years should teach wisdom.
^8But there is a spirit in man:
And the inspiration of the Almighty giveth them understanding.
^9Great men are not always wise:
Neither do the aged understand judgment.
^10Therefore I said, Hearken to me;
I also will shew mine opinion.

^11Behold, I waited for your words;
I gave ear to your reasons,
Whilst ye searched out what to say.
^12Yea, I attended unto you,
And, behold, there was none of you that convinced Job,
Or that answered his words:
^13Lest ye should say, We have found out wisdom:
God thrusteth him down, not man.
^14Now he hath not directed his words against me:
Neither will I answer him with your speeches.

^15They were amazed, they answered no more:
They left off speaking.
^16When I had waited, (for they spake not,
But stood still, and answered no more;)
^17I said, I will answer also my part,
I also will shew mine opinion.
^18For I am full of matter,
The spirit within me constraineth me.
^19Behold, my belly is as wine which hath no vent;
It is ready to burst like new bottles.
^20I will speak, that I may be refreshed:
I will open my lips and answer.
^21Let me not, I pray you, accept any man’s person,
Neither let me give flattering titles unto man.
^22For I know not to give flattering titles;
In so doing my maker would soon take me away.

XXXIII

^1Wherefore, Job, I pray thee, hear my speeches,
And hearken to all my words.
^2Behold, now I have opened my mouth,
My tongue hath spoken in my mouth.
^3My words shall be of the uprightness of my heart:
And my lips shall utter knowledge clearly.
^4The spirit of God hath made me,
And the breath of the Almighty hath given me life.
^5If thou canst answer me,
Set thy words in order before me, stand up.
^6Behold, I am according to thy wish in God’s stead:
I also am formed out of the clay.
^7Behold, my terror shall not make thee afraid,
Neither shall my hand be heavy upon thee.

^8Surely thou hast spoken in mine hearing,
And I have heard the voice of thy words, saying,
^9I am clean without transgression, I am innocent;
Neither is there iniquity in me.
^10Behold, he findeth occasions against me,
He counteth me for his enemy,
^11He putteth my feet in the stocks,
He marketh all my paths.

^12Behold, in this thou art not just:
I will answer thee, that God is greater than man.
^13Why dost thou strive against him?
For he giveth not account of any of his matters.
^14For God speaketh once, yea twice,
Yet man perceiveth it not.
^15In a dream, in a vision of the night,
When deep sleep falleth upon men,
In slumberings upon the bed;
^16Then he openeth the ears of men,
And sealeth their instruction,
^17That he may withdraw man from his purpose,
And hide pride from man.
^18He keepeth back his soul from the pit,
And his life from perishing by the sword.

^19He is chastened also with pain upon his bed,
And the multitude of his bones with strong pain:
^20So that his life abhorreth bread,
And his soul dainty meat.
^21His flesh is consumed away, that it cannot be seen;
And his bones that were not seen stick out.
^22Yea, his soul draweth near unto the grave,
And his life to the destroyers.

^23If there be a messenger with him,
An interpreter, one among a thousand,
To shew unto man his uprightness:
^24Then he is gracious unto him, and saith,
Deliver him from going down to the pit:
I have found a ransom.
^25His flesh shall be fresher than a child’s:
He shall return to the days of his youth:
^26He shall pray unto God, and he will be favourable unto him:
And he shall see his face with joy:
For he will render unto man his righteousness.
^27He looketh upon men, and if any say,
I have sinned, and perverted that which was right,
And it profited me not;
^28He will deliver his soul from going into the pit,
And his life shall see the light.

^29Lo, all these things worketh God
Oftentimes with man,
^30To bring back his soul from the pit,
To be enlightened with the light of the living.
^31Mark well, O Job, hearken unto me:
Hold thy peace, and I will speak.
^32If thou hast anything to say, answer me:
Speak, for I desire to justify thee.
^33If not, hearken unto me:
Hold thy peace, and I shall teach thee wisdom.

XXXIV

^1Furthermore Elihu answered and said,

^2Hear my words, O ye wise men;
And give ear unto me, ye that have knowledge.
^3For the ear trieth words,
As the mouth tasteth meat.
^4Let us choose to us judgment:
Let us know among ourselves what is good.
^5For Job hath said, I am righteous:
And God hath taken away my judgment.
^6Should I lie against my right?
My wound is incurable without transgression.
^7What man is like Job,
Who drinketh up scorning like water?
^8Which goeth in company with the workers of iniquity,
And walketh with wicked men.
^9For he hath said, It profiteth a man nothing
That he should delight himself with God.

^10Therefore hearken unto me ye, men of understanding:
Far be it from God, that he should do wickedness;
And from the Almighty, that he should commit iniquity.
^11For the work of a man shall he render unto him,
And cause every man to find according to his ways.
^12Yea, surely God will not do wickedly,
Neither will the Almighty pervert judgment.
^13Who hath given him a charge over the earth?
Or who hath disposed the whole world?
^14If he set his heart upon man,
If he gather unto himself his spirit and his breath;
^15All flesh shall perish together,
And man shall turn again unto dust.

^16If now thou hast understanding, hear this:
Hearken to the voice of my words.
^17Shall even he that hateth right govern?
And wilt thou condemn him that is most just?
^18Is it fit to say to a king, Thou art wicked?
And to princes, Ye are ungodly?
^19How much less to him that accepteth not the persons of princes,
Nor regardeth the rich more than the poor?
For they all are the work of his hands.
^20In a moment shall they die,
And the people shall be troubled at midnight, and pass away:
And the mighty shall be taken away without hand.

^21For his eyes are upon the ways of man,
And he seeth all his goings.
^22There is no darkness, nor shadow of death,
Where the workers of iniquity may hide themselves.
^23For he will not lay upon man more than right;
That he should enter into judgment with God.
^24He shall break in pieces mighty men without number,
And set others in their stead.
^25Therefore he knoweth their works,
And he overturneth them in the night,
So that they are destroyed.
^26He striketh them as wicked men
In the open sight of others;
^27Because they turned back from him,
And would not consider any of his ways:
^28So that they cause the cry of the poor to come unto him,
And he heareth the cry of the afflicted.
^29When he giveth quietness, who then can make trouble?
And when he hideth his face, who then can behold him?
Whether it be done against a nation, or against a man only:
^30That the hypocrite reign not,
Lest the people be ensnared.

^31Surely it is meet to be said unto God,
I have borne chastisement, I will not offend any more:
^32That which I see not teach thou me:
If I have done iniquity, I will do no more.
^33Should it be according to thy mind?
He will recompense it, whether thou refuse,
Or whether thou choose; and not I:
Therefore speak what thou knowest.
^34Let men of understanding tell me,
And let a wise man hearken unto me.
^35Job hath spoken without knowledge,
And his words were without wisdom.
^36My desire is that Job may be tried unto the end
Because of his answers for wicked men.
^37For he addeth rebellion unto his sin,
He clappeth his hands among us,
And multiplieth his words against God.

XXXV

^1Elihu spake moreover, and said,

^2Thinkest thou this to be right,
That thou saidst, My righteousness is more than God’s?
^3For thou saidst, What advantage will it be unto thee?
And, What profit shall I have, if I be cleansed from my sin?
^4I will answer thee,
And thy companions with thee.
^5Look unto the heavens, and see;
And behold the clouds which are higher than thou.
^6If thou sinnest, what doest thou against him?
Or if thy transgressions be multiplied, what doest thou unto him?
^7If thou be righteous, what givest thou him?
Or what receiveth he of thine hand?
^8Thy wickedness may hurt a man as thou art;
And thy righteousness may profit the son of man.

^9By reason of the multitude of oppressions they make the oppressed to cry:
They cry out by reason of the arm of the mighty.
^10But none saith, Where is God my maker,
Who giveth songs in the night;
^11Who teacheth us more than the beasts of the earth,
And maketh us wiser than the fowls of heaven?
^12There they cry, but none giveth answer,
Because of the pride of evil men.
^13Surely God will not hear vanity,
Neither will the Almighty regard it.
^14Although thou sayest thou shalt not see him,
Yet judgment is before him; therefore trust thou in him.
^15But now, because it is not so, he hath visited in his anger;
Yet he knoweth it not in great extremity:
^16Therefore doth Job open his mouth in vain;
He multiplieth words without knowledge.

XXXVI

^1Elihu also proceeded, and said,

^2Suffer me a little, and I will shew thee
That I have yet to speak on God’s behalf.
^3I will fetch my knowledge from afar,
And will ascribe righteousness to my Maker.
^4For truly my words shall not be false:
He that is perfect in knowledge is with thee.

^5Behold, God is mighty, and despiseth not any:
He is mighty in strength and wisdom.
^6He preserveth not the life of the wicked:
But giveth right to the poor.
^7He withdraweth not his eyes from the righteous:
But with kings are they on the throne;
Yea, he doth establish them for ever, and they are exalted.
^8And if they be bound in fetters,
And be holden in cords of affliction;
^9Then he sheweth them their work,
And their transgressions that they have exceeded.
^10He openeth also their ear to discipline,
And commandeth that they return from iniquity.
^11If they obey and serve him,
They shall spend their days in prosperity,
And their years in pleasures.
^12But if they obey not, they shall perish by the sword,
And they shall die without knowledge.

^13But the hypocrites in heart heap up wrath:
They cry not when he bindeth them.
^14They die in youth,
And their life is among the unclean.
^15He delivereth the poor in his affliction,
And openeth their ears in oppression.
^16Even so would he have removed thee out of the strait
Into a broad place, where there is no straitness;
And that which should be set on thy table should be full of fatness.

^17But thou hast fulfilled the judgment of the wicked:
Judgment and justice take hold on thee.
^18Because there is wrath, beware lest he take thee away with his stroke:
Then a great ransom cannot deliver thee.
^19Will he esteem thy riches?
No, not gold, nor all the forces of strength.
^20Desire not the night,
When people are cut off in their place.
^21Take heed, regard not iniquity:
For this hast thou chosen rather than affliction.
^22Behold, God exalteth by his power:
Who teacheth like him?
^23Who hath enjoined him his way?
Or who can say, Thou hast wrought iniquity?

^24Remember that thou magnify his work,
Which men behold.
^25Every man may see it;
Man may behold it afar off.
^26Behold, God is great, and we know him not,
Neither can the number of his years be searched out.
^27For he maketh small the drops of water:
They pour down rain according to the vapour thereof:
^28Which the clouds do drop
And distil upon man abundantly.
^29Also can any understand the spreadings of the clouds,
Or the noise of his tabernacle?
^30Behold, he spreadeth his light upon it,
And covereth the bottom of the sea.
^31For by them judgeth he the people;
He giveth meat in abundance.
^32With clouds he covereth the light;
And commandeth it not to shine by the cloud that cometh betwixt.
^33The noise thereof sheweth concerning it,
The cattle also concerning the vapour.

XXXVII

^1At this also my heart trembleth,
And is moved out of his place.
^2Hear attentively the noise of his voice,
And the sound that goeth out of his mouth.
^3He directeth it under the whole heaven,
And his lightning unto the ends of the earth.
^4After it a voice roareth:
He thundereth with the voice of his excellency;
And he will not stay them when his voice is heard.
^5God thundereth marvellously with his voice;
Great things doeth he, which we cannot comprehend.
^6For he saith to the snow, Be thou on the earth;
Likewise to the small rain,
And to the great rain of his strength.
^7He sealeth up the hand of every man;
That all men may know his work.
^8Then the beasts go into dens,
And remain in their places.
^9Out of the south cometh the whirlwind:
And cold out of the north.
^10By the breath of God frost is given:
And the breadth of the waters is straitened.
^11Also by watering he wearieth the thick cloud:
He scattereth his bright cloud:
^12And it is turned round about by his counsels:
That they may do whatsoever he commandeth them
Upon the face of the world in the earth.
^13He causeth it to come,
Whether for correction, or for his land, or for mercy.
^14Hearken unto this, O Job:
Stand still, and consider the wondrous works of God.
^15Dost thou know when God disposed them,
And caused the light of his cloud to shine?
^16Dost thou know the balancings of the clouds,
The wondrous works of him which is perfect in knowledge?
^17How thy garments are warm,
When he quieteth the earth by the south wind?
^18Hast thou with him spread out the sky,
Which is strong, and as a molten looking glass?
^19Teach us what we shall say unto him;
For we cannot order our speech by reason of darkness.
^20Shall it be told him that I speak?
If a man speak, surely he shall be swallowed up.

^21And now men see not the bright light which is in the clouds:
But the wind passeth, and cleanseth them.
^22Fair weather cometh out of the north:
With God is terrible majesty.
^23Touching the Almighty, we cannot find him out:
He is excellent in power, and in judgment,
And in plenty of justice: he will not afflict.
^24Men do therefore fear him:
He respecteth not any that are wise of heart.

XXXVIII

^1Then the Lord answered Job out of the whirlwind, and said,

^2Who is this that darkeneth counsel
By words without knowledge?
^3Gird up now thy loins like a man;
For I will demand of thee, and answer thou me.

^4Where wast thou when I laid the foundations of the earth?
Declare, if thou hast understanding.
^5Who hath laid the measures thereof, if thou knowest?
Or who hath stretched the line upon it?
^6Whereupon are the foundations thereof fastened?
Or who laid the corner stone thereof;
^7When the morning stars sang together,
And all the sons of God shouted for joy?

^8Or who shut up the sea with doors,
When it brake forth, as if it had issued out of the womb?
^9When I made the cloud the garment thereof,
And thick darkness a swaddlingband for it,
^10And brake up for it my decreed place,
And set bars and doors,
^11And said, Hitherto shalt thou come, but no further:
And here shall thy proud waves be stayed?

^12Hast thou commanded the morning since thy days;
And caused the dayspring to know his place;
^13That it might take hold of the ends of the earth,
That the wicked might be shaken out of it?
^14It is turned as clay to the seal;
And they stand as a garment.
^15And from the wicked their light is withholden,
And the high arm shall be broken.

^16Hast thou entered into the springs of the sea?
Or hast thou walked in the search of the depth?
^17Have the gates of death been opened unto thee?
Or hast thou seen the doors of the shadow of death?
^18Hast thou perceived the breadth of the earth?
Declare if thou knowest it all.

^19Where is the way where light dwelleth?
And as for darkness, where is the place thereof,
^20That thou shouldest take it to the bound thereof,
And that thou shouldest know the paths to the house thereof?
^21Knowest thou it, because thou wast then born?
Or because the number of thy days is great?

^22Hast thou entered into the treasures of the snow?
Or hast thou seen the treasures of the hail,
^23Which I have reserved against the time of trouble,
Against the day of battle and war?
^24By what way is the light parted,
Which scattereth the east wind upon the earth?

^25Who hath divided a watercourse for the overflowing of waters,
Or a way for the lightning of thunder;
^26To cause it to rain on the earth, where no man is;
On the wilderness, wherein there is no man;
^27To satisfy the desolate and waste ground;
And to cause the bud of the tender herb to spring forth?
^28Hath the rain a father?
Or who hath begotten the drops of dew?
^29Out of whose womb came the ice?
And the hoary frost of heaven, who hath gendered it?
^30The waters are hid as with a stone,
And the face of the deep is frozen.

^31Canst thou bind the sweet influences of Pleiades,
Or loose the bands of Orion?
^32Canst thou bring forth Mazzaroth in his season?
Or canst thou guide Arcturus with his sons?
^33Knowest thou the ordinances of heaven?
Canst thou set the dominion thereof in the earth?

^34Canst thou lift up thy voice to the clouds,
That abundance of waters may cover thee?
^35Canst thou send lightnings, that they may go,
And say unto thee, Here we are?
^36Who hath put wisdom in the inward parts?
Or who hath given understanding to the heart?
^37Who can number the clouds in wisdom?
Or who can stay the bottles of heaven,
^38When the dust groweth into hardness,
And the clods cleave fast together?

^39Wilt thou hunt the prey for the lion?
Or fill the appetite of the young lions,
^40When they couch in their dens,
And abide in the covert to lie in wait?
^41Who provideth for the raven his food?
When his young ones cry unto God,
They wander for lack of meat.

XXXIX

^1Knowest thou the time when the wild goats of the rock bring forth?
Or canst thou mark when the hinds do calve?
^2Canst thou number the months that they fulfil?
Or knowest thou the time when they bring forth?
^3They bow themselves, they bring forth their young ones,
They cast out their sorrows.
^4Their young ones are in good liking, they grow up with corn;
They go forth, and return not unto them.

^5Who hath sent out the wild ass free?
Or who hath loosed the bands of the wild ass?
^6Whose house I have made the wilderness,
And the barren land his dwellings.
^7He scorneth the multitude of the city,
Neither regardeth he the crying of the driver.
^8The range of the mountains is his pasture,
And he searcheth after every green thing.

^9Will the unicorn be willing to serve thee,
Or abide by thy crib?
^10Canst thou bind the unicorn with his band in the furrow?
Or will he harrow the valleys after thee?
^11Wilt thou trust him, because his strength is great?
Or wilt thou leave thy labour to him?
^12Wilt thou believe him, that he will bring home thy seed,
And gather it into thy barn?

^13Gavest thou the goodly wings unto the peacocks?
Or wings and feathers unto the ostrich?
^14Which leaveth her eggs in the earth,
And warmeth them in dust,
^15And forgetteth that the foot may crush them,
Or that the wild beast may break them.
^16She is hardened against her young ones, as though they were not her’s:
Her labour is in vain without fear;
^17Because God hath deprived her of wisdom,
Neither hath he imparted to her understanding.
^18What time she lifteth up herself on high,
She scorneth the horse and his rider.

^19Hast thou given the horse strength?
Hast thou clothed his neck with thunder?
^20Canst thou make him afraid as a grasshopper?
The glory of his nostrils is terrible.
^21He paweth in the valley, and rejoiceth in his strength:
He goeth on to meet the armed men.
^22He mocketh at fear, and is not affrighted;
Neither turneth he back from the sword.
^23The quiver rattleth against him,
The glittering spear and the shield.
^24He swalloweth the ground with fierceness and rage:
Neither believeth he that it is the sound of the trumpet.
^25He saith among the trumpets, Ha, ha;
And he smelleth the battle afar off,
The thunder of the captains, and the shouting.

^26Doth the hawk fly by thy wisdom,
And stretch her wings toward the south?
^27Doth the eagle mount up at thy command,
And make her nest on high?
^28She dwelleth and abideth on the rock,
Upon the crag of the rock, and the strong place.
^29From thence she seeketh the prey,
And her eyes behold afar off.
^30Her young ones also suck up blood:
And where the slain are, there is she.

XL

^1Moreover the Lord answered Job, and said,

^2Shall he that contendeth with the Almighty instruct him?
He that reproveth God, let him answer it.

^3Then Job answered the Lord, and said,

^4Behold, I am vile; what shall I answer thee?
I will lay mine hand upon my mouth.
^5Once have I spoken; but I will not answer:
Yea, twice; but I will proceed no further.

^6Then answered the Lord unto Job out of the whirlwind, and said,

^7Gird up thy loins now like a man:
I will demand of thee, and declare thou unto me.
^8Wilt thou also disannul my judgment?
Wilt thou condemn me, that thou mayest be righteous?
^9Hast thou an arm like God?
Or canst thou thunder with a voice like him?

^10Deck thyself now with majesty and excellency;
And array thyself with glory and beauty.
^11Cast abroad the rage of thy wrath:
And behold every one that is proud, and abase him.
^12Look on every one that is proud, and bring him low;
And tread down the wicked in their place.
^13Hide them in the dust together;
And bind their faces in secret.
^14Then will I also confess unto thee
That thine own right hand can save thee.

^15Behold now behemoth, which I made with thee;
He eateth grass as an ox.
^16Lo now, his strength is in his loins,
And his force is in the navel of his belly.
^17He moveth his tail like a cedar:
The sinews of his stones are wrapped together.
^18His bones are as strong pieces of brass;
His bones are like bars of iron.

^19He is the chief of the ways of God:
He that made him can make his sword to approach unto him.
^20Surely the mountains bring him forth food,
Where all the beasts of the field play.
^21He lieth under the shady trees,
In the covert of the reed, and fens.
^22The shady trees cover him with their shadow;
The willows of the brook compass him about.
^23Behold, he drinketh up a river, and hasteth not:
He trusteth that he can draw up Jordan into his mouth.
^24He taketh it with his eyes:
His nose pierceth through snares.

XLI

^1Canst thou draw out leviathan with an hook?
Or his tongue with a cord which thou lettest down?
^2Canst thou put an hook into his nose?
Or bore his jaw through with a thorn?
^3Will he make many supplications unto thee?
Will he speak soft words unto thee?
^4Will he make a covenant with thee?
Wilt thou take him for a servant for ever?
^5Wilt thou play with him as with a bird?
Or wilt thou bind him for thy maidens?
^6Shall the companions make a banquet of him?
Shall they part him among the merchants?
^7Canst thou fill his skin with barbed irons?
Or his head with fish spears?
^8Lay thine hand upon him,
Remember the battle, do no more.
^9Behold, the hope of him is in vain:
Shall not one be cast down even at the sight of him?
^10None is so fierce that dare stir him up:
Who then is able to stand before me?
^11Who hath prevented me, that I should repay him?
Whatsoever is under the whole heaven is mine.

^12I will not conceal his parts,
Nor his power, nor his comely proportion.
^13Who can discover the face of his garment?
Or who can come to him with his double bridle?
^14Who can open the doors of his face?
His teeth are terrible round about.
^15His scales are his pride,
Shut up together as with a close seal.
^16One is so near to another,
That no air can come between them.
^17They are joined one to another,
They stick together, that they cannot be sundered.
^18By his neesings a light doth shine,
And his eyes are like the eyelids of the morning.
^19Out of his mouth go burning lamps,
And sparks of fire leap out.
^20Out of his nostrils goeth smoke,
As out of a seething pot or caldron.
^21His breath kindleth coals,
And a flame goeth out of his mouth.
^22In his neck remaineth strength,
And sorrow is turned into joy before him.
^23The flakes of his flesh are joined together:
They are firm in themselves; they cannot be moved.
^24His heart is as firm as a stone;
Yea, as hard as a piece of the nether millstone.
^25When he raiseth up himself, the mighty are afraid:
By reason of breakings they purify themselves.
^26The sword of him that layeth at him cannot hold:
The spear, the dart, nor the habergeon.
^27He esteemeth iron as straw,
And brass as rotten wood.
^28The arrow cannot make him flee:
Slingstones are turned with him into stubble.
^29Darts are counted as stubble:
He laugheth at the shaking of a spear.
^30Sharp stones are under him:
He spreadeth sharp pointed things upon the mire.
^31He maketh the deep to boil like a pot:
He maketh the sea like a pot of ointment.
^32He maketh a path to shine after him;
One would think the deep to be hoary.
^33Upon earth there is not his like,
Who is made without fear.
^34He beholdeth all high things:
He is a king over all the children of pride.

XLII

^1Then Job answered the Lord, and said,

^2I know that thou canst do every thing,
And that no thought can be withholden from thee.
^3Who is he that hideth counsel without knowledge?
Therefore have I uttered that I understood not;
Things too wonderful for me, which I knew not.
^4Hear, I beseech thee, and I will speak:
I will demand of thee, and declare thou unto me.
^5I have heard of thee by the hearing of the ear:
But now mine eye seeth thee.
^6Wherefore I abhor myself,
And repent in dust and ashes.

^7And it was so, that after the Lord had spoken these words unto Job, the Lord said to Eliphaz the Temanite, My wrath is kindled against thee, and against thy two friends: for ye have not spoken of me the thing that is right, as my servant Job hath. ^8Therefore take unto you now seven bullocks and seven rams, and go to my servant Job, and offer up for yourselves a burnt offering; and my servant Job shall pray for you: for him will I accept: lest I deal with you after your folly, in that ye have not spoken of me the thing which is right, like my servant Job. ^9So Eliphaz the Temanite and Bildad the Shuhite and Zophar the Naamathite went, and did according as the Lord commanded them: the Lord also accepted Job. ^10And the Lord turned the captivity of Job, when he prayed for his friends: also the Lord gave Job twice as much as he had before. ^11Then came there unto him all his brethren, and all his sisters, and all they that had been of his acquaintance before, and did eat bread with him in his house: and they bemoaned him, and comforted him over all the evil that the Lord had brought upon him: every man also gave him a piece of money, and every one an earring of gold. ^12So the Lord blessed the latter end of Job more than his beginning: for he had fourteen thousand sheep, and six thousand camels, and a thousand yoke of oxen, and a thousand she asses. ^13He had also seven sons and three daughters. ^14And he called the name of the first, Jemima; and the name of the second, Kezia; and the name of the third, Kerenhappuch. ^15And in all the land were no women found so fair as the daughters of Job: and their father gave them inheritance among their brethren. ^16After this lived Job an hundred and forty years, and saw his sons, and his sons’ sons, even four generations. ^17So Job died, being old and full of days.

The Second Book of

Psalms

XLII

^1As the hart panteth after the water brooks, so panteth my soul after thee, O God.
^2My soul thirsteth for God, for the living God: when shall I come and appear before God?
^3My tears have been my meat day and night, while they continually say unto me, Where is thy God?
^4When I remember these things, I pour out my soul in me: for I had gone with the multitude, I went with them to the house of God, with the voice of joy and praise, with a multitude that kept holyday.
^5Why art thou cast down, O my soul? and why art thou disquieted in me? hope thou in God: for I shall yet praise him for the help of his countenance.
^6O my God, my soul is cast down within me: therefore will I remember thee from the land of Jordan, and of the Hermonites, from the hill Mizar.
^7Deep calleth unto deep at the noise of thy waterspouts: all thy waves and thy billows are gone over me.
^8Yet the Lord will command his lovingkindness in the day time, and in the night his song shall be with me, and my prayer unto the God of my life.
^9I will say unto God my rock, Why hast thou forgotten me? why go I mourning because of the oppression of the enemy?
^10As with a sword in my bones, mine enemies reproach me; while they say daily unto me, Where is thy God?
^11Why art thou cast down, O my soul? and why art thou disquieted within me? hope thou in God: for I shall yet praise him, who is the health of my countenance, and my God.

XLIII

^1Judge me, O God, and plead my cause against an ungodly nation: O deliver me from the deceitful and unjust man.
^2For thou art the God of my strength: why dost thou cast me off? why go I mourning because of the oppression of the enemy?
^3O send out thy light and thy truth: let them lead me; let them bring me unto thy holy hill, and to thy tabernacles.
^4Then will I go unto the altar of God, unto God my exceeding joy: yea, upon the harp will I praise thee, O God my God.
^5Why art thou cast down, O my soul? and why art thou disquieted within me? hope in God: for I shall yet praise him, who is the health of my countenance, and my God.

XLIV

^1We have heard with our ears, O God, our fathers have told us, what work thou didst in their days, in the times of old.
^2How thou didst drive out the heathen with thy hand, and plantedst them; how thou didst afflict the people, and cast them out.
^3For they got not the land in possession by their own sword, neither did their own arm save them: but thy right hand, and thine arm, and the light of thy countenance, because thou hadst a favour unto them.
^4Thou art my King, O God: command deliverances for Jacob.
^5Through thee will we push down our enemies: through thy name will we tread them under that rise up against us.
^6For I will not trust in my bow, neither shall my sword save me.
^7But thou hast saved us from our enemies, and hast put them to shame that hated us.
^8In God we boast all the day long, and praise thy name for ever.
Selah.
^9But thou hast cast off, and put us to shame; and goest not forth with our armies.
^10Thou makest us to turn back from the enemy: and they which hate us spoil for themselves.
^11Thou hast given us like sheep appointed for meat; and hast scattered us among the heathen.
^12Thou sellest thy people for nought, and dost not increase thy wealth by their price.
^13Thou makest us a reproach to our neighbours, a scorn and a derision to them that are round about us.
^14Thou makest us a byword among the heathen, a shaking of the head among the people.
^15My confusion is continually before me, and the shame of my face hath covered me,
^16For the voice of him that reproacheth and blasphemeth; by reason of the enemy and avenger.
^17All this is come upon us; yet have we not forgotten thee, neither have we dealt falsely in thy covenant.
^18Our heart is not turned back, neither have our steps declined from thy way;
^19Though thou hast sore broken us in the place of dragons, and covered us with the shadow of death.
^20If we have forgotten the name of our God, or stretched out our hands to a strange god;
^21Shall not God search this out? for he knoweth the secrets of the heart.
^22Yea, for thy sake are we killed all the day long; we are counted as sheep for the slaughter.
^23Awake, why sleepest thou, O Lord? arise, cast us not off for ever.
^24Wherefore hidest thou thy face, and forgettest our affliction and our oppression?
^25For our soul is bowed down to the dust: our belly cleaveth unto the earth.
^26Arise for our help, and redeem us for thy mercies’ sake.

XLV

^1My heart is inditing a good matter: I speak of the things which I have made touching the king: my tongue is the pen of a ready writer.
^2Thou art fairer than the children of men: grace is poured into thy lips: therefore God hath blessed thee for ever.
^3Gird thy sword upon thy thigh, O most mighty, with thy glory and thy majesty.
^4And in thy majesty ride prosperously because of truth and meekness and righteousness; and thy right hand shall teach thee terrible things.
^5Thine arrows are sharp in the heart of the king’s enemies; whereby the people fall under thee.
^6Thy throne, O God, is for ever and ever: the sceptre of thy kingdom is a right sceptre.
^7Thou lovest righteousness, and hatest wickedness: therefore God, thy God, hath anointed thee with the oil of gladness above thy fellows.
^8All thy garments smell of myrrh, and aloes, and cassia, out of the ivory palaces, whereby they have made thee glad.
^9Kings’ daughters were among thy honourable women: upon thy right hand did stand the queen in gold of Ophir.
^10Hearken, O daughter, and consider, and incline thine ear; forget also thine own people, and thy father’s house;
^11So shall the king greatly desire thy beauty: for he is thy Lord; and worship thou him.
^12And the daughter of Tyre shall be there with a gift; even the rich among the people shall intreat thy favour.
^13The king’s daughter is all glorious within: her clothing is of wrought gold.
^14She shall be brought unto the king in raiment of needlework: the virgins her companions that follow her shall be brought unto thee.
^15With gladness and rejoicing shall they be brought: they shall enter into the king’s palace.
^16Instead of thy fathers shall be thy children, whom thou mayest make princes in all the earth.
^17I will make thy name to be remembered in all generations: therefore shall the people praise thee for ever and ever.

XLVI

^1God is our refuge and strength, a very present help in trouble.
^2Therefore will not we fear, though the earth be removed, and though the mountains be carried into the midst of the sea;
^3Though the waters thereof roar and be troubled, though the mountains shake with the swelling thereof.
Selah.
^4There is a river, the streams whereof shall make glad the city of God, the holy place of the tabernacles of the most High.
^5God is in the midst of her; she shall not be moved: God shall help her, and that right early.
^6The heathen raged, the kingdoms were moved: he uttered his voice, the earth melted.
^7The Lord of hosts is with us; the God of Jacob is our refuge.
Selah.
^8Come, behold the works of the Lord, what desolations he hath made in the earth.
^9He maketh wars to cease unto the end of the earth; he breaketh the bow, and cutteth the spear in sunder; he burneth the chariot in the fire.
^10Be still, and know that I am God: I will be exalted among the heathen, I will be exalted in the earth.
^11The Lord of hosts is with us; the God of Jacob is our refuge.
Selah.

XLVII

^1O clap your hands, all ye people; shout unto God with the voice of triumph.
^2For the Lord most high is terrible; he is a great King over all the earth.
^3He shall subdue the people under us, and the nations under our feet.
^4He shall choose our inheritance for us, the excellency of Jacob whom he loved.
Selah.
^5God is gone up with a shout, the Lord with the sound of a trumpet.
^6Sing praises to God, sing praises: sing praises unto our King, sing praises.
^7For God is the King of all the earth: sing ye praises with understanding.
^8God reigneth over the heathen: God sitteth upon the throne of his holiness.
^9The princes of the people are gathered together, even the people of the God of Abraham: for the shields of the earth belong unto God: he is greatly exalted.

XLVIII

^1Great is the Lord, and greatly to be praised in the city of our God, in the mountain of his holiness.
^2Beautiful for situation, the joy of the whole earth, is mount Zion, on the sides of the north, the city of the great King.
^3God is known in her palaces for a refuge.
^4For, lo, the kings were assembled, they passed by together.
^5They saw it, and so they marvelled; they were troubled, and hasted away.
^6Fear took hold upon them there, and pain, as of a woman in travail.
^7Thou breakest the ships of Tarshish with an east wind.
^8As we have heard, so have we seen in the city of the Lord of hosts, in the city of our God: God will establish it for ever.
Selah.
^9We have thought of thy lovingkindness, O God, in the midst of thy temple.
^10According to thy name, O God, so is thy praise unto the ends of the earth: thy right hand is full of righteousness.
^11Let mount Zion rejoice, let the daughters of Judah be glad, because of thy judgments.
^12Walk about Zion, and go round about her: tell the towers thereof.
^13Mark ye well her bulwarks, consider her palaces; that ye may tell it to the generation following.
^14For this God is our God for ever and ever: he will be our guide even unto death.

XLIX

^1Hear this, all ye people; give ear, all ye inhabitants of the world:
^2Both low and high, rich and poor, together.
^3My mouth shall speak of wisdom; and the meditation of my heart shall be of understanding.
^4I will incline mine ear to a parable: I will open my dark saying upon the harp.
^5Wherefore should I fear in the days of evil, when the iniquity of my heels shall compass me about?
^6They that trust in their wealth, and boast themselves in the multitude of their riches;
^7None of them can by any means redeem his brother, nor give to God a ransom for him:
^8(For the redemption of their soul is precious, and it ceaseth for ever:)
^9That he should still live for ever, and not see corruption.
^10For he seeth that wise men die, likewise the fool and the brutish person perish, and leave their wealth to others.
^11Their inward thought is, that their houses shall continue for ever, and their dwelling places to all generations; they call their lands after their own names.
^12Nevertheless man being in honour abideth not: he is like the beasts that perish.
^13This their way is their folly: yet their posterity approve their sayings.
Selah.
^14Like sheep they are laid in the grave; death shall feed on them; and the upright shall have dominion over them in the morning; and their beauty shall consume in the grave from their dwelling.
^15But God will redeem my soul from the power of the grave: for he shall receive me.
Selah.
^16Be not thou afraid when one is made rich, when the glory of his house is increased;
^17For when he dieth he shall carry nothing away: his glory shall not descend after him.
^18Though while he lived he blessed his soul: and men will praise thee, when thou doest well to thyself.
^19He shall go to the generation of his fathers; they shall never see light.
^20Man that is in honour, and understandeth not, is like the beasts that perish.

L

^1The mighty God, even the Lord, hath spoken, and called the earth from the rising of the sun unto the going down thereof.
^2Out of Zion, the perfection of beauty, God hath shined.
^3Our God shall come, and shall not keep silence: a fire shall devour before him, and it shall be very tempestuous round about him.
^4He shall call to the heavens from above, and to the earth, that he may judge his people.
^5Gather my saints together unto me; those that have made a covenant with me by sacrifice.
^6And the heavens shall declare his righteousness: for God is judge himself.
Selah.
^7Hear, O my people, and I will speak; O Israel, and I will testify against thee: I am God, even thy God.
^8I will not reprove thee for thy sacrifices or thy burnt offerings, to have been continually before me.
^9I will take no bullock out of thy house, nor he goats out of thy folds.
^10For every beast of the forest is mine, and the cattle upon a thousand hills.
^11I know all the fowls of the mountains: and the wild beasts of the field are mine.
^12If I were hungry, I would not tell thee: for the world is mine, and the fulness thereof.
^13Will I eat the flesh of bulls, or drink the blood of goats?
^14Offer unto God thanksgiving; and pay thy vows unto the most High:
^15And call upon me in the day of trouble: I will deliver thee, and thou shalt glorify me.
^16But unto the wicked God saith, What hast thou to do to declare my statutes, or that thou shouldest take my covenant in thy mouth?
^17Seeing thou hatest instruction, and casteth my words behind thee.
^18When thou sawest a thief, then thou consentedst with him, and hast been partaker with adulterers.
^19Thou givest thy mouth to evil, and thy tongue frameth deceit.
^20Thou sittest and speakest against thy brother; thou slanderest thine own mother’s son.
^21These things hast thou done, and I kept silence; thou thoughtest that I was altogether such an one as thyself: but I will reprove thee, and set them in order before thine eyes.
^22Now consider this, ye that forget God, lest I tear you in pieces, and there be none to deliver.
^23Whoso offereth praise glorifieth me: and to him that ordereth his conversation aright will I shew the salvation of God.

LI

^1Have mercy upon me, O God, according to thy lovingkindness: according unto the multitude of thy tender mercies blot out my transgressions.
^2Wash me throughly from mine iniquity, and cleanse me from my sin.
^3For I acknowledge my transgressions: and my sin is ever before me.
^4Against thee, thee only, have I sinned, and done this evil in thy sight: that thou mightest be justified when thou speakest, and be clear when thou judgest.
^5Behold, I was shapen in iniquity; and in sin did my mother conceive me.
^6Behold, thou desirest truth in the inward parts: and in the hidden part thou shalt make me to know wisdom.
^7Purge me with hyssop, and I shall be clean: wash me, and I shall be whiter than snow.
^8Make me to hear joy and gladness; that the bones which thou hast broken may rejoice.
^9Hide thy face from my sins, and blot out all mine iniquities.
^10Create in me a clean heart, O God; and renew a right spirit within me.
^11Cast me not away from thy presence; and take not thy holy spirit from me.
^12Restore unto me the joy of thy salvation; and uphold me with thy free spirit.
^13Then will I teach transgressors thy ways; and sinners shall be converted unto thee.
^14Deliver me from bloodguiltiness, O God, thou God of my salvation: and my tongue shall sing aloud of thy righteousness.
^15O Lord, open thou my lips; and my mouth shall shew forth thy praise.
^16For thou desirest not sacrifice; else would I give it: thou delightest not in burnt offering.
^17The sacrifices of God are a broken spirit: a broken and a contrite heart, O God, thou wilt not despise.
^18Do good in thy good pleasure unto Zion: build thou the walls of Jerusalem.
^19Then shalt thou be pleased with the sacrifices of righteousness, with burnt offering and whole burnt offering: then shall they offer bullocks upon thine altar.

LII

^1Why boastest thou thyself in mischief, O mighty man? the goodness of God endureth continually.
^2The tongue deviseth mischiefs; like a sharp razor, working deceitfully.
^3Thou lovest evil more than good; and lying rather than to speak righteousness.
Selah.
^4Thou lovest all devouring words, O thou deceitful tongue.
^5God shall likewise destroy thee for ever, he shall take thee away, and pluck thee out of thy dwelling place, and root thee out of the land of the living.
Selah.
^6The righteous also shall see, and fear, and shall laugh at him:
^7Lo, this is the man that made not God his strength; but trusted in the abundance of his riches, and strengthened himself in his wickedness.
^8But I am like a green olive tree in the house of God: I trust in the mercy of God for ever and ever.
^9I will praise thee for ever, because thou hast done it: and I will wait on thy name; for it is good before thy saints.

LIII

^1The fool hath said in his heart, There is no God. Corrupt are they, and have done abominable iniquity: there is none that doeth good.
^2God looked down from heaven upon the children of men, to see if there were any that did understand, that did seek God.
^3Every one of them is gone back: they are altogether become filthy; there is none that doeth good, no, not one.
^4Have the workers of iniquity no knowledge? who eat up my people as they eat bread: they have not called upon God.
^5There were they in great fear, where no fear was: for God hath scattered the bones of him that encampeth against thee: thou hast put them to shame, because God hath despised them.
^6Oh that the salvation of Israel were come out of Zion! When God bringeth back the captivity of his people, Jacob shall rejoice, and Israel shall be glad.

LIV

^1Save me, O God, by thy name, and judge me by thy strength.
^2Hear my prayer, O God; give ear to the words of my mouth.
^3For strangers are risen up against me, and oppressors seek after my soul: they have not set God before them.
Selah.
^4Behold, God is mine helper: the Lord is with them that uphold my soul.
^5He shall reward evil unto mine enemies: cut them off in thy truth.
^6I will freely sacrifice unto thee: I will praise thy name, O Lord; for it is good.
^7For he hath delivered me out of all trouble: and mine eye hath seen his desire upon mine enemies.

LV

^1Give ear to my prayer, O God; and hide not thyself from my supplication.
^2Attend unto me, and hear me: I mourn in my complaint, and make a noise;
^3Because of the voice of the enemy, because of the oppression of the wicked: for they cast iniquity upon me, and in wrath they hate me.
^4My heart is sore pained within me: and the terrors of death are fallen upon me.
^5Fearfulness and trembling are come upon me, and horror hath overwhelmed me.
^6And I said, Oh that I had wings like a dove! for then would I fly away, and be at rest.
^7Lo, then would I wander far off, and remain in the wilderness.
Selah.
^8I would hasten my escape from the windy storm and tempest.
^9Destroy, O Lord, and divide their tongues: for I have seen violence and strife in the city.
^10Day and night they go about it upon the walls thereof: mischief also and sorrow are in the midst of it.
^11Wickedness is in the midst thereof: deceit and guile depart not from her streets.
^12For it was not an enemy that reproached me; then I could have borne it: neither was it he that hated me that did magnify himself against me; then I would have hid myself from him:
^13But it was thou, a man mine equal, my guide, and mine acquaintance.
^14We took sweet counsel together, and walked unto the house of God in company.
^15Let death seize upon them, and let them go down quick into hell: for wickedness is in their dwellings, and among them.
^16As for me, I will call upon God; and the Lord shall save me.
^17Evening, and morning, and at noon, will I pray, and cry aloud: and he shall hear my voice.
^18He hath delivered my soul in peace from the battle that was against me: for there were many with me.
^19God shall hear, and afflict them, even he that abideth of old. Selah. Because they have no changes, therefore they fear not God.
^20He hath put forth his hands against such as be at peace with him: he hath broken his covenant.
^21The words of his mouth were smoother than butter, but war was in his heart: his words were softer than oil, yet were they drawn swords.
^22Cast thy burden upon the Lord, and he shall sustain thee: he shall never suffer the righteous to be moved.
^23But thou, O God, shalt bring them down into the pit of destruction: bloody and deceitful men shall not live out half their days; but I will trust in thee.

LVI

^1Be merciful unto me, O God: for man would swallow me up; he fighting daily oppresseth me.
^2Mine enemies would daily swallow me up: for they be many that fight against me, O thou most High.
^3What time I am afraid, I will trust in thee.
^4In God I will praise his word, in God I have put my trust; I will not fear what flesh can do unto me.
^5Every day they wrest my words: all their thoughts are against me for evil.
^6They gather themselves together, they hide themselves, they mark my steps, when they wait for my soul.
^7Shall they escape by iniquity? in thine anger cast down the people, O God.
^8Thou tellest my wanderings: put thou my tears into thy bottle: are they not in thy book?
^9When I cry unto thee, then shall mine enemies turn back: this I know; for God is for me.
^10In God will I praise his word: in the Lord will I praise his word.
^11In God have I put my trust: I will not be afraid what man can do unto me.
^12Thy vows are upon me, O God: I will render praises unto thee.
^13For thou hast delivered my soul from death: wilt not thou deliver my feet from falling, that I may walk before God in the light of the living?

LVII

^1Be merciful unto me, O God, be merciful unto me: for my soul trusteth in thee: yea, in the shadow of thy wings will I make my refuge, until these calamities be overpast.
^2I will cry unto God most high; unto God that performeth all things for me.
^3He shall send from heaven, and save me from the reproach of him that would swallow me up. Selah. God shall send forth his mercy and his truth.
^4My soul is among lions: and I lie even among them that are set on fire, even the sons of men, whose teeth are spears and arrows, and their tongue a sharp sword.
^5Be thou exalted, O God, above the heavens; let thy glory be above all the earth.
^6They have prepared a net for my steps; my soul is bowed down: they have digged a pit before me, into the midst whereof they are fallen themselves.
Selah.
^7My heart is fixed, O God, my heart is fixed: I will sing and give praise.
^8Awake up, my glory; awake, psaltery and harp: I myself will awake early.
^9I will praise thee, O Lord, among the people: I will sing unto thee among the nations.
^10For thy mercy is great unto the heavens, and thy truth unto the clouds.
^11Be thou exalted, O God, above the heavens: let thy glory be above all the earth.

LVIII

^1Do ye indeed speak righteousness, O congregation? do ye judge uprightly, O ye sons of men?
^2Yea, in heart ye work wickedness; ye weigh the violence of your hands in the earth.
^3The wicked are estranged from the womb: they go astray as soon as they be born, speaking lies.
^4Their poison is like the poison of a serpent: they are like the deaf adder that stoppeth her ear;
^5Which will not hearken to the voice of charmers, charming never so wisely.
^6Break their teeth, O God, in their mouth: break out the great teeth of the young lions, O Lord.
^7Let them melt away as waters which run continually: when he bendeth his bow to shoot his arrows, let them be as cut in pieces.
^8As a snail which melteth, let every one of them pass away: like the untimely birth of a woman, that they may not see the sun.
^9Before your pots can feel the thorns, he shall take them away as with a whirlwind, both living, and in his wrath.
^10The righteous shall rejoice when he seeth the vengeance: he shall wash his feet in the blood of the wicked.
^11So that a man shall say, Verily there is a reward for the righteous: verily he is a God that judgeth in the earth.

LIX

^1Deliver me from mine enemies, O my God: defend me from them that rise up against me.
^2Deliver me from the workers of iniquity, and save me from bloody men.
^3For, lo, they lie in wait for my soul: the mighty are gathered against me; not for my transgression, nor for my sin, O Lord.
^4They run and prepare themselves without my fault: awake to help me, and behold.
^5Thou therefore, O Lord God of hosts, the God of Israel, awake to visit all the heathen: be not merciful to any wicked transgressors.
Selah.
^6They return at evening: they make a noise like a dog, and go round about the city.
^7Behold, they belch out with their mouth: swords are in their lips: for who, say they, doth hear?
^8But thou, O Lord, shalt laugh at them; thou shalt have all the heathen in derision.
^9Because of his strength will I wait upon thee: for God is my defence.
^10The God of my mercy shall prevent me: God shall let me see my desire upon mine enemies.
^11Slay them not, lest my people forget: scatter them by thy power; and bring them down, O Lord our shield.
^12For the sin of their mouth and the words of their lips let them even be taken in their pride: and for cursing and lying which they speak.
^13Consume them in wrath, consume them, that they may not be: and let them know that God ruleth in Jacob unto the ends of the earth.
Selah.
^14And at evening let them return; and let them make a noise like a dog, and go round about the city.
^15Let them wander up and down for meat, and grudge if they be not satisfied.
^16But I will sing of thy power; yea, I will sing aloud of thy mercy in the morning: for thou hast been my defence and refuge in the day of my trouble.
^17Unto thee, O my strength, will I sing: for God is my defence, and the God of my mercy.

LX

^1O God, thou hast cast us off, thou hast scattered us, thou hast been displeased; O turn thyself to us again.
^2Thou hast made the earth to tremble; thou hast broken it: heal the breaches thereof; for it shaketh.
^3Thou hast shewed thy people hard things: thou hast made us to drink the wine of astonishment.
^4Thou hast given a banner to them that fear thee, that it may be displayed because of the truth.
Selah.
^5That thy beloved may be delivered; save with thy right hand, and hear me.
^6God hath spoken in his holiness; I will rejoice, I will divide Shechem, and mete out the valley of Succoth.
^7Gilead is mine, and Manasseh is mine; Ephraim also is the strength of mine head; Judah is my lawgiver;
^8Moab is my washpot; over Edom will I cast out my shoe: Philistia, triumph thou because of me.
^9Who will bring me into the strong city? who will lead me into Edom?
^10Wilt not thou, O God, which hadst cast us off? and thou, O God, which didst not go out with our armies?
^11Give us help from trouble: for vain is the help of man.
^12Through God we shall do valiantly: for he it is that shall tread down our enemies.

LXI

^1Hear my cry, O God; attend unto my prayer.
^2From the end of the earth will I cry unto thee, when my heart is overwhelmed: lead me to the rock that is higher than I.
^3For thou hast been a shelter for me, and a strong tower from the enemy.
^4I will abide in thy tabernacle for ever: I will trust in the covert of thy wings.
Selah.
^5For thou, O God, hast heard my vows: thou hast given me the heritage of those that fear thy name.
^6Thou wilt prolong the king’s life: and his years as many generations.
^7He shall abide before God for ever: O prepare mercy and truth, which may preserve him.
^8So will I sing praise unto thy name for ever, that I may daily perform my vows.

LXII

^1Truly my soul waiteth upon God: from him cometh my salvation.
^2He only is my rock and my salvation; he is my defence; I shall not be greatly moved.
^3How long will ye imagine mischief against a man? ye shall be slain all of you: as a bowing wall shall ye be, and as a tottering fence.
^4They only consult to cast him down from his excellency: they delight in lies: they bless with their mouth, but they curse inwardly.
Selah.
^5My soul, wait thou only upon God; for my expectation is from him.
^6He only is my rock and my salvation: he is my defence; I shall not be moved.
^7In God is my salvation and my glory: the rock of my strength, and my refuge, is in God.
^8Trust in him at all times; ye people, pour out your heart before him: God is a refuge for us.
Selah.
^9Surely men of low degree are vanity, and men of high degree are a lie: to be laid in the balance, they are altogether lighter than vanity.
^10Trust not in oppression, and become not vain in robbery: if riches increase, set not your heart upon them.
^11God hath spoken once; twice have I heard this; that power belongeth unto God.
^12Also unto thee, O Lord, belongeth mercy: for thou renderest to every man according to his work.

LXIII

^1O God, thou art my God; early will I seek thee: my soul thirsteth for thee, my flesh longeth for thee in a dry and thirsty land, where no water is;
^2To see thy power and thy glory, so as I have seen thee in the sanctuary.
^3Because thy lovingkindness is better than life, my lips shall praise thee.
^4Thus will I bless thee while I live: I will lift up my hands in thy name.
^5My soul shall be satisfied as with marrow and fatness; and my mouth shall praise thee with joyful lips:
^6When I remember thee upon my bed, and meditate on thee in the night watches.
^7Because thou hast been my help, therefore in the shadow of thy wings will I rejoice.
^8My soul followeth hard after thee: thy right hand upholdeth me.
^9But those that seek my soul, to destroy it, shall go into the lower parts of the earth.
^10They shall fall by the sword: they shall be a portion for foxes.
^11But the king shall rejoice in God; every one that sweareth by him shall glory: but the mouth of them that speak lies shall be stopped.

LXIV

^1Hear my voice, O God, in my prayer: preserve my life from fear of the enemy.
^2Hide me from the secret counsel of the wicked; from the insurrection of the workers of iniquity:
^3Who whet their tongue like a sword, and bend their bows to shoot their arrows, even bitter words:
^4That they may shoot in secret at the perfect: suddenly do they shoot at him, and fear not.
^5They encourage themselves in an evil matter: they commune of laying snares privily; they say, Who shall see them?
^6They search out iniquities; they accomplish a diligent search: both the inward thought of every one of them, and the heart, is deep.
^7But God shall shoot at them with an arrow; suddenly shall they be wounded.
^8So they shall make their own tongue to fall upon themselves: all that see them shall flee away.
^9And all men shall fear, and shall declare the work of God; for they shall wisely consider of his doing.
^10The righteous shall be glad in the Lord, and shall trust in him; and all the upright in heart shall glory.

LXV

^1Praise waiteth for thee, O God, in Sion: and unto thee shall the vow be performed.
^2O thou that hearest prayer, unto thee shall all flesh come.
^3Iniquities prevail against me: as for our transgressions, thou shalt purge them away.
^4Blessed is the man whom thou choosest, and causest to approach unto thee, that he may dwell in thy courts: we shall be satisfied with the goodness of thy house, even of thy holy temple.
^5By terrible things in righteousness wilt thou answer us, O God of our salvation; who art the confidence of all the ends of the earth, and of them that are afar off upon the sea:
^6Which by his strength setteth fast the mountains; being girded with power:
^7Which stilleth the noise of the seas, the noise of their waves, and the tumult of the people.
^8They also that dwell in the uttermost parts are afraid at thy tokens: thou makest the outgoings of the morning and evening to rejoice.
^9Thou visitest the earth, and waterest it: thou greatly enrichest it with the river of God, which is full of water: thou preparest them corn, when thou hast so provided for it.
^10Thou waterest the ridges thereof abundantly: thou settlest the furrows thereof: thou makest it soft with showers: thou blessest the springing thereof.
^11Thou crownest the year with thy goodness; and thy paths drop fatness.
^12They drop upon the pastures of the wilderness: and the little hills rejoice on every side.
^13The pastures are clothed with flocks; the valleys also are covered over with corn; they shout for joy, they also sing.

LXVI

^1Make a joyful noise unto God, all ye lands:
^2Sing forth the honour of his name: make his praise glorious.
^3Say unto God, How terrible art thou in thy works! through the greatness of thy power shall thine enemies submit themselves unto thee.
^4All the earth shall worship thee, and shall sing unto thee; they shall sing to thy name.
Selah.
^5Come and see the works of God: he is terrible in his doing toward the children of men.
^6He turned the sea into dry land: they went through the flood on foot: there did we rejoice in him.
^7He ruleth by his power for ever; his eyes behold the nations: let not the rebellious exalt themselves.
Selah.
^8O bless our God, ye people, and make the voice of his praise to be heard:
^9Which holdeth our soul in life, and suffereth not our feet to be moved.
^10For thou, O God, hast proved us: thou hast tried us, as silver is tried.
^11Thou broughtest us into the net; thou laidst affliction upon our loins.
^12Thou hast caused men to ride over our heads; we went through fire and through water: but thou broughtest us out into a wealthy place.
^13I will go into thy house with burnt offerings: I will pay thee my vows,
^14Which my lips have uttered, and my mouth hath spoken, when I was in trouble.
^15I will offer unto thee burnt sacrifices of fatlings, with the incense of rams; I will offer bullocks with goats.
Selah.
^16Come and hear, all ye that fear God, and I will declare what he hath done for my soul.
^17I cried unto him with my mouth, and he was extolled with my tongue.
^18If I regard iniquity in my heart, the Lord will not hear me:
^19But verily God hath heard me; he hath attended to the voice of my prayer.
^20Blessed be God, which hath not turned away my prayer, nor his mercy from me.

LXVII

^1God be merciful unto us, and bless us; and cause his face to shine upon us;
Selah.
^2That thy way may be known upon earth, thy saving health among all nations.
^3Let the people praise thee, O God; let all the people praise thee.
^4O let the nations be glad and sing for joy: for thou shalt judge the people righteously, and govern the nations upon earth.
Selah.
^5Let the people praise thee, O God; let all the people praise thee.
^6Then shall the earth yield her increase; and God, even our own God, shall bless us.
^7God shall bless us; and all the ends of the earth shall fear him.

LXVIII

^1Let God arise, let his enemies be scattered: let them also that hate him flee before him.
^2As smoke is driven away, so drive them away: as wax melteth before the fire, so let the wicked perish at the presence of God.
^3But let the righteous be glad; let them rejoice before God: yea, let them exceedingly rejoice.
^4Sing unto God, sing praises to his name: extol him that rideth upon the heavens by his name Jah, and rejoice before him.
^5A father of the fatherless, and a judge of the widows, is God in his holy habitation.
^6God setteth the solitary in families: he bringeth out those which are bound with chains: but the rebellious dwell in a dry land.
^7O God, when thou wentest forth before thy people, when thou didst march through the wilderness; Selah:
^8The earth shook, the heavens also dropped at the presence of God: even Sinai itself was moved at the presence of God, the God of Israel.
^9Thou, O God, didst send a plentiful rain, whereby thou didst confirm thine inheritance, when it was weary.
^10Thy congregation hath dwelt therein: thou, O God, hast prepared of thy goodness for the poor.
^11The Lord gave the word: great was the company of those that published it.
^12Kings of armies did flee apace: and she that tarried at home divided the spoil.
^13Though ye have lien among the pots, yet shall ye be as the wings of a dove covered with silver, and her feathers with yellow gold.
^14When the Almighty scattered kings in it, it was white as snow in Salmon.
^15The hill of God is as the hill of Bashan; an high hill as the hill of Bashan.
^16Why leap ye, ye high hills? this is the hill which God desireth to dwell in; yea, the Lord will dwell in it for ever.
^17The chariots of God are twenty thousand, even thousands of angels: the Lord is among them, as in Sinai, in the holy place.
^18Thou hast ascended on high, thou hast led captivity captive: thou hast received gifts for men; yea, for the rebellious also, that the Lord God might dwell among them.
^19Blessed be the Lord, who daily loadeth us with benefits, even the God of our salvation.
Selah.
^20He that is our God is the God of salvation; and unto God the Lord belong the issues from death.
^21But God shall wound the head of his enemies, and the hairy scalp of such an one as goeth on still in his trespasses.
^22The Lord said, I will bring again from Bashan, I will bring my people again from the depths of the sea:
^23That thy foot may be dipped in the blood of thine enemies, and the tongue of thy dogs in the same.
^24They have seen thy goings, O God; even the goings of my God, my King, in the sanctuary.
^25The singers went before, the players on instruments followed after; among them were the damsels playing with timbrels.
^26Bless ye God in the congregations, even the Lord, from the fountain of Israel.
^27There is little Benjamin with their ruler, the princes of Judah and their council, the princes of Zebulun, and the princes of Naphtali.
^28Thy God hath commanded thy strength: strengthen, O God, that which thou hast wrought for us.
^29Because of thy temple at Jerusalem shall kings bring presents unto thee.
^30Rebuke the company of spearmen, the multitude of the bulls, with the calves of the people, till every one submit himself with pieces of silver: scatter thou the people that delight in war.
^31Princes shall come out of Egypt; Ethiopia shall soon stretch out her hands unto God.
^32Sing unto God, ye kingdoms of the earth; O sing praises unto the Lord; Selah:
^33To him that rideth upon the heavens of heavens, which were of old; lo, he doth send out his voice, and that a mighty voice.
^34Ascribe ye strength unto God: his excellency is over Israel, and his strength is in the clouds.
^35O God, thou art terrible out of thy holy places: the God of Israel is he that giveth strength and power unto his people. Blessed be God.

LXIX

^1Save me, O God; for the waters are come in unto my soul.
^2I sink in deep mire, where there is no standing: I am come into deep waters, where the floods overflow me.
^3I am weary of my crying: my throat is dried: mine eyes fail while I wait for my God.
^4They that hate me without a cause are more than the hairs of mine head: they that would destroy me, being mine enemies wrongfully, are mighty: then I restored that which I took not away.
^5O God, thou knowest my foolishness; and my sins are not hid from thee.
^6Let not them that wait on thee, O Lord God of hosts, be ashamed for my sake: let not those that seek thee be confounded for my sake, O God of Israel.
^7Because for thy sake I have borne reproach; shame hath covered my face.
^8I am become a stranger unto my brethren, and an alien unto my mother’s children.
^9For the zeal of thine house hath eaten me up; and the reproaches of them that reproached thee are fallen upon me.
^10When I wept, and chastened my soul with fasting, that was to my reproach.
^11I made sackcloth also my garment; and I became a proverb to them.
^12They that sit in the gate speak against me; and I was the song of the drunkards.
^13But as for me, my prayer is unto thee, O Lord, in an acceptable time: O God, in the multitude of thy mercy hear me, in the truth of thy salvation.
^14Deliver me out of the mire, and let me not sink: let me be delivered from them that hate me, and out of the deep waters.
^15Let not the waterflood overflow me, neither let the deep swallow me up, and let not the pit shut her mouth upon me.
^16Hear me, O Lord; for thy lovingkindness is good: turn unto me according to the multitude of thy tender mercies.
^17And hide not thy face from thy servant; for I am in trouble: hear me speedily.
^18Draw nigh unto my soul, and redeem it: deliver me because of mine enemies.
^19Thou hast known my reproach, and my shame, and my dishonour: mine adversaries are all before thee.
^20Reproach hath broken my heart; and I am full of heaviness: and I looked for some to take pity, but there was none; and for comforters, but I found none.
^21They gave me also gall for my meat; and in my thirst they gave me vinegar to drink.
^22Let their table become a snare before them: and that which should have been for their welfare, let it become a trap.
^23Let their eyes be darkened, that they see not; and make their loins continually to shake.
^24Pour out thine indignation upon them, and let thy wrathful anger take hold of them.
^25Let their habitation be desolate; and let none dwell in their tents.
^26For they persecute him whom thou hast smitten; and they talk to the grief of those whom thou hast wounded.
^27Add iniquity unto their iniquity: and let them not come into thy righteousness.
^28Let them be blotted out of the book of the living, and not be written with the righteous.
^29But I am poor and sorrowful: let thy salvation, O God, set me up on high.
^30I will praise the name of God with a song, and will magnify him with thanksgiving.
^31This also shall please the Lord better than an ox or bullock that hath horns and hoofs.
^32The humble shall see this, and be glad: and your heart shall live that seek God.
^33For the Lord heareth the poor, and despiseth not his prisoners.
^34Let the heaven and earth praise him, the seas, and every thing that moveth therein.
^35For God will save Zion, and will build the cities of Judah: that they may dwell there, and have it in possession.
^36The seed also of his servants shall inherit it: and they that love his name shall dwell therein.

LXX

^1Make haste, O God, to deliver me; make haste to help me, O Lord.
^2Let them be ashamed and confounded that seek after my soul: let them be turned backward, and put to confusion, that desire my hurt.
^3Let them be turned back for a reward of their shame that say, Aha, aha.
^4Let all those that seek thee rejoice and be glad in thee: and let such as love thy salvation say continually, Let God be magnified.
^5But I am poor and needy: make haste unto me, O God: thou art my help and my deliverer; O Lord, make no tarrying.

LXXI

^1In thee, O Lord, do I put my trust: let me never be put to confusion.
^2Deliver me in thy righteousness, and cause me to escape: incline thine ear unto me, and save me.
^3Be thou my strong habitation, whereunto I may continually resort: thou hast given commandment to save me; for thou art my rock and my fortress.
^4Deliver me, O my God, out of the hand of the wicked, out of the hand of the unrighteous and cruel man.
^5For thou art my hope, O Lord God: thou art my trust from my youth.
^6By thee have I been holden up from the womb: thou art he that took me out of my mother’s bowels: my praise shall be continually of thee.
^7I am as a wonder unto many; but thou art my strong refuge.
^8Let my mouth be filled with thy praise and with thy honour all the day.
^9Cast me not off in the time of old age; forsake me not when my strength faileth.
^10For mine enemies speak against me; and they that lay wait for my soul take counsel together,
^11Saying, God hath forsaken him: persecute and take him; for there is none to deliver him.
^12O God, be not far from me: O my God, make haste for my help.
^13Let them be confounded and consumed that are adversaries to my soul; let them be covered with reproach and dishonour that seek my hurt.
^14But I will hope continually, and will yet praise thee more and more.
^15My mouth shall shew forth thy righteousness and thy salvation all the day; for I know not the numbers thereof.
^16I will go in the strength of the Lord God: I will make mention of thy righteousness, even of thine only.
^17O God, thou hast taught me from my youth: and hitherto have I declared thy wondrous works.
^18Now also when I am old and greyheaded, O God, forsake me not; until I have shewed thy strength unto this generation, and thy power to every one that is to come.
^19Thy righteousness also, O God, is very high, who hast done great things: O God, who is like unto thee!
^20Thou, which hast shewed me great and sore troubles, shalt quicken me again, and shalt bring me up again from the depths of the earth.
^21Thou shalt increase my greatness, and comfort me on every side.
^22I will also praise thee with the psaltery, even thy truth, O my God: unto thee will I sing with the harp, O thou Holy One of Israel.
^23My lips shall greatly rejoice when I sing unto thee; and my soul, which thou hast redeemed.
^24My tongue also shall talk of thy righteousness all the day long: for they are confounded, for they are brought unto shame, that seek my hurt.

LXXII

^1Give the king thy judgments, O God, and thy righteousness unto the king’s son.
^2He shall judge thy people with righteousness, and thy poor with judgment.
^3The mountains shall bring peace to the people, and the little hills, by righteousness.
^4He shall judge the poor of the people, he shall save the children of the needy, and shall break in pieces the oppressor.
^5They shall fear thee as long as the sun and moon endure, throughout all generations.
^6He shall come down like rain upon the mown grass: as showers that water the earth.
^7In his days shall the righteous flourish; and abundance of peace so long as the moon endureth.
^8He shall have dominion also from sea to sea, and from the river unto the ends of the earth.
^9They that dwell in the wilderness shall bow before him; and his enemies shall lick the dust.
^10The kings of Tarshish and of the isles shall bring presents: the kings of Sheba and Seba shall offer gifts.
^11Yea, all kings shall fall down before him: all nations shall serve him.
^12For he shall deliver the needy when he crieth; the poor also, and him that hath no helper.
^13He shall spare the poor and needy, and shall save the souls of the needy.
^14He shall redeem their soul from deceit and violence: and precious shall their blood be in his sight.
^15And he shall live, and to him shall be given of the gold of Sheba: prayer also shall be made for him continually; and daily shall he be praised.
^16There shall be an handful of corn in the earth upon the top of the mountains; the fruit thereof shall shake like Lebanon: and they of the city shall flourish like grass of the earth.
^17His name shall endure for ever: his name shall be continued as long as the sun: and men shall be blessed in him: all nations shall call him blessed.
^18Blessed be the Lord God, the God of Israel, who only doeth wondrous things.
^19And blessed be his glorious name for ever: and let the whole earth be filled with his glory; Amen, and Amen.
^20The prayers of David the son of Jesse are ended.

The Third Book of

Psalms

LXXIII

^1Truly God is good to Israel, even to such as are of a clean heart.
^2But as for me, my feet were almost gone; my steps had well nigh slipped.
^3For I was envious at the foolish, when I saw the prosperity of the wicked.
^4For there are no bands in their death: but their strength is firm.
^5They are not in trouble as other men; neither are they plagued like other men.
^6Therefore pride compasseth them about as a chain; violence covereth them as a garment.
^7Their eyes stand out with fatness: they have more than heart could wish.
^8They are corrupt, and speak wickedly concerning oppression: they speak loftily.
^9They set their mouth against the heavens, and their tongue walketh through the earth.
^10Therefore his people return hither: and waters of a full cup are wrung out to them.
^11And they say, How doth God know? and is there knowledge in the most High?
^12Behold, these are the ungodly, who prosper in the world; they increase in riches.
^13Verily I have cleansed my heart in vain, and washed my hands in innocency.
^14For all the day long have I been plagued, and chastened every morning.
^15If I say, I will speak thus; behold, I should offend against the generation of thy children.
^16When I thought to know this, it was too painful for me;
^17Until I went into the sanctuary of God; then understood I their end.
^18Surely thou didst set them in slippery places: thou castedst them down into destruction.
^19How are they brought into desolation, as in a moment! they are utterly consumed with terrors.
^20As a dream when one awaketh; so, O Lord, when thou awakest, thou shalt despise their image.
^21Thus my heart was grieved, and I was pricked in my reins.
^22So foolish was I, and ignorant: I was as a beast before thee.
^23Nevertheless I am continually with thee: thou hast holden me by my right hand.
^24Thou shalt guide me with thy counsel, and afterward receive me to glory.
^25Whom have I in heaven but thee? and there is none upon earth that I desire beside thee.
^26My flesh and my heart faileth: but God is the strength of my heart, and my portion for ever.
^27For, lo, they that are far from thee shall perish: thou hast destroyed all them that go a whoring from thee.
^28But it is good for me to draw near to God: I have put my trust in the Lord God, that I may declare all thy works.

LXXIV

^1O God, why hast thou cast us off for ever? why doth thine anger smoke against the sheep of thy pasture?
^2Remember thy congregation, which thou hast purchased of old; the rod of thine inheritance, which thou hast redeemed; this mount Zion, wherein thou hast dwelt.
^3Lift up thy feet unto the perpetual desolations; even all that the enemy hath done wickedly in the sanctuary.
^4Thine enemies roar in the midst of thy congregations; they set up their ensigns for signs.
^5A man was famous according as he had lifted up axes upon the thick trees.
^6But now they break down the carved work thereof at once with axes and hammers.
^7They have cast fire into thy sanctuary, they have defiled by casting down the dwelling place of thy name to the ground.
^8They said in their hearts, Let us destroy them together: they have burned up all the synagogues of God in the land.
^9We see not our signs: there is no more any prophet: neither is there among us any that knoweth how long.
^10O God, how long shall the adversary reproach? shall the enemy blaspheme thy name for ever?
^11Why withdrawest thou thy hand, even thy right hand? pluck it out of thy bosom.
^12For God is my King of old, working salvation in the midst of the earth.
^13Thou didst divide the sea by thy strength: thou brakest the heads of the dragons in the waters.
^14Thou brakest the heads of leviathan in pieces, and gavest him to be meat to the people inhabiting the wilderness.
^15Thou didst cleave the fountain and the flood: thou driedst up mighty rivers.
^16The day is thine, the night also is thine: thou hast prepared the light and the sun.
^17Thou hast set all the borders of the earth: thou hast made summer and winter.
^18Remember this, that the enemy hath reproached, O Lord, and that the foolish people have blasphemed thy name.
^19O deliver not the soul of thy turtledove unto the multitude of the wicked: forget not the congregation of thy poor for ever.
^20Have respect unto the covenant: for the dark places of the earth are full of the habitations of cruelty.
^21O let not the oppressed return ashamed: let the poor and needy praise thy name.
^22Arise, O God, plead thine own cause: remember how the foolish man reproacheth thee daily.
^23Forget not the voice of thine enemies: the tumult of those that rise up against thee increaseth continually.

LXXV

^1Unto thee, O God, do we give thanks, unto thee do we give thanks: for that thy name is near thy wondrous works declare.
^2When I shall receive the congregation I will judge uprightly.
^3The earth and all the inhabitants thereof are dissolved: I bear up the pillars of it.
Selah.
^4I said unto the fools, Deal not foolishly: and to the wicked, Lift not up the horn:
^5Lift not up your horn on high: speak not with a stiff neck.
^6For promotion cometh neither from the east, nor from the west, nor from the south.
^7But God is the judge: he putteth down one, and setteth up another.
^8For in the hand of the Lord there is a cup, and the wine is red; it is full of mixture; and he poureth out of the same: but the dregs thereof, all the wicked of the earth shall wring them out, and drink them.
^9But I will declare for ever; I will sing praises to the God of Jacob.
^10All the horns of the wicked also will I cut off; but the horns of the righteous shall be exalted.

LXXVI

^1In Judah is God known: his name is great in Israel.
^2In Salem also is his tabernacle, and his dwelling place in Zion.
^3There brake he the arrows of the bow, the shield, and the sword, and the battle.
Selah.
^4Thou art more glorious and excellent than the mountains of prey.
^5The stouthearted are spoiled, they have slept their sleep: and none of the men of might have found their hands.
^6At thy rebuke, O God of Jacob, both the chariot and horse are cast into a dead sleep.
^7Thou, even thou, art to be feared: and who may stand in thy sight when once thou art angry?
^8Thou didst cause judgment to be heard from heaven; the earth feared, and was still,
^9When God arose to judgment, to save all the meek of the earth.
Selah.
^10Surely the wrath of man shall praise thee: the remainder of wrath shalt thou restrain.
^11Vow, and pay unto the Lord your God: let all that be round about him bring presents unto him that ought to be feared.
^12He shall cut off the spirit of princes: he is terrible to the kings of the earth.

LXXVII

^1I cried unto God with my voice, even unto God with my voice; and he gave ear unto me.
^2In the day of my trouble I sought the Lord: my sore ran in the night, and ceased not: my soul refused to be comforted.
^3I remembered God, and was troubled: I complained, and my spirit was overwhelmed.
Selah.
^4Thou holdest mine eyes waking: I am so troubled that I cannot speak.
^5I have considered the days of old, the years of ancient times.
^6I call to remembrance my song in the night: I commune with mine own heart: and my spirit made diligent search.
^7Will the Lord cast off for ever? and will he be favourable no more?
^8Is his mercy clean gone for ever? doth his promise fail for evermore?
^9Hath God forgotten to be gracious? hath he in anger shut up his tender mercies?
Selah.
^10And I said, This is my infirmity: but I will remember the years of the right hand of the most High.
^11I will remember the works of the Lord: surely I will remember thy wonders of old.
^12I will meditate also of all thy work, and talk of thy doings.
^13Thy way, O God, is in the sanctuary: who is so great a God as our God?
^14Thou art the God that doest wonders: thou hast declared thy strength among the people.
^15Thou hast with thine arm redeemed thy people, the sons of Jacob and Joseph.
Selah.
^16The waters saw thee, O God, the waters saw thee; they were afraid: the depths also were troubled.
^17The clouds poured out water: the skies sent out a sound: thine arrows also went abroad.
^18The voice of thy thunder was in the heaven: the lightnings lightened the world: the earth trembled and shook.
^19Thy way is in the sea, and thy path in the great waters, and thy footsteps are not known.
^20Thou leddest thy people like a flock by the hand of Moses and Aaron.

LXXVIII

^1Give ear, O my people, to my law: incline your ears to the words of my mouth.
^2I will open my mouth in a parable: I will utter dark sayings of old:
^3Which we have heard and known, and our fathers have told us.
^4We will not hide them from their children, shewing to the generation to come the praises of the Lord, and his strength, and his wonderful works that he hath done.
^5For he established a testimony in Jacob, and appointed a law in Israel, which he commanded our fathers, that they should make them known to their children:
^6That the generation to come might know them, even the children which should be born; who should arise and declare them to their children:
^7That they might set their hope in God, and not forget the works of God, but keep his commandments:
^8And might not be as their fathers, a stubborn and rebellious generation; a generation that set not their heart aright, and whose spirit was not stedfast with God.
^9The children of Ephraim, being armed, and carrying bows, turned back in the day of battle.
^10They kept not the covenant of God, and refused to walk in his law;
^11And forgat his works, and his wonders that he had shewed them.
^12Marvellous things did he in the sight of their fathers, in the land of Egypt, in the field of Zoan.
^13He divided the sea, and caused them to pass through; and he made the waters to stand as an heap.
^14In the daytime also he led them with a cloud, and all the night with a light of fire.
^15He clave the rocks in the wilderness, and gave them drink as out of the great depths.
^16He brought streams also out of the rock, and caused waters to run down like rivers.
^17And they sinned yet more against him by provoking the most High in the wilderness.
^18And they tempted God in their heart by asking meat for their lust.
^19Yea, they spake against God; they said, Can God furnish a table in the wilderness?
^20Behold, he smote the rock, that the waters gushed out, and the streams overflowed; can he give bread also? can he provide flesh for his people?
^21Therefore the Lord heard this, and was wroth: so a fire was kindled against Jacob, and anger also came up against Israel;
^22Because they believed not in God, and trusted not in his salvation:
^23Though he had commanded the clouds from above, and opened the doors of heaven,
^24And had rained down manna upon them to eat, and had given them of the corn of heaven.
^25Man did eat angels’ food: he sent them meat to the full.
^26He caused an east wind to blow in the heaven: and by his power he brought in the south wind.
^27He rained flesh also upon them as dust, and feathered fowls like as the sand of the sea:
^28And he let it fall in the midst of their camp, round about their habitations.
^29So they did eat, and were well filled: for he gave them their own desire;
^30They were not estranged from their lust. But while their meat was yet in their mouths,
^31The wrath of God came upon them, and slew the fattest of them, and smote down the chosen men of Israel.
^32For all this they sinned still, and believed not for his wondrous works.
^33Therefore their days did he consume in vanity, and their years in trouble.
^34When he slew them, then they sought him: and they returned and enquired early after God.
^35And they remembered that God was their rock, and the high God their redeemer.
^36Nevertheless they did flatter him with their mouth, and they lied unto him with their tongues.
^37For their heart was not right with him, neither were they stedfast in his covenant.
^38But he, being full of compassion, forgave their iniquity, and destroyed them not: yea, many a time turned he his anger away, and did not stir up all his wrath.
^39For he remembered that they were but flesh; a wind that passeth away, and cometh not again.
^40How oft did they provoke him in the wilderness, and grieve him in the desert!
^41Yea, they turned back and tempted God, and limited the Holy One of Israel.
^42They remembered not his hand, nor the day when he delivered them from the enemy.
^43How he had wrought his signs in Egypt, and his wonders in the field of Zoan.
^44And had turned their rivers into blood; and their floods, that they could not drink.
^45He sent divers sorts of flies among them, which devoured them; and frogs, which destroyed them.
^46He gave also their increase unto the caterpiller, and their labour unto the locust.
^47He destroyed their vines with hail, and their sycomore trees with frost.
^48He gave up their cattle also to the hail, and their flocks to hot thunderbolts.
^49He cast upon them the fierceness of his anger, wrath, and indignation, and trouble, by sending evil angels among them.
^50He made a way to his anger; he spared not their soul from death, but gave their life over to the pestilence;
^51And smote all the firstborn in Egypt; the chief of their strength in the tabernacles of Ham:
^52But made his own people to go forth like sheep, and guided them in the wilderness like a flock.
^53And he led them on safely, so that they feared not: but the sea overwhelmed their enemies.
^54And he brought them to the border of his sanctuary, even to this mountain, which his right hand had purchased.
^55He cast out the heathen also before them, and divided them an inheritance by line, and made the tribes of Israel to dwell in their tents.
^56Yet they tempted and provoked the most high God, and kept not his testimonies:
^57But turned back, and dealt unfaithfully like their fathers: they were turned aside like a deceitful bow.
^58For they provoked him to anger with their high places, and moved him to jealousy with their graven images.
^59When God heard this, he was wroth, and greatly abhorred Israel:
^60So that he forsook the tabernacle of Shiloh, the tent which he placed among men;
^61And delivered his strength into captivity, and his glory into the enemy’s hand.
^62He gave his people over also unto the sword; and was wroth with his inheritance.
^63The fire consumed their young men; and their maidens were not given to marriage.
^64Their priests fell by the sword; and their widows made no lamentation.
^65Then the Lord awaked as one out of sleep, and like a mighty man that shouteth by reason of wine.
^66And he smote his enemies in the hinder parts: he put them to a perpetual reproach.
^67Moreover he refused the tabernacle of Joseph, and chose not the tribe of Ephraim:
^68But chose the tribe of Judah, the mount Zion which he loved.
^69And he built his sanctuary like high palaces, like the earth which he hath established for ever.
^70He chose David also his servant, and took him from the sheepfolds:
^71From following the ewes great with young he brought him to feed Jacob his people, and Israel his inheritance.
^72So he fed them according to the integrity of his heart; and guided them by the skilfulness of his hands.

LXXIX

^1O god, the heathen are come into thine inheritance; thy holy temple have they defiled; they have laid Jerusalem on heaps.
^2The dead bodies of thy servants have they given to be meat unto the fowls of the heaven, the flesh of thy saints unto the beasts of the earth.
^3Their blood have they shed like water round about Jerusalem; and there was none to bury them.
^4We are become a reproach to our neighbours, a scorn and derision to them that are round about us.
^5How long, Lord? wilt thou be angry for ever? shall thy jealousy burn like fire?
^6Pour out thy wrath upon the heathen that have not known thee, and upon the kingdoms that have not called upon thy name.
^7For they have devoured Jacob, and laid waste his dwelling place.
^8O remember not against us former iniquities: let thy tender mercies speedily prevent us: for we are brought very low.
^9Help us, O God of our salvation, for the glory of thy name: and deliver us, and purge away our sins, for thy name’s sake.
^10Wherefore should the heathen say, Where is their God? let him be known among the heathen in our sight by the revenging of the blood of thy servants which is shed.
^11Let the sighing of the prisoner come before thee; according to the greatness of thy power preserve thou those that are appointed to die;
^12And render unto our neighbours sevenfold into their bosom their reproach, wherewith they have reproached thee, O Lord.
^13So we thy people and sheep of thy pasture will give thee thanks for ever: we will shew forth thy praise to all generations.

LXXX

^1Give ear, O Shepherd of Israel, thou that leadest Joseph like a flock; thou that dwellest between the cherubims, shine forth.
^2Before Ephraim and Benjamin and Manasseh stir up thy strength, and come and save us.
^3Turn us again, O God, and cause thy face to shine; and we shall be saved.
^4O Lord God of hosts, how long wilt thou be angry against the prayer of thy people?
^5Thou feedest them with the bread of tears; and givest them tears to drink in great measure.
^6Thou makest us a strife unto our neighbours: and our enemies laugh among themselves.
^7Turn us again, O God of hosts, and cause thy face to shine; and we shall be saved.
^8Thou hast brought a vine out of Egypt: thou hast cast out the heathen, and planted it.
^9Thou preparedst room before it, and didst cause it to take deep root, and it filled the land.
^10The hills were covered with the shadow of it, and the boughs thereof were like the goodly cedars.
^11She sent out her boughs unto the sea, and her branches unto the river.
^12Why hast thou then broken down her hedges, so that all they which pass by the way do pluck her?
^13The boar out of the wood doth waste it, and the wild beast of the field doth devour it.
^14Return, we beseech thee, O God of hosts: look down from heaven, and behold, and visit this vine;
^15And the vineyard which thy right hand hath planted, and the branch that thou madest strong for thyself.
^16It is burned with fire, it is cut down: they perish at the rebuke of thy countenance.
^17Let thy hand be upon the man of thy right hand, upon the son of man whom thou madest strong for thyself.
^18So will not we go back from thee: quicken us, and we will call upon thy name.
^19Turn us again, O Lord God of hosts, cause thy face to shine; and we shall be saved.

LXXXI

^1Sing aloud unto God our strength: make a joyful noise unto the God of Jacob.
^2Take a psalm, and bring hither the timbrel, the pleasant harp with the psaltery.
^3Blow up the trumpet in the new moon, in the time appointed, on our solemn feast day.
^4For this was a statute for Israel, and a law of the God of Jacob.
^5This he ordained in Joseph for a testimony, when he went out through the land of Egypt: where I heard a language that I understood not.
^6I removed his shoulder from the burden: his hands were delivered from the pots.
^7Thou calledst in trouble, and I delivered thee; I answered thee in the secret place of thunder: I proved thee at the waters of Meribah.
Selah.
^8Hear, O my people, and I will testify unto thee: O Israel, if thou wilt hearken unto me;
^9There shall no strange god be in thee; neither shalt thou worship any strange god.
^10I am the Lord thy God, which brought thee out of the land of Egypt: open thy mouth wide, and I will fill it.
^11But my people would not hearken to my voice; and Israel would none of me.
^12So I gave them up unto their own hearts’ lust: and they walked in their own counsels.
^13Oh that my people had hearkened unto me, and Israel had walked in my ways!
^14I should soon have subdued their enemies, and turned my hand against their adversaries.
^15The haters of the Lord should have submitted themselves unto him: but their time should have endured for ever.
^16He should have fed them also with the finest of the wheat: and with honey out of the rock should I have satisfied thee.

LXXXII

^1God standeth in the congregation of the mighty; he judgeth among the gods.
^2How long will ye judge unjustly, and accept the persons of the wicked?
Selah.
^3Defend the poor and fatherless: do justice to the afflicted and needy.
^4Deliver the poor and needy: rid them out of the hand of the wicked.
^5They know not, neither will they understand; they walk on in darkness: all the foundations of the earth are out of course.
^6I have said, Ye are gods; and all of you are children of the most High.
^7But ye shall die like men, and fall like one of the princes.
^8Arise, O God, judge the earth: for thou shalt inherit all nations.

LXXXIII

^1Keep not thou silence, O God: hold not thy peace, and be not still, O God.
^2For, lo, thine enemies make a tumult: and they that hate thee have lifted up the head.
^3They have taken crafty counsel against thy people, and consulted against thy hidden ones.
^4They have said, Come, and let us cut them off from being a nation; that the name of Israel may be no more in remembrance.
^5For they have consulted together with one consent: they are confederate against thee:
^6The tabernacles of Edom, and the Ishmaelites; of Moab, and the Hagarenes;
^7Gebal, and Ammon, and Amalek; the Philistines with the inhabitants of Tyre;
^8Assur also is joined with them: they have holpen the children of Lot.
Selah.
^9Do unto them as unto the Midianites; as to Sisera, as to Jabin, at the brook of Kison:
^10Which perished at Endor: they became as dung for the earth.
^11Make their nobles like Oreb, and like Zeeb: yea, all their princes as Zebah, and as Zalmunna:
^12Who said, Let us take to ourselves the houses of God in possession.
^13O my God, make them like a wheel; as the stubble before the wind.
^14As the fire burneth a wood, and as the flame setteth the mountains on fire;
^15So persecute them with thy tempest, and make them afraid with thy storm.
^16Fill their faces with shame; that they may seek thy name, O Lord.
^17Let them be confounded and troubled for ever; yea, let them be put to shame, and perish:
^18That men may know that thou, whose name alone is Jehovah, art the most high over all the earth.

LXXXIV

^1How amiable are thy tabernacles, O Lord of hosts!
^2My soul longeth, yea, even fainteth for the courts of the Lord: my heart and my flesh crieth out for the living God.
^3Yea, the sparrow hath found an house, and the swallow a nest for herself, where she may lay her young, even thine altars, O Lord of hosts, my King, and my God.
^4Blessed are they that dwell in thy house: they will be still praising thee.
Selah.
^5Blessed is the man whose strength is in thee; in whose heart are the ways of them.
^6Who passing through the valley of Baca make it a well; the rain also filleth the pools.
^7They go from strength to strength, every one of them in Zion appeareth before God.
^8O Lord God of hosts, hear my prayer: give ear, O God of Jacob.
Selah.
^9Behold, O God our shield, and look upon the face of thine anointed.
^10For a day in thy courts is better than a thousand. I had rather be a doorkeeper in the house of my God, than to dwell in the tents of wickedness.
^11For the Lord God is a sun and shield: the Lord will give grace and glory: no good thing will he withhold from them that walk uprightly.
^12O Lord of hosts, blessed is the man that trusteth in thee.

LXXXV

^1Lord, thou hast been favourable unto thy land: thou hast brought back the captivity of Jacob.
^2Thou hast forgiven the iniquity of thy people, thou hast covered all their sin.
Selah.
^3Thou hast taken away all thy wrath: thou hast turned thyself from the fierceness of thine anger.
^4Turn us, O God of our salvation, and cause thine anger toward us to cease.
^5Wilt thou be angry with us for ever? wilt thou draw out thine anger to all generations?
^6Wilt thou not revive us again: that thy people may rejoice in thee?
^7Shew us thy mercy, O Lord, and grant us thy salvation.
^8I will hear what God the Lord will speak: for he will speak peace unto his people, and to his saints: but let them not turn again to folly.
^9Surely his salvation is nigh them that fear him; that glory may dwell in our land.
^10Mercy and truth are met together; righteousness and peace have kissed each other.
^11Truth shall spring out of the earth; and righteousness shall look down from heaven.
^12Yea, the Lord shall give that which is good; and our land shall yield her increase.
^13Righteousness shall go before him; and shall set us in the way of his steps.

LXXXVI

^1Bow down thine ear, O Lord, hear me: for I am poor and needy.
^2Preserve my soul; for I am holy: O thou my God, save thy servant that trusteth in thee.
^3Be merciful unto me, O Lord: for I cry unto thee daily.
^4Rejoice the soul of thy servant: for unto thee, O Lord, do I lift up my soul.
^5For thou, Lord, art good, and ready to forgive; and plenteous in mercy unto all them that call upon thee.
^6Give ear, O Lord, unto my prayer; and attend to the voice of my supplications.
^7In the day of my trouble I will call upon thee: for thou wilt answer me.
^8Among the gods there is none like unto thee, O Lord; neither are there any works like unto thy works.
^9All nations whom thou hast made shall come and worship before thee, O Lord; and shall glorify thy name.
^10For thou art great, and doest wondrous things: thou art God alone.
^11Teach me thy way, O Lord; I will walk in thy truth: unite my heart to fear thy name.
^12I will praise thee, O Lord my God, with all my heart: and I will glorify thy name for evermore.
^13For great is thy mercy toward me: and thou hast delivered my soul from the lowest hell.
^14O God, the proud are risen against me, and the assemblies of violent men have sought after my soul; and have not set thee before them.
^15But thou, O Lord, art a God full of compassion, and gracious, longsuffering, and plenteous in mercy and truth.
^16O turn unto me, and have mercy upon me; give thy strength unto thy servant, and save the son of thine handmaid.
^17Shew me a token for good; that they which hate me may see it, and be ashamed: because thou, Lord, hast holpen me, and comforted me.

LXXXVII

^1His foundation is in the holy mountains.
^2The Lord loveth the gates of Zion more than all the dwellings of Jacob.
^3Glorious things are spoken of thee, O city of God.
Selah.
^4I will make mention of Rahab and Babylon to them that know me: behold Philistia, and Tyre, with Ethiopia; this man was born there.
^5And of Zion it shall be said, This and that man was born in her: and the highest himself shall establish her.
^6The Lord shall count, when he writeth up the people, that this man was born there.
Selah.
^7As well the singers as the players on instruments shall be there: all my springs are in thee.

LXXXVIII

^1O lord God of my salvation, I have cried day and night before thee:
^2Let my prayer come before thee: incline thine ear unto my cry;
^3For my soul is full of troubles: and my life draweth nigh unto the grave.
^4I am counted with them that go down into the pit: I am as a man that hath no strength:
^5Free among the dead, like the slain that lie in the grave, whom thou rememberest no more: and they are cut off from thy hand.
^6Thou hast laid me in the lowest pit, in darkness, in the deeps.
^7Thy wrath lieth hard upon me, and thou hast afflicted me with all thy waves.
Selah.
^8Thou hast put away mine acquaintance far from me; thou hast made me an abomination unto them: I am shut up, and I cannot come forth.
^9Mine eye mourneth by reason of affliction: Lord, I have called daily upon thee, I have stretched out my hands unto thee.
^10Wilt thou shew wonders to the dead? shall the dead arise and praise thee?
Selah.
^11Shall thy lovingkindness be declared in the grave? or thy faithfulness in destruction?
^12Shall thy wonders be known in the dark? and thy righteousness in the land of forgetfulness?
^13But unto thee have I cried, O Lord; and in the morning shall my prayer prevent thee.
^14Lord, why castest thou off my soul? why hidest thou thy face from me?
^15I am afflicted and ready to die from my youth up: while I suffer thy terrors I am distracted.
^16Thy fierce wrath goeth over me; thy terrors have cut me off.
^17They came round about me daily like water; they compassed me about together.
^18Lover and friend hast thou put far from me, and mine acquaintance into darkness.

LXXXIX

^1I will sing of the mercies of the Lord for ever: with my mouth will I make known thy faithfulness to all generations.
^2For I have said, Mercy shall be built up for ever: thy faithfulness shalt thou establish in the very heavens.
^3I have made a covenant with my chosen, I have sworn unto David my servant,
^4Thy seed will I establish for ever, and build up thy throne to all generations.
Selah.
^5And the heavens shall praise thy wonders, O Lord: thy faithfulness also in the congregation of the saints.
^6For who in the heaven can be compared unto the Lord? who among the sons of the mighty can be likened unto the Lord?
^7God is greatly to be feared in the assembly of the saints, and to be had in reverence of all them that are about him.
^8O Lord God of hosts, who is a strong Lord like unto thee? or to thy faithfulness round about thee?
^9Thou rulest the raging of the sea: when the waves thereof arise, thou stillest them.
^10Thou hast broken Rahab in pieces, as one that is slain; thou hast scattered thine enemies with thy strong arm.
^11The heavens are thine, the earth also is thine: as for the world and the fulness thereof, thou hast founded them.
^12The north and the south thou hast created them: Tabor and Hermon shall rejoice in thy name.
^13Thou hast a mighty arm: strong is thy hand, and high is thy right hand.
^14Justice and judgment are the habitation of thy throne: mercy and truth shall go before thy face.
^15Blessed is the people that know the joyful sound: they shall walk, O Lord, in the light of thy countenance.
^16In thy name shall they rejoice all the day: and in thy righteousness shall they be exalted.
^17For thou art the glory of their strength: and in thy favour our horn shall be exalted.
^18For the Lord is our defence; and the Holy One of Israel is our king.
^19Then thou spakest in vision to thy holy one, and saidst, I have laid help upon one that is mighty; I have exalted one chosen out of the people.
^20I have found David my servant; with my holy oil have I anointed him:
^21With whom my hand shall be established: mine arm also shall strengthen him.
^22The enemy shall not exact upon him; nor the son of wickedness afflict him.
^23And I will beat down his foes before his face, and plague them that hate him.
^24But my faithfulness and my mercy shall be with him: and in my name shall his horn be exalted.
^25I will set his hand also in the sea, and his right hand in the rivers.
^26He shall cry unto me, Thou art my father, my God, and the rock of my salvation.
^27Also I will make him my firstborn, higher than the kings of the earth.
^28My mercy will I keep for him for evermore, and my covenant shall stand fast with him.
^29His seed also will I make to endure for ever, and his throne as the days of heaven.
^30If his children forsake my law, and walk not in my judgments;
^31If they break my statutes, and keep not my commandments;
^32Then will I visit their transgression with the rod, and their iniquity with stripes.
^33Nevertheless my lovingkindness will I not utterly take from him, nor suffer my faithfulness to fail.
^34My covenant will I not break, nor alter the thing that is gone out of my lips.
^35Once have I sworn by my holiness that I will not lie unto David.
^36His seed shall endure for ever, and his throne as the sun before me.
^37It shall be established for ever as the moon, and as a faithful witness in heaven.
Selah.
^38But thou hast cast off and abhorred, thou hast been wroth with thine anointed.
^39Thou hast made void the covenant of thy servant: thou hast profaned his crown by casting it to the ground.
^40Thou hast broken down all his hedges; thou hast brought his strong holds to ruin.
^41All that pass by the way spoil him: he is a reproach to his neighbours.
^42Thou hast set up the right hand of his adversaries; thou hast made all his enemies to rejoice.
^43Thou hast also turned the edge of his sword, and hast not made him to stand in the battle.
^44Thou hast made his glory to cease, and cast his throne down to the ground.
^45The days of his youth hast thou shortened: thou hast covered him with shame.
Selah.
^46How long, Lord? wilt thou hide thyself for ever? shall thy wrath burn like fire?
^47Remember how short my time is: wherefore hast thou made all men in vain?
^48What man is he that liveth, and shall not see death? shall he deliver his soul from the hand of the grave?
Selah.
^49Lord, where are thy former lovingkindnesses, which thou swarest unto David in thy truth?
^50Remember, Lord, the reproach of thy servants; how I do bear in my bosom the reproach of all the mighty people;
^51Wherewith thine enemies have reproached, O Lord; wherewith they have reproached the footsteps of thine anointed.
^52Blessed be the Lord for evermore. Amen, and Amen.

The Fifth Book of

Psalms

CVII

^1O give thanks unto the Lord, for he is good: for his mercy endureth for ever.
^2Let the redeemed of the Lord say so, whom he hath redeemed from the hand of the enemy;
^3And gathered them out of the lands, from the east, and from the west, from the north, and from the south.
^4They wandered in the wilderness in a solitary way; they found no city to dwell in.
^5Hungry and thirsty, their soul fainted in them.
^6Then they cried unto the Lord in their trouble, and he delivered them out of their distresses.
^7And he led them forth by the right way, that they might go to a city of habitation.
^8Oh that men would praise the Lord for his goodness, and for his wonderful works to the children of men!
^9For he satisfieth the longing soul, and filleth the hungry soul with goodness.
^10Such as sit in darkness and in the shadow of death, being bound in affliction and iron;
^11Because they rebelled against the words of God, and contemned the counsel of the most High:
^12Therefore he brought down their heart with labour; they fell down, and there was none to help.
^13Then they cried unto the Lord in their trouble, and he saved them out of their distresses.
^14He brought them out of darkness and the shadow of death, and brake their bands in sunder.
^15Oh that men would praise the Lord for his goodness, and for his wonderful works to the children of men!
^16For he hath broken the gates of brass, and cut the bars of iron in sunder.
^17Fools because of their transgression, and because of their iniquities, are afflicted.
^18Their soul abhorreth all manner of meat; and they draw near unto the gates of death.
^19Then they cry unto the Lord in their trouble, and he saveth them out of their distresses.
^20He sent his word, and healed them, and delivered them from their destructions.
^21Oh that men would praise the Lord for his goodness, and for his wonderful works to the children of men!
^22And let them sacrifice the sacrifices of thanksgiving, and declare his works with rejoicing.
^23They that go down to the sea in ships, that do business in great waters;
^24These see the works of the Lord, and his wonders in the deep.
^25For he commandeth, and raiseth the stormy wind, which lifteth up the waves thereof.
^26They mount up to the heaven, they go down again to the depths: their soul is melted because of trouble.
^27They reel to and fro, and stagger like a drunken man, and are at their wit’s end.
^28Then they cry unto the Lord in their trouble, and he bringeth them out of their distresses.
^29He maketh the storm a calm, so that the waves thereof are still.
^30Then are they glad because they be quiet; so he bringeth them unto their desired haven.
^31Oh that men would praise the Lord for his goodness, and for his wonderful works to the children of men!
^32Let them exalt him also in the congregation of the people, and praise him in the assembly of the elders.
^33He turneth rivers into a wilderness, and the watersprings into dry ground;
^34A fruitful land into barrenness, for the wickedness of them that dwell therein.
^35He turneth the wilderness into a standing water, and dry ground into watersprings.
^36And there he maketh the hungry to dwell, that they may prepare a city for habitation;
^37And sow the fields, and plant vineyards, which may yield fruits of increase.
^38He blesseth them also, so that they are multiplied greatly; and suffereth not their cattle to decrease.
^39Again, they are minished and brought low through oppression, affliction, and sorrow.
^40He poureth contempt upon princes, and causeth them to wander in the wilderness, where there is no way.
^41Yet setteth he the poor on high from affliction, and maketh him families like a flock.
^42The righteous shall see it, and rejoice: and all iniquity shall stop her mouth.
^43Whoso is wise, and will observe these things, even they shall understand the lovingkindness of the Lord.

CVIII

^1O god, my heart is fixed; I will sing and give praise, even with my glory.
^2Awake, psaltery and harp: I myself will awake early.
^3I will praise thee, O Lord, among the people: and I will sing praises unto thee among the nations.
^4For thy mercy is great above the heavens: and thy truth reacheth unto the clouds.
^5Be thou exalted, O God, above the heavens: and thy glory above all the earth;
^6That thy beloved may be delivered: save with thy right hand, and answer me.
^7God hath spoken in his holiness; I will rejoice, I will divide Shechem, and mete out the valley of Succoth.
^8Gilead is mine; Manasseh is mine; Ephraim also is the strength of mine head; Judah is my lawgiver;
^9Moab is my washpot; over Edom will I cast out my shoe; over Philistia will I triumph.
^10Who will bring me into the strong city? who will lead me into Edom?
^11Wilt not thou, O God, who hast cast us off? and wilt not thou, O God, go forth with our hosts?
^12Give us help from trouble: for vain is the help of man.
^13Through God we shall do valiantly: for he it is that shall tread down our enemies.

CIX

^1Hold not thy peace, O God of my praise;
^2For the mouth of the wicked and the mouth of the deceitful are opened against me: they have spoken against me with a lying tongue.
^3They compassed me about also with words of hatred; and fought against me without a cause.
^4For my love they are my adversaries: but I give myself unto prayer.
^5And they have rewarded me evil for good, and hatred for my love.
^6Set thou a wicked man over him: and let Satan stand at his right hand.
^7When he shall be judged, let him be condemned: and let his prayer become sin.
^8Let his days be few; and let another take his office.
^9Let his children be fatherless, and his wife a widow.
^10Let his children be continually vagabonds, and beg: let them seek their bread also out of their desolate places.
^11Let the extortioner catch all that he hath; and let the strangers spoil his labour.
^12Let there be none to extend mercy unto him: neither let there be any to favour his fatherless children.
^13Let his posterity be cut off; and in the generation following let their name be blotted out.
^14Let the iniquity of his fathers be remembered with the Lord; and let not the sin of his mother be blotted out.
^15Let them be before the Lord continually, that he may cut off the memory of them from the earth.
^16Because that he remembered not to shew mercy, but persecuted the poor and needy man, that he might even slay the broken in heart.
^17As he loved cursing, so let it come unto him: as he delighted not in blessing, so let it be far from him.
^18As he clothed himself with cursing like as with his garment, so let it come into his bowels like water, and like oil into his bones.
^19Let it be unto him as the garment which covereth him, and for a girdle wherewith he is girded continually.
^20Let this be the reward of mine adversaries from the Lord, and of them that speak evil against my soul.
^21But do thou for me, O God the Lord, for thy name’s sake: because thy mercy is good, deliver thou me.
^22For I am poor and needy, and my heart is wounded within me.
^23I am gone like the shadow when it declineth: I am tossed up and down as the locust.
^24My knees are weak through fasting; and my flesh faileth of fatness.
^25I became also a reproach unto them: when they looked upon me they shaked their heads.
^26Help me, O Lord my God: O save me according to thy mercy:
^27That they may know that this is thy hand; that thou, Lord, hast done it.
^28Let them curse, but bless thou: when they arise, let them be ashamed; but let thy servant rejoice.
^29Let mine adversaries be clothed with shame, and let them cover themselves with their own confusion, as with a mantle.
^30I will greatly praise the Lord with my mouth; yea, I will praise him among the multitude.
^31For he shall stand at the right hand of the poor, to save him from those that condemn his soul.

CX

^1The Lord said unto my Lord, Sit thou at my right hand, until I make thine enemies thy footstool.
^2The Lord shall send the rod of thy strength out of Zion: rule thou in the midst of thine enemies.
^3Thy people shall be willing in the day of thy power, in the beauties of holiness from the womb of the morning: thou hast the dew of thy youth.
^4The Lord hath sworn, and will not repent, Thou art a priest for ever after the order of Melchizedek.
^5The Lord at thy right hand shall strike through kings in the day of his wrath.
^6He shall judge among the heathen, he shall fill the places with the dead bodies; he shall wound the heads over many countries.
^7He shall drink of the brook in the way: therefore shall he lift up the head.

CXI

^1Praise ye the Lord. I will praise the Lord with my whole heart, in the assembly of the upright, and in the congregation.
^2The works of the Lord are great, sought out of all them that have pleasure therein.
^3His work is honourable and glorious: and his righteousness endureth for ever.
^4He hath made his wonderful works to be remembered: the Lord is gracious and full of compassion.
^5He hath given meat unto them that fear him: he will ever be mindful of his covenant.
^6He hath shewed his people the power of his works, that he may give them the heritage of the heathen.
^7The works of his hands are verity and judgment; all his commandments are sure.
^8They stand fast for ever and ever, and are done in truth and uprightness.
^9He sent redemption unto his people: he hath commanded his covenant for ever: holy and reverend is his name.
^10The fear of the Lord is the beginning of wisdom: a good understanding have all they that do his commandments: his praise endureth for ever.

CXII

^1Praise ye the Lord. Blessed is the man that feareth the Lord, that delighteth greatly in his commandments.
^2His seed shall be mighty upon earth: the generation of the upright shall be blessed.
^3Wealth and riches shall be in his house: and his righteousness endureth for ever.
^4Unto the upright there ariseth light in the darkness: he is gracious, and full of compassion, and righteous.
^5A good man sheweth favour, and lendeth: he will guide his affairs with discretion.
^6Surely he shall not be moved for ever: the righteous shall be in everlasting remembrance.
^7He shall not be afraid of evil tidings: his heart is fixed, trusting in the Lord.
^8His heart is established, he shall not be afraid, until he see his desire upon his enemies.
^9He hath dispersed, he hath given to the poor; his righteousness endureth for ever; his horn shall be exalted with honour.
^10The wicked shall see it, and be grieved; he shall gnash with his teeth, and melt away: the desire of the wicked shall perish.

CXIII

^1Praise ye the Lord. Praise, O ye servants of the Lord, praise the name of the Lord.
^2Blessed be the name of the Lord from this time forth and for evermore.
^3From the rising of the sun unto the going down of the same the Lord’s name is to be praised.
^4The Lord is high above all nations, and his glory above the heavens.
^5Who is like unto the Lord our God, who dwelleth on high,
^6Who humbleth himself to behold the things that are in heaven, and in the earth!
^7He raiseth up the poor out of the dust, and lifteth the needy out of the dunghill;
^8That he may set him with princes, even with the princes of his people.
^9He maketh the barren woman to keep house, and to be a joyful mother of children. Praise ye the Lord.

CXIV

^1When Israel went out of Egypt, the house of Jacob from a people of strange language;
^2Judah was his sanctuary, and Israel his dominion.
^3The sea saw it, and fled: Jordan was driven back.
^4The mountains skipped like rams, and the little hills like lambs.
^5What ailed thee, O thou sea, that thou fleddest? thou Jordan, that thou wast driven back?
^6Ye mountains, that ye skipped like rams; and ye little hills, like lambs?
^7Tremble, thou earth, at the presence of the Lord, at the presence of the God of Jacob;
^8Which turned the rock into a standing water, the flint into a fountain of waters.

CXV

^1Not unto us, O Lord, not unto us, but unto thy name give glory, for thy mercy, and for thy truth’s sake.
^2Wherefore should the heathen say, Where is now their God?
^3But our God is in the heavens: he hath done whatsoever he hath pleased.
^4Their idols are silver and gold, the work of men’s hands.
^5They have mouths, but they speak not: eyes have they, but they see not:
^6They have ears, but they hear not: noses have they, but they smell not:
^7They have hands, but they handle not: feet have they, but they walk not: neither speak they through their throat.
^8They that make them are like unto them; so is every one that trusteth in them.
^9O Israel, trust thou in the Lord: he is their help and their shield.
^10O house of Aaron, trust in the Lord: he is their help and their shield.
^11Ye that fear the Lord, trust in the Lord: he is their help and their shield.
^12The Lord hath been mindful of us: he will bless us; he will bless the house of Israel; he will bless the house of Aaron.
^13He will bless them that fear the Lord, both small and great.
^14The Lord shall increase you more and more, you and your children.
^15Ye are blessed of the Lord which made heaven and earth.
^16The heaven, even the heavens, are the Lord’s: but the earth hath he given to the children of men.
^17The dead praise not the Lord, neither any that go down into silence.
^18But we will bless the Lord from this time forth and for evermore. Praise the Lord.

CXVI

^1I love the Lord, because he hath heard my voice and my supplications.
^2Because he hath inclined his ear unto me, therefore will I call upon him as long as I live.
^3The sorrows of death compassed me, and the pains of hell gat hold upon me: I found trouble and sorrow.
^4Then called I upon the name of the Lord; O Lord, I beseech thee, deliver my soul.
^5Gracious is the Lord, and righteous; yea, our God is merciful.
^6The Lord preserveth the simple: I was brought low, and he helped me.
^7Return unto thy rest, O my soul; for the Lord hath dealt bountifully with thee.
^8For thou hast delivered my soul from death, mine eyes from tears, and my feet from falling.
^9I will walk before the Lord in the land of the living.
^10I believed, therefore have I spoken: I was greatly afflicted:
^11I said in my haste, All men are liars.
^12What shall I render unto the Lord for all his benefits toward me?
^13I will take the cup of salvation, and call upon the name of the Lord.
^14I will pay my vows unto the Lord now in the presence of all his people.
^15Precious in the sight of the Lord is the death of his saints.
^16O Lord, truly I am thy servant; I am thy servant, and the son of thine handmaid: thou hast loosed my bonds.
^17I will offer to thee the sacrifice of thanksgiving, and will call upon the name of the Lord.
^18I will pay my vows unto the Lord now in the presence of all his people.
^19In the courts of the Lord’s house, in the midst of thee, O Jerusalem. Praise ye the Lord.

CXVII

^1O praise the Lord, all ye nations: praise him, all ye people.
^2For his merciful kindness is great toward us: and the truth of the Lord endureth for ever. Praise ye the Lord.

CXVIII

^1O give thanks unto the Lord; for he is good: because his mercy endureth for ever.
^2Let Israel now say, that his mercy endureth for ever.
^3Let the house of Aaron now say, that his mercy endureth for ever.
^4Let them now that fear the Lord say, that his mercy endureth for ever.
^5I called upon the Lord in distress: the Lord answered me, and set me in a large place.
^6The Lord is on my side; I will not fear: what can man do unto me?
^7The Lord taketh my part with them that help me: therefore shall I see my desire upon them that hate me.
^8It is better to trust in the Lord than to put confidence in man.
^9It is better to trust in the Lord than to put confidence in princes.
^10All nations compassed me about: but in the name of the Lord will I destroy them.
^11They compassed me about; yea, they compassed me about: but in the name of the Lord I will destroy them.
^12They compassed me about like bees: they are quenched as the fire of thorns: for in the name of the Lord I will destroy them.
^13Thou hast thrust sore at me that I might fall: but the Lord helped me.
^14The Lord is my strength and song, and is become my salvation.
^15The voice of rejoicing and salvation is in the tabernacles of the righteous: the right hand of the Lord doeth valiantly.
^16The right hand of the Lord is exalted: the right hand of the Lord doeth valiantly.
^17I shall not die, but live, and declare the works of the Lord.
^18The Lord hath chastened me sore: but he hath not given me over unto death.
^19Open to me the gates of righteousness: I will go into them, and I will praise the Lord:
^20This gate of the Lord, into which the righteous shall enter.
^21I will praise thee: for thou hast heard me, and art become my salvation.
^22The stone which the builders refused is become the head stone of the corner.
^23This is the Lord’s doing; it is marvellous in our eyes.
^24This is the day which the Lord hath made; we will rejoice and be glad in it.
^25Save now, I beseech thee, O Lord: O Lord, I beseech thee, send now prosperity.
^26Blessed be he that cometh in the name of the Lord: we have blessed you out of the house of the Lord.
^27God is the Lord, which hath shewed us light: bind the sacrifice with cords, even unto the horns of the altar.
^28Thou art my God, and I will praise thee: thou art my God, I will exalt thee.
^29O give thanks unto the Lord; for he is good: for his mercy endureth for ever.

CXIX

^1Blessed are the undefiled in the way, who walk in the law of the Lord.
^2Blessed are they that keep his testimonies, and that seek him with the whole heart.
^3They also do no iniquity: they walk in his ways.
^4Thou hast commanded us to keep thy precepts diligently.
^5O that my ways were directed to keep thy statutes!
^6Then shall I not be ashamed, when I have respect unto all thy commandments.
^7I will praise thee with uprightness of heart, when I shall have learned thy righteous judgments.
^8I will keep thy statutes: O forsake me not utterly.
^9Wherewithal shall a young man cleanse his way? by taking heed thereto according to thy word.
^10With my whole heart have I sought thee: O let me not wander from thy commandments.
^11Thy word have I hid in mine heart, that I might not sin against thee.
^12Blessed art thou, O Lord: teach me thy statutes.
^13With my lips have I declared all the judgments of thy mouth.
^14I have rejoiced in the way of thy testimonies, as much as in all riches.
^15I will meditate in thy precepts, and have respect unto thy ways.
^16I will delight myself in thy statutes: I will not forget thy word.
^17Deal bountifully with thy servant, that I may live, and keep thy word.
^18Open thou mine eyes, that I may behold wondrous things out of thy law.
^19I am a stranger in the earth: hide not thy commandments from me.
^20My soul breaketh for the longing that it hath unto thy judgments at all times.
^21Thou hast rebuked the proud that are cursed, which do err from thy commandments.
^22Remove from me reproach and contempt; for I have kept thy testimonies.
^23Princes also did sit and speak against me: but thy servant did meditate in thy statutes.
^24Thy testimonies also are my delight and my counsellors.
^25My soul cleaveth unto the dust: quicken thou me according to thy word.
^26I have declared my ways, and thou heardest me: teach me thy statutes.
^27Make me to understand the way of thy precepts: so shall I talk of thy wondrous works.
^28My soul melteth for heaviness: strengthen thou me according unto thy word.
^29Remove from me the way of lying: and grant me thy law graciously.
^30I have chosen the way of truth: thy judgments have I laid before me.
^31I have stuck unto thy testimonies: O Lord, put me not to shame.
^32I will run the way of thy commandments, when thou shalt enlarge my heart.
^33Teach me, O Lord, the way of thy statutes; and I shall keep it unto the end.
^34Give me understanding, and I shall keep thy law; yea, I shall observe it with my whole heart.
^35Make me to go in the path of thy commandments; for therein do I delight.
^36Incline my heart unto thy testimonies, and not to covetousness.
^37Turn away mine eyes from beholding vanity; and quicken thou me in thy way.
^38Stablish thy word unto thy servant, who is devoted to thy fear.
^39Turn away my reproach which I fear: for thy judgments are good.
^40Behold, I have longed after thy precepts: quicken me in thy righteousness.
^41Let thy mercies come also unto me, O Lord, even thy salvation, according to thy word.
^42So shall I have wherewith to answer him that reproacheth me: for I trust in thy word.
^43And take not the word of truth utterly out of my mouth; for I have hoped in thy judgments.
^44So shall I keep thy law continually for ever and ever.
^45And I will walk at liberty: for I seek thy precepts.
^46I will speak of thy testimonies also before kings, and will not be ashamed.
^47And I will delight myself in thy commandments, which I have loved.
^48My hands also will I lift up unto thy commandments, which I have loved; and I will meditate in thy statutes.
^49Remember the word unto thy servant, upon which thou hast caused me to hope.
^50This is my comfort in my affliction: for thy word hath quickened me.
^51The proud have had me greatly in derision: yet have I not declined from thy law.
^52I remembered thy judgments of old, O Lord; and have comforted myself.
^53Horror hath taken hold upon me because of the wicked that forsake thy law.
^54Thy statutes have been my songs in the house of my pilgrimage.
^55I have remembered thy name, O Lord, in the night, and have kept thy law.
^56This I had, because I kept thy precepts.
^57Thou art my portion, O Lord: I have said that I would keep thy words.
^58I intreated thy favour with my whole heart: be merciful unto me according to thy word.
^59I thought on my ways, and turned my feet unto thy testimonies.
^60I made haste, and delayed not to keep thy commandments.
^61The bands of the wicked have robbed me: but I have not forgotten thy law.
^62At midnight I will rise to give thanks unto thee because of thy righteous judgments.
^63I am a companion of all them that fear thee, and of them that keep thy precepts.
^64The earth, O Lord, is full of thy mercy: teach me thy statutes.
^65Thou hast dealt well with thy servant, O Lord, according unto thy word.
^66Teach me good judgment and knowledge: for I have believed thy commandments.
^67Before I was afflicted I went astray: but now have I kept thy word.
^68Thou art good, and doest good; teach me thy statutes.
^69The proud have forged a lie against me: but I will keep thy precepts with my whole heart.
^70Their heart is as fat as grease; but I delight in thy law.
^71It is good for me that I have been afflicted; that I might learn thy statutes.
^72The law of thy mouth is better unto me than thousands of gold and silver.
^73Thy hands have made me and fashioned me: give me understanding, that I may learn thy commandments.
^74They that fear thee will be glad when they see me; because I have hoped in thy word.
^75I know, O Lord, that thy judgments are right, and that thou in faithfulness hast afflicted me.
^76Let, I pray thee, thy merciful kindness be for my comfort, according to thy word unto thy servant.
^77Let thy tender mercies come unto me, that I may live: for thy law is my delight.
^78Let the proud be ashamed; for they dealt perversely with me without a cause: but I will meditate in thy precepts.
^79Let those that fear thee turn unto me, and those that have known thy testimonies.
^80Let my heart be sound in thy statutes; that I be not ashamed.
^81My soul fainteth for thy salvation: but I hope in thy word.
^82Mine eyes fail for thy word, saying, When wilt thou comfort me?
^83For I am become like a bottle in the smoke; yet do I not forget thy statutes.
^84How many are the days of thy servant? when wilt thou execute judgment on them that persecute me?
^85The proud have digged pits for me, which are not after thy law.
^86All thy commandments are faithful: they persecute me wrongfully; help thou me.
^87They had almost consumed me upon earth; but I forsook not thy precepts.
^88Quicken me after thy lovingkindness; so shall I keep the testimony of thy mouth.
^89For ever, O Lord, thy word is settled in heaven.
^90Thy faithfulness is unto all generations: thou hast established the earth, and it abideth.
^91They continue this day according to thine ordinances: for all are thy servants.
^92Unless thy law had been my delights, I should then have perished in mine affliction.
^93I will never forget thy precepts: for with them thou hast quickened me.
^94I am thine, save me: for I have sought thy precepts.
^95The wicked have waited for me to destroy me: but I will consider thy testimonies.
^96I have seen an end of all perfection: but thy commandment is exceeding broad.
^97O how I love thy law! it is my meditation all the day.
^98Thou through thy commandments hast made me wiser than mine enemies: for they are ever with me.
^99I have more understanding than all my teachers: for thy testimonies are my meditation.
^100I understand more than the ancients, because I keep thy precepts.
^101I have refrained my feet from every evil way, that I might keep thy word.
^102I have not departed from thy judgments: for thou hast taught me.
^103How sweet are thy words unto my taste! yea, sweeter than honey to my mouth!
^104Through thy precepts I get understanding: therefore I hate every false way.
^105Thy word is a lamp unto my feet, and a light unto my path.
^106I have sworn, and I will perform it, that I will keep thy righteous judgments.
^107I am afflicted very much: quicken me, O Lord, according unto thy word.
^108Accept, I beseech thee, the freewill offerings of my mouth, O Lord, and teach me thy judgments.
^109My soul is continually in my hand: yet do I not forget thy law.
^110The wicked have laid a snare for me: yet I erred not from thy precepts.
^111Thy testimonies have I taken as an heritage for ever: for they are the rejoicing of my heart.
^112I have inclined mine heart to perform thy statutes alway, even unto the end.
^113I hate vain thoughts: but thy law do I love.
^114Thou art my hiding place and my shield: I hope in thy word.
^115Depart from me, ye evildoers: for I will keep the commandments of my God.
^116Uphold me according unto thy word, that I may live: and let me not be ashamed of my hope.
^117Hold thou me up, and I shall be safe: and I will have respect unto thy statutes continually.
^118Thou hast trodden down all them that err from thy statutes: for their deceit is falsehood.
^119Thou puttest away all the wicked of the earth like dross: therefore I love thy testimonies.
^120My flesh trembleth for fear of thee; and I am afraid of thy judgments.
^121I have done judgment and justice: leave me not to mine oppressors.
^122Be surety for thy servant for good: let not the proud oppress me.
^123Mine eyes fail for thy salvation, and for the word of thy righteousness.
^124Deal with thy servant according unto thy mercy, and teach me thy statutes.
^125I am thy servant; give me understanding, that I may know thy testimonies.
^126It is time for thee, Lord, to work: for they have made void thy law.
^127Therefore I love thy commandments above gold; yea, above fine gold.
^128Therefore I esteem all thy precepts concerning all things to be right; and I hate every false way.
^129Thy testimonies are wonderful: therefore doth my soul keep them.
^130The entrance of thy words giveth light; it giveth understanding unto the simple.
^131I opened my mouth, and panted: for I longed for thy commandments.
^132Look thou upon me, and be merciful unto me, as thou usest to do unto those that love thy name.
^133Order my steps in thy word: and let not any iniquity have dominion over me.
^134Deliver me from the oppression of man: so will I keep thy precepts.
^135Make thy face to shine upon thy servant; and teach me thy statutes.
^136Rivers of waters run down mine eyes, because they keep not thy law.
^137Righteous art thou, O Lord, and upright are thy judgments.
^138Thy testimonies that thou hast commanded are righteous and very faithful.
^139My zeal hath consumed me, because mine enemies have forgotten thy words.
^140Thy word is very pure: therefore thy servant loveth it.
^141I am small and despised: yet do not I forget thy precepts.
^142Thy righteousness is an everlasting righteousness, and thy law is the truth.
^143Trouble and anguish have taken hold on me: yet thy commandments are my delights.
^144The righteousness of thy testimonies is everlasting: give me understanding, and I shall live.
^145I cried with my whole heart; hear me, O Lord: I will keep thy statutes.
^146I cried unto thee; save me, and I shall keep thy testimonies.
^147I prevented the dawning of the morning, and cried: I hoped in thy word.
^148Mine eyes prevent the night watches, that I might meditate in thy word.
^149Hear my voice according unto thy lovingkindness: O Lord, quicken me according to thy judgment.
^150They draw nigh that follow after mischief: they are far from thy law.
^151Thou art near, O Lord; and all thy commandments are truth.
^152Concerning thy testimonies, I have known of old that thou hast founded them for ever.
^153Consider mine affliction, and deliver me: for I do not forget thy law.
^154Plead my cause, and deliver me: quicken me according to thy word.
^155Salvation is far from the wicked: for they seek not thy statutes.
^156Great are thy tender mercies, O Lord: quicken me according to thy judgments.
^157Many are my persecutors and mine enemies; yet do I not decline from thy testimonies.
^158I beheld the transgressors, and was grieved; because they kept not thy word.
^159Consider how I love thy precepts: quicken me, O Lord, according to thy lovingkindness.
^160Thy word is true from the beginning: and every one of thy righteous judgments endureth for ever.
^161Princes have persecuted me without a cause: but my heart standeth in awe of thy word.
^162I rejoice at thy word, as one that findeth great spoil.
^163I hate and abhor lying: but thy law do I love.
^164Seven times a day do I praise thee because of thy righteous judgments.
^165Great peace have they which love thy law: and nothing shall offend them.
^166Lord, I have hoped for thy salvation, and done thy commandments.
^167My soul hath kept thy testimonies; and I love them exceedingly.
^168I have kept thy precepts and thy testimonies: for all my ways are before thee.
^169Let my cry come near before thee, O Lord: give me understanding according to thy word.
^170Let my supplication come before thee: deliver me according to thy word.
^171My lips shall utter praise, when thou hast taught me thy statutes.
^172My tongue shall speak of thy word: for all thy commandments are righteousness.
^173Let thine hand help me; for I have chosen thy precepts.
^174I have longed for thy salvation, O Lord; and thy law is my delight.
^175Let my soul live, and it shall praise thee; and let thy judgments help me.
^176I have gone astray like a lost sheep; seek thy servant; for I do not forget thy commandments.

CXX

^1In my distress I cried unto the Lord, and he heard me.
^2Deliver my soul, O Lord, from lying lips, and from a deceitful tongue.
^3What shall be given unto thee? or what shall be done unto thee, thou false tongue?
^4Sharp arrows of the mighty, with coals of juniper.
^5Woe is me, that I sojourn in Mesech, that I dwell in the tents of Kedar!
^6My soul hath long dwelt with him that hateth peace.
^7I am for peace: but when I speak, they are for war.

CXXI

^1I will lift up mine eyes unto the hills, from whence cometh my help.
^2My help cometh from the Lord, which made heaven and earth.
^3He will not suffer thy foot to be moved: he that keepeth thee will not slumber.
^4Behold, he that keepeth Israel shall neither slumber nor sleep.
^5The Lord is thy keeper: the Lord is thy shade upon thy right hand.
^6The sun shall not smite thee by day, nor the moon by night.
^7The Lord shall preserve thee from all evil: he shall preserve thy soul.
^8The Lord shall preserve thy going out and thy coming in from this time forth, and even for evermore.

CXXII

^1I was glad when they said unto me, Let us go into the house of the Lord.
^2Our feet shall stand within thy gates, O Jerusalem.
^3Jerusalem is builded as a city that is compact together:
^4Whither the tribes go up, the tribes of the Lord, unto the testimony of Israel, to give thanks unto the name of the Lord.
^5For there are set thrones of judgment, the thrones of the house of David.
^6Pray for the peace of Jerusalem: they shall prosper that love thee.
^7Peace be within thy walls, and prosperity within thy palaces.
^8For my brethren and companions’ sakes, I will now say, Peace be within thee.
^9Because of the house of the Lord our God I will seek thy good.

CXXIII

^1Unto thee lift I up mine eyes, O thou that dwellest in the heavens.
^2Behold, as the eyes of servants look unto the hand of their masters, and as the eyes of a maiden unto the hand of her mistress; so our eyes wait upon the Lord our God, until that he have mercy upon us.
^3Have mercy upon us, O Lord, have mercy upon us: for we are exceedingly filled with contempt.
^4Our soul is exceedingly filled with the scorning of those that are at ease, and with the contempt of the proud.

CXXIV

^1If it had not been the Lord who was on our side, now may Israel say;
^2If it had not been the Lord who was on our side, when men rose up against us:
^3Then they had swallowed us up quick, when their wrath was kindled against us:
^4Then the waters had overwhelmed us, the stream had gone over our soul:
^5Then the proud waters had gone over our soul.
^6Blessed be the Lord, who hath not given us as a prey to their teeth.
^7Our soul is escaped as a bird out of the snare of the fowlers: the snare is broken, and we are escaped.
^8Our help is in the name of the Lord, who made heaven and earth.

CXXV

^1They that trust in the Lord shall be as mount Zion, which cannot be removed, but abideth for ever.
^2As the mountains are round about Jerusalem, so the Lord is round about his people from henceforth even for ever.
^3For the rod of the wicked shall not rest upon the lot of the righteous; lest the righteous put forth their hands unto iniquity.
^4Do good, O Lord, unto those that be good, and to them that are upright in their hearts.
^5As for such as turn aside unto their crooked ways, the Lord shall lead them forth with the workers of iniquity: but peace shall be upon Israel.

CXXVI

^1When the Lord turned again the captivity of Zion, we were like them that dream.
^2Then was our mouth filled with laughter, and our tongue with singing: then said they among the heathen, The Lord hath done great things for them.
^3The Lord hath done great things for us; whereof we are glad.
^4Turn again our captivity, O Lord, as the streams in the south.
^5They that sow in tears shall reap in joy.
^6He that goeth forth and weepeth, bearing precious seed, shall doubtless come again with rejoicing, bringing his sheaves with him.

CXXVII

^1Except the Lord build the house, they labour in vain that build it: except the Lord keep the city, the watchman waketh but in vain.
^2It is vain for you to rise up early, to sit up late, to eat the bread of sorrows: for so he giveth his beloved sleep.
^3Lo, children are an heritage of the Lord: and the fruit of the womb is his reward.
^4As arrows are in the hand of a mighty man; so are children of the youth.
^5Happy is the man that hath his quiver full of them: they shall not be ashamed, but they shall speak with the enemies in the gate.

CXXVIII

^1Blessed is every one that feareth the Lord; that walketh in his ways.
^2For thou shalt eat the labour of thine hands: happy shalt thou be, and it shall be well with thee.
^3Thy wife shall be as a fruitful vine by the sides of thine house: thy children like olive plants round about thy table.
^4Behold, that thus shall the man be blessed that feareth the Lord.
^5The Lord shall bless thee out of Zion: and thou shalt see the good of Jerusalem all the days of thy life.
^6Yea, thou shalt see thy children’s children, and peace upon Israel.

CXXIX

^1Many a time have they afflicted me from my youth, may Israel now say:
^2Many a time have they afflicted me from my youth: yet they have not prevailed against me.
^3The plowers plowed upon my back: they made long their furrows.
^4The Lord is righteous: he hath cut asunder the cords of the wicked.
^5Let them all be confounded and turned back that hate Zion.
^6Let them be as the grass upon the housetops, which withereth afore it groweth up:
^7Wherewith the mower filleth not his hand; nor he that bindeth sheaves his bosom.
^8Neither do they which go by say, The blessing of the Lord be upon you: we bless you in the name of the Lord.

CXXX

^1Out of the depths have I cried unto thee, O Lord.
^2Lord, hear my voice: let thine ears be attentive to the voice of my supplications.
^3If thou, Lord, shouldest mark iniquities, O Lord, who shall stand?
^4But there is forgiveness with thee, that thou mayest be feared.
^5I wait for the Lord, my soul doth wait, and in his word do I hope.
^6My soul waiteth for the Lord more than they that watch for the morning: I say, more than they that watch for the morning.
^7Let Israel hope in the Lord: for with the Lord there is mercy, and with him is plenteous redemption.
^8And he shall redeem Israel from all his iniquities.

CXXXI

^1Lord, my heart is not haughty, nor mine eyes lofty: neither do I exercise myself in great matters, or in things too high for me.
^2Surely I have behaved and quieted myself, as a child that is weaned of his mother: my soul is even as a weaned child.
^3Let Israel hope in the Lord from henceforth and for ever.

CXXXII

^1Lord, remember David, and all his afflictions:
^2How he sware unto the Lord, and vowed unto the mighty God of Jacob;
^3Surely I will not come into the tabernacle of my house, nor go up into my bed;
^4I will not give sleep to mine eyes, or slumber to mine eyelids,
^5Until I find out a place for the Lord, an habitation for the mighty God of Jacob.
^6Lo, we heard of it at Ephratah: we found it in the fields of the wood.
^7We will go into his tabernacles: we will worship at his footstool.
^8Arise, O Lord, into thy rest; thou, and the ark of thy strength.
^9Let thy priests be clothed with righteousness; and let thy saints shout for joy.
^10For thy servant David’s sake turn not away the face of thine anointed.
^11The Lord hath sworn in truth unto David; he will not turn from it; Of the fruit of thy body will I set upon thy throne.
^12If thy children will keep my covenant and my testimony that I shall teach them, their children shall also sit upon thy throne for evermore.
^13For the Lord hath chosen Zion; he hath desired it for his habitation.
^14This is my rest for ever: here will I dwell; for I have desired it.
^15I will abundantly bless her provision: I will satisfy her poor with bread.
^16I will also clothe her priests with salvation: and her saints shall shout aloud for joy.
^17There will I make the horn of David to bud: I have ordained a lamp for mine anointed.
^18His enemies will I clothe with shame: but upon himself shall his crown flourish.

CXXXIII

^1Behold, how good and how pleasant it is for brethren to dwell together in unity!
^2It is like the precious ointment upon the head, that ran down upon the beard, even Aaron’s beard: that went down to the skirts of his garments;
^3As the dew of Hermon, and as the dew that descended upon the mountains of Zion: for there the Lord commanded the blessing, even life for evermore.

CXXXIV

^1Behold, bless ye the Lord, all ye servants of the Lord, which by night stand in the house of the Lord.
^2Lift up your hands in the sanctuary, and bless the Lord.
^3The Lord that made heaven and earth bless thee out of Zion.

CXXXV

^1Praise ye the Lord. Praise ye the name of the Lord; praise him, O ye servants of the Lord.
^2Ye that stand in the house of the Lord, in the courts of the house of our God.
^3Praise the Lord; for the Lord is good: sing praises unto his name; for it is pleasant.
^4For the Lord hath chosen Jacob unto himself, and Israel for his peculiar treasure.
^5For I know that the Lord is great, and that our Lord is above all gods.
^6Whatsoever the Lord pleased, that did he in heaven, and in earth, in the seas, and all deep places.
^7He causeth the vapours to ascend from the ends of the earth; he maketh lightnings for the rain; he bringeth the wind out of his treasuries.
^8Who smote the firstborn of Egypt, both of man and beast.
^9Who sent tokens and wonders into the midst of thee, O Egypt, upon Pharaoh, and upon all his servants.
^10Who smote great nations, and slew mighty kings;
^11Sihon king of the Amorites, and Og king of Bashan, and all the kingdoms of Canaan:
^12And gave their land for an heritage, an heritage unto Israel his people.
^13Thy name, O Lord, endureth for ever; and thy memorial, O Lord, throughout all generations.
^14For the Lord will judge his people, and he will repent himself concerning his servants.
^15The idols of the heathen are silver and gold, the work of men’s hands.
^16They have mouths, but they speak not; eyes have they, but they see not;
^17They have ears, but they hear not; neither is there any breath in their mouths.
^18They that make them are like unto them: so is every one that trusteth in them.
^19Bless the Lord, O house of Israel: bless the Lord, O house of Aaron:
^20Bless the Lord, O house of Levi: ye that fear the Lord, bless the Lord.
^21Blessed be the Lord out of Zion, which dwelleth at Jerusalem. Praise ye the Lord.

CXXXVI

^1O give thanks unto the Lord; for he is good: for his mercy endureth for ever.
^2O give thanks unto the God of gods: for his mercy endureth for ever.
^3O give thanks to the Lord of lords: for his mercy endureth for ever.
^4To him who alone doeth great wonders: for his mercy endureth for ever.
^5To him that by wisdom made the heavens: for his mercy endureth for ever.
^6To him that stretched out the earth above the waters: for his mercy endureth for ever.
^7To him that made great lights: for his mercy endureth for ever:
^8The sun to rule by day: for his mercy endureth for ever:
^9The moon and stars to rule by night: for his mercy endureth for ever.
^10To him that smote Egypt in their firstborn: for his mercy endureth for ever:
^11And brought out Israel from among them: for his mercy endureth for ever:
^12With a strong hand, and with a stretched out arm: for his mercy endureth for ever.
^13To him which divided the Red sea into parts: for his mercy endureth for ever:
^14And made Israel to pass through the midst of it: for his mercy endureth for ever:
^15But overthrew Pharaoh and his host in the Red sea: for his mercy endureth for ever.
^16To him which led his people through the wilderness: for his mercy endureth for ever.
^17To him which smote great kings: for his mercy endureth for ever:
^18And slew famous kings: for his mercy endureth for ever:
^19Sihon king of the Amorites: for his mercy endureth for ever:
^20And Og the king of Bashan: for his mercy endureth for ever:
^21And gave their land for an heritage: for his mercy endureth for ever:
^22Even an heritage unto Israel his servant: for his mercy endureth for ever.
^23Who remembered us in our low estate: for his mercy endureth for ever:
^24And hath redeemed us from our enemies: for his mercy endureth for ever.
^25Who giveth food to all flesh: for his mercy endureth for ever.
^26O give thanks unto the God of heaven: for his mercy endureth for ever.

CXXXVII

^1By the rivers of Babylon, there we sat down, yea, we wept, when we remembered Zion.
^2We hanged our harps upon the willows in the midst thereof.
^3For there they that carried us away captive required of us a song; and they that wasted us required of us mirth, saying, Sing us one of the songs of Zion.
^4How shall we sing the Lord’s song in a strange land?
^5If I forget thee, O Jerusalem, let my right hand forget her cunning.
^6If I do not remember thee, let my tongue cleave to the roof of my mouth; if I prefer not Jerusalem above my chief joy.
^7Remember, O Lord, the children of Edom in the day of Jerusalem; who said, Rase it, rase it, even to the foundation thereof.
^8O daughter of Babylon, who art to be destroyed; happy shall he be, that rewardeth thee as thou hast served us.
^9Happy shall he be, that taketh and dasheth thy little ones against the stones.

CXXXVIII

^1I will praise thee with my whole heart: before the gods will I sing praise unto thee.
^2I will worship toward thy holy temple, and praise thy name for thy lovingkindness and for thy truth: for thou hast magnified thy word above all thy name.
^3In the day when I cried thou answeredst me, and strengthenedst me with strength in my soul.
^4All the kings of the earth shall praise thee, O Lord, when they hear the words of thy mouth.
^5Yea, they shall sing in the ways of the Lord: for great is the glory of the Lord.
^6Though the Lord be high, yet hath he respect unto the lowly: but the proud he knoweth afar off.
^7Though I walk in the midst of trouble, thou wilt revive me: thou shalt stretch forth thine hand against the wrath of mine enemies, and thy right hand shall save me.
^8The Lord will perfect that which concerneth me: thy mercy, O Lord, endureth for ever: forsake not the works of thine own hands.

CXXXIX

^1O lord, thou hast searched me, and known me.
^2Thou knowest my downsitting and mine uprising, thou understandest my thought afar off.
^3Thou compassest my path and my lying down, and art acquainted with all my ways.
^4For there is not a word in my tongue, but, lo, O Lord, thou knowest it altogether.
^5Thou hast beset me behind and before, and laid thine hand upon me.
^6Such knowledge is too wonderful for me; it is high, I cannot attain unto it.
^7Whither shall I go from thy spirit? or whither shall I flee from thy presence?
^8If I ascend up into heaven, thou art there: if I make my bed in hell, behold, thou art there.
^9If I take the wings of the morning, and dwell in the uttermost parts of the sea;
^10Even there shall thy hand lead me, and thy right hand shall hold me.
^11If I say, Surely the darkness shall cover me; even the night shall be light about me.
^12Yea, the darkness hideth not from thee; but the night shineth as the day: the darkness and the light are both alike to thee.
^13For thou hast possessed my reins: thou hast covered me in my mother’s womb.
^14I will praise thee; for I am fearfully and wonderfully made: marvellous are thy works; and that my soul knoweth right well.
^15My substance was not hid from thee, when I was made in secret, and curiously wrought in the lowest parts of the earth.
^16Thine eyes did see my substance, yet being unperfect; and in thy book all my members were written, which in continuance were fashioned, when as yet there was none of them.
^17How precious also are thy thoughts unto me, O God! how great is the sum of them!
^18If I should count them, they are more in number than the sand: when I awake, I am still with thee.
^19Surely thou wilt slay the wicked, O God: depart from me therefore, ye bloody men.
^20For they speak against thee wickedly, and thine enemies take thy name in vain.
^21Do not I hate them, O Lord, that hate thee? and am not I grieved with those that rise up against thee?
^22I hate them with perfect hatred: I count them mine enemies.
^23Search me, O God, and know my heart: try me, and know my thoughts:
^24And see if there be any wicked way in me, and lead me in the way everlasting.

CXL

^1Deliver me, O Lord, from the evil man: preserve me from the violent man;
^2Which imagine mischiefs in their heart; continually are they gathered together for war.
^3They have sharpened their tongues like a serpent; adders’ poison is under their lips.
Selah.
^4Keep me, O Lord, from the hands of the wicked; preserve me from the violent man; who have purposed to overthrow my goings.
^5The proud have hid a snare for me, and cords; they have spread a net by the wayside; they have set gins for me.
Selah.
^6I said unto the Lord, Thou art my God: hear the voice of my supplications, O Lord.
^7O God the Lord, the strength of my salvation, thou hast covered my head in the day of battle.
^8Grant not, O Lord, the desires of the wicked: further not his wicked device; lest they exalt themselves.
Selah.
^9As for the head of those that compass me about, let the mischief of their own lips cover them.
^10Let burning coals fall upon them: let them be cast into the fire; into deep pits, that they rise not up again.
^11Let not an evil speaker be established in the earth: evil shall hunt the violent man to overthrow him.
^12I know that the Lord will maintain the cause of the afflicted, and the right of the poor.
^13Surely the righteous shall give thanks unto thy name: the upright shall dwell in thy presence.

CXLI

^1Lord, I cry unto thee: make haste unto me; give ear unto my voice, when I cry unto thee.
^2Let my prayer be set forth before thee as incense; and the lifting up of my hands as the evening sacrifice.
^3Set a watch, O Lord, before my mouth; keep the door of my lips.
^4Incline not my heart to any evil thing, to practise wicked works with men that work iniquity: and let me not eat of their dainties.
^5Let the righteous smite me; it shall be a kindness: and let him reprove me; it shall be an excellent oil, which shall not break my head: for yet my prayer also shall be in their calamities.
^6When their judges are overthrown in stony places, they shall hear my words; for they are sweet.
^7Our bones are scattered at the grave’s mouth, as when one cutteth and cleaveth wood upon the earth.
^8But mine eyes are unto thee, O God the Lord: in thee is my trust; leave not my soul destitute.
^9Keep me from the snares which they have laid for me, and the gins of the workers of iniquity.
^10Let the wicked fall into their own nets, whilst that I withal escape.

CXLII

^1I cried unto the Lord with my voice; with my voice unto the Lord did I make my supplication.
^2I poured out my complaint before him; I shewed before him my trouble.
^3When my spirit was overwhelmed within me, then thou knewest my path. In the way wherein I walked have they privily laid a snare for me.
^4I looked on my right hand, and beheld, but there was no man that would know me: refuge failed me; no man cared for my soul.
^5I cried unto thee, O Lord: I said, Thou art my refuge and my portion in the land of the living.
^6Attend unto my cry; for I am brought very low: deliver me from my persecutors; for they are stronger than I.
^7Bring my soul out of prison, that I may praise thy name: the righteous shall compass me about; for thou shalt deal bountifully with me.

CXLIII

^1Hear my prayer, O Lord, give ear to my supplications: in thy faithfulness answer me, and in thy righteousness.
^2And enter not into judgment with thy servant: for in thy sight shall no man living be justified.
^3For the enemy hath persecuted my soul; he hath smitten my life down to the ground; he hath made me to dwell in darkness, as those that have been long dead.
^4Therefore is my spirit overwhelmed within me; my heart within me is desolate.
^5I remember the days of old; I meditate on all thy works; I muse on the work of thy hands.
^6I stretch forth my hands unto thee: my soul thirsteth after thee, as a thirsty land.
Selah.
^7Hear me speedily, O Lord: my spirit faileth: hide not thy face from me, lest I be like unto them that go down into the pit.
^8Cause me to hear thy lovingkindness in the morning; for in thee do I trust: cause me to know the way wherein I should walk; for I lift up my soul unto thee.
^9Deliver me, O Lord, from mine enemies: I flee unto thee to hide me.
^10Teach me to do thy will; for thou art my God: thy spirit is good; lead me into the land of uprightness.
^11Quicken me, O Lord, for thy name’s sake: for thy righteousness’ sake bring my soul out of trouble.
^12And of thy mercy cut off mine enemies, and destroy all them that afflict my soul: for I am thy servant.

CXLIV

^1Blessed be the Lord my strength which teacheth my hands to war, and my fingers to fight:
^2My goodness, and my fortress; my high tower, and my deliverer; my shield, and he in whom I trust; who subdueth my people under me.
^3Lord, what is man, that thou takest knowledge of him! or the son of man, that thou makest account of him!
^4Man is like to vanity: his days are as a shadow that passeth away.
^5Bow thy heavens, O Lord, and come down: touch the mountains, and they shall smoke.
^6Cast forth lightning, and scatter them: shoot out thine arrows, and destroy them.
^7Send thine hand from above; rid me, and deliver me out of great waters, from the hand of strange children;
^8Whose mouth speaketh vanity, and their right hand is a right hand of falsehood.
^9I will sing a new song unto thee, O God: upon a psaltery and an instrument of ten strings will I sing praises unto thee.
^10It is he that giveth salvation unto kings: who delivereth David his servant from the hurtful sword.
^11Rid me, and deliver me from the hand of strange children, whose mouth speaketh vanity, and their right hand is a right hand of falsehood:
^12That our sons may be as plants grown up in their youth; that our daughters may be as corner stones, polished after the similitude of a palace:
^13That our garners may be full, affording all manner of store: that our sheep may bring forth thousands and ten thousands in our streets:
^14That our oxen may be strong to labour; that there be no breaking in, nor going out; that there be no complaining in our streets.
^15Happy is that people, that is in such a case: yea, happy is that people, whose God is the Lord.

CXLV

^1I will extol thee, my God, O king; and I will bless thy name for ever and ever.
^2Every day will I bless thee; and I will praise thy name for ever and ever.
^3Great is the Lord, and greatly to be praised; and his greatness is unsearchable.
^4One generation shall praise thy works to another, and shall declare thy mighty acts.
^5I will speak of the glorious honour of thy majesty, and of thy wondrous works.
^6And men shall speak of the might of thy terrible acts: and I will declare thy greatness.
^7They shall abundantly utter the memory of thy great goodness, and shall sing of thy righteousness.
^8The Lord is gracious, and full of compassion; slow to anger, and of great mercy.
^9The Lord is good to all: and his tender mercies are over all his works.
^10All thy works shall praise thee, O Lord; and thy saints shall bless thee.
^11They shall speak of the glory of thy kingdom, and talk of thy power;
^12To make known to the sons of men his mighty acts, and the glorious majesty of his kingdom.
^13Thy kingdom is an everlasting kingdom, and thy dominion endureth throughout all generations.
^14The Lord upholdeth all that fall, and raiseth up all those that be bowed down.
^15The eyes of all wait upon thee; and thou givest them their meat in due season.
^16Thou openest thine hand, and satisfiest the desire of every living thing.
^17The Lord is righteous in all his ways, and holy in all his works.
^18The Lord is nigh unto all them that call upon him, to all that call upon him in truth.
^19He will fulfil the desire of them that fear him: he also will hear their cry, and will save them.
^20The Lord preserveth all them that love him: but all the wicked will he destroy.
^21My mouth shall speak the praise of the Lord: and let all flesh bless his holy name for ever and ever.

CXLVI

^1Praise ye the Lord. Praise the Lord, O my soul.
^2While I live will I praise the Lord: I will sing praises unto my God while I have any being.
^3Put not your trust in princes, nor in the son of man, in whom there is no help.
^4His breath goeth forth, he returneth to his earth; in that very day his thoughts perish.
^5Happy is he that hath the God of Jacob for his help, whose hope is in the Lord his God:
^6Which made heaven, and earth, the sea, and all that therein is: which keepeth truth for ever:
^7Which executeth judgment for the oppressed: which giveth food to the hungry. The Lord looseth the prisoners:
^8The Lord openeth the eyes of the blind: the Lord raiseth them that are bowed down: the Lord loveth the righteous:
^9The Lord preserveth the strangers; he relieveth the fatherless and widow: but the way of the wicked he turneth upside down.
^10The Lord shall reign for ever, even thy God, O Zion, unto all generations. Praise ye the Lord.

CXLVII

^1Praise ye the Lord: for it is good to sing praises unto our God; for it is pleasant; and praise is comely.
^2The Lord doth build up Jerusalem: he gathereth together the outcasts of Israel.
^3He healeth the broken in heart, and bindeth up their wounds.
^4He telleth the number of the stars; he calleth them all by their names.
^5Great is our Lord, and of great power: his understanding is infinite.
^6The Lord lifteth up the meek: he casteth the wicked down to the ground.
^7Sing unto the Lord with thanksgiving; sing praise upon the harp unto our God:
^8Who covereth the heaven with clouds, who prepareth rain for the earth, who maketh grass to grow upon the mountains.
^9He giveth to the beast his food, and to the young ravens which cry.
^10He delighteth not in the strength of the horse: he taketh not pleasure in the legs of a man.
^11The Lord taketh pleasure in them that fear him, in those that hope in his mercy.
^12Praise the Lord, O Jerusalem; praise thy God, O Zion.
^13For he hath strengthened the bars of thy gates; he hath blessed thy children within thee.
^14He maketh peace in thy borders, and filleth thee with the finest of the wheat.
^15He sendeth forth his commandment upon earth: his word runneth very swiftly.
^16He giveth snow like wool: he scattereth the hoarfrost like ashes.
^17He casteth forth his ice like morsels: who can stand before his cold?
^18He sendeth out his word, and melteth them: he causeth his wind to blow, and the waters flow.
^19He sheweth his word unto Jacob, his statutes and his judgments unto Israel.
^20He hath not dealt so with any nation: and as for his judgments, they have not known them. Praise ye the Lord.

CXLVIII

^1Praise ye the Lord. Praise ye the Lord from the heavens: praise him in the heights.
^2Praise ye him, all his angels: praise ye him, all his hosts.
^3Praise ye him, sun and moon: praise him, all ye stars of light.
^4Praise him, ye heavens of heavens, and ye waters that be above the heavens.
^5Let them praise the name of the Lord: for he commanded, and they were created.
^6He hath also stablished them for ever and ever: he hath made a decree which shall not pass.
^7Praise the Lord from the earth, ye dragons, and all deeps:
^8Fire, and hail; snow, and vapours; stormy wind fulfilling his word:
^9Mountains, and all hills; fruitful trees, and all cedars:
^10Beasts, and all cattle; creeping things, and flying fowl:
^11Kings of the earth, and all people; princes, and all judges of the earth:
^12Both young men, and maidens; old men, and children:
^13Let them praise the name of the Lord: for his name alone is excellent; his glory is above the earth and heaven.
^14He also exalteth the horn of his people, the praise of all his saints; even of the children of Israel, a people near unto him. Praise ye the Lord.

CXLIX

^1Praise ye the Lord. Sing unto the Lord a new song, and his praise in the congregation of saints.
^2Let Israel rejoice in him that made him: let the children of Zion be joyful in their King.
^3Let them praise his name in the dance: let them sing praises unto him with the timbrel and harp.
^4For the Lord taketh pleasure in his people: he will beautify the meek with salvation.
^5Let the saints be joyful in glory: let them sing aloud upon their beds.
^6Let the high praises of God be in their mouth, and a two-edged sword in their hand;
^7To execute vengeance upon the heathen, and punishments upon the people;
^8To bind their kings with chains, and their nobles with fetters of iron;
^9To execute upon them the judgment written: this honour have all his saints. Praise ye the Lord.

CL

^1Praise ye the Lord. Praise God in his sanctuary: praise him in the firmament of his power.
^2Praise him for his mighty acts: praise him according to his excellent greatness.
^3Praise him with the sound of the trumpet: praise him with the psaltery and harp.
^4Praise him with the timbrel and dance: praise him with stringed instruments and organs.
^5Praise him upon the loud cymbals: praise him upon the high sounding cymbals.
^6Let every thing that hath breath praise the Lord. Praise ye the Lord.